<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ViewNLM-v2.3.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JKMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15201497</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2816832</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2004.19.3.341</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Rapid Prenatal Diagnosis of Down Syndrome Using Quantitative Fluorescent PCR in Uncultured Amniocytes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Moon-Hee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>Hyun-Mee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Do-Jin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Bom-Yi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Eun-Hee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Jae-Hyug</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Moon-Young</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Jung-Yeol</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>So-Yeon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1">Laboratory of Medical Genetics, Samsung Cheil Hospital &#x00026; Women's Healthcare Center, Sungkyunkwan University, School of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>*</label>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Samsung Cheil Hospital &#x00026; Women's Healthcare Center, Sungkyunkwan University, School of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Address for correspondence: So-Yeon Park, Ph.D. Laboratory of Medical Genetics, Samsung Cheil Hospital &#x00026; Women's Healthcare Center, 1-19 Mookjung-dong, Chung-gu, Seoul 100-380, Korea. Tel: +82.2-2278-4574, Fax: +82.2-2000-7679, <email>genelab@samsung.co.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Rapid prenatal diagnosis of common chromosome aneuploidies have been successful through quantitative fluoresent PCR (QF-PCR) assays and small tandem repeat (STR) markers. The purpose of our study was to investigate the clinical feasibility for rapid prenatal detection of Down syndrome using the quantitative fluorescent PCR in uncultured amniocytes. DNA was extracted from uncultured amniotic fluid of normal karyotype (n=200) and of Down syndrome (n=21). It was amplified using QF-PCR with four STR markers located on chromosome 21. Among normal samples, the ranges of diallelic peaks for at least one STR marker were 1.0-1.3 for D21S11, 1.0-1.4 for D21S1411 and 1.0-1.5 for D21S1270. Down syndrome samples showed trisomic triallelic patterns or trisomic diallelic patterns. The sensitivity, specificity, and efficiency of the assay for detecting Down syndrome were 95.4%, 100%, and 99.5%, respectively. Rapid prenatal diagnosis of Down syndrome using QF-PCR is a reliable technique that aids clinical management of pregnancy.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Polymerase Chain Reaotion</kwd><kwd>Primed In Situ Labeling</kwd><kwd>Prenatal Diagnosis</kwd><kwd>Down Syndrome</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Analysis of uncultured fetal cells by fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) has been used as a rapid alternative in screening for common chromosomal aneuploidies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Although FISH usually takes only 24 to 48 hr, it is expensive and intensively laborious. Recently, quantitative fluorescent PCR (QF-PCR) of single tandem repeats (STRs) has been developed for rapid prenatal diagnosis of aneuploidies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). This approach has been used extensively by several groups on research basis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>), and the diagnosis of aneuploidies by QF-PCR of STRs has now been validated as a reliable method applicable in many laboratories.</p><p>In this study, we investigated the clinical feasibility of QF-PCR for rapid prenatal diagnosis of trisomy 21.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><p>Genomic DNA extraction was performed on the cell pellet obtained from 1 to 2 mL of amniotic fluid from 200 normal samples and 21 samples with trisomy 21. The karyotypes of all amniotic fluid samples were performed previously by conventional cytogenetic analysis. DNA was extracted by incubating cell pellets with InstaGene Matrix (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, U.S.A.). A single tube multiplex PCR was carried out by STR markers specific for chromosome 21. D21S11, D21S1411, and D21S1270 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) were used to test all samples for chromosome 21. D21S1412 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>) was added to test samples found to be homozygous for the first three STR (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The QF-PCR amplification of STR markers was performed in a total volume of 25 &#x000b5;L containing 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 200 &#x000b5;m/L dNTP, 10-30 pmol of each primer, PCR buffer, 2U <italic>Taq</italic> polymerase, and 10 &#x000b5;L genomic DNA. After the initial denaturation at 94&#x02103; for 5 min, hot start PCR was followed by 25 cycles of 94&#x02103; for 35 sec, 58&#x02103; for 35 sec, 72&#x02103; for 40 sec and final extension was for 5 min at 72&#x02103;. For fragment analysis of PCR products, ABI 3100 and GeneScan 3.7 (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, U.S.A.) were used.</p><p>The statistical analysis of the heterozygosity for each STR marker between the published population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) and the Korean population were analyzed using the Z-test. A <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003e;1.96 was taken as significant.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>The majority of normal samples showed diallelic peaks with a ratio of 1:1 for each STR marker (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Among normal samples, the ranges of diallelic peaks were 1.0-1.3 for D21S11, 1.0-1.4 for D21S1411 and 1.0-1.5 for D21S1270 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Down syndrome samples that confirmed karyotypes with 47,+21 showed trisomic triallelic patterns with an allele peak ratio 1:1:1, or trisomic diallelic patterns with an allele peak ratio 2:1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). However, one case that showed low-level mosaicism with a karyotype of 47,XX,+21[23]/46,XX [218] failed to be detected by QF-PCR. In complete trisomic 21 samples, the ranges of diallelic peaks were 1.6-2.4 for D21S11, 2.2-2.7 for D21S1411, and 1.7-2.9 for D21S1270 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>).</p><p>All but one normal samples were heterozygous and informative for at least one STR marker (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>).</p><p>The sensitivity, specificity, and efficiency of QF-PCR for the detection of Down syndrome were 95.4%, 100%, and 99.5%, respectively. The false positive and the false negative rates were 0% (0/200) and 4.7% (1/21), respectively. All results were obtained within 24 to 48 hr.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>QF-PCR for the detection of chromosome specific repeated sequences has been improved to include several STR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). It is based on the incorporation of fluorochromes into the products of PCR amplification via oligonucleotide primers specific for each STR and on the assumption that, within the early exponential phase of PCR amplification, the amount of specific STR produced is proportional to the quantity of initial target sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). In normal heterozygotes, the ratio of the fluorescent intensity of the two peaks should be close to 1:1. If the STR marker is highly polymorphic, few normal subjects should be homozygotes and show one peak. In a trisomic patient, the three doses of an STR marker can be detected either as three peaks of fluorescent intensity with a ratio 1:1:1 (trisomic triallelic) or as a pattern of two peaks with a ratio 2:1 (trisomic diallelic). Using the high polymorphism of the STR markers, very few trisomic patients should show a single peak of fluorescent intensity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>).</p><p>Our results present that the fluorescent intensity ratios showed a definite difference between normal disomic diallelic samples and diallelic trisomy 21 samples.</p><p>In the present study, we used the markers as published previously. It was shown that heterozygosity of markers was low in our population compared to the published data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref>). At the D21S11 and D21S1411 markers, a significant differences were found. We expected a difference of genetic diversity between an ethnic groups and it was supported by other previous reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>).</p><p>Although 4 samples showed heterozygous for only one STR, even after using the extra marker, the use of combined STR markers could reduce the likelihood of homozygosity and consequently, the frequency of uninformative STR patterns. Only one out of 220 samples was homozygous for all STR tested (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>). As a results, we emphasize that the informative rate of our experiment is prominent than other studies so far (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>).</p><p>Yoon et al. reported three false positive in the multiplex QF-PCR using two of STR markers for Down syndrome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). As it is well known, the preferential amplification of multiplex PCR is a potential problem that result in an incorrect genetic typing and is effected by low denaturation temperatures, low amount of DNA, and differential allelic priming. In this study, there were no false positive results from multiplex QF-PCR using three of STR markers. It is reported that a maximum primer set used in the multiplex QF-PCR is twelve up to now (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>).</p><p>One case of low level mosaicism for trisomy 21 with a karyotype of 47,XX,+21[23]/46,XX[218] resulted in a false negative result. Several studies reported that mosaicism for trisomy was able to be detected by QF-PCR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>), but based on our own and other published experiences, mosaicism, maternal contamination, structural abnormality, deletion and duplication syndrome are not likely to be detected by the QF-PCR technique (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). However, it is possible that future development, such as the use of extensive panel of markers to cover other key chromosomes, will result in significant improvements in the detection rate.</p><p>An advantage of using QF-PCR technique is that it is less time consuming and less laborious and this assay is useful on small volumes of amniotic fluid (1-2 mL). In this study, some results were obtained within 8 hr.</p><p>Our experiment demonstrates that QF-PCR can provide a rapid and accurate clinical method for prenatal identification of Down syndrome and also serve as an adjunctive test to help cytogenetics to reduce significant amounts of emotional stress experienced by patients and physicians. In further studies, we will test a larger scale population with expanded panel of markers for other numerical aberrations, such as trisomy 13 or 18 and sex chromosome aneuploidies.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><p>This study was supported by a grant of the Cheil Medical Encouragement Foundation.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klinger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Landes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shook</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Osathanondh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leverone</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Houseal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid detection of chromosome aneuploidies in uncultured amniocytes by using fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH)</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>1992</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1609805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thilaganathan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sairam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of prenatal chromosomal analysis using multicolor fluorescent in situ hybridization</article-title><source>Bjog</source><year>2000</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>262</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansfield</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis of Down syndrome and other aneuploidies using quantitative polymerase chain reaction and small tandem repeat polymorphisms</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>1993</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8490622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pertl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yau</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherlock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Adinolfi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid molecular method for prenatal detection of Down's syndrome</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1994</year><volume>343</volume><fpage>1197</fpage><lpage>1198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7909872</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pertl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Weitgasser</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroisel</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherlock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Adinolfi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid detection of trisomies 21 and 18 and sexing by quantitative fluorescent multiplex PCR</article-title><source>Hum Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8682507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Findlay</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Toth-Pal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Marton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Quirke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prenatal detection of trisomy 21 and 18 from amniotic fluid by quantitative fluorescent polymerase chain reaction</article-title><source>J Med Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9507392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Macdonald</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Leedham</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McConachie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhanjal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid and simple prenatal DNA diagnosis of Down's syndrome</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1998</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9800738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenderny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hecher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackeloer</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kochhan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Held</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of aneuploidy in chromosomes X, Y, 13, 18 and 21 by QF-PCR in 662 selected pregnancies at risk</article-title><source>Mol Hum Reprod</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>855</fpage><lpage>860</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10956559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levett</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liddle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A large-scale evaluation of amnio-PCR for the rapid prenatal diagnosis of fetal trisomy</article-title><source>Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol</source><year>2001</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11251918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbs</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yau</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Scriven</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Docherty</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogilvie</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and implementation of a new rapid aneuploidy diagnostic service within the UK National Health Service and implications for the future of prenatal diagnosis</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2001</year><volume>358</volume><fpage>1057</fpage><lpage>1061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11589937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pertl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroisel</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hausler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherlock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>AdinolfiM</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative fluorescence polymerase chain reaction for the rapid prenatal detection of common aneuploidies and fetal sex</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><year>1997</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>899</fpage><lpage>906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9369843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative or semi-quantitative PCR: reality versus myth</article-title><source>PCR Methods Appl</source><year>1992</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1490169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ku</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Korean population study of the nine STR loci FGA, VWA, D3S1358, D18S51, D21S11, D8S1179, D7S820, D13S317 and D5S818</article-title><source>Int J Legal Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11197626</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Statistical analysis for estimating heterogeneity of the Korean population in DNA typing using STR loci</article-title><source>Int J Legal Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12111318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allele frequencies of 15 STR loci using AmpF/STR Identifiler kit in a Korean population</article-title><source>Forensic Sci Int</source><year>2003</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12969628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid prenatal detection of Down and Edwards syndromes by fluorescent polymerase chain reaction with short tandem repeat markers</article-title><source>Yonsei Med J</source><year>2002</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12402367</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Electrophoregram of the QF-PCR products from normal and trisomy 21 samples. Fragment size in bp shown on horizontal axis, arbitrary fluorescence units shown on vertical axis. Markers labelled according to locus, size, and peak areas. Normal diploid sample: all markers are heterozygous and exhibit two peaks with a 1:1 ratio. Trisomy 21 sample: chromosome 21 markers exhibit three peaks with a 1:1:1 ratio or two peaks with a 2:1 ratio.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-19-341-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>STR markers used for quantitative fluorescent PCR<sup>*</sup></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-19-341-i001"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>*</sup>Reference: Mann, et al. 2001 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Polymorphism and ratio of peak areas in 200 normal samples</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-19-341-i002"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Polymorphism and ratio of peak areas in trisomy 21 samples<sup>*</sup></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-19-341-i003"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>*</sup>One case with mosaicism was excluded.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Evaluation for each STR marker and combined STR markers<sup>*</sup></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-19-341-i004"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>*</sup>One of false negative was excluded.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Evaluation of markers in the Korean population</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-19-341-i005"/></table-wrap></floats-group></article>