<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25023009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4097343</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep05684</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep05684</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A New Sealed Lithium-Peroxide Battery with a Co-Doped Li<sub>2</sub>O Cathode in a Superconcentrated Lithium Bis(fluorosulfonyl)amide Electrolyte</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Okuoka</surname><given-names>Shin-ichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ogasawara</surname><given-names>Yoshiyuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suga</surname><given-names>Yosuke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hibino</surname><given-names>Mitsuhiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kudo</surname><given-names>Tetsuichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>Hironobu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yonehara</surname><given-names>Koji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sumida</surname><given-names>Yasutaka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Yuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Atsuo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oshima</surname><given-names>Masaharu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tochigi</surname><given-names>Eita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>Naoya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ikuhara</surname><given-names>Yuichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>Noritaka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Advanced Materials Research Center, Nippon Shokubai Co.</institution>, Ltd. 5-8, Nishi Otabi-cho, Suita, Osaka, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Applied Chemistry, School of Engineering, The University of Tokyo</institution>, 7-3-1 Hongo, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Chemical System Engineering, School of Engineering, The University of Tokyo</institution>, 7-3-1 Hongo, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="a4"><label>4</label><institution>Synchrotron Radiation Research Organization, The University of Tokyo</institution>, 7-3-1 Hongo, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="a5"><label>5</label><institution>Institute of Engineering Innovation, School of Engineering, The University of Tokyo</institution>, 2-11-16 Yayoi, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo, <country>Japan</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>tmizuno@mail.ecc.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>07</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>5684</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>05</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>06</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014, Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder in order to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We propose a new sealed battery operating on a redox reaction between an oxide (O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup>) and a peroxide (O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup>) with its theoretical specific energy of 2570&#x02005;Wh kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (897&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 2.87&#x02005;V) and demonstrate that a Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode exhibits a reversible capacity over 190&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, a high rate capability, and a good cyclability with a superconcentrated lithium bis(fluorosulfonyl)amide electrolyte in acetonitrile. The reversible capacity is largely dominated by the O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup>/O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> redox reaction between oxide and peroxide with some contribution of the Co<sup>2+</sup>/Co<sup>3+</sup> redox reaction.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Rechargeable lithium ion batteries (LIBs) operating on shuttling of lithium between the negative and positive electrodes, both of which are composed of topotactic insertion hosts of lithium such as graphite and LiCoO<sub>2</sub>, are indispensable to our society as power sources for portable and large electronic appliances such as notebook computers and electric vehicles. However, their energy densities are rather modest; even the state-of-the-art LIBs do not exceed 250&#x02005;Wh kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Therefore, various researches are being carried out to develop post-LIBs with much higher energy densities.</p><p>One of the approaches is utilization of electrode materials operating on so-called conversion reactions and the theoretical specific capacity is 714&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for the reaction of CoO + 2Li<sup>+</sup> + 2e<sup>&#x02212;</sup> &#x02192; Co + Li<sub>2</sub>O<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>, while the severe hysteresis in voltage between the charging and discharging processes generally limits the energy efficiency. Moreover, some metal oxides including CoO show surprisingly good cycling reversibility despite the highly destructive nature of the conversion reaction. However, such oxide materials can be used only for anodes, because their working potentials are typically in the range of 0&#x02013;1&#x02005;V (vs. Li/Li<sup>+</sup>) and low. Recently, some fluorides such as BiF<sub>3</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref> and FeF<sub>2</sub> (or FeF<sub>3</sub>)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref> have been reported to operate at higher potentials (2.7&#x02013;3.4&#x02005;V), while their poor kinetics and reversibility are problems.</p><p>Another approach is a development of a lithium-air (Li-O<sub>2</sub>) battery by use of atmospheric O<sub>2</sub> with a theoretical specific energy of 3400&#x02005;Wh kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> even including the weight of oxygen in the discharged product (Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>). However, the actual capacity or the energy is dependent on the pore volumes of the cathode matrices where Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is formed, the pores are clogged with solids, and the discharge is prohibited by the limitation of the oxygen supply. In addition, there are more serious inherent problems of the open device, suffering from the coexisting moisture and CO<sub>2</sub>, and safety for the application to electronic vehicles. The main discharge product for Li-O<sub>2</sub> batteries is Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> according to the reaction (the equilibrium potential, <italic>E</italic>&#x000b0; (vs. Li/Li<sup>+</sup>))<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>, <disp-formula id="m1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e364" xlink:href="srep05684-m1.jpg"/></disp-formula>The subsequent reduction of Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> has recently been pointed out to take place to form Li<sub>2</sub>O during the deep discharge according to the reaction<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, <disp-formula id="m2"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e379" xlink:href="srep05684-m2.jpg"/></disp-formula>However, there is no report on the repetition of the charge and discharge utilizing the reaction between Li<sub>2</sub>O (or O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup>) and Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (or O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup>). The investigation on LIB cathodes such as LiCoO<sub>2</sub> and Li-rich layered oxides shows not only the charge compensation mechanism involving transition metal ions but also some contribution of the reversible redox reaction of oxygen atoms<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>. Therefore, we have reached an idea that Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> would act as a 3&#x02005;V-level cathode utilizing the redox couple of oxide (O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup>)/peroxide (O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup>) [<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m2">equation (2)</xref>]. In addition, a certain electrode catalyst or mediator would selectively accelerate the thermodynamically more favourable backward reaction of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m2">equation (2)</xref> instead of the backward reaction of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m1">equation (1)</xref> and the following reaction, <disp-formula id="m3"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e430" xlink:href="srep05684-m3.jpg"/></disp-formula>Here, we propose a new sealed battery operating on a redox reaction between O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> and O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> with its theoretical specific energy of 2570&#x02005;Wh kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (897&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 2.87&#x02005;V, see the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Information</xref>) based on the reaction, <disp-formula id="m4"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e451" xlink:href="srep05684-m4.jpg"/></disp-formula>and demonstrate that a Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode exhibits a reversible capacity over 190&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, a high rate capability, and a good cyclability with a superconcentrated lithium bis(fluorosulfonyl)amide (LiFSA) electrolyte in acetonitrile<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>. The reversible capacity is largely dominated by the reaction of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m2">equation (2)</xref> with some contribution of the redox reaction of Co ions.</p><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Preparation and Characterization of the Co-Doped Li<sub>2</sub>O Cathode</title><p>The powders (Co/Li = 0.025&#x02013;0.2) of Li<sub>2</sub>O and Co<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> were pulverized and the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O were obtained. Among them, the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O (Co/Li = 0.1) showed the best charge-discharge performance (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S1a</xref>). The electronic conductivity of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O (Co/Li = 0.1) powder compact was 5.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>2</sup>&#x02005;k&#x003a9; cm, while Li<sub>2</sub>O is an insulator. Therefore, the resulting Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O (Co/Li = 0.1) was hereafter used as a cathode and the specific capacity was calculated on the basis of the total weight of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O. Rh<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> and IrO<sub>2</sub> could also act similarly to Co<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4 </sub>(<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S1b</xref>).</p><p>In the X-ray diffraction (XRD) pattern of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>), broad peaks of anti-fluorite-type Li<sub>2</sub>O and a weak peak at 44.8&#x000b0; of cubic LiCoO<sub>2</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref> were observed, while peaks of spinel-type Co<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> were not observed. The peak intensity of the cubic LiCoO<sub>2</sub> increased upon increase in the Co/Li ratio.</p><p>The Co K-edge X-ray absorption near edge structure (XANES) measurement of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O was carried out to investigate the oxidation states and coordination environments of the Co species (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>). The absorption edge position agreed with that of starting Co<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, indicating that the average Co valence does not change under mechanical milling conditions. The pre-edge peak of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O was stronger than those of Co<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> and LiCoO<sub>2</sub> and as strong as that of the spinel CoAl<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, in which every Co<sup>2+</sup> ion is located at the tetrahedral site. This absorption represents the transition of the 1s electron to an unoccupied d orbital of Co ions, which is an electric dipole forbidden transition in an ideal octahedral symmetry, while the noncentrosymmetric tetrahedral environment allows the transition<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>. Thus, the intense pre-edge peak shows the presence of considerable amounts of tetrahedral Co.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Electrochemical Performance</title><p>The charge and discharge curves of the cell consisting of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode, a Li metal anode, and a superconcentrated 4&#x02005;M LiFSA electrolyte in acetonitrile<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref> are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>. The charge voltage gradually increased and reached approximately 3.2&#x02005;V above 150&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The discharge and charge curves from the first to 15th cycle almost unchanged with the constant coulombic efficiency of <italic>ca</italic>. 96% at 45&#x02005;mA g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1a</xref>). The 1st discharge capacity reached 195&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at a low current density of 13.5&#x02005;mA g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and the capacity of 133&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> can be discharged even at a very high current density of 1080&#x02005;mA g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at which the capacity of 200&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> can be charged in 11&#x02005;min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1b</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Co K-edge XANES Measurement of the Co-Doped Li<sub>2</sub>O Cathode during the Charge and Discharge Process</title><p>The Co K-edge XANES spectra were measured at various charge and discharge capacities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>). In the charge process from 0 to 54&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the absorption edge position shifted to the higher photon energy, indicating the oxidation of Co<sup>2+</sup> to Co<sup>3+</sup>. By the further increase in the capacity the edge position of Co<sup>3+</sup> did not change. In the discharge process after the charge to 270&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the absorption edge position hardly changed in the range of 0&#x02013;162&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and then returned to the initial position upon the discharge to 250&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Peroxide Analysis in the Co-Doped Li<sub>2</sub>O Cathode during the Charge and Discharge Process</title><p>We quantified O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> species in the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode at various charge and discharge capacities. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3a</xref> shows the amounts of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> (detected as O<sub>2</sub>) in the cathode at various charge capacities. In the range of 0&#x02013;54&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the amounts of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> were negligible. In the region 54&#x02013;216&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the amounts of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> increased and the slope from 162&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 216&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> corresponded to 0.5 O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup>/e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>. In the final region of 216&#x02013;270&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the amounts of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> more gradually increased.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3d</xref> shows amounts of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> in the cathode at various discharge capacities after the charge to 270&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. In the region of 0&#x02013;162&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the amounts of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> decreased and the slope from 0&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 108&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> corresponded to 0.5 O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup>/e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>. In the final region of 162&#x02013;250&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> was hardly detected. We also quantified the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> species in the cathode recharged to 270&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The amount of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> was 2.31&#x02005;mmol g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in approximate agreement with that for the first charge.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Observation and Analysis of the Cathode during the Charge</title><p>The in-situ gas phase analysis during the charge process was conducted. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4b</xref>, cumulative amounts (per weight of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode) of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> evolved are shown together with its charge curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4a</xref>). In the range of 0&#x02013;216&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, O<sub>2</sub> was hardly observed, and then the amount of O<sub>2</sub> evolution monotonically increased. The slope of O<sub>2</sub> evolution in the range of 324&#x02013;594&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> almost corresponded to 0.25 O<sub>2</sub>/e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>. The XRD 111 peak intensity of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O was approximately linearly weakened with increase in the charge capacity from 0 to 324&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and was more slowly weakened at 540 and 580&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4c</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S4</xref>). The evolution of CO<sub>2</sub> was not observed in the whole range of the charge process.</p><p>Direct observation of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode charged to 270&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> was attempted with high resolution transmission electron microscopy (HRTEM). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref> shows the HRTEM image and the fast Fourier transform (FFT) pattern. Since some spots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5b</xref> lie on the circles estimated with the Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> crystal structure, many fringe regions surrounded by red circles in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5a</xref> are likely attributable to Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. In contrast, for the starting cathode before the charge, since all spots (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S5b</xref>) lie on the circles estimated with Li<sub>2</sub>O or cubic LiCoO<sub>2</sub> crystal structures, many fringe regions surrounded by red circles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S5a</xref>) are likely attributable to Li<sub>2</sub>O or cubic LiCoO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Upon increase in Co content above Co/Li = 0.1, the discharge capacity decreased (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S1a</xref>) and the XRD peak intensity of cubic LiCoO<sub>2</sub> increased (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>), suggesting that the resulting cubic LiCoO<sub>2</sub> is inactive for the charge and discharge reactions at the voltage of 2.0&#x02013;3.2&#x02005;V (vs. Li/Li<sup>+</sup>) as has been reported in ref. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>).</p><p>In the XRD pattern of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>), broad peaks of anti-fluorite-type Li<sub>2</sub>O and a weak peak at 44.8&#x000b0; of cubic LiCoO<sub>2</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref> were observed, while peaks of spinel-type Co<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> were not observed. The volume fractions of Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O and cubic LiCoO<sub>2</sub> were estimated to be 0.90:0.10 with the parameters of 111 reflection of Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O and 200 one of cubic LiCoO<sub>2</sub> in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Table S1</xref> (see the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Information</xref>). The Co K-edge XANES spectrum of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O shows the presence of considerable amounts of tetrahedral Co (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>). These results indicate that most of Co ions are substitutionally doped in the tetrahedral Li sites of the anti-fluorite Li<sub>2</sub>O structure with formation of vacancies at the same sites due to charge compensation. Co<sup>2+</sup> and Co<sup>3+</sup> in the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O would be randomly distributed at the tetrahedral sites in a defective anti-fluorite structure, since the XRD pattern was not identical to that of the defective anti-fluorite structure, in which Co ions were ordered in the tetrahedral sites<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>.</p><p>The Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode, of which the theoretical specific capacity is calculated to be 556&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> based on the weight of Li<sub>2</sub>O in the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O (see the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Information</xref>), exhibited a reversible capacity over 190&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, a high rate capability, and a good cyclability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). The electronic conductivity of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O powder compact was 5.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>2</sup>&#x02005;k&#x003a9; cm and of the same level (5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>2</sup>&#x02005;k&#x003a9; cm) as that of LiMn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>, showing that the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O can work as an electrode material. This conductivity is possibly explained by narrowing of the Li<sub>2</sub>O band gap by formation of the impurity state with the dope of Co or becoming metallic by the carrier dope. The coulombic efficiency of the present system is 96% and still below 100%. This is possibly explained by the progress of the side reaction of solid electrolyte interface formation during the charge other than CO<sub>2</sub> formation.</p><p>To clarify the oxidation states of Co and the presence of O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> in the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode, the Co K-edge XANES measurement and quantification of O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> species were carried out at various charge and discharge capacities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">3</xref>). In the charge process from 0 to 54&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the oxidation of Co<sup>2+</sup> to Co<sup>3+</sup> proceeds without the O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> oxidation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figures 3a and 3b</xref>). The oxidation of Co<sup>2+</sup> to Co<sup>3+</sup> in the charge process is completed at the charge capacity &#x02264;54&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in accord with the theoretical capacity (39&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) of the cathode due to the oxidation of Co<sup>2+</sup> to Co<sup>3+</sup>. In the region of 54&#x02013;216&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the amounts of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> increased and the slope from 162&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 216&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> corresponded to 0.5 O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup>/e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, suggesting the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> formation according to the backward reaction of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m2">equation (2)</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3a</xref>). In the final region of 216&#x02013;270&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the amounts of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> more gradually increased. Considering the O<sub>2</sub> evolution curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4b</xref>), both the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> formation and O<sub>2</sub> evolution reactions likely proceed in this region.</p><p>In the discharge process from 0 to 162&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the amounts of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> decreased and the slope from 0&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 108&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> corresponded to 0.5 O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup>/e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, suggesting the consumption of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> according to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m2">equation (2)</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3d</xref>). In the final region of 162&#x02013;250&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> was hardly detected, indicating that the discharge mostly consists of the reduction of Co<sup>3+</sup> to Co<sup>2+</sup>, in agreement with the Co K-edge XANES results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figures 2b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">3e</xref>). In the recharge process to 270&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, the amount of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> was 2.31&#x02005;mmol g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in approximate agreement with that for the first charge, suggesting reversible formation of O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> in the repeated cycles.</p><p>It is essentially important for the present battery that no substantial amount of O<sub>2</sub> is released in the charge process. Moreover, CO<sub>2</sub> evolution accompanied by anodic side reactions between Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and carbon additives or electrolytes has been pointed out as a problem of the Li-O<sub>2</sub> batteries<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>. In the range of 0&#x02013;216&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, O<sub>2</sub> was hardly observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4b</xref>), suggesting that the side reactions of O<sub>2</sub> evolution do not proceed and Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O is oxidized according to the reaction, 2O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> &#x02192; O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> + 2e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, with some contribution of the oxidation of Co ions. The slope of 0.25 O<sub>2</sub>/e<sup>&#x02212;</sup> in the range of 324&#x02013;594&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> suggests that O<sub>2</sub> is formed according to the direct reaction (i) 2Li<sub>2</sub>O &#x02192; O<sub>2</sub> + 4Li<sup>+</sup> + 4e<sup>&#x02212;</sup> and/or the consecutive reaction (ii) 2Li<sub>2</sub>O &#x02192; Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> + 2Li<sup>+</sup> + 2e<sup>&#x02212;</sup> &#x02192; O<sub>2</sub> + 4Li<sup>+</sup> + 4e<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (the overall reaction, 2O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> &#x02192; O<sub>2</sub> + 4e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>). The investigation on the mechanism of the O<sub>2</sub> evolution is in progress. The XRD 111 peak intensity of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O was approximately linearly weakened with increase in the charge capacity toward the theoretical capacity of 556&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4c</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S4</xref>). The upper deviation from the linear line at 540 and 580&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> is probably due to the O<sub>2</sub> evolution. While the HRTEM image shows fringe regions attributed to Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref>), the XRD patterns of Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O upon charged to 270, 324 and 540&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> showed no Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signal (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S4</xref>) because of the small amount and poor crystallinity. The evolution of CO<sub>2</sub> was not observed in the whole range of the charge process, showing that the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode is free from side reactions to produce CO<sub>2</sub> and the superconcentrated LiFSA electrolyte in acetonitrile is stable under the present conditions.</p><p>All results demonstrate that the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode is charged without the O<sub>2</sub> evolution in the region of 0&#x02013;216&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4b</xref>) via the oxidation of Co<sup>2+</sup> to Co<sup>3+</sup> (0&#x02013;54&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2a</xref>) and the subsequent oxidation of O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> to O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> (54&#x02013;216&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3a</xref>) according to the reaction, 2Li<sub>2</sub>O &#x02192; Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> + 2Li<sup>+</sup> + 2e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>: <italic>E</italic>&#x000b0; = 2.87&#x02005;V. In the higher capacity range, O<sub>2</sub> was evolved, suggesting the progress of reactions with the higher equilibrium potential, 2Li<sub>2</sub>O &#x02192; O<sub>2</sub> + 4Li<sup>+</sup> + 4e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>: <italic>E</italic>&#x000b0; = 2.91&#x02005;V and/or Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> &#x02192; O<sub>2</sub> + 2Li<sup>+</sup> + 2e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>: <italic>E</italic>&#x000b0; = 2.96&#x02005;V as expected thermodynamically. At the present stage, the reversible specific capacity of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode was <italic>ca</italic>. 200&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and lower than its theoretical 556&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p><p>In conclusion, we have proposed and demonstrated a new sealed and high-rate battery operating on a redox reaction between O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> and O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> with the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode and a superconcentrated LiFSA electrolyte in acetonitrile; a reversible capacity over 190 mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, a high rate capability, and a good cyclability. The reversible capacity was largely dominated by the reaction, O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> + 2e<sup>&#x02212;</sup> &#x02194; 2O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup>, with some contribution of the redox reaction of Co. The present specific capacity of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode is still lower than its theoretical 556&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The investigation of roles of Co in the redox reaction between O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> and O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> and the state of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> species in the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O would lead to the improvement of the specific capacity.</p></sec><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Preparation of the Co-Doped Li<sub>2</sub>O</title><p>Accurately weighed powders of Li<sub>2</sub>O (Kojundo Chemical Laboratory co., ltd.) and Co<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> (Wako Pure Chemical Industry, ltd.) were loaded into a zirconia milling pot (45&#x02005;mL) in an Ar-filled glove box (LABmaster SP, MBRAUN) at atomic ratio of Co/Li = 0.1. The milling pot was fixed in a planetary ball mill machine (Pulverisette 7, Fritsch) and agitated with zirconia milling balls (10&#x02005;mm diameter &#x000d7; 25) at 600&#x02005;rpm for 200&#x02005;h. Then, the milling pot was opened in an Ar-filled glove box and a dark green powder was collected. The elemental analysis of the resulting powder was carried out by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectroscopy (ICP-AES); Li 28.7&#x02005;wt%, Co 24.0&#x02005;wt%, atomic ratio of Co/Li = 0.099.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Electrochemical Measurements</title><p>The Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode was prepared by blending the active material thoroughly with powder acetylene black and polytetrafluoroethylene at the weight ratio of 45:50:5. The material was then pressed on an Al mesh (100 mesh) current collector to form an electrode. The cathode, a Li anode pressed on a Cu foil current collector, a concentrated electrolyte solution of 4&#x02005;M LiFSA in acetonitrile<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>, and a glass fibre filter (GA-55, Toyo Roshi Kaisha, Ltd.) as a separator were assembled in two-electrode cells (HS Test Cell or CR2032 coin-type cell, Hosen Corp.). All these procedures were carried out in an Ar-filled glove box. The charge and discharge tests were conducted with a battery charge/discharge system HJ1001SD8 (Hokuto Denko Corporation).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Characterization of Materials</title><p>The elemental analysis of Li and Co was performed by ICP-AES with ICPS-8100 (Shimadzu). The Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O powder (11.37&#x02005;mg) was weighed in an Ar-filled glove box and dissolved into 1&#x02005;mL of an aqueous solution (6&#x02005;M HCl). The solution was diluted in a volumetric flask to 100&#x02005;mL and then 5&#x02005;mL of the solution was diluted in a volumetric flask to 50&#x02005;mL. The concentrations of Li and Co were quantified with standard solutions of Li and Co (0&#x02013;4&#x02005;ppm).</p><p>Powder XRD patterns were measured using the monochromatized Cu-K<sub>&#x003b1;1</sub> radiation on a RIGAKU Smart-Lab system. Every sample was mounted in a gas-tight holder with a Be window filled with Ar. The charged or discharged Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode was removed from the cell, washed three times with acetonitrile, and dried under vacuum. All procedures were carried out in an Ar-filled glove box.</p><p>The oxidation states and coordination environments of Co in the cathode were observed with XANES measurements. The XANES measurements at the Co K-edge were carried out on the BL14B2 beamline at the SPring-8 synchrotron radiation facility (8&#x02005;GeV, 100&#x02005;mA) of the Japan Synchrotron Radiation Research Institute (JASRI) in Hyogo, Japan. A Si(111) two-crystal monochromator was used for the measurements of Co K-edge XANES spectra. Ion chambers filled with N<sub>2</sub> (100%) and N<sub>2</sub> (85%)/Ar (15%) were used for the I<sub>0</sub>/I detector. XANES spectra at Co K-edge were collected in a transmission mode, and the total acquisition time was 6&#x02005;min per spectrum. Data reduction was performed by using the REX2000 program (Rigaku Co., Ltd.).</p><p>The HRTEM measurements of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode pristine and after charged to 270&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> were carried out on a JEM-4010 microscope (JEOL, Japan) at an accelerating voltage of 400&#x02005;kV.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Measurements of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> Evolution in the Charging Process</title><p>The Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode (11.3&#x02005;mg) was pressed on an Al mesh as a current collector. The negative electrode was a metallic Li foil pressed on a Cu mesh. These electrodes, a glass fibre filter separator, and a 4&#x02005;M LiFSA electrolyte were assembled in a two electrode beaker cell. The resulting beaker cell, a circulation cylinder, and a 2-position 6-port valve with a sampling loop were assembled. All these procedures were carried out in an Ar-filled glove box. Then, the system was transferred outside and connected to the gas flow system directly connected to a quadrupole mass spectrometer (OmniStar GSD301, Pfeiffer Vacuum) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S6</xref>). The galvanostatic charging test was conducted at a rate of 4.5&#x02005;mA g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (50.9&#x02005;&#x003bc;A) for 168&#x02005;h at room temperature (<italic>ca</italic>. 298&#x02005;K) with SI 1287 (Solartron) potentio/galvanostat. The gases in the cell were transferred to the sampling loop by using the circulating cylinder and the analysis was conducted every 12&#x02005;h with the mass spectrometer as follows: The gases in the sampling loop were purged with a carrier gas (He, 50&#x02005;mL min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) by switching the valve and transferred into the mass spectrometer. To remove a vapour of acetonitrile, the purged gases were passed through a cold trap (<italic>ca</italic>. 193&#x02005;K). The concentrations of O<sub>2</sub> (<italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> = 32) and CO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> = 44) were determined with the integrated peak areas of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> (with respect to that of Ar (<italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> = 40)), respectively.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Analysis of Peroxide in Cathodes</title><p>The charged or discharged cathodes were removed from the coin-type cell, washed three times with acetonitrile, and dried under vacuum. Then, the sample, 1&#x02005;g of ice water in a small glass container frozen with liquid nitrogen at 77&#x02005;K, and a small amount of Pt powder (&#x0003c;1&#x02005;mg) were put into the beaker cell (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S6</xref>) and the beaker cell was closed with a gas tight glass cap. The resulting beaker cell, a circulation cylinder, and a 2-position 6-port valve with a sampling loop were assembled. All these procedures were carried out in an Ar-filled glove box. Then, the system was quickly transferred outside and connected to the gas flow system directly connected to a quadrupole mass spectrometer (OmniStar GSD301, Pfeiffer Vacuum) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S6</xref>). Before the ice melted, the background oxygen concentration in the cell was analysed with the quadrupole mass spectrometer. Then, the sample was dispersed in the ice melting water and O<sub>2</sub> was evolved in the presence of a Pt catalyst. The amount of O<sub>2</sub> evolved was quantitatively estimated with the quadrupole mass spectrometer in the same way as that described in the section of measurements of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> evolution in the charging process. It was confirmed in a separate experiment that the amount of Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is quantitatively estimated with the amount of O<sub>2</sub> evolved in the presence of the Pt catalyst according to the reaction, Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> &#x02192; 0.5O<sub>2</sub> + Li<sub>2</sub>O. To confirm the origin of oxygen atoms in the peroxide in the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode, the labelled experiment was carried out by using H<sub>2</sub><sup>18</sup>O in an N<sub>2</sub>-filled glove box to prevent overlapping of the <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> value of <sup>36</sup>Ar with that of <sup>18</sup>O<sub>2</sub>. For the mass analysis of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode charged to 270&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, a signal at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> = 32 was observed and those at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> = 34 and 36 were not observed (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Figure S7</xref>). These results show that the oxygen atoms in the O<sub>2</sub> result from those in the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>N.M. conceived the project. S.O., H.O., K.Y. and Y.S. synthesized the material. S.O., Y.O. and Y.S. tested the battery, with direction from M.H., T.K., Y.Y., A.Y. and N.M. S.O. and Y.O. collected and analysed data for X-ray diffraction and X-ray absorption near edge structure measurements, with direction from M.H. and M.O. Y.O. designed and conducted experiments for gas phase analysis and peroxide analysis. E.T. collected and analysed data for electron microscopy, with direction from N.S. and Y.I. N.M. and T.K. supervised the project. S.O., Y.O., M.H., T.K. and N.M. wrote the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="d33e28" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep05684-s1.doc"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank T. Honma and H. Ofuchi (JASRI) for XANES measurements. This work is supported by the Japan Society of the Promotion of Science (JSPS) through its &#x0201c;Funding Program for World-Leading Innovative R&#x00026;D on Science and Technology (FIRST Program)&#x0201d; and Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Researches from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Poizot</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laruelle</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grugeon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Tarascon</surname><given-names>J-M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Nano-sized transition-metal oxides as negative-electrode materials for lithium-ion batteries</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>407</volume>, <fpage>496</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>499</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11028997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bervas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Investigation of the lithiation and delithiation conversion mechanisms of bismuth fluoride nanocomposites</article-title>. <source>J. Electrochem. Soc.</source>
<volume>153</volume>, <fpage>A799</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>A808</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Badway</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cosandey</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Amatucci</surname><given-names>G. G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Carbon-metal fluoride nanocomposites structure and electrochemistry of FeF<sub>3</sub>:C</article-title>. <source>J. Electrochem. Soc.</source>
<volume>150</volume>, <fpage>A1209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>A1218</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A polymer electrolyte-based rechargeable lithium/oxygen battery</article-title>. <source>J. Electrochem. Soc.</source>
<volume>143</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage> (<year>1996</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ogasawara</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>D&#x000e9;bart</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holzapfel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nov&#x000e1;k</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Rechargeable Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> electrode for lithium batteries</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>128</volume>, <fpage>1390</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1393</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16433559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Discharge characteristic of a non-aqueous electrolyte Li/O<sub>2</sub> battery</article-title>. <source>J. Power Sources</source>
<volume>195</volume>, <fpage>1235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1240</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.-C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gasteiger</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crumlin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McGuire, Jr</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Shao-Horn</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Electrocatalytic activity studies of select metal surfaces and implications in Li-air batteries</article-title>. <source>J. Electrochem. Soc.</source>
<volume>157</volume>, <fpage>A1016</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>A1025</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thapa</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Mesoporous &#x003b1;-MnO<sub>2</sub>/Pd catalyst air electrode for rechargeable lithium&#x02013;air battery</article-title>. <source>J. Power Sources</source>
<volume>196</volume>, <fpage>7016</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7020</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trahan</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Cobalt phthalocyanine catalyzed lithium-air batteries</article-title>. <source>J. Electrochem. Soc.</source>
<volume>160</volume>, <fpage>A1577</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>A1586</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sathiya</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Reversible anionic redox chemistry in high-capacity layered-oxide electrodes</article-title>. <source>Nat. Mater.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>827</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>835</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23852398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sathiya</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>High performance Li<sub>2</sub>Ru<sub>1&#x02212;<italic>y</italic></sub>Mn<italic><sub>y</sub></italic>O<sub>3</sub> (0.2 &#x02264; <italic>y</italic> &#x02264; 0.8) cathode materials for rechargeable lithium-ion batteries: Their understanding</article-title>. <source>Chem. Mater.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1131</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koga</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Different oxygen redox participation for bulk and surface: A possible global explanation for the cycling mechanism of Li<sub>1.20</sub>Mn<sub>0.54</sub>Co<sub>0.13</sub>Ni<sub>0.13</sub>O<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>J. Power Sources</source>
<volume>236</volume>, <fpage>250</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>258</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Oxygen contribution on Li-ion intercalation-deintercalation in LiCoO<sub>2</sub> investigated by O K-edge and Co L-edge X-ray absorption spectroscopy</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. B</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>2526</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2532</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Unusual stability of acetonitrile-based superconcentrated electrolytes for fast-charging lithium-ion batteries</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>136</volume>, <fpage>5039</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5046</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24654781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Antaya</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cearns</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reimers</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Dahn</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>In situ growth of layered, spinel, and rock-salt LiCoO<sub>2</sub> by laser ablation deposition</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Phys.</source>
<volume>76</volume>, <fpage>2799</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2806</lpage> (<year>1994</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>X-ray absorption spectroscopic studies at the cobalt <italic>K</italic>-edge on a reduced Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-supported rhenium-promoted cobalt Fischer-Tropsch catalyst</article-title>. <source>Chem. Mater.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1247</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Symmetry dependence of x-ray absorption near-edge structure at the metal <italic>K</italic> edge of 3<italic>d</italic> transition metal compounds</article-title>. <source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>79</volume>, <fpage>1918</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1920</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Farcy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pereira-Ramos</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Baffier</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Electrochemical properties of low temperature crystallized LiCoO<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>J. Electrochem. Soc.</source>
<volume>144</volume>, <fpage>1179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1184</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Narukawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Anti-fluorite type Li<sub>6</sub>CoO<sub>4</sub>, Li<sub>5</sub>FeO<sub>4</sub>, and Li<sub>6</sub>MnO<sub>4</sub> as the cathode for lithium secondary batteries</article-title>. <source>Solid State Ionics</source>
<volume>122</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luge</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Hoppe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A new cobaltate with isolated anion structure: Li<sub>6</sub>[CoO<sub>4</sub>]</article-title>. <source>Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem.</source>
<volume>534</volume>, <fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage> (<year>1986</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zane</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Some aspects of LiMn<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub> electrochemistry in the 4 volt range</article-title>. <source>J. Electrochem. Soc.</source>
<volume>142</volume>, <fpage>2551</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2557</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Freunberger</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Reactions in the rechargeable lithium-O<sub>2</sub> battery with alkyl carbonate electrolytes</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>133</volume>, <fpage>8040</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8047</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21524112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bethune</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shelby</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Girishkumar</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Luntz</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Solvents' critical role in nonaqueous lithium-oxygen battery electrochemistry</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. Lett.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>1161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1166</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ottakam Thotiyl</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freunberger</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The carbon electrode in nonaqueous Li-O<sub>2</sub> cells</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>135</volume>, <fpage>494</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>500</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23190204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Electrochemical performances of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode.</title><p>(a) Charge and discharge voltage curves in repeated charge/discharge cycles at 45&#x02005;mA g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. (b) Charge and discharge voltage curves at various current densities (13.5&#x02013;1080&#x02005;mA g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Each testing cell was charged to 200&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and then discharged to the cut off voltage of 2.0&#x02005;V at a constant current density.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep05684-f1"/></fig><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Co K-edge XANES spectra of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode at various charge and discharge capacities.</title><p>The current densities were 4.5&#x02005;mA g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The insets show the absorption edge regions of the spectra. (a) Charge process. (b) Discharge process.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep05684-f2"/></fig><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Analysis of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathodes after the charge and the discharge.</title><p>(a) and (d) Analytical peroxide amounts of the cathodes after the charge (a) and discharge (d). (b) and (e) Co K-edge XANES absorption edge positions of the cathodes after the charge (b) and discharge (e). (c) and (f) Charge (c) and discharge (f) voltage curves at current density of 4.5&#x02005;mA g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep05684-f3"/></fig><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Voltage, gas evolution, XRD peak intensity of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O cathode in the charge process.</title><p>(a) The voltage curve. (b) Cumulative amounts of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> evolved in the charge process at the current density of 4.5&#x02005;mA g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The slope of 0.25 O<sub>2</sub>/e<sup>&#x02212;</sup> indicates theoretical rate of O<sub>2</sub> evolution according to the reaction, 2O<sup>2&#x02212;</sup> &#x02192; 4e<sup>&#x02212;</sup> + O<sub>2</sub>. (c) The XRD 111 peak intensity of Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O. The peak intensity at 0&#x02005;mAh g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> was taken as a unity. The black line is a theoretical line of change in the peak intensity.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep05684-f4"/></fig><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>HRTEM image and FFT pattern of the Co-doped Li<sub>2</sub>O.</title><p>(a) HRTEM image after the charge. The areas in red circles were obtained by the inverse Fourier transformation of the spots in the FFT pattern that are attributed to Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. The periods of the fringe in the areas were confirmed to be equal to those in Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. (b) FFT pattern of the HRTEM image. The white circles are on the basis of Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep05684-f5"/></fig></floats-group></article>