<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Comparative advantage and strategic specialization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Wiley</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-07-03">2017-07-03</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Minwook</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
							<email>mwkang@ntu.edu.sg</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Nanyang Technological University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SG">Singapore</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Economics, School of Social Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanyang Technological University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>14 Nanyang Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>637332</postCode>
									<country key="SG">Singapore</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Comparative advantage and strategic specialization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Review of International Economics</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Rev Int Econ</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0965-7576</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="19"/>
							<date type="published" when="2017-07-03" />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/roie.12300</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T21:11+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>This paper shows that a strong comparative advantage is necessary for free trade and specialization in a 2 3 2 symmetric Ricardian model to be achieved in a Nash equilibrium. Governments strategically control labor distribution across industries, and representative agents maximize Cobb-Douglas utilities. A Nash equilibrium with complete specialization is achieved if and only if relative productivity exceeds a key value of 3, which is considered a very large number based on previous empirical studies. This paper also introduces a two-stage game where each government chooses labor distribution first and then tariffs. In this two-stage game, complete specialization is never achieved for any relative productivity level. Finally, by generalizing the Cobb-Douglas model into constant elasticity of substitution (CES) preferences, I show that if immiserizing growth effects exist, complete specialization could not be achieved for any level of relative productivity.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">| IN TRO DUCT IO N</head><p>The two most important questions in international trade are the normative question of "why should nations pursue free trade?" and the positive question of "do nations have incentives to pursue free trade?" The former question is well explained by David Ricardo, in that comparative advantage is the source of mutual benefits from world trade. This paper indicates that the answer to the second question also relies on comparative advantage; a strong comparative advantage is necessary for nations to strategically pursue free trade in a Ricardian model. Defining the degree of comparative advantage as the relative productivity between more and less competitive industries in a symmetric Ricardian model with Cobb-Douglas preferences, this paper shows that a Nash equilibrium with complete specialization is achieved if and only if the measure exceeds a key value of 3, a very large number based on previous empirical studies. This paper also shows that complete specialization cannot be achieved if the government implements import tariffs in addition to labor distribution policies, or if there exist immiserizing growth effects.</p><p>A rational government wants to manipulate the terms of trade by protecting the less competitive sector and controlling the more competitive one. However, protectionism under strong comparative advantage results in a decrease in the domestic production size and consequently a decrease in its welfare. Therefore, a strong mutual comparative advantage should be present in order to achieve free trade. Otherwise, the government would use trade policies such as export subsidies or import tariffs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Costinot, Donaldson, Vogel, and Werning (2015)</ref> explored the relationship between comparative advantage and optimal trade taxes. Their optimal trade taxes aim to control the production size of more competitive sectors with comparative advantage to manipulate the terms of trade. <ref type="bibr">1</ref> The difference between <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Costinot et al. (2015)</ref> and this paper is that the former considered import tariff and export subsidy as their strategies with a passive foreign government whereas the latter considers governments' intervention in labor distribution in a Nash equilibrium.</p><p>Even though this paper assumes that governments directly control the labor distribution across industries rather than using indirect tools such as trade taxes, both <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Costinot et al. (2015)</ref> and this paper are based on the same main logic that welfare can be improved by manipulating the terms of trade. 2 There are many examples of policies that effectively reallocate labor towards low productivity section. Governments use various types of assistance policies such as domestic subsidies, antidumping laws, and industry bailouts to help less competitive domestic industries. These polices potentially reallocate the labor distribution from high to low productive sectors.</p><p>The main model of this paper uses a simplified framework of Ricardian models described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Dornbusch, Fischer, and Samuelson (1977)</ref> where Cobb-Douglas utility functions are used and the number of goods is two. In this paper, a representative agent in each country has a Cobb-Douglas utility function, which is considered to have a "medium" value of elasticity of substitution. <ref type="bibr">3</ref> The elasticity of substitution derived from the utility function is the main factor in determining the equilibrium prices, or equivalently, the terms of trade. To maximize the utility of the representative agent, each government strategically determines the quantities of labor in the two industries. <ref type="bibr">4</ref> A government's incentive for specialization primarily depends on how much the two countries have a mutual comparative advantage. To define a measure of comparative advantage, this paper introduces a symmetric model in which one country's labor productivity of its more (less) competitive industry is equal to the other country's labor productivity in the more (less) competitive industry. With the help of the symmetric structure, the measure of comparative advantage is defined as the ratio of higher labor productivity to lower labor productivity, which is equal to the relative autarky price. The main results are that (1) the degree of specialization strictly increases in comparative advantage, and (2) only if comparative advantage exceeds or equals to the number 3 would a complete specialization be achieved in a Nash equilibrium.</p><p>The value of relative productivity 3 is a very large number based on previous empirical evidence. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Costinot, Donaldson, and Komunjer (2012)</ref> measured relative productivities across 21 countries and 13 industries based on the year 1997. 5 Normalizing all industries to the United States and in all countries for the food industry, there is no single value of relative productivity among 260 values (20 countries 3 13 industries) that is greater than 3 or less than 1/3. Among the 260 values, 253 of them are in the range of [0.5,2]. The maximum is 2.74, which is the relative productivity of the Korean chemicals industry relative to that of the United States. The minimum value is 0.49, which is the relative productivity of the Hungarian transport industry relative to that of the United States. Considering that 3 is an unrealistically large value of relative productivity, the main result in this paper may imply that it would be hard for countries to agree on free trade and complete specialization without any international organizations. <ref type="bibr">6</ref> The model in this paper is closely related to the theory of immiserizing growth developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bhagwati (1958)</ref>, which indicates that export-biased growth might deteriorate the terms of trade sufficiently such as to decrease the welfare of the economy. <ref type="bibr">7</ref> In the context of the Ricardian model, export-biased growth can be interpreted as the expansion of the more competitive industry without contraction of the less competitive industry. However, the government's action on labor distribution not only has the expansion effect (i.e., immiserizing growth effect) but also the contraction effect. Therefore, this paper investigates how each effect, separately, affects the government's incentive to avoid complete specialization.</p><p>It is well known that a lower elasticity of substitution increases the possibility of having immiserizing growth effects (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bhagwati, Brecher, &amp; Hatta, 1983</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">, 1984</ref>. Therefore, I extend the baseline model by including a constant elasticity of substitution (CES) utility function with a general elasticityof-substitution parameter. With the extended model, I show that if the elasticity of substitution is lower than 0.5, which is the condition for the existence of immiserizing growth effect, complete specialization could never be achieved for any value of relative productivity. Although this paper shows that there is no immiserizing growth effect with Cobb-Douglas utility functions, the other effects (including the direct effect and terms-of-trade effects from the contraction) prevents complete specialization if the relative productivity is smaller than 3.</p><p>This paper also investigates how Nash equilibrium specialization is determined when governments are allowed to implement import tariffs. Specifically, I introduce a two-stage game where each government first strategically chooses labor distribution and then optimal import tariffs. This paper shows that complete specialization can never be achieved in such a two-stage game. This result of missing complete specialization is closely related to <ref type="bibr">Riezman (1988, 1990)</ref>, where agents are endowed with goods. The two-stage game in this paper reproduces the results of <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kennan and Riezman (1990)</ref>, where the optimal tariffs are a function of the endowments. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kennan and Riezman (1990)</ref> show that a more equal (asymmetrical) distribution of endowments between the two sectors results in lower (higher) tariffs and thus higher (lower) utility in a Nash tariff war. In the two-stage game, "endowments" are endogenously chosen by the government's strategic action on labor distribution. Governments know that if they choose more specialized labor distribution, which implies a more asymmetrical endowment distribution in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kennan and Riezman's (1990)</ref> model, it will end up with the Nash equilibrium with higher tariffs and thus lower utilities. To avoid this destructive tariff war under asymmetrical endowment distribution, governments would have incentives to avoid specialization of labor distribution in the two-stage game. The main results of this paper support this logic, as it shows that the degree of specialization under the two-stage game is strictly lower than that under the onestage game.</p><p>The rest of the paper proceeds as follows. Section 2 introduces the Ricardian model with Cobb-Douglas utility. Section 3 derives the best response functions of the labor inputs. Section 4 discusses how the degree of comparative advantage affects the Nash equilibrium trade specialization. Section 5 introduces a two-stage game where each government strategically chooses labor distribution first and then tariffs. Section 6 investigates how the theory of immiserizing growth is related to the main model of this paper. Section 7 concludes the paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">| THE M ODE L</head><p>There are two countries A and B and two goods x and y. The labor productivities of good x in countries A and B are ffiffi ffi k p and 1= ffiffi ffi k p , respectively. The labor productivities of good y in countries A and B are 1= ffiffi ffi k p and ffiffi ffi k p , respectively. The two countries are endowed with the same amount of labor unit 1. They can invest the labor to produce either good x or good y. The country A's strategy a 2 ½0; 1 represents the amount of labor units invested on good x while country B's strategy b 2 ½0; 1 represents the amount of labor units invested on good y. The production plan in countries A and B is shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>.</p><p>Without loss of generality, we assume that k ! 1. Where k 5 1, the labor productivities of two goods in both countries are identical. Where k is strictly greater than 1, the absolute and comparative advantages across the two countries arise. Country A has k times higher labor productivity in producing good x than country B while country B has k times higher labor productivity in producing good y than country A. Therefore, we can denote k as the degree of comparative advantage (DCA). 8 For k &gt; 1, complete specialization is achieved if two countries' strategies a and b are both equal to 1.</p><p>The representative agent's utility function in each country follows Cobb-Douglas preferences:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">U A x A ; y A ð Þ5 ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi x A y A p and U B x B ; y B ð Þ5 ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi x B y B p :</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">| THE B ES T RES P ONS E F U NCTI O NS</head><p>Given the two countries' strategies, a and b, country A's maximization problem is given by max</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">x A ;y A U A x A ; y A ð Þ; subject to px A 1qy A a ffiffi ffi k p p1 12a ffiffi ffi k p q;</formula><p>( <ref type="formula">1)</ref>where p and q are prices of good x and good y, respectively. From Equation (1), we can derive country A's indirect utility function as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">I A p; q; a ð Þ5 a ffiffi ffi k p p1 12a ffiffi k p q ffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi 2pq p 5a ffiffi ffi k 2 r ffiffi ffi p q r 1 12a ffiffiffiffiffi 2k p ffiffi ffi q p r :<label>(2)</label></formula><p>By the market clearing condition, we can derive the relative price as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">p q 5 12a ffiffi k p 1b ffiffi ffi k p a ffiffi ffi k p 1 12b ffiffi k p :<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Plugging Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">3</ref>into Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">2</ref>, we get country A's utility as a function of a and b:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">I A ðajbÞ5a ffiffi ffi k 2 r ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 12a ffiffi k p 1b ffiffi ffi k p a ffiffi ffi k p 1 12b ffiffi k p v u u t 1 12a ffiffiffiffiffi 2k p ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi a ffiffi ffi k p 1 12b ffiffi k p 12a ffiffi k p 1b ffiffi ffi k p v u u t :<label>(4)</label></formula><p>The function I A ðajbÞ has the following properties:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">(i) I 00</formula><p>A ðajbÞ&lt;0 for all a; b 2 ½0; 1-(see the proof in Appendix (A1)) (ii) I 0 A ð0jbÞ&gt;0 for all b 2 ½0; 1-(see the proof in Appendix (A2)) (iii) I 0 A ð1jbÞ&lt;0 for all b 2 ½0; 1, if k &lt; 3-(see the proof in Appendix (A3)) (iv)</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">I 0 A ð1j1Þ&gt;0, if k &gt; 3-(see the proof in Appendix (A4)) (v) I 0</formula><p>A ð1j1Þ50, if k 5 3-(see the proof in Appendix (A4)) A ðajbÞ5 o 2 I A ðajbÞ oa 2 . Property (i) is necessary to prove the existence of the best response function a(b). Property (i) implies that for all b 2 ½0; 1, I A ðajbÞ is either strictly monotone in a 2 ½0; 1 or has an interior maximum value. In either case, for any b 2 ½0; 1, there exists a unique value of a 2 ½0; 1 that maximizes I A ðajbÞ.</p><p>From properties (i), (ii), and (iii), we know that the image of the best response function excludes 1 if k &lt; 3. This implies that country A (B) has no incentive to achieve the complete specialization no matter what country B (A)'s labor distribution is if the degree of comparative advantage is small enough, i.e., k &lt; 3.</p><p>Properties (i) and (iv) imply that if k ! 3 the best response function has a maximum value 1 if b 5 1. This also implies that country A (B) has an incentive to achieve complete specialization if the degree of comparative advantage k is greater or equal to 3 and country B (A) has achieved complete specialization.</p><p>Finally, property (v) implies that where k 5 3, country A (B) has an incentive to achieve complete specialization if and only if country B (A) does.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">| THE N AS H EQ UI LI BRI UM</head><p>Because of the symmetric structure between the two countries, the economy has a Nash equilibrium where a 5 b. The Nash equilibrium (a*,b*) satisfies the following equation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">I 0 A ða Ã ja Ã Þ5I 0 A ðb Ã jb Ã Þ5I 0 B ða Ã ja Ã Þ5I 0 B ðb Ã jb Ã Þ50:<label>(5)</label></formula><p>Solving Equation (5), we have 9</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">a Ã 5b Ã 5 3k21 6k212k 2 ;<label>(6)</label></formula><p>where k &lt; 3. The next step is to verify that the solution (6) is the unique and stable Nash equilibrium, which is proven with the following properties (vi) to (viii).</p><p>(vi) If k &lt; 3, there is a unique solution a* for the equation I 0</p><p>A ða Ã ja Ã Þ50, i.e., a(a*) 5 a*. The solution is that a Ã 5ð3k21Þ=ð6k212k 2 Þ-(see the proof in Appendix (A5)) (vii) If k &lt; 3, the slope of the best response function a(b) at ða Ã ; b Ã Þ5 3k21 6k212k 2 ; 3k21 6k212k 2 À Á is strictly less than 1. Therefore, the Nash equilibrium is stable-(see the proof in Appendix (A6)) (viii) If k ! 3, there is no solution for a Ã 2 ½0; 1 for the equation I 0</p><p>A ða Ã ja Ã Þ50-(see the proof in Appendix (A7)).</p><p>Properties (vi) and (vii) directly show that the unique stable Nash equilibrium where k &lt; 3, is</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">a Ã ; b Ã ð Þ5 3k21 6k212k 2 ; 3k21 6k212k 2<label>(7)</label></formula><p>which is strictly less than 1, implying that complete specialization is not achieved if k &lt; 3. Where k ! 3, by property (viii), we know that the best response function a(b) does not intersect the 458 line for any value of b 2 ½0; 1Þ. The only point, where the two best response functions a(b) and bðaÞ intersect, is (1, 1), which is also the unique and stable Nash equilibrium. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figures 1(a)</ref> and (b) illustrate the Nash equilibrium with best response functions for the cases: k &lt; 3 and k ! 3.</p><p>The main result of this paper is summarized in the following proposition.</p><p>Proposition 1 Complete specialization is achieved if and only if the degree of comparative advantage (DCA) is equal to or greater than 3. Where the DCA is less than 3, the degree of specialization strictly increases in the DCA. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> shows the relationship between the degree of (Nash equilibrium) specialization and the degree of comparative advantage. The graph shows that (1) the degree of specialization increases with the degree of comparative advantage and (2) the complete specialization is achieved where the degree of comparative advantage is greater than 3. In a closed economy, the optimal value of a is 1/2 regardless of the degree of comparative advantage. Therefore, for any value of k 2 ð1; 1Þ, the degree of specialization, i.e., the Nash equilibrium a*(5 b*) is higher in the open economy than that in the closed economy.</p><p>The reason why complete specialization is not achieved in a lower level of comparative advantage is attributed to the terms-of-trade effect. If one country (country A) specializes in the production of one good (good x), the other country (country B) would take advantage of this by producing both goods (goods x and y) so that the relative price of good y compared with that of good x will be high owing to the scarcity of good y. In this case, the terms of trade become favorable to country B. If the degree of comparative advantage is low, this terms-of-trade effect dominates the welfare loss from the efficient production plan and consequently countries would choose nonspecialized labor distribution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">| TW O-S TAGE G AM E WI T H LABO R DI S TR IB UTI ON P OLI CY A ND TA RI F F S</head><p>This section incorporates the conventional trade policy, import tariffs, into the main model of this paper following <ref type="bibr">Riezman (1988, 1990)</ref>. Specifically, I introduce a two-stage game in which each government strategically determines labor distribution first, and then determines optimal tariff policy. Once the labor distribution is fixed, this model is the same as <ref type="bibr">Riezman (1988, 1990)</ref>, in which agents are endowed with goods. The main result of this section is that complete specialization in this two-stage game is never achieved for any degree of comparative advantage. This result is related to <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Kennan and Riezman's (1990)</ref> finding that a more asymmetrical distribution of endowments between export and import sectors results in higher tariffs and lower utilities. Because asymmetrical distribution implies a high degree of specialization in the model, governments would try to deviate from complete specialization to avoid severe tariff wars.</p><p>Given (a,b), we assume that countries A and B impose proportional tariffs. Then, country A's budget constraint is</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">px A 1q 11t A ð Þy A pa ffiffi ffi k p 1q 11t A ð Þ 12a ffiffi ffi k p 1S A ;<label>(8)</label></formula><p>where t A represents country A's proportional tariff and S A is the lump-sum subsidy. The collected tariff is rebated to the representative consumer, so we have S A 5q Ã t A y Ã A 2 12a ffiffi k p , where q* is the equilibrium price of good y and y Ã A is country A's equilibrium consumption of good y. In the same way, country B's budget constraint is</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">p 11t B ð Þx B 1qy B p 11t B ð Þ 12b ffiffi ffi k p 1qb ffiffi ffi k p 1S B ;<label>(9)</label></formula><p>where t B represents country B's proportional tariff and</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">S B 5q Ã t B y Ã B 2 12b ffiffi k p</formula><p>is the lump-sum subsidy.</p><p>This section proves that under the described two-stage game, complete specialization cannot be achieved in the Nash equilibrium. By contradiction, assume that the two countries are in the state of complete specialization, i.e., ða; bÞ5ð1; 1Þ. In this case, as shown in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kennan and Riezman (1988)</ref>, the Nash equilibrium tariffs ðt Ã A ; t Ã B Þ diverge to infinity, i.e., ðt Ã A ; t Ã B Þ5ð1; 1Þ. Then, the consumers cannot afford to buy the imported good and, consequently, utility will converge to zero (see Appendix B for the proof). <ref type="bibr">10</ref> If country A deviates from complete specialization, i.e., a &lt; 1, the utility value under autarky will be positive since x A 5 a, y B 51a, and I A 5 ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi að12aÞ p &gt;0. After the trade, country A can increase its utility value more than that under autarky. Therefore, when country B is in the state of complete specialization, country A has an incentive to deviate from complete specialization. Under the symmetric structure of this model, both countries have mutual incentives to deviate from complete specialization. Therefore, for any degree of comparative advantage, complete specialization could not be achieved in the two-stage game.</p><p>Proposition 2 In a two-stage game where each government chooses the labor distribution first and then import tariffs, complete specialization cannot be achieved in the Nash equilibrium.</p><p>This paper also performs the numerical analysis for the Nash equilibrium specialization in the twostage game. 11 <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref> compares the degree of specialization under the one-stage with that under the two-stage game. The numerical analysis indicates that the degree of specialization under the two-stage game is strictly lower than that of the one-stage game. This is because as country A's degree of specialization is higher, country B's tariff policy is more effective in decreasing the world price of country A's export good. To avoid country B's tariff attacks, country A would strategically choose less specialized industry composition. In this symmetric model, the same logic can be applied to country B. Therefore, both countries have mutual incentives to pursue lower degree of specialization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">| IM MI S E RI ZI NG GR OW TH AN D S TRA TEG IC S P ECI AL IZ ATI ON</head><p>The model in this paper is closely related to the immiserizing growth model developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Bhagwati (1958)</ref>. The immiserizing growth effect implies that an increase in the production of exporting sectors decreases the price of the exporting goods sufficiently to decrease welfare. In the Ricardian model, an expansion in the exporting sector necessarily implies a contraction in the importing sector. Therefore, this paper investigates how the expansionary and contractionary effects separately affect welfare. I modify the indirect utility function of country A in Equation (2) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">I A p; q; a; a 0 ð Þ 5 a ffiffi ffi k p p1 12a 0 ffiffi k p q ffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi 2pq p 5a ffiffi ffi k 2 r ffiffi ffi p q r 1 12a 0 ffiffiffiffiffi 2k p ffiffi ffi q p r ;<label>(11)</label></formula><p>where increases in a and a 0 represent the expansion and the contraction effects, respectively. If a 0 5 a, the indirect utility function in Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">11</ref>is the same as that in Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_2">2</ref>. We assume that country B is in the state of complete specialization, i.e., b 5 1. Then, the relative price in terms of (a,a 0 ) is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">p q 5 12a 0 ffiffi k p 1 ffiffi ffi k p a ffiffi ffi k p 5 12a 0 ak 1 1 a :<label>(12)</label></formula><p>Then, from Equations (11) and (12), we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">I A a; a 0 ð Þ5 ffiffi ffi a p ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi 12a 0 1k p ffiffi ffi 2 p ffiffi ffi k p |fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} 5EXða;a 0 Þ 1 12a 0 ð Þ ffiffi ffi a p ffiffi ffi 2 p ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi 12a 0 1k p |fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} 5IMða;a 0 Þ :<label>(13)</label></formula><p>There are two terms in country A's utility function in Equation (13). The first term EX(a,a 0 ) is the utility contribution of the exporting sector, while the second <ref type="figure">term IM(a,a 0 )</ref> is that of the importing sector. The exporting-sector contribution EX(a,a 0 ) is affected by both a and a 0 . By the definition of the immiserizing growth model, country A experiences the immiserizing growth effect if oEX(a,a 0 )/oa &lt; 0, which means that expansion of the exporting sector decreases welfare. With Cobb-Douglas utility function, we have oEX(a,a 0 )/oa &gt; 0 (see Equation <ref type="formula">14</ref>), which implies that there is no immiserizing growth effect. EX(a,a 0 ) is also affected by a 0 because the contraction of the import sector affects the relative price of the exporting good. As a 0 increases, the relative price p/q decreases and thus, EX(a,a 0 ) decreases, i.e., oEX(a,a 0 )/oa 0 &lt; 0. oIM(a,a 0 )/oa is equal to zero, where (a,a 0 ) <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">5 (1,1)</ref>, because of the domestic production of the imported good where a 0 5 1 is zero. Lastly, we have oIM(a,a 0 )/oa 0 &lt; 0, because the lower production of imported goods negatively affects utility.</p><p>Where (a,a 0 ) 5 (1,1), we derive the following four effects from Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_15">13</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">oEXða; a 0 Þ=oa5 ffiffi ffi k p =2; (14) oEXða; a 0 Þ=oa 0 521= 2 ffiffi ffi k p ; (15) oIMða; a 0 Þ=oa50;<label>(16)</label></formula><p>and oIMða; a 0 Þ=oa 0 521= ffiffi ffi k p :</p><p>If the sum of the four effects from Equations (14) to (17) (i.e., ffiffi ffi</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">k p =221= 2 ffiffi ffi k p À Á 21= ffiffi ffi k p</formula><p>is negative), country A would have an incentive to deviate from complete specialization. Similar to the result in Proposition 1, if k is smaller than 3, the sum is negative; the sum is zero if k 5 3; and the sum is positive if k &lt; 3.</p><p>While there is no immiserizing growth effect with Cobb-Douglas utility functions, it would be interesting to investigate the relationship between the immiserizing growth effect and strategic specialization under more general utility functions. As indicated in <ref type="bibr">Hatta (1983, 1984)</ref>, the immiserizing growth effect can exist for low values of elasticity of substitution between export and import goods. Therefore, in this section, we generalize the utility function with CES parameters:</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">U A x A ; y A ð Þ5 1 2 x E21 E A 1 1 2 y E21 E A E E21 and U B x B ; y B ð Þ5 1 2 x E21 E B 1 1 2 y E21 E B E E21 ;<label>(18)</label></formula><p>where E represents the elasticity of substitution between the export and import goods. As E ! 1, the utility function converges to Cobb-Douglas utility such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">U A x A ; y A ð Þ5 ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi x A y A p and U B x B ; y B ð Þ5 ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi x B y B p</formula><p>: With the CES utility function, we have the following indirect utility function and the relative price if b 5 1:</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">I A p; q; a; a 0 ð Þ 5 a ffiffi ffi k p p1 12a 0 ffiffi ffi k p q = 1 2 E p 12E 1 1 2 E q 12E 1=ð12EÞ 5a ffiffi ffi k p 1 2 E 1 1 2 E q p 12E ! 1=ðE21Þ 1 12a 0 ffiffi ffi k p 1 2 E p q 12E 1 1 2 E ! 1=ðE21Þ<label>(19)</label></formula><p>and p q 5</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">12a 0 ffiffi k p 1 ffiffi ffi k p a ffiffi ffi k p ! 1=E :<label>(20)</label></formula><p>From Equations (19) and (20), we can derive country A's utility function in terms of (a,a 0 ):</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">I A a; a 0 ð Þ5 a ffiffi ffi k p 1 2 1 1 2 a ffiffi ffi k p 12a 0 ffiffi ffi k p 1 ffiffi ffi k p 0 B B @ 1 C C A 12E E 0 B B B @ 1 C C C A 1=ðE21Þ |fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} EXða;a 0 Þ 1 12a 0 ffiffi ffi k p 1 2 12a 0 ffiffi ffi k p 1 ffiffi ffi k p a ffiffi ffi k p 0 B B @ 1 C C A 12E E 1 1 2 0 B B B @ 1 C C C A 1=ðE21Þ |fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl}</formula><p>IMða;a 0 Þ :</p><p>Under the same logic as the Cobb-Douglas utility case, we can investigate country A's incentive to deviate from complete specialization (i.e., (a,a 0 ) 5 (1,1)) when country B is in the state of complete specialization, i.e., b 5 1. The four different effects when (a,a 0 ) 5 (1,1) and b 5 1 are as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">oEXða; a 0 Þ=oa5 ð2112EÞ 2E ffiffi ffi k p ;<label>(21)</label></formula><p>oEXða; a 0 Þ=oa 0 52</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">1 2E ffiffi ffi k p &lt;0;<label>(22)</label></formula><p>oIMða; a 0 Þ=oa50;</p><p>and oIMða; a 0 Þ=oa 0 52 1 ffiffi ffi k p &lt;0:</p><p>Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_24">21</ref>indicates that there exists an immiserizing growth effect if the elasticity of substitution (E) is smaller than or equal to 0.5. <ref type="bibr">12</ref> Because the other effects in Equations (22) to (24) are smaller than or equal to zero, having immiserizing growth effects is the sufficient condition for missing complete specialization in a Nash equilibrium for any level of DCA (k). This is summarized in the following proposition.</p><p>Proposition 3 If the immiserizing growth effect exists (i.e., the elasticity of substitution is lower than 0.5), complete specialization is not achieved for any level of comparative advantage. (See the proof in Appendix (A8).)</p><p>Letting the sum of the four effects from Equations (22) to (24) be zero, we have a simple relationship between E and k, E5 k11 ð Þ= 2k22 ð Þ, which is plotted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref>. The area below the curve indicates nonspecialization parameter combinations of ðE; kÞ. For E&lt;0:5 a country will not fully specialize for any value of k. For the Cobb-Douglas case explored in this paper, where E51, k needs to be more than 3 for complete specialization. For E to 1 (perfect substitutes), countries fully specialize for any k &gt; 1. Moreover, the graph shows that a country will not fully specialize if the immiserizing growth effect exists (i.e., the elasticity of substitution is lower than 0.5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">| CONC LUD IN G REM ARK S</head><p>The main finding of this paper is that when the government can control labor distribution, strong comparative advantage is necessary for complete specialization to be achieved in a Nash equilibrium. This paper also investigates how immiserizing growth effects are related to incomplete specialization in a CES framework. From the stylized model, this paper shows that the existence of immiserizing growth effects is the sufficient condition for missing complete specialization. Finally, this paper introduces a two-stage game where governments choose labor distribution and then optimal tariffs. In this two-stage game, complete specialization is never achieved for any degree of comparative advantage. All of these results imply that it would be difficult for countries to agree on free trade without any help from international organizations.</p><p>The alternative explanation for incomplete specialization might be a commodity-aggregation problem. While 1-or 2-digit Standard International Trade Classification (SITC) results in a smaller degree of complete specialization across countries, finer digit levels (such as 3 or 4 digits) show different patterns. For example, both the United States and China have strong manufacturing export industries but the United States is more specialized in transportation equipment while China is more specialized in electronic equipment. Another explanation for the missing complete specialization could be from the Ricardo-Viner model, in which there are immobile factor endowments such as land and capital. In contrast to the classical Ricardian model where labor productivity is constant, the marginal return of labor decreases as the quantity of labor input increases in the Ricardo-Viner model. This diminishing marginal-return effect prevents countries from completely giving up their less competitive industries.</p><p>Another remaining question is how the elasticity of substitution between export and import goods affects the Nash equilibrium of specialization. The main reason why countries avoid specialization is that they want to improve the terms of trade through strategic labor distribution policy. Therefore, it is expected that for lower elasticity of substitution values, complete specialization is difficult to achieve, as shown in Section 6. However, under perfect substitutes utility, i.e., Uðx; yÞ5x1y, it is apparent that the Nash equilibrium with complete specialization would be achieved for any degree of comparative advantage, because the prices are not affected by labor distribution in this case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p>The author appreciates helpful comments from the two anonymous referees, Xiaoping Chen, Wilfred Ethier, Pinelopi Koujianou Goldberg, Karl Shell, and Lei Sandy Ye, and, in addition, wishes to thank Linh My Ton for research assistance. The author gratefully acknowledges research support from Nanyang Technological University AcRF Tier-1 Grant (RG171/14).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>NOTE S</head><p>1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Brunnermeier and Sannikov (2015)</ref> also indicated that government's capital control in undercapitalized countries can recover the optimal terms of trade and, therefore, improve welfare because firms in those countries do not internalize the negative effects of too high investment on the terms of trade. <ref type="bibr">2</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bagwell and Staiger (2011)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Broda, Limao, and Weinstein (2008)</ref> suggested empirical evidence that countries use optimal tariffs in order to manipulate the terms of trade. <ref type="bibr">3</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Dornbusch, Fischer, and Samuelson (1977)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Eaton and Kortum (2002)</ref> used an identical Cobb-Douglas preference in a Ricardian model with a continuum of goods. 4 Many research papers have shown that the existence of protectionism such as tariffs, quota, and environmental regulations is the state of Nash equilibrium because countries try to improve the terms of trade through protectionism. For Nash tariff wars, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Johnson (1950)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Gorman (1958)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kennan and Riezman (1988)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Gros (1987)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Syropoulos (2002)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Zissimos (2009)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Ogawa (2012)</ref>. For Nash quota wars, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Rodriguez (1974)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Tower (1975)</ref>. For strategic environmental regulations, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Barrett (1994)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Kennedy (1994)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Burguet and Sempere (2003)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Bhattacharya and Pal (2010)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">5</ref> The list of 13 industries is food, textiles, wood, paper, fuel, chemicals, plastic, minerals, metals, machinery, electrical transport and manufacturing not elsewhere classified. The list of 21 countries is Australia, Belgium-Luxembourg, Czech Republic, Denmark, Spain, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Ireland, Italy, Japan, Korea, the Netherlands, Poland, Portugal, Slovakia, Sweden, United Kingdom, and United States. The measures of relative productivity are computed using relative producer prices from the Groningen Growth and Development Centre (GGDC) Productivity Level Database. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Inklaar and Timmer (2008)</ref> for details. <ref type="bibr">6</ref> Depending on the choice of a country for normalization rather than the United States, some relative productivities might exceed 3. However, considering U.S. markets share the largest portion in the world economy, using the United States as the standard country would be most appropriate. <ref type="bibr">7</ref> Also see <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bhagwati and Johnson (1960)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bhagwati (1968</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Bhagwati ( , 1969</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Bhagwati et al. (1984)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">8</ref> Once the representative agent's smooth preferences are revealed, comparative advantage can be interpreted as differences in relative autarky prices between the two countries. Because of Cobb-Douglas utility functions, the measure of comparative advantage based on relative autkary prices is identical to that based on relative productivity. 9 See the proof in Appendix (A5). <ref type="bibr">10</ref> The Metzler paradox can also explain why the two countries have a mutual destructive tariff war under complete specialization. The relative domestic price of the foreign good under complete specialization is</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">q 11t A ð Þ p 5 ð11t A Þð21t B Þ 21t A :<label>(10)</label></formula><p>10 (It can be derived from Equation (B3) in Appendix B.) From Equation (10), we know that an increase in t A increases the relative domestic price of the imported good. This is the Metzler paradox, in which the imposition of a tariff on imports decreases the relative internal price of that good. Under the paradoxical price changes, an increase in tariff will necessarily increase real purchasing power for domestic consumers. 11 The Matlab code is downloadable in mwkang.site11.com/code/rie2016. <ref type="bibr">12</ref> The Ricardian model introduced in this paper has a combination of effects that include expansion and contraction, so it is not obvious whether the condition oEX(a,a 0 )/oa &lt; 0 clearly represents the immiserizing growth effect. To clarify this issue, it is worth presenting a simple model of endowment economy. With the same CES utility functions as in Equation 18, country A's endowment for good (x, y) is ffiffi ffi k p a; 0 À Á and country B's endowment is 0; ffiffi ffi k p a 0 À Á . In this endowment economy, there exists closed form solutions for the equilibrium allocations, and the condition for country A's welfare to decrease as a increases is that E &lt; 0.5 for any value of a 0 &gt; 0, a ! a 0 , and k &gt; 0, which is the same as the condition in Equation (21).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIGU RE 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The Nash equilibrium [Colour figure can be viewed at wileyonlinelibrary.com] FIGU RE 2 Comparative advantage and specialization [Colour figure can be viewed at wileyonlinelibrary.com]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIGU RE 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Comparative advantage and specialization in the two-stage game [Colour figure can be viewed at wileyonlinelibrary.com]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>FIGU RE 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>The elasticity of substitution and complete specialization [Colour figure can be viewed at wileyonlinelibrary.com]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The amount of production</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="5">Good x</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Good y</cell></row><row><cell>Country A</cell><cell cols="2">a</cell><cell>ffiffi ffi k p</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>ð</cell><cell cols="2">12a</cell><cell>Þ=</cell><cell>ffiffi ffi k p</cell></row><row><cell>Country B</cell><cell>ð</cell><cell cols="2">12b</cell><cell>Þ=</cell><cell>p</cell><cell>ffiffi ffi k</cell><cell cols="2">b</cell><cell>p</cell><cell>ffiffi ffi k</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>How to cite this article: Kang M. Comparative advantage and strategic specialization. Rev Int Econ. 2018;26:1-19. https://doi.org/10.1111/roie.12300 APPENDIX A: PROOFS A1 | Proof of property (i) I A ðajbÞ is given by</p><p>The function (A1) is composed of two parts: A and B. I will show that each part is strictly concave in a where 0 &lt; a &lt; 1. Part A in (A1) can be expressed as</p><p>Replacing 11bk and 12b k with t 1 (where 1&lt;t 1 &lt;11kÞ and t 2 (where 0&lt;t 2 &lt;1=kÞ, respectively, the second derivative of (A2) with respect to a is</p><p>Because the ranges for t 1 and t 2 are 1&lt;t 1 &lt;11k and 0&lt;t 2 &lt;1=k;</p><p>Equation (A3) is strictly negative. Part B in (A1) can be expressed as</p><p>Replacing 11bk and 12b k with t 1 and t 2 , respectively, the second derivative of (A4) with respect to a is</p><p>Because 1&lt;t 1 &lt;11k and 0&lt;t 2 &lt;1=k, (A5) is strictly negative. Therefore, we have I 00 A ðajbÞ&lt;0.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A2 | Proof of property (ii)</head><p>From Appendix (A1), we know that I A ðajbÞ can be expressed in terms of t 1 and t 2 :</p><p>(A6) where t 1 511bk and t 2 5 12b k :</p><p>Taking the derivative of (A6) with respect to a, we have</p><p>Where a 5 0, the first order condition of I A ðajbÞ with respect to a is</p><p>which is strictly positive because t 2 &lt;1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A3 | Proof of property (iii)</head><p>From Equation (A7), we can derive I 0 A ð1; bÞ as</p><p>where</p><p>The denominator in (A8) is strictly positive. Therefore, we need to show that the numerator in (A8) is strictly negative for all b 2 ½0; 1 and k 2 ½1; 3Þ. The numerator in (A8) can be expressed in terms of b and k as </p><p>From Equation (A10), we know that hðb; 3Þ is strictly increasing in b 2 ½0; 1. Where b 5 1, we have h(1,3) 5 0. Therefore, h(b,k) is strictly negative for all b 2 ½0; 1 and k 2 ½1; 3Þ.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A4 | Proof of properties (iv) and (v)</head><p>Referring to Equation (A8), we have</p><p>where t 1 511bk and t 2 5 12b k :</p><p>Where ða; bÞ5ð1; 1Þ, we have t 1 5 1 1 k and t 2 5 0. Thus, from Equation (A11), we obtain</p><p>which is strictly positive if k &lt; 3 and strictly negative if k &gt; 3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A5 | Proof of property (vi)</head><p>Referring to Equation (A7), we have</p><p>q where t 1 511bk and t 2 5 12b k :</p><p>Plugging t 1 5 1 1 ak and t 2 5 12a k ; we obtain</p><p>Solving the equation, I 0 A ða Ã ja Ã Þ50 from Equation (A13), we have</p><p>which is strictly increasing in k and reaches 1 where k 5 3. Where k&gt;3; (A14) exceeds 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A6 | Proof of property (vii)</head><p>In the Nash equilibrium, i.e., aðb Ã Þ5a Ã , we have the following equation:</p><p>Implicitly differentiating (A15) with respect to b, we acquire</p><p>Plugging ða; bÞ5 3k21 6k212k 2 into (A16), we have</p><p>which is strictly less than 1 where k 2 ½1; 3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A7 | Proof of Property (viii)</head><p>Referring to Equation (A14), we have</p><p>which is a unique solution for I 0 A ða Ã ja Ã Þ50. Where k &gt; 3, a*(k) exceeds 1. Thus, if k &gt; 3, there is no solution for a* in the range of [0,1] for the equation I 0</p><p>A ða Ã ja Ã Þ50.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A8 | Proof of Proposition 2</head><p>From Equation (21), we know that the necessary and sufficient condition for the existence of immiserizing growth effects is that E &gt; 0.5. From Equations (21) to (24), we know that I A increases as a decreases if a 5 a 0 5 1. This means that if country B is in the state of complete specialization (i.e., b 5 1), country A does not have an incentive to achieve complete specialization. The same logic is applied to country B. Therefore, they have mutual incentives to deviate from complete specialization.</p><p>APPENDIX B: ANALYSIS OF THE TWO-STAGE GAME In the economy described in Section 6, country A's consumption on goods x and y are</p><p>From (B1), country A's indirect utility is</p><p>By the market clearing conditions and maximization, the relative world price of good x is</p><p>Under complete specialization, i.e., (a,b) 5 (1,1), country A's utility is</p><p>(B4) which is strictly increasing in t A but strictly decreasing in t B . Therefore, under complete specialization, the Nash equilibrium for tariffs is ðt Ã A ; t Ã B Þ5ð1; 1Þ. Now, we assume that the economy is not in the state of complete specialization. Partially differentiating p/q with respect to t A , we have FIGU RE B1 The best response functions where k 5 3 in the two-stage game [Colour figure can be viewed at</p><p>From Equations (B2) and (B5), we can derive the best response tariff function t A (t B ;a,b), that maximizes country A's utility conditional on t B . In the same way, we can derive country B's best response tariff function, t B (t A ;a,b). Plugging t A (t B ;a,b) and t B (t A ;a,b) into I A p q ; t A ; t B ; a; b , we have country A's indirect utility function in terms of (a,b), which is denoted as I T A ða; bÞ. From I T A ða; bÞ, we can derive the best response function a(b) that maximizes I T A ða; bÞ given b. In the same way, country B's best response function b(a) can be derived. For example, where k 5 3, the two best response functions, a(b) and b(a), are shown in <ref type="figure">Figure B1</ref>, where the Nash equilibrium is (a*, b*) 5 (0.62,0.62).</p><p>From a(b) and b(a), we can derive the Nash equilibrium specialization (a*,b*) which satisfies a (b*) 5 a* and b(a*) 5 b*. By the symmetric structure of the model, we always have a* 5 b. From the derivations of t A ðt B ; a; bÞ and t B ðt A ; a; bÞ, I apply a numerical analysis using Matlab. The Matlab code can be downloaded in mwkang.site11.com/code/rie2016.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What Do Trade Negotiators Negotiate About? Empirical Evidence from the World Trade Organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kyle</forename><surname>Bagwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Staiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/aer.101.4.1238</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www.nber.org/papers/w12727.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">American Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-8282</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1238" to="1273" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-06" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strategic environmental policy and intrenational trade</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Scott</forename><surname>Barrett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0047-2727(94)90039-6</idno>
		<idno type="PII">0047-2727(94)90039-6</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-0H8DGS2V-W</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">CCFD99510AA972E2D0CD5DF4908F2130AA25CF31</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Public Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Public Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0047-2727</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="338" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-07" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Notes on Some Controversies in the Theory of International Trade</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jagdish</forename><surname>Bhagwati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Harry</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2227483</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Economic Journal</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Economic Journal</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0013-0133</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">277</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">74</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1960-03" />
			<publisher>JSTOR</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immiserizing Growth: A Geometrical Note</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jagdish</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Bhagwati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2295990</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-H99X96WW-L</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">E7B916C2A191608A7B7FC16B0B0B28363DFFE36F</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0034-6527</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">201</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1958-06" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distortions and Immiserizing Growth: A Generalization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jagdish</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Bhagwati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2296774</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-Q4P140ZJ-S</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">0D94C397EAAB0CA7B78C0B5EF86D999AE2927069</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0034-6527</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">481</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1968-10" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal policies and immiserizing growth</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Bhagwati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="967" to="970" />
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The generalized theory of transfers and welfare: Bilateral transfers in a multilateral world</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Bhagwati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brecher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hatta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="606" to="618" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The paradoxes of immiserizing growth and donor-enriching “recipient-immiserizing” transfers: A tale of two literatures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jagdish</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Bhagwati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Richard</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brecher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tatsuo</forename><surname>Hatta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/bf02706608</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/1BB-4Q6QK1RV-N</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">F8450D4A13A57ABFC7D4A3CDA7004CE0C73A7EA8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of World Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Weltwirtschaftliches Archiv</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1610-2878</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1610-2886</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="228" to="243" />
			<date type="published" when="1984-06" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental standards as strategic outcomes: A simple model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rabindra</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Bhattacharya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rupayan</forename><surname>Pal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.reseneeco.2009.11.001</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www.igidr.ac.in/pdf/publication/WP-2008-028.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Resource and Energy Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Resource and Energy Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0928-7655</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="408" to="420" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-08" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal Tariffs and Market Power: The Evidence</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Christian</forename><surname>Broda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nuno</forename><surname>Limão</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/aer.98.5.2032</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/bc91/4277ac9cd9d30b3b2a13eee946459a900f27.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">American Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-8282</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2032" to="2065" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-11" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">International Credit Flows and Pecuniary Externalities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Markus</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Brunnermeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yuliy</forename><surname>Sannikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/mac.20140054</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.cesifo-group.de/DocDL/cesifo1_wp5170.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Journal: Macroeconomics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">American Economic Journal: Macroeconomics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1945-7707</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1945-7715</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="338" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-01" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trade liberalization, environmental policy, and welfare</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Roberto</forename><surname>Burguet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jaume</forename><surname>Sempere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0095-0696(02)00032-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Economics and Management</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Environmental Economics and Management</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0095-0696</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-07" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What Goods Do Countries Trade? A Quantitative Exploration of Ricardo&apos;s Ideas</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Costinot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Donaldson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Komunjer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/restud/rdr033</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://dspace.mit.edu/bitstream/1721.1/72973/1/Costinot_What%20Goods.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0034-6527</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1467-937X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="581" to="608" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-09-28" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative Advantage and Optimal Trade Policy *</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Arnaud</forename><surname>Costinot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dave</forename><surname>Donaldson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><surname>Vogel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Iván</forename><surname>Werning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/qje/qjv007</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://dspace.mit.edu/bitstream/1721.1/104097/1/Costinot_Comparative%20advantage.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0033-5533</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1531-4650</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="659" to="702" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-02-03" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative advantage, trade, and payments in a Ricardian model with a continuum of goods</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dornbusch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Samuelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="823" to="839" />
			<date type="published" when="1977" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Technology, Geography, and Trade</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><surname>Eaton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Samuel</forename><surname>Kortum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1468-0262.00352</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-5R6JSZF8-0</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">F26A7AE7228F657858AB4DA4B786B3ABB41A21F5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Econometrica</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0012-9682</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1468-0262</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1741" to="1779" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-09" />
			<publisher>The Econometric Society</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tariffs, Retaliation, and the Elasticity of Demand for Imports</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gorman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2295983</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-L3TMWW4T-S</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">3C38244EACFBCDF9F428877D6713B6D47CDB7D75</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0034-6527</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">133</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1958-06" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A note on the optimal tariff, retaliation and the welfare loss from tariff wars in a framework with intra-industry trade</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Gros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0022-1996(87)90061-4</idno>
		<idno type="PII">0022-1996(87)90061-4</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-J6D40V8D-C</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">1FD96D15B35CBD62383D84E73EEA569331C43BFE</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of International Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-1996</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3-4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="357" to="367" />
			<date type="published" when="1987-11" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">GGDC productivity level database: International comparisons of output</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Inklaar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Timmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Groningen Growth and Development Centre, University of Groningen</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical Report</note>
	<note>inputs and productivity at the industry level</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimum Welfare and Maximum Revenue Tariffs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Harry</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2296268</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-GZ7MSZ92-J</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">CD1DDDA8FF563B14B0436A4D6C984B73760B6B63</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0034-6527</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">28</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1951" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do Big Countries Win Tariff Wars?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Kennan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Raymond</forename><surname>Riezman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1142/9789814390125_0004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Trade Agreements and Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>WORLD SCIENTIFIC</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013-03-27" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="51" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal Tariff Equilibria with Customs Unions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Kennan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Raymond</forename><surname>Riezman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1142/9789814390125_0005</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://conservancy.umn.edu/bitstream/11299/55261/1/1982-172.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Trade Agreements and Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>WORLD SCIENTIFIC</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013-03-27" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="66" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Equilibrium Pollution Taxes in Open Economies with Imperfect Competition</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Peter</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1006/jeem.1994.1025</idno>
		<idno type="PII">S0095-0696(84)71025-4</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-LNVXB5WW-D</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">DDCF04B2F995D91C95DB802EAB939B1611F94EBE</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/9af6/fc9476ef06c0b6673adfed142e78a0ed964c.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Environmental Economics and Management</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Environmental Economics and Management</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0095-0696</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-07" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The structure of Nash equilibrium tariffs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yoshitomo</forename><surname>Ogawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00199-010-0599-x</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/VQC-BZMHLDR2-L</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">F13D33B5617F2B1687B72EA4104D95A285AE2991</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economic Theory</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Econ Theory</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0938-2259</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1432-0479</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-02-16" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The non-equivalence of tariffs and quotas under retaliation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Carlos</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0022-1996(74)90048-8</idno>
		<idno type="PII">0022-1996(74)90048-8</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-SM7V5DS9-3</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">F9841C30499C3ADBC70F6978CB0739AF76AD1F90</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of International Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-1996</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="298" />
			<date type="published" when="1974-08" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimum Tariffs and Retaliation Revisited: How Country Size Matters</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Constantinos</forename><surname>Syropoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1467-937x.t01-1-00028</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-DBMQ7S13-1</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">25C68C1EF3E09DE2B9EA71B490183C6EFD0F3CE4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Rev Econ Studies</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0034-6527</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1467-937X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="707" to="727" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-08" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Optimum Quota and Retaliation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Edward</forename><surname>Tower</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2296799</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-TTJVXWXL-F</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">5C50ADEC6F11594C74AC332B42F3D59234A5A5BC</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Review of Economic Studies</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0034-6527</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">623</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1975-10" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimum tariffs and retaliation: How country numbers matter</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ben</forename><surname>Zissimos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jinteco.2009.04.003</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www.accessecon.com/pubs/VUECON/vu08-w02.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of International Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-1996</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="276" to="286" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-07" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
