<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Exploring regional and gender disparities in Beninese primary school attendance: a multilevel approach</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Informa UK Limited</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-02-13">13 Feb 2018.</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kyle</forename><surname>Mcnabb</surname></persName>
							<email>mcnabb@wider.unu.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">UNU-WIDER</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>United Nations</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University World Institute for Development Economics Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Helsinki</settlement>
									<country key="FI">Finland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UNU-WIDER United Nations University World Institute for Development Economics Research, Katajanokanlaituri</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>6B, FI</addrLine>
									<postCode>00160</postCode>
									<settlement>Helsinki</settlement>
									<country key="FI">Finland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Exploring regional and gender disparities in Beninese primary school attendance: a multilevel approach</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Education Economics</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Education Economics</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0964-5292</idno>
						<idno type="eISSN">1469-5782</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="534" to="556"/>
							<date type="published" when="2018-02-13">13 Feb 2018.</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09645292.2018.1426732</idno>
					<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/09645292.2018.1426732?needAccess=true" />
					<note type="submission">Received 3 January 2017 Accepted 8 January 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T22:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Economic development</term>
					<term>demand for schooling</term>
					<term>Africa</term>
					<term>school attendance</term>
					<term>multilevel model JEL CLASSIFICATION I25</term>
					<term>O12</term>
					<term>I21</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>DHS data is combined with school supply statistics to study primary school attendance in the 2005-06 school year in Benin, a country that has seen almost unparalleled increases in attendance since the 1990s. Results of a logistic regression model highlight the important role played by factors such as household wealth or religion and that gender disparities in education persist in Benin. The opportunity cost of attending school is also investigated. In order to explain regional disparities in attendance, a multilevel model is estimated; results from a random-slopes model highlight those communes where reductions in the cost of schooling could see the greatest improvements in primary school attendance rates.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Benin has witnessed almost unparalleled improvements in primary school attendance since 1990, yet remains virtually ignored in the literature surveying education outcomes in developing countries. The Gross Enrolment Rate (GER), defined as the number of students attending school as a percentage of the school age population, soared from around 50% to well over 100% between 1990 and 2012. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> By 2012, the Net Enrolment Rate (NER), defined as the percentage of school age students attending school, stood at 95 percent (UIS 2017), well above the average in Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) of just 77 percent. However, despite this impressive progress, severe geographical disparities persist in Benin's primary school attendance rates. According to the most recent Beninese Demographic and Health Survey (DHS) in 2012, there are still communes where less than one third of children attend. This study aims to shed light these disparities by assessing the relative importance of demand-(i.e. on the part of the student, or their family) and supply-side factors (i.e. availability of school facilities) on primary school attendance rates during the 2005-06 school year. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> That is to say, I investigate whether some communes lag behind others due simply to a lack of schools, or whether other socioeconomic or sociocultural factors at the household level help to explain attendance rates.</p><p>To approach this question, individual-and household-level data from the Beninese DHS is combined with detailed commune-level schooling data from the Beninese Institute for Statistics <ref type="bibr">(INSAE)</ref>. Results from a logistic regression model suggest that household wealth, religion, parental education and the supply of schools all predict the likelihood of a child attending school. Furthermore, results also indicate that as average distance to school increases, the likelihood that boys who work in the field attend school decreases to a greater extent than those who did not work.</p><p>This echoes the findings of, for example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Lincove (2012)</ref> or <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Huisman and Smits (2009)</ref> and also presents evidence that distance to school captures the opportunity cost of attending, which is greater when time spent travelling replaces potentially-income generating work. There is little evidence to suggest that simply living in a rural area, for example, explains lower attendance.</p><p>Whilst a number of existing studies on primary school attendance (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Huisman and Smits 2009)</ref> have acknowledged that factors at the community, district or national level play an important role in explaining school attendance, few have explicitly accounted for such cluster-level interdependence in the estimation strategy. Therefore, this study also presents results from a multilevel logistic model, which accounts for unobserved heterogeneity between higher level clusters (i.e. at the household and commune level), in order to assess the level at which most variation in school attendance rates is seen. A three-level random intercepts model shows that there are a large number of communes with a significantly lower than average primary attendance rate, but that only around 11% of this variation is attributable to factors at the commune level. After controlling for both household and commune level factors, less than 5% of the variation in attendance is due to commune-level factors, suggesting that the majority of the between-commune variation in attendance rates is attributable to household-level characteristics. In a similar vein to <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Delprato and Sabates (2015)</ref>, a random slopes model is also estimated, where the wealth coefficient is allowed to vary between communes. This identifies those communes where attendance is below average, but the effect of household wealth on school attendance is above average. Such results could potentially be of use to policymakers in identifying those areas where interventions that raised household wealth (or lowered the cost of schooling) might be most effective in increasing school attendance rates.</p><p>In addition to explaining the regional disparities present in Benin's primary school attendance rates, this study also examines differences in attendance by gender. Despite impressive progress in reducing the gender gap since 1990, the results presented herein suggest that the factors explaining girls' school attendance differ to those for boys. In particular, adopted girls and those that worked (either alongside or in place of attending school) were significantly less likely to attend school, whilst these variables were not significant explanatory factors for boys. At the same time, however, the results suggest that distance to school was not an important factor in girls' attendance. These results are explored further below.</p><p>The broad contributions to the literature are therefore twofold: Firstly, evidence is presented on the determinants of primary school attendance for Benin, a context that has not previously been considered in the empirical literature surrounding primary schooling, but in which vast changes have been seen over recent years. Secondly, the use of a multilevel model helps to provide additional insights on regional disparities that many similar studies, from other developing countries, neglect to consider.</p><p>This study proceeds as follows. Section 2 describes the Beninese context in detail. Section 3 discusses the theoretical predictions and empirical results surrounding primary school attendance in developing countries, with an emphasis on not only the economic rationale, but also the sociocultural factors that might dictate whether or not a child is sent to school. In particular, results from similar studies in Sub Saharan Africa (SSA) are surveyed. Section 4 presents the variables and methodology chosen for this study. Results for the single-level logistic model are presented in section 5, whilst the multilevel strategy is outlined and presented in section 6. Section 7 concludes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">The Beninese context</head><p>Benin provides an intriguing case study in education and development. Along with an economic crisis that forced the closure of teacher training colleges and large scale cuts to the civil service in the 1980's, the socialist regime's failed attempts at reform (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Allen 1989)</ref> left Benin ranking amongst the worst performing countries in the world with regards primary school enrolment and gender parity; just 51 per cent of all children and less than one in four girls were attending primary school in 1990 (UIS 2017); the ODI (2011, 4) describes the education system at this time as 'deeply dysfunctional and inequitable'. However, the democratically elected government prioritised education in 1990 and as a result of systemic reform, Benin has seen almost unparalleled (at least in SSA) progress in terms of primary school enrolment rates. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> Between 1990 and 2010, average adult years of education (Barro and Lee 2013) increased from 2.13 to 4.35 (only Mali saw a greater increase in the same period), gross and net enrollment soared and the gender gap was virtually eliminated in many regions. In October 2006, primary education was made free for all. Benin also performs well in terms of primary school availability. <ref type="bibr">INSAE and Macro International (2007)</ref> report that in the 2005-06 school yearwhich is studied in detail below -93.7% of households lived within 4 km of a primary school; 79.1% lived less than 1 km away. Furthermore, there was relatively little difference between rural and urban areas, where 91.9 and 96.2% of households respectively resided within 4 km of the nearest primary school. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> plots Benin's progress in net primary school enrolment rates against the average for SSA, developing countries and the worlddespite missing data for many years, the trend is clear: NERs rose from around 40% (52% male, 27% female) in 1990 to 94% (99% male, 88% female) in 2012. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Gross primary enrolment rose from 51% to 123% in the same period. Progress in increasing enrolment of girls in primary school has been particularly impressive: The Gender Parity Index (GPI) rose from 0.50 in 1990 to 0.89 in 2012only Guinea matched this progress in SSA. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> Yet these figures do not tell the whole story in Benin, as large regional disparities persist at both the department and commune level. To examine these, I turn to data from the 2006 wave of the DHS, where the ratio presented might best be defined as the Net Primary Attendance Rate as it shows the percentage of primary school age children whose parents reported that they were attending primary school in 2005-06. Some departments were still struggling with net primary attendance rates of as little as 29% (unweighted department average), whilst others saw rates of over 75%. The national average was 56%. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> shows net primary attendance (male and female combined) by commune in 2006. <ref type="bibr">6</ref> It is clear that estimates of the net primary enrolment rate for, e.g. 2006 are somewhat higher than the net primary attendance rate. This is likely due to a number of factors. Firstly, measures of enrolment might include those children who enroll, but do not subsequently regularly attend school (see e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Omoeva et al. 2013)</ref>. Secondly, there is evidence that over-reporting by public officials can lead to upward bias in enrolment statistics; <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Sandefur and Glassman (2015)</ref>, for example report evidence of this in contexts such as Kenya or Rwanda, where pupil fees had been replaced by top-down per pupil grants, creating a financial incentive to inflate enrolment numbers. These explanations might well go some way to explaining the observed discrepancy between enrolment and attendance in Benin.</p><p>Whilst it is clear that commune-level attendance rates vary widely across the country, there also exists significant intra-department variation. Take, for example, the department of Borgou; Net primary attendance rates in 2006 ranged from just 23% in the commune of Kalale to almost 80% in Parakou. Despite the Beninese government's continued prioritisation of access to education, regional disparities such as these persist. Indeed, even by 2012 many communes had net primary attendance rates close to 90%, but some still lagged behind in the 20-30% range. <ref type="bibr">7</ref> Whilst the NER (or in this case, the net primary attendance rate) represents a significantly more useful indicator than gross primary enrolment, it still does not tell the whole story; the official definition (UNESCO 2012) is</p><p>The number of children of official primary school age who are enrolled in primary education as a percentage of the total children of the official school age population.</p><p>It therefore pays no attention to what grade a child is in; an 11-year-old, who is, strictly speaking, of school age, having just entered the first grade is counted as enrolledyet they have arrived in primary school some 5 years late. Whilst the empirical analysis here does not specifically consider on-time-enrolment, a look at the age distribution of those attending primary school is nonetheless interesting. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref> uses data from two waves of the DHS in order to highlight progress in the age distribution of primary school attendance in Benin between the 2005-06 and the 2011-12 school years. In 2011-12, the mode age of primary school attendees was 9 years old, at which over 75 percent of children were attending primary school, compared to 10 years old in 2005-06. Some of the most notable improvements come when looking to younger children: the earlier survey showed that, for example, just 35% of 6 year olds (the official starting age in Benin) were attending primary school in 2005-06; by 2011-12 this had risen to 61%. Thus, in addition to the increases in enrolment outlined above, there is also evidence of improvements in on-time enrolment. <ref type="bibr">8</ref> 3. Theoretical predictions and empirical evidence 3.1. Demand side <ref type="bibr">Becker (1975, 45)</ref> argues that 'The most important single determinant of the amount invested in human capital may well be its profitability or rate of return.' In other words, it makes sense to invest in human capital, or in this case send a child to school, if the expected benefits outweigh the costs incurred. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">9</ref> Costs, of course, are measured in both direct and indirect termsthe former constitute items such as school fees, books, transport or uniforms, and the latter the opportunity cost of attending <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Becker 1975)</ref>. The opportunity cost of attending school is often higher in developing countries, where children commonly contribute to total household income through work. Children might make a direct contribution to household income, whereby the child works on the farm or in the marketplace, or an indirect contribution, where their help around the home or family business frees up the time of adults to earn more money <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Colclough, Rose, and Tembon 2000)</ref>. Such 'indirect contributions' are particularly pertinent for girls, who are more often required to assist with childcare etc. However, working and school attendance are rarely mutually exclusive in developing countries. Evidence from Burkina Faso (De Hoop and Rosati 2014), Kenya <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Buchmann 2000)</ref> and Ethiopia (Admassie 2003) suggests that it is commonplace across Africa that children both work and attend school. Indeed, de Hoop and Rosati (ibid) found that the amount of time children in Burkina Faso spent working or helping with chores did not fall substantially (and in some cases even increased) even following the receipt of subsidies that reduced the cost of schooling. However, there is evidence that in rural areas, children enrolled at the start of the school year might be pulled out of school in order to help with the harvest in autumn <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Colclough, Rose, and Tembon (2000)</ref>.</p><p>Empirical work often proxies cost of schooling with a measure of distance to school; time spent travelling to school could be used, for example, to work on the family farm, or help with household chores. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Lincove (2012)</ref> or <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Huisman and Smits (2009)</ref> found distance to school to be inversely related with the likelihood of school attendance; <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Delprato and Sabates (2015)</ref>, however, found no effects on the likelihood of late entry in Nigeria. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">10</ref> Turning to the benefits of attending primary school, these might not be immediately clear to parents or students in a developing country context. If there is a lack of job market opportunities in an area, then there will be a limited expected return to education. Even if opportunities were to arise in the future, parents might not reasonably be able to foresee this happening. If a child is expected to, for example, work on a family plot of land, then numeracy and literacy skills might well be of limited value, at least compared to the physical strength that he or she could have been building, which may prove more valuable for his or her future work. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Colclough, Rose, and Tembon (2000)</ref> highlight that in contexts where gender discrimination exists and the gender balance in labour markets is skewed in favour of males, that the benefits of education will be lower for girls. Thus, even with equitable access to schooling, there may still be significant challenges to convince parents of the benefits of educating daughters.</p><p>In developing countries, it is by no means guaranteed that parents will be able to accurately measure or estimate the benefits of educating a child. If information on job market opportunities is unavailable, education is deemed unnecessary for rural farm labour, or if families live in a community where few adults are educated, then parents (especially those who have not attended school themselves) are likely to undervalue the benefits. In a context where either the future returns to education are unknown, the benefits of education will be undervalued. The costs, whether direct or indirect, are more easily observable.</p><p>Costs and benefits must also be weighed in terms of household wealth, income or expenditures. If the costs are small in relation to either of these measures, then it is more likely that parents can afford to send their children to school. It is commonplace for household surveys to stratify households into wealth quintiles (the DHS, for example, does this via a principal components analysis); empirical results often find that the likelihood of attending school increases from the lowest quintile to the highest <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Huisman and Smits 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Kazeem, Jensen, and Stokes 2010)</ref>, although this is not necessarily always the case; e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Lincove (2012)</ref>, found no direct effect of household wealth on primary school attendance in Uganda, but did find that the effects of other explanatory variables varied in magnitude according to wealth quintile.</p><p>The economic rationale for sending a child to school is, however, just one side of the story: there are various sociocultural differences with respect to religion, caste, tradition or tribe that might interlink with economic decisions to dictate the norms followed by parents with regard to education. Indeed, it is probable that these factors might be driven more by norms at the community or state level, than at the household level <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Delprato and Sabates 2015)</ref>. In societies where patriarchal norms persist, parents may place a higher value on the education of boys over girls. This often stems from the lack of social security or pension system, meaning that male children are expected to provide for their parents in old age; concurrently, it is common that daughters join their husband's family at marriage <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Colclough, Rose, and Tembon 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Huisman and Smits 2009)</ref>, and thus their own parents will realise no financial reward to their education. However, the findings of Eloundou-Enyegye and Calvès (2006) provide a challenge to this traditional viewpoint: their study suggests that in some contexts, married women often remitted to their own families (e.g. in Cameroon) and that their capacity to do so actually increased, the more educated they were. Their study also notes the significant control that women in West Africa, and Benin in particular, have over their own earnings. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">11</ref> A further disadvantage for girls arises if the nearest school is quite far away; it might be that they are not allowed to attend until they are slightly older, due to the perceived dangers of walking alone, or physical effort of walking a long distance.</p><p>Religion also plays a significant role in the likelihood of children, specifically girls, being sent to school. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Csapo (1981)</ref> cites the distrust of Western education by Muslims or the more traditional Islamic views on the education of women, as outlined in the Qur'an, as potential barriers to education for girls in Nigeria. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Lincove (2015)</ref> found that Muslim children in Nigeria were, on average, 23% less likely to attend schoolbut the effect was more than double for girls (31%) than for boys (15%), a finding echoed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Kazeem, Jensen, and Stokes (2010)</ref> who found the same result for Nigeria, although the order of magnitude is dramatically largertheir regressions suggest that Muslim children were five times less likely to attend school than Christians. Lincove (2012), however, found no effect of being a Muslim on primary school attendance in Uganda and Buchmann <ref type="formula">2000</ref>'s regression results found that Muslim children were no less likely to attend school than their Christian counterparts in Kenya. So, whilst theory predicts that different religions or traditions might place different importance on schooling, the empirical evidence for SSA is mixed.</p><p>The education level of parents is also an important consideration: it is highly probable that if parents have attended school themselves, and benefitted from the education received, that they would be more likely to send their own children to school. In terms of the economic rationale, this might allow the parent to better appreciate and estimate the benefits of education for their own child; this may be particularly true for girls if their mother has attained a certain level of education. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">12</ref> Various household or family level factors such as household size, birth order, whether or not a child is adopted, etc. might also be considered as explanatory factors with regards a child's likelihood of attending school. In terms of economic rationale, a larger number of children increases competition for limited household resources <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Lincove 2015)</ref>. As a result, it might be that children with more siblings cannot attend school as they are required to complete more tasks at home in order to contribute to household income and the direct costs of sending many children to school are obviously higher. At the same time however, a larger number of children might increase the likelihood that any one child can attend school as there are more hands to work and contribute to overall household income. Thus, the direction of this effect is, ex ante, unclear. Colclough, Rose, and Tembon <ref type="formula">2000</ref>presents evidence that in Ethiopia, the average number of children in a household was higher for school attendees than for dropouts; <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Glick and Sahn (2006)</ref> found that as the number of children in a household increased, there was no impact on the likelihood that a child would attend a public primary school in Madagascar, although it did decrease the likelihood of a child attending private school. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Lincove (2015)</ref> found no effect of the number of children in a household in Uganda and only marginally significant effects for girls in Nigeria.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Supply side</head><p>The above discussion has highlighted that numerous factors interlink to dictate whether or not a child will be sent to school by his or her parents. However, considering only factors on the demand side ignores many of the considerations that a parent might make. Including estimates of the supply of schooling is crucial to avoid omitted variable bias when carrying out empirical analyses of school attendance. Often, however, institutional data for the total number of schools, pupil teacher ratios (PTR) etc., is only available at the national or regional level, making consolidation with survey data at the community or village very level difficult. As a result, many studies fail to accurately account for the supply of schooling. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">13</ref> School quality is often measured by the PTR, although this variable is clearly endogenous in regressions where the dependent variable is school attendance rates. Other variables that have been used to represent school quality include the percentage of teachers who are qualified (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Lavy 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Huisman and Smits 2009)</ref>, percentage of teachers who are female (often considered key in explaining girls' participation in education e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Glick 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Huisman and Smits 2009</ref>) the use of multigrade teaching <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Glick and Sahn 2006)</ref> and the condition of classrooms etc. However, the effect of these variables on primary school attendance is mixed and it is not unreasonable to argue that some of these measures might matter more for explaining school achievement than attendance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Data and methodology</head><p>Whilst geographical variation in primary attendance rates is explored in detail below in the form of a multilevel model, a simple logistic regression is presented first. The advantage of doing this lies in the ability to compute average marginal effects which allow us to gain an understanding of the relative magnitudes of the covariates considered. The single level logit regression estimated takes the following form</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">ln p i 1 − p i = b 0i + b 1 S i + b 2 H i + b 2 C i + e i (1)</formula><p>where the dependent variable is a dummy equal to 1 if child i was of official primary school age and attended school during the 2005-06 school year. S is the vector of student-level characteristics; H the vector of household level characteristics and the vector C contains commune-level characteristics.</p><p>The dependent variable used in the empirical analysis is a dummy variable equal to 1 if a child of primary school age was attending primary school in 2005-06 Interviewees were asked 'During the 2005-06 school year, which ended in June 2006, did (name) attend school at some point' (Author translation from French original in <ref type="bibr">INSAE and Macro International 2007, 370)</ref>. 14 The 2006 DHS for Benin took place between the 3rd of August and 18th November 2006. It should be noted that there was a policy change in mid-October 2006, whereby the elimination of school fees was completed in all regions. However, this is unlikely to impact upon the analysis here, as the question pertains to the school year ending in June 2006.</p><p>The DHS data is stratified as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Benin ↓ Departments (12) ↓ Communes (77) ↓ 'Clusters' (Primary Sampling Unit [PSU]) (750) ↓ Households (17,511) ↓ Individuals (90,650) ↓ ↓</formula><p>Not School Age (73,556) School Age <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(17,</ref><ref type="bibr">094)</ref> Of the 90,650 individuals, 17,094 were of school age. Of these, 57% were attending primary school. Control variables are included at the individual, household and commune level; <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> presents summary statistics of these. Just under half of the sample was female (48%), 3.5% were adopted and it appears common that children of school age also work; some 73% did so. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">15</ref> With regard to those children who were adopted, the definition reveals that they are in 'foster care' and not related to any other household member; 89% of their mothers and 77% of their fathers were still known to be alive; fewer than 4% had lost both parents. It is thus difficult to speculate on the reasons for adoption, but one reason could be due to infertility of adoptive parents: DHS (2004b), suggests that in Benin, 61% of primarily sterile women reside in a household with at least one adopted child (compared to 38% of primarily fertile women), the highest in the sample of 48 developing countries considered. Indeed, in the West African region, the study found that more than half of childless couples lived in a household with an adopted child. An alternative explanation is that children are adopted principally to help out with work around the house. Adopted girls, for example, were more likely to carry out domestic work (78%) than biological daughters (64%) and less likely to attend primary school conditional on also carrying out this type of work (29% v 58% for adoptees and biological daughters respectively). There was no significant difference between adopted sons and biological sons in terms of work (70% and 71% did, respectively).</p><p>Turning to the household level variables, a set of dummy variables is included in order to control for the household head's religion, the DHS wealth index (a composite index constructed using principal components analysis ranking households from 1 ['Poorest'] to 5 <ref type="bibr">['Richest']</ref>) and the education level of the household head (a set of dummy variables for none, primary, secondary or tertiary). <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">16</ref> One quarter of households were Catholic, 26% Islamic and 21% Vodoun. Around 65% of household heads had no formal education whatsoever; of the remainder that did attend school, 21% had primary, 13% had secondary and the remaining 2% had a university education. Whilst ideally the child's mother or father's education level would be included in the analysis here (as the head is not always the parent of the children included in the sample), it was not possible to identify the parent of each child from the 2006 Beninese DHS due to missing data. School Essential is a dummy variable taking the value equal to one if the respondent answered yes to the survey question 'Do you need to be able to send children to school'. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">17</ref> This variable captures household stated preferences for educationsome 79% of households considered school to be essential. Parents who undervalue education (even if they themselves have gone to school) might be less likely to educate their own children. The average household size was just over 8 and this ranged from 2 to 36. Also included is a dummy variable equal to one if the child resided in a rural area (64% did so).</p><p>At the commune level, controls are included for the average distance to school and the (log) number of schools per school-age children in each commune. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">18</ref> To construct a measure of average distance to school, I follow <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Huisman and Smits (2009)</ref> as follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Avg Distance = km 2 No of Schools p<label>(2)</label></formula><p>One unavoidable weakness of this approach lies with those children who reside close to the border of one commune, but might attend a school situated in another. However, this is perhaps the best approximation available, given the data on hand. 19  <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref> presents benchmark results for equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. In all following tables, the dependent variable is as outlined above. It can be considered a close approximation to the NER, although is again perhaps best defined as a net primary attendance rate. The Log-odds ratio is shown, along with average marginal effects (the latter in square brackets). 20 Both are included, as the log odds are more comparable with the multilevel results later (as it is not possible to obtain marginal effects following that procedure) whilst the marginal effects are somewhat more intuitive and help to give a sense of the magnitude of the effects of the covariates. 21 Column 1 includes the entire sample, whilst columns 2 and 3 perform the same regression for boys and girls respectively. Looking first at the individual level factors, the likelihood of attending primary school is significantly lower for girls than it is for boys: this is in line with expectations, given the considerable gender disparities that exist(ed) in enrolment at primary school for Benin's young girls. Specifically, the results suggest that girls aged 6-11 were around 9% less likely to attend primary school than are boys. Age and its square suggest a non-linear relationship with the dependent variable, reflecting the pattern outlined in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref> above. The results also suggest that adopted children are less likely to attend school than those related to the family; in a context where income might be low it is understandable that households might give preference to the education of biological children. Interestingly, however, column three highlights that the significance of this variable comes entirely from girls who are around 20% less likely to be enrolled in school than a biological daughter; adopted sons appear to face no such disadvantage compared to biological ones. Further inquiry showed that of four types of child (biological son, biological daughter, adopted son and adopted daughter), adopted daughters were the least likely of any to attend school, even when compared to adopted sons. <ref type="bibr">22</ref> An alternative way to frame this inquiry is to include an interaction term ( female * adopted) in the full sample. When tested, this yielded an identical result, with a similar marginal effect (0.19). Lincove (2012) found a similar result in Uganda, however her results actually showed a larger impact for fostered boys than fostered girlsthe opposite of what is presented here, whilst <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Huisman and Smits (2009)</ref> found an overall negative effect on the likelihood of foster children attending school in their panel of 30 developing countries. Worked is a dummy variable equal to 1 if children in the sample carried out any kind of work alongside studying. Again, girls appear to be at a disadvantage compared to boys, with the likelihood of being in school 5% lower for those girls who worked, compared to those who did not. 23 This is explored in more detail below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Results</head><p>Turning to the household's religion, the results suggest that children of Islamic households were around 7% less likely to be sent to school than those from Christian homes (the reference category). <ref type="bibr">24</ref> Those of parents following traditional / other religion were about 4% less likely to attend. The DHS surveys also inquired as to the ethnicity of individuals, however this was often closely correlated to religion and did not provide any additional insights when tested in the model (not shown). It is clear that as household wealth increases, so too does the likelihood that children attend primary school. For instance, those in the lowest wealth quintile were some 29% less likely to attend school than those in the richest (the reference category). This echoes results in studies such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Huisman and Smits (2009)</ref>, or Delprato and Sabates (2015) (Nigeria), which also found an increasing likelihood of school attendance as household wealth level increased, although <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Lincove (2012)</ref> found no effects of household wealth on primary school attendance in Uganda. The effects of household wealth again suggest some difference by gender: girls from the poorest households face a slightly lower disadvantage to boys, compared to the upper quintile, perhaps a reflection of the higher value placed on boys' work. This is explored in more detail below. Similarly, household heads that had attended primary or secondary school were more likely to send their own children to primary school than those with no education (the reference category); there is little difference here by gender. Obviously, it might be the case that richer families are often more educated, or it might be the case that Christian families are more likely to be wealthier (reside in wealthier regions, etc.). In order to investigate, <ref type="table">Tables 3 and 4</ref> display the predictive margins of being in a Christian home by wealth level and the predictive margins of having a more educated household head by wealth level respectively.</p><p>It is clear that, holding wealth level constant, household religion and household head's education still have an impact on the likelihood of a child attending school. In particular, children of Christian parents are consistently around 5-6% more likely to attend school, regardless of household wealth level. Turning to <ref type="table">Table 4</ref>, again it is clear that holding wealth constant, the likelihood that a child is sent to school is greater for those household heads with primary, compared to no, education and greater for those with secondary compared to primary education. Interestingly, holding wealth level fixed, the household head having a tertiary education does not increase the probability that a child will attend school compared to a secondary level education. Potential explanations for this finding are (i) Secondary education may be sufficient for a household head to obtain a job that pays well enough to cover the costs (both direct and indirect) of schooling so that most or all children in their household can attend, or (ii) Anyone capable of completing secondary school already fully understands the benefits of sending a child to at least primary school; it does not require a tertiary education to appreciate this. <ref type="bibr">25</ref> Looking at the commune-averaged variables in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>, male children in rural areas are less likely to be enrolled than males in urban areas; it also seems that distance to school matters only for boys. This result emerges in direct conflict to the thinking that parents will be less likely to send their female children to school because of the long distance to walk, fear of attack etc. The supply of schools is however importantthe variable Schools per 5-14 year olds reflects the number of schools in a given commune, divided by the population aged 5-14 years. The positive and significant coefficient on this variable for children of both genders suggests that having controlled for demand-side factors, school availability also matters for primary attendance rates. However, these results warrant closer inspection; due to the relatively high correlation between average distance to school and number of schools (−0.57), the effects of these variables are examined in isolation. The results in columns 4 and 6 suggest that both distance and the number of schools respectively appear to affect the likelihood that a child is enrolled. However, when interacted with the rural dummy (columns 5 and 7), it appears that neither distance to school nor the number of schools have a stronger effect in rural areas, although the signs are in the expected direction. As a further check on the role of distance to school, columns 8 and 9 investigate the extent to which this variable can shed light on the opportunity cost of primary school attendance by subdividing the sample by gender and examining the interaction of distance to school and whether or not a child worked. <ref type="bibr">26</ref> There is no significant effect of distance on girls' attendance if they worked (column 9), however the result for boys presents evidence that the distance to school is an important concern for those that worked alongside studying (column 8). The negative and significant coefficient on the interaction term suggests that boys who worked alongside studying were even less likely to attend a school the further away it was, compared to those who did not work. This lends supports to the hypothesis that the opportunity cost of schooling is taken into account when deciding whether or not to send a child to school. Indeed, it suggests that the opportunity cost of sending boys to school was higher than girls. <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 5</ref> investigates the role of work further, examining the effect of distance to school on the likelihood that a child attends school, according to gender and the type of work carried out. The sample is subdivided by those who 'worked in the field' and those carrying out 'domestic work'. <ref type="bibr">27</ref> The results show that those working in the field faced the greatest opportunity cost to attending school; an increase in average distance to school of 1 km reduced the likelihood that boys (girls) would attend by around 8% (4%). We also see that distance is a significant determinant of primary school attendance for boys who carried out domestic work, but not girls. A number of explanations for the differences observed between genders might be considered: Firstly, boys' labour, or the nature of their labour, may contribute more to family income than girls' and so the opportunity costs of travel time are more heavily felt. Indeed, of those children carrying out 'work in the field', 68% were boys; conversely, only 37% of children that carried out 'domestic work' were boys. The significant coefficient on distance for those boys carrying out domestic work suggests that the nature of this work might differ between gendersand that the domestic tasks carried out by boys was more valuable to the household. Secondly, the climate in Benin at that time, of promoting primary school enrolment for all, might have seen parents under pressure to (be seen to) send daughters to school, so even those required to work were encouraged to attend to a greater extent than were sons. This result complements the findings of, for example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Colclough, Rose, and Tembon (2000)</ref> who found that boys in both Guinea and Ethiopia that had dropped out of school did so primarily to earn money. Although, <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Buchmann (2000)</ref> found that from a sample of 146 children who had dropped out of school in Kenya, only one did so for employment and one to help in the household. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.">Testing an alternative dependent variable</head><p>Whilst the dependent variable used above adheres closely to a measure of net primary attendance in Benin, it is not a perfect barometer of primary school attendance. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref> showed that many children in primary school in 2005-06 fell outside the official age category of 6-11. Furthermore, related studies in this field have imposed different criteria for classifying primary school attendance status: <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Huisman and Smits (2009)</ref> consider only those aged 8-11 in a panel of 30 countries; Lincove (2015), those aged 6-13 in Nigeria and Uganda (although crucially, omit any children that had already progressed to secondary school); Buchmann (2000) those aged 13-18 in Kenya; Lincove (2012), those aged 6-12 years old in Uganda. To the best of my knowledge, only <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Deininger (2003)</ref> provides estimates for a number of alternative age ranges (Uganda). Whilst some of this disparity in the choice of dependent variable naturally results from different official starting ages and length of school cycles in each country, it can hamper the comparability of results across studies and across countries. An appealing approach is outlined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Omoeva et al. (2013)</ref>, who argue in favour of classing the school age as between 7 and 14 years old and abandoning the arbitrary definitions of 'primary' or 'secondary'. These bounds are influenced by the fact that ' … in all countries, compulsory education begins by age 7 or earlier' and ' … the ILO minimum age convention establishes age 15 as the minimum legal age for entering any form of employment … ' <ref type="bibr">(Omoeva et al. 2013, 48)</ref>. As a result, any child falling within this age bracket should be expected to be in school. To follow this definition for the Beninese sample would lead to the loss of those children aged 5 or 6 who are, by all accounts, of school age. However, by extending the upper age range of the sample to 14, the analysis can account for many more children attending, or who have completed, primary school. In the robustness checks included in Appendix A, the dependent variable is thus a dummy equal to 1 if (i) a child is aged between 5 and 14 and (ii) (s)he is in, or has completed, primary school. <ref type="bibr">28</ref> All of the previously reported results hold using this alternative dependent variable; the only differences arising are small changes in the magnitude of certain independent variables.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">A multilevel approach</head><p>The results in section 5 have highlighted that factors on both the demand and supply side were important determinants of primary school attendance in Benin in the 2005-06 school year. As shown in section 2, stark regional disparities exist Benin with regards to primary school attendance rates. Whilst a number of studies acknowledge that factors at the household, community or district level might impact on school attendance in SSA (for example <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Lavy [1996]</ref>;  or <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Huisman and Smits [2009]</ref>), only <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Delprato and Sabates (2015)</ref> have explicitly modelled this econometrically by taking account of unobserved heterogeneity between higher level clusters. However, their study focused on late entry as opposed to primary attendance. The consequence for the econometric analysis of ignoring this is a violation of the assumption that observations are independent from one another; unobserved heterogeneity at higher levels leads to cluster-level interdependence between units <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Skrondal and Rabe-Hesketh 2004)</ref>. The traditional approach to dealing with such data is to turn to a multilevel (or hierarchical) linear model (MLM) (HLM), the simplest of which is the random-intercepts or variance components model which estimates a random intercept for every higher-level unit, such as commune or department etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.">Random intercepts model</head><p>After testing various multilevel structures, it turned out that whilst all performed better than the single level model above, a three-level model, as estimated below, was preferred to any two-level model. <ref type="bibr">29</ref> The basic variance components model takes the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">ln p ijkl 1 − p ijkl = b 0 + m k + w jk + 1 ijk (3)</formula><p>where</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">m k N(0, s 2 m ) w jk N(0, s 2 w ) 1 ijk N(0, s 2 1 )<label>(4)</label></formula><p>ln</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">p ijk 1 − p ijk</formula><p>is the log-odds that child i in household j in commune k is attending school. b 0 is the intercept shared by all individuals, households and communes. m k is the effect of commune k, w jk . The effect of household j and 1 ijk is the child level residual error. The models here are computedsing second-order penalized quasi-likelihood (PQL2) in MLwiN <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Rasbash et al. 2015)</ref> via the Stata module runmlwin <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Leckie and Charlton 2013)</ref>. When selecting the appropriate means by which to estimate multilevel equations, it is necessary to choose a method at is both the most unbiased, but also computationally feasible. Simulations in <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Rodriguez and Goldman (2001)</ref> show that 2nd order Penalised Quasi Likelihood (PQL) estimation provided the closest approximation to maximum likelihood estimation (MLE), out of the choice of 1st and 2nd order marginal quasi-likelihood (MQL) and 1st and 2nd order PQL. Whilst, ideally, MLE would be used to obtain all the estimates, this is computationally very intensive for models beyond the null; Stata's commands such as xtmelogit often take many hours or days to converge, if at all. Appendix B displays estimates of the variance of the random effects in equation <ref type="formula">3</ref>using MQL1, MQL2, PQL1, PQL2 and MLE; Whilst there is still a downward bias in the estimates of s 2 m and s 2 w compared to MLE, PQL2 performs substantially better than the other quasi-likelihood estimators. Given that MLE estimates for models beyond the null are computationally very difficult to obtain, PQL2 is the preferred method here.</p><p>Column 1 of <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 6</ref> displays results from the random intercepts model, as per equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref>. Odds ratios are displayed; it is not possible to compute marginal effects for multilevel models. The estimate of b 0 suggests that the log-odds of a child of school age attending primary school in an 'average' household / commune is 0.32.</p><p>In order to examine and interpret each of the variance components outlined above in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, a variance partition coefficient (VPC) can be calculated which, for the model estimated in column (1) of <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 6</ref>, ' … report[s] the proportion of the observed variance at each level of the model hierarchy' <ref type="bibr">(Leckie 2013, 21)</ref> Thus the VPC provides an indication of those levels at which most residual variation in the likelihood of attending school exists. The discussion in section 2 has already highlighted the significant inter-commune disparity in primary school attendance rates, so the expectation is that a significant amount of variation will exist at this level. The VPC's are calculated for the commune and household respectively, as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">VPC m = s 2 m s 2 m + s 2 w + s 2 1<label>(5)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_7">VPC w = s 2 w s 2 m + s 2 w + s 2 1<label>(6)</label></formula><p>In the case of a binary outcome, s 2 1 is fixed at p 2 3 ≈ 3.29, the variance of the standard logistic distribution. For the null model, the VPC's are 0.240 and 0.113 for the household and commune respectively. Thus, for the null model considered in column 1, 24% of variation in primary school attendance rates is between households, but only 11.3% between communes. An alternative means by which to interpret variance components is the intra-class correlation coefficient (ICC), which measus correlation or similarity between observed responses within a given higher-level cluster unit. The ICC for the commune level, r m , and the household level, r w is calculated as follows </p><formula xml:id="formula_8">r m = s 2 m s 2 m + s 2 w + s 2 1<label>(7)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">r w = s 2 m + s 2 w s 2 m + s 2 w + s 2 1 (8)</formula><p>Thus, an ICC of 0.113 for the commune level represents the between-commune correlation in the odds that a child is attending school. An ICC of 0.353 shows that the between-household withincommune correlation is much higher, suggesting a higher correlation in the odds that any two children from different households in the one commune are attending school, compared to any two children from different households in different communes.</p><p>A caterpillar plot of the commune-level residuals, in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>, shows a significant number of communes where the 95% confidence interval does not overlap with zero, suggesting that primary attendance rates are significantly higher or lower than average in these communes. The significant between-commune-within-department variance, discussed in section two, is also confirmed here; <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref> illustrates that whilst some departments, such as Alibori or Plateau, contain only communes with a negative random intercept residual, others such as Atacora, Borgou or Zou, contain communes where the random effect is both above and below the average. <ref type="bibr">30</ref> In column 2 of <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 6</ref>, covariates are included at the individual level. The VPC in columns 2-4, takes on a slightly different interpretation; in these models, it represents the degree of unexplained variance that exists at each higher level. Having controlled for individual level factors, we see that the 12% of residual variance in primary school attendance exists between communes and some 31% between households.</p><p>When household-level variables are included in column 3 of <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 6</ref>, the variance component attributable to the household level falls from 1.800 to 1.418, representing a reduction in betweenhousehold variance of 21%. 31 Thus, the household covariates included (household wealth, religion, size and stated preferences for education) explain around a fifth of the residual variation in primary school attendance rates. The remaining household-level variation is attributable to unobserved household factors. The VPC for the household and commune fall to 27.9% and 7.3% respectively.</p><p>In column 4, commune-level variables are added to the model. Immediately clear is that the commune-level variance component falls from 0.355 to 0.241; the VPC for communes falls from 7% to 4.9%. Thus, the inclusion of distance to school and number of schools in the model helps to explain around one third of the commune-level variation in primary school attendance. This result suggests that the regional differences observed in Benin are down to other unobserved factors at the commune-level. These might be, for example, regional differences in labour markets, culture or traditions. The model has also shown that overall, relatively little of the regional variation in primary school attendance rates displayed in Benin is attributable to commune-level factors: Only 4.9% of the total remaining variation is at the commune-level, whilst some 30% is due to unobserved factors at the household level.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.">Random slopes model</head><p>The random-intercepts model of section 6.1 assumed that the effects of each of the independent variables was fixed across communes, and across households within communes. In order to test the validity of this assumption, it is possible to estimate a random slopes model, that allows both the intercept and the coefficient (slope) of explanatory variables to vary randomly across higher level units. The particular focus here is on commune-level effects of household wealth on primary school attendance. <ref type="bibr">32</ref> The model takes the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">ln p ijk 1 − p ijk = b 0 + b 1 x 1ijk . . . . . . + m 0k + m 1k x 1 k + w jk + 1 ijk<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Column 5 of <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 6</ref> reports the results of equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">9</ref>, which allows the slope of mean-centered wealth to vary across communes. The effect of wealth on the log-odds of attending school in commune k (i.e. the average effect of wealth) is given by b 1 + m 1k , which in this case is estimated to be 0.498 + m 1k . The between-commune variance in the effects of wealth, m 1k , is estimated to be 0.037. The between-commune variance in primary attendance, m k , falls from 0.241 to 0.214, which suggests that the distribution ofealth does indeed vary across communes (otherwise m k would have remained unchanged). The estimated commune interceptwealth slope covariance is negative (−0.043) which shows that those communes with below average primary school attendance rates (i.e. where m 0k &lt; 0) also tend to have above average effects of wealth on attendance (i.e. where m 1k . 0). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 6</ref> plots m 1k against m 0k .</p><p>In terms of potential policies to improve primary school attendance rates, this exposition is useful. Communes in the upper left quadrant represent those where the effect of wealth on primary school attendance is above average, whilst attendance itself lies below average. Therefore, these communes represent those areas where the greatest improvements in primary school attendance rates could be realized through policy interventions that either raise income or lower the cost of schooling. Interestingly, the average household wealth level of the 33 communes lying in this quadrant is below the national average. 33 This suggests that, by and large, interventions or policies that increased household income in the poorest communes nationally could see large increases in primary school attendance rates. <ref type="bibr">34</ref> The analysis of section 5 suggests that by lowering average distance to school (by building more schools, improving the road network etc.), this might free up time for boys to work (and as such contribute to family income) alongside studying, thus lowering the opportunity cost of attending school. This provides a clear example of how supply and demand side considerations work hand-in-hand to determine whether a child is sent to school.</p><p>Conversely, those communes lying in the lower left quadrant represent communes where primary attendance rates are below average, but the effect of wealth is also limited; increasing household wealth in such regions might have a limited impact on primary school attendance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Conclusion</head><p>This study has sought to shed light on the determinants of primary school attendance rates in Benin, a country that despite seeing almost unparalleled improvements in attendance, gender parity and completion of primary school over the last two decades, has been practically ignored in the literature. These results have presented numerous insights. Large regional disparities existed during the year of study  and indeed, still do, in the most recent DHS data (2011-12). The empirical analysis has presented evidence that factors on both the demand and supply side are predictors of whether or not a child will be enrolled in school. Richer households, those following a Christian religion and those with more educated household heads were more likely to send their children to school. Despite the narrowing gender gap in Benin at the time, girls still faced a lower likelihood of attending school than boys; adopted girls seemed at the greatest disadvantage. Focusing on the role of child labour, the empirical results highlight that those boys that worked alongside studying faced a higher opportunity cost of travel time to school than girls. In particular, it appears that distance to school mattered more for boys who worked in the field than those carrying out domestic work and that distance was only a significant determinant for those girls who worked in the field. In so far as working in the field generated more income for the household than did domestic work, then these results might be taken as an indication that distance to school goes some way to capturing the opportunity cost of attending.</p><p>Whilst much of the literature investigating the determinants of school attendance or enrolment has acknowledged that factors at the community or state level might play a part in determining enrolment trends, many studies continue to ignore higher level clustering in the data. In attempting to shed light on the large regional disparities that exist in Beninese primary school attendance, the present work explicitly accounts for higher level variation in school attendance by using a multilevel modelling strategy. A three-level random intercepts model, estimated at the individual, household and commune level, highlighted that there were a number of communes where primary school attendance was significantly lower than average. After controlling for individual, household and commune-level factors, the model is able to explain a large portion of the betweencommune variance in primary attendance rates. However, it also suggests that much of the residual variance in primary school attendance between communes is actually due to factors at the household level. A random slopes model suggests a number of communes where primary school attendance is below average and the effect of household wealth on attendance is above average. Such regions might stand to benefit most, in terms of primary school attendance rates, from government policies that raised household incomes, or reduced the costs of schooling.</p><p>Notes school attendance would not be captured. Secondly, the dependent variable is measured at the individual level and the distance variable at the commune level, so reverse causality is not likely to be an issue. 20. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Bartus (2005)</ref> for explanation of why it is preferable to present AMEs when a model contains a large number of dummy variables. 21. As such, I comment on the marginal effects below. 22. Results not shown, but available upon request 23. The results of a logit model where female and worked were interacted revealed a similar result (not shown), with the AME around −5%. 24. The 'Christian' category includes 'Protestant', 'Catholic', 'Celeste' &amp; 'Other Christian. 25. It might also be the case that the sample of heads with tertiary education is simply too small to accurately capture the effect. Only 300 children lived in a household with such a head, out of the sample of <ref type="bibr">17,094. 26</ref>. No significant differences were uncovered here when differentiating between rural and urban, or when including the 'Number of Schools' variable. 27. The types of work considered are 'work in the field' and 'domestic work'. These categories represent 50 and 44% of the respondents, whilst the vast majority of the remaining children were categorised as "other". 28. Thus, children currently in secondary school and those who have completed primary school but not gone on to secondary education are also included. 29. This judgement was made on the basis of LR-test statistics. 30. Initial diagnostics deemed that the computational complexity of adding a department level to the model in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table  6</ref> led to little gain in model performance. As such it was not included, but the graphical insight here is nonetheless useful. 31. In the multilevel models here, mean-centred wealth is included rather than the individual wealth quintiles, allowing estimation of the random slopes model, below. 32. This was deemed the most policy-relevant variable to focus on in this section. That is, the results help us to identify those communes where interventions that raised household wealth (or reduced the costs of schooling) would be most productive in increasing primary school attendance. It could have focused on, for example, household head's education level, but as that variable measures past educational attainment (and not something like literacy or numeracy), it is more difficult to envisage an appropriate policy response to influence this. 33. 23 of 33 had mean wealth levels below the national average. 34. Of course, any increases in attendance may potentially be limited by the availability of schools, teachers or supplies. However, such considerations are beyond the scope of the current analysis and, indeed, could not be investigated with the data at hand.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Net enrolment ratios 1990-2012.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Net primary school attendance (%) by commune, 2006. Source: Author's own calculations from the 2006 DHS (Mean = 56%).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Primary attendance age distribution: 2005-06 vs. 2011-12.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Random intercept residuals by commune.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Between-commune within-department variation in random intercepts.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Commune slopes vs commune intercepts.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Summary statistics.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Mean</cell><cell>Std. Dev.</cell><cell>Min</cell><cell>Max</cell></row><row><cell>Net attendance 2005-06</cell><cell>0.570</cell><cell>0.495</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Individual level</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>0.475</cell><cell>0.499</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Adopted</cell><cell>0.035</cell><cell>0.183</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Worked</cell><cell>0.729</cell><cell>0.444</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Worked in the field</cell><cell>0.318</cell><cell>0.444</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Domestic Work</cell><cell>0.367</cell><cell>0.482</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Other</cell><cell>0.044</cell><cell>0.206</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Household level</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Household religion</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Christian a</cell><cell>0.432</cell><cell>0.495</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Islam</cell><cell>0.256</cell><cell>0.437</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Traditional / Other</cell><cell>0.312</cell><cell>0.463</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Household wealth</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Poorest</cell><cell>0.222</cell><cell>0.416</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Poorer</cell><cell>0.220</cell><cell>0.414</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Middle</cell><cell>0.205</cell><cell>0.404</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Richer</cell><cell>0.193</cell><cell>0.395</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Richest</cell><cell>0.160</cell><cell>0.366</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Household head education level</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Primary</cell><cell>0.214</cell><cell>0.410</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>0.130</cell><cell>0.337</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Higher</cell><cell>0.018</cell><cell>0.132</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>School considered essential?</cell><cell>0.790</cell><cell>0.407</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Household size</cell><cell>8.174</cell><cell>4.104</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Rural</cell><cell>0.639</cell><cell>0.480</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Commune level</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Distance to school</cell><cell>1.279</cell><cell>0.971</cell><cell>0.134</cell><cell>5.399</cell></row><row><cell>(log) Schools per 5-14 year olds</cell><cell>−5.977</cell><cell>0.238</cell><cell>−6.577</cell><cell>−5.471</cell></row><row><cell>Observations: 17,094</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>a Christian includes 'Catholic', 'Protestant', 'Celeste' and 'Other Christian'. Traditional/Other includes the cat- egories 'Vodoun', 'Other Traditional', 'Other Religion' and 'No Religion'.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Determinants of primary school attendance, logit estimation. Log odds shown. Average Marginal Effects shown in square brackets. Controls for the survey month included but not shown.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>Sample</cell><cell>All</cell><cell>Boys</cell><cell>Girls</cell><cell>All</cell><cell>All</cell><cell>All</cell><cell>All</cell><cell>Boys</cell><cell>Girls</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>−0.446***</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>−0.444***</cell><cell>−0.444***</cell><cell>−0.444***</cell><cell>−0.444***</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.055)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.055)</cell><cell>(0.055)</cell><cell>(0.056)</cell><cell>(0.056)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>[−0.088***]</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>[−0.088***]</cell><cell>[−0.088***]</cell><cell>[−0.088***]</cell><cell>[−0.088***]</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Age</cell><cell>2.440***</cell><cell>2.650***</cell><cell>2.259***</cell><cell>2.441***</cell><cell>2.440***</cell><cell>2.437***</cell><cell>2.436***</cell><cell>2.650***</cell><cell>2.259***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.116)</cell><cell>(0.148)</cell><cell>(0.167)</cell><cell>(0.115)</cell><cell>(0.115)</cell><cell>(0.116)</cell><cell>(0.116)</cell><cell>(0.146)</cell><cell>(0.165)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>[0.481***]</cell><cell>[0.490***]</cell><cell>[0.469***]</cell><cell>[0.484***]</cell><cell>[0.481***]</cell><cell>[0.481***]</cell><cell>[0.481***]</cell><cell>[0.491***]</cell><cell>[0.471***]</cell></row><row><cell>Age 2</cell><cell>−0.128***</cell><cell>−0.137***</cell><cell>−0.120***</cell><cell>−0.128***</cell><cell>−0.128***</cell><cell>−0.128***</cell><cell>−0.128***</cell><cell>−0.137***</cell><cell>−0.120***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.009)</cell><cell>(0.010)</cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.009)</cell><cell>(0.010)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>[−0.025***]</cell><cell>[−0.025***]</cell><cell>[−0.025***]</cell><cell>[−0.025***]</cell><cell>[−0.025***]</cell><cell>[−0.025***]</cell><cell>[−0.025***]</cell><cell>[−0.025***]</cell><cell>[−0.025***]</cell></row><row><cell>Adopted</cell><cell>−0.681***</cell><cell>−0.086</cell><cell>−0.980***</cell><cell>−0.674***</cell><cell>−0.675***</cell><cell>−0.689***</cell><cell>−0.690***</cell><cell>−0.095</cell><cell>−0.978***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.182)</cell><cell>(0.178)</cell><cell>(0.214)</cell><cell>(0.183)</cell><cell>(0.184)</cell><cell>(0.180)</cell><cell>(0.180)</cell><cell>(0.178)</cell><cell>(0.216)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>[−0.134***]</cell><cell>[−0.016]</cell><cell>[−0.203***]</cell><cell>[−0.134***]</cell><cell>[−0.135***]</cell><cell>[−0.136***]</cell><cell>[−0.136***]</cell><cell>[−0.018]</cell><cell>[−0.204***]</cell></row><row><cell>Worked</cell><cell>−0.117</cell><cell>0.0163</cell><cell>−0.230***</cell><cell>−0.122</cell><cell>−0.121</cell><cell>−0.125</cell><cell>−0.122</cell><cell>0.451***</cell><cell>−0.122</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.080)</cell><cell>(0.091)</cell><cell>(0.089)</cell><cell>(0.079)</cell><cell>(0.079)</cell><cell>(0.079)</cell><cell>(0.079)</cell><cell>(0.134)</cell><cell>(0.178)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>[−0.023]</cell><cell>[0.003]</cell><cell>[−0.048***]</cell><cell>[−0.024]</cell><cell>[−0.023]</cell><cell>[−0.025]</cell><cell>[−0.024]</cell><cell>[0.084***]</cell><cell>[−0.026]</cell></row><row><cell>Household size</cell><cell>−0.015**</cell><cell>−0.018**</cell><cell>−0.013</cell><cell>−0.017***</cell><cell>−0.017***</cell><cell>−0.016**</cell><cell>−0.016**</cell><cell>−0.019***</cell><cell>−0.016*</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.006)</cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.008)</cell><cell>(0.006)</cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.006)</cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.009)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 .Table 4 .</head><label>34</label><figDesc>Predictive margins of religion, by household wealth level. Predictive margins of household head's education, by household wealth level.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Wealth level</cell><cell>Christian</cell><cell>Predictive margin</cell></row><row><cell>Poorest</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>0.394</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell>0.455</cell></row><row><cell>Poorer</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>0.489</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell>0.551</cell></row><row><cell>Middle</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>0.585</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell>0.644</cell></row><row><cell>Richer</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>0.655</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell>0.710</cell></row><row><cell>Richest</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>0.675</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell>0.728</cell></row><row><cell>Wealth level</cell><cell>Head education</cell><cell>Predictive margin</cell></row><row><cell>Poorest</cell><cell>None</cell><cell>0.383</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Primary</cell><cell>0.464</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>0.528</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Tertiary</cell><cell>0.446</cell></row><row><cell>Poorer</cell><cell>None</cell><cell>0.478</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Primary</cell><cell>0.561</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>0.623</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Tertiary</cell><cell>0.543</cell></row><row><cell>Middle</cell><cell>None</cell><cell>0.575</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Primary</cell><cell>0.655</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>0.710</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Tertiary</cell><cell>0.637</cell></row><row><cell>Richer</cell><cell>None</cell><cell>0.647</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Primary</cell><cell>0.720</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>0.769</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Tertiary</cell><cell>0.704</cell></row><row><cell>Richest</cell><cell>None</cell><cell>0.667</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Primary</cell><cell>0.738</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Secondary</cell><cell>0.785</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Tertiary</cell><cell>0.723</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Effect of distance to school, by gender and work status. here contains all covariates as in Column 4 ofTable 2, but only the distance to school variable is shown. Stan-</figDesc><table><row><cell>Gender</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Boys</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Girls</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Work status</cell><cell>No</cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell>No</cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Type of work</cell><cell>n/a</cell><cell>All</cell><cell>Field</cell><cell>Domestic</cell><cell>n/a</cell><cell>All</cell><cell>Field</cell><cell>Domestic</cell></row><row><cell>Distance to school</cell><cell>−0.072</cell><cell>−0.325***</cell><cell>−0.390***</cell><cell>−0.299***</cell><cell>−0.044</cell><cell>−0.088</cell><cell>−0.214**</cell><cell>−0.098</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.090)</cell><cell>(0.065)</cell><cell>(0.081)</cell><cell>(0.091)</cell><cell>(0.083)</cell><cell>(0.065)</cell><cell>(0.098)</cell><cell>(0.076)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>[−0.012]</cell><cell>[−0.062***]</cell><cell>[−0.079***]</cell><cell>[0.044***]</cell><cell>[−0.009]</cell><cell>[0.019]</cell><cell>[−0.044**]</cell><cell>[−0.019]</cell></row><row><cell>Observations</cell><cell>2562</cell><cell>6407</cell><cell>3708</cell><cell>2302</cell><cell>2063</cell><cell>6062</cell><cell>1738</cell><cell>3941</cell></row><row><cell>The model estimated</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>dard errors, clustered at the commune level, in parentheses. *p &lt; 0.1; **p &lt; 0.05; ***p &lt; 0.01; Log odds shown. Average Marginal Effects shown in square brackets.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Multilevel models.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Random intercepts</cell><cell></cell><cell>Random slopes</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>Individual level characteristics</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell></cell><cell>−0.538***</cell><cell>−0.582***</cell><cell>−0.582***</cell><cell>−0.578***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.042)</cell><cell>(0.043)</cell><cell>(0.043)</cell><cell>(0.043)</cell></row><row><cell>Age</cell><cell></cell><cell>3.171***</cell><cell>3.183***</cell><cell>3.182***</cell><cell>3.163***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.139)</cell><cell>(0.140)</cell><cell>(0.140)</cell><cell>(0.139)</cell></row><row><cell>Age 2</cell><cell></cell><cell>−0.167***</cell><cell>−0.167***</cell><cell>−0.167***</cell><cell>−0.166</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.008)</cell><cell>(0.008)</cell><cell>(0.008)</cell><cell>(0.008)</cell></row><row><cell>Adopted</cell><cell></cell><cell>−0.658***</cell><cell>−0.924***</cell><cell>−0.917***</cell><cell>−0.929***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.117)</cell><cell>(0.118)</cell><cell>(0.118)</cell><cell>(0.117)</cell></row><row><cell>Worked</cell><cell></cell><cell>−0.297***</cell><cell>−0.167***</cell><cell>−0.156***</cell><cell>−0.137**</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.055)</cell><cell>(0.055)</cell><cell>(0.054)</cell><cell>(0.054)</cell></row><row><cell>Household level characteristics</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Household size</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>−0.019***</cell><cell>−0.015**</cell><cell>−0.015***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.007)</cell></row><row><cell>Religion</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Islam</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>−0.386***</cell><cell>−0.311***</cell><cell>−0.327***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.078)</cell><cell>(0.079)</cell><cell>(0.079)</cell></row><row><cell>Traditional / Other</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>−0.401***</cell><cell>−0.414***</cell><cell>−0.413***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.063)</cell><cell>(0.063)</cell><cell>(0.063)</cell></row><row><cell>Grand mean -centred wealth level</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.507***</cell><cell>0.497***</cell><cell>0.498***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.024)</cell><cell>(0.024)</cell><cell>(0.033)</cell></row><row><cell>Household head's education</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Primary</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.460***</cell><cell>0.447***</cell><cell>0.329***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.063)</cell><cell>(0.063)</cell><cell>(0.063)</cell></row><row><cell>Secondary</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.714***</cell><cell>0.701***</cell><cell>0.696***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.089)</cell><cell>(0.089)</cell><cell>(0.089)</cell></row><row><cell>Tertiary</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.418**</cell><cell>0.368*</cell><cell>0.371*</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.207)</cell><cell>(0.206)</cell><cell>(0.206)</cell></row><row><cell>School essential?</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.154**</cell><cell>0.134**</cell><cell>0.125***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.064)</cell><cell>(0.064)</cell><cell>(0.064)</cell></row><row><cell>Rural</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>−0.248***</cell><cell></cell><cell>−0.236***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.062)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.062)</cell></row><row><cell>Commune level characteristics</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Distance to school</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>−0.165**</cell><cell>−0.0210</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.079)</cell><cell>(0.077)</cell></row><row><cell>(ln) Schools per 5-14 year olds</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.073***</cell><cell>1.128***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(0.303)</cell><cell>(0.289)</cell></row><row><cell>Intercept (β 0 )</cell><cell>0.322***</cell><cell>−13.528***</cell><cell>−13.544***</cell><cell>−6.646***</cell><cell>−6.422***</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.089)</cell><cell>(0.577)</cell><cell>(0.603)</cell><cell>(1.842)</cell><cell>(1.764)</cell></row><row><cell>Random effects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Level 2: Household</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Intercept variance</cell><cell>1.223</cell><cell>1.800</cell><cell>1.418</cell><cell>1.422</cell><cell>1.373</cell></row><row><cell>VPC w :</cell><cell>0.240</cell><cell>0.310</cell><cell>0.279</cell><cell>0.287</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>ICC:</cell><cell>0.353</cell><cell>0.430</cell><cell>0.352</cell><cell>0.336</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Level 3: Commune</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Intercept variance</cell><cell>0.573</cell><cell>0.700</cell><cell>0.368</cell><cell>0.241</cell><cell>0.214</cell></row><row><cell>VPC m :</cell><cell>0.113</cell><cell>0.120</cell><cell>0.073</cell><cell>0.049</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>ICC:</cell><cell>0.113</cell><cell>0.120</cell><cell>0.073</cell><cell>0.049</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Wealth slope variance</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0.037</cell></row><row><cell>Intercept -Wealth slope covariance</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>−0.043</cell></row><row><cell>Observations:</cell><cell>17,094</cell><cell>17,094</cell><cell>17,094</cell><cell>17,094</cell><cell>17,094</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Odds ratios shown. Standard errors in parentheses; *p &lt; 0.1; **p &lt; 0.05; ***p &lt; 0.01.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2">K. MCNABB</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4">K. MCNABB</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6">K. MCNABB</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8">K. MCNABB</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">K. MCNABB</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgement</head><p>This article was prepared within the UNU-WIDER project on Gender and Development. I am grateful for useful comments from two anonymous referees. Any remaining errors are my own.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disclosure statement</head><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the author.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Impressive GERs, however, cannot be taken at face value. By definition, a value greater than 100 might point to a system playing catch-up, or a large number of students entering late or repeating grades</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Both are likely to apply in the Beninese context</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">This year was chosen as it was the most recent for which both DHS and INSAE data were available</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">For a more detailed account of the backdrop to the 1990 reforms, see ODI</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">I rely here on the UIS data as it allows for comparisons with world and regional averages; the regional averages are based on UIS estimates</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The GPI is calculated as female gross enrolment divided by male gross enrolment. Thus this statistic equals 1 when gender parity is achieved</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">INSAE has not made available its school supply statistics for 2011-12</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Unfortunately</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>so the main analysis here focuses on the 2005-06 round of the DHS, where complimentary statistics from INSAE are available</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">This is in a household production function framework, where parents are deemed to make investment decisions on the part of all household members</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Often times it is not possible to have a precise measure of distance between house and school, so approximations based on population and area of a state must be made</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>When even this data is missing, a simple rural or urban dummy might be included in estimations and, within reason. pick up some of the same effect</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">who confirm the existence of disconnected financial spheres between husband and wife in Benin</title>
		<editor>LeMay-Boucher and Dagnelie</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Other studies finding positive effects of parental education on school attendance are, for example</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Delprato and Sabates</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Kazeem, Jensen, and Stokes</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Huisman and Smits</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Glick and Sahn. Lavy (1996) and Lincove</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Handa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">In line with the discussion above and evidence from other developing country contexts, the data also shows that of those attending school, some 72% also worked, compared to 73% of those not attending school. Thus, it is clear that work and school attendance are not mutually exclusive activities in the Beninese context</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Whilst the index is not, for the most part, equivalized for household size, this does not differ significantly across wealth quintiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dhs</forename><surname>See</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>for a detailed report on the construction of the wealth index</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The set of possible answers was &apos;No&apos;, &apos;Yes, essential&apos; or &apos;Yes, more or less necessary&apos;. This question was asked to all households</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>not only those containing children of school age</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Unfortunately, it was not possible to obtain population estimates for the age range of 6-11, the official primary school age. Thus, the number of schools per children aged 5-14 is shown</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">There are sometimes concerns surrounding endogeneity of distance-to-school variables: for example, the endogenous placement of schools, in areas where primary enrolment is low. However, this is unlikely to be a concern here: Firstly, the data is cross-sectional and therefore only measures the number of schools at one point in time -any phenomenon where more schools were being built as a result of initially low primary References Admassie, A. 2003</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Educational Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="185" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Child Labour and Schooling in the Context of a Subsistence Rural Economy: Can They Be Compatible?</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Benin</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Benin, the Congo</title>
		<editor>C. Allen, M. S. Radu, and K. Somerville</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Pinter</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="144" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new data set of educational attainment in the world, 1950–2010</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Barro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jong</forename><forename type="middle">Wha</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jdeveco.2012.10.001</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-3878</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="198" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-09" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimation of Marginal Effects Using Margeff</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bartus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stata Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="329" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human Capital, a Theoretical and Empirical Analysis, with Special Reference to Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In National Bureau of Economic Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
			<publisher>Columbia University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Family Structure, Parental Perceptions, and Child Labor in Kenya: What Factors Determine Who is Enrolled in School?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Claudia</forename><surname>Buchmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/3006177</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Forces</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Social Forces</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0037-7732</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1349</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000-06" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gender Inequalities in Primary Schooling: The Roles of Poverty and Adverse Cultural Practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Colclough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tembon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Educational Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Religious, Social and Economic Factors Hindering the Education of Girls in Northern Nigeria</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marg</forename><surname>Csapo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/0305006810170307</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Education</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Comparative Education</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0305-0068</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1360-0486</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="319" />
			<date type="published" when="1981-09" />
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does promoting school attendance reduce child labor? Evidence from Burkina Faso&apos;s BRIGHT project</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jacobus</forename><surname>De Hoop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Furio</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Rosati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.econedurev.2013.11.001</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economics of Education Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Economics of Education Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0272-7757</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-04" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does cost of schooling affect enrollment by the poor? Universal primary education in Uganda</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Klaus</forename><surname>Deininger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0272-7757(02)00053-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economics of Education Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Economics of Education Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0272-7757</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="305" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-06" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multilevel analysis of late entry in Nigeria</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marcos</forename><surname>Delprato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ricardo</forename><surname>Sabates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/1743727x.2014.903917</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Research &amp; Method in Education</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">International Journal of Research &amp; Method in Education</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1743-727X</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1743-7288</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-04" />
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The DHS Wealth Index</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Dhs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/CR6/CR6.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">DHS Comparative Reports, 6. Accessed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Infecundity, Infertility, and Childlessness in Developing Countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Dhs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/topics/infertility/DHS-CR9.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">DHS Comparative Reports, 9</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Till Marriage Do Us Part: Education and Remittances from Married Women in Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Eloundou-Enyegue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Calvès</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/3542130</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Education Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Comparative Education Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0010-4086</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<publisher>JSTOR</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What Policies will Reduce Gender Schooling Gaps in Developing Countries: Evidence and Interpretation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Glick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.worlddev.2007.09.014</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Development</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">World Development</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0305-750X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1623" to="1646" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-09" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The demand for primary schooling in Madagascar: Price, quality, and the choice between public and private providers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Glick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Sahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jdeveco.2005.01.001</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdf.usaid.gov/pdf_docs/PNADC115.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-3878</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="118" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-02" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Raising primary school enrolment in developing countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sudhanshu</forename><surname>Handa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0304-3878(02)00055-x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-3878</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-10" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of Household- and District-Level Factors on Primary School Enrollment in 30 Developing Countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Janine</forename><surname>Huisman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jeroen</forename><surname>Smits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.worlddev.2008.01.007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Development</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">World Development</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0305-750X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-01" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Analyse Économique (INSAE) and Macro International Inc</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<pubPlace>Calverton, Maryland, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Institut National de la Statistique et de l</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Enquête Démographique et de Santé (EDSB-III) -Bénin</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">School Attendance in Nigeria: Understanding the Impact and Intersection of Gender, Urban‐Rural Residence, and Socioeconomic Status</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Aramidé</forename><surname>Kazeem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Leif</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle"> Shannon</forename><surname>Stokes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/652139</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">26448653</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC4593499</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://europepmc.org/articles/pmc4593499?pdf=render" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comparative Education Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Comparative Education Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0010-4086</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1545-701X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="319" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-05" />
			<publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">School supply constraints and children&apos;s educational outcomes in rural Ghana</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Victor</forename><surname>Lavy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0304-3878(96)00416-6</idno>
		<idno type="PII">S0304-3878(96)00416-6</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-T3FBJLNL-7</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">6F3995019CED215BD6AEBF94154F0CCB7BA76882</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-3878</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="314" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-12" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Module 11: Three-level Multilevel Models, Stata Practical</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Leckie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.cmm.bris.ac.uk/lemma" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Centre for Multilevel Modelling. Accessed 10-4-2015</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">runmlwin: A Program to Run theMLwiNMultilevel Modeling Software from withinStata</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">George</forename><surname>Leckie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chris</forename><surname>Charlton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.18637/jss.v052.i11</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.jstatsoft.org/index.php/jss/article/view/v052i11/v52i11.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Statistical Software</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">J. Stat. Soft.</title>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1548-7660</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<publisher>Foundation for Open Access Statistic</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">THE DIVORCED FINANCIAL SPHERES OF BENINESE SPOUSES</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Philippe</forename><surname>Lemay-Boucher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Olivier</forename><surname>Dagnelie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/jid.2839</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-3WC9SKWT-7</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">F85E11CAB25313E1009B52CC2F40AA597F60620B</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of International Development</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">J. Int. Dev.</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0954-1748</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-05-14" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of price on school enrollment under Uganda&apos;s policy of free primary education</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jane</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lincove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.econedurev.2012.04.007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economics of Education Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Economics of Education Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0272-7757</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="799" to="811" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-10" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving Identification of Demand-Side Obstacles to Schooling: Findings from Revealed and Stated Preference Models in Two SSA Countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jane</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lincove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.worlddev.2014.07.018</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Development</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">World Development</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0305-750X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-02" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Benin&apos;s Progress in Education: Expanding Access and Closing the Gender Gap</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Odi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<publisher>Overseas Development Institute</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Out of School Children. Data Challenges in Measuring Access to Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Omoeva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sylla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hatch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>fhi360. Accessed 25-6-2015</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.fhi360.org/sites/default/files/media/documents/Out_of_school_children_data_challenges.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Education Policy and Data Center</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">MLwiN Version 2.35. Centre for Multilevel Modelling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rasbash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Charlton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Browne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Healy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Bristol</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Assessment of Estimation Procedures for Multilevel Models with Binary Responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">German</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Noreen</forename><surname>Goldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2983404</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society. Series A (Statistics in Society)</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society. Series A (Statistics in Society)</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0964-1998</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">73</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>JSTOR</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Political Economy of Bad Data: Evidence from African Survey and Administrative Statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Justin</forename><surname>Sandefur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amanda</forename><surname>Glassman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00220388.2014.968138</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Development Studies</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Journal of Development Studies</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-0388</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1743-9140</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="116" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-02" />
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Generalized Latent Variable Modelling: Multilevel, Longitudinal, and Structural Equation Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Skrondal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rabe-Hesketh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<publisher>Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boca Raton, FL</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UIS Frequently Asked Questions. Education Statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Uis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>20/10/2015</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.uis.unesco.org/Education/Documents/FAQ-education-statistics-rev5-en.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">UNESCO Institute for Statistics. Accessed</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-08-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Enrolment Ratios</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
