<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">MDY volume 18 issue 1 Cover and Front matter</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cambridge University Press (CUP)</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Cambridge University Press (CUP)</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2013-12-19">2013-12-19</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michele</forename><surname>Boldrin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><surname>Turnovsky</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Spear</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jean-Pascal</forename><surname>Bénassy</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paris</forename><surname>Cepremap</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Willem</forename><surname>Buiter</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>London</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pierpaolo</forename><surname>Benigno</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Guido</forename><surname>Carli</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joydeep</forename><surname>Bhattacharya</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Francois</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Velde</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Federal</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Kansas</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>356 Snow Hall, 1460 Jayhawk Boulevard</addrLine>
									<postCode>66045-7523</postCode>
									<settlement>Lawrence</settlement>
									<region>KS</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">The Center for Financial Stability</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1120 Avenue of the Americas, 4th Floor</addrLine>
									<postCode>10036</postCode>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Washington University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>One Brookings Drive, MO63130, and Universidad Carlos III, Madrid; Gregory D. Hess, 500 East 9th Street</addrLine>
									<settlement>St. Louis</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Claremont McKenna College</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>91711</postCode>
									<settlement>Claremont</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Washington</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box 353330</postBox>
									<postCode>98195</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>WA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">UCLA</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>405 Hilgard Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>2261, 90024</postCode>
									<settlement>Bunche Hall, Los Angeles</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Graduate School of Industrial Administration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Carnegie Mellon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>15213. Local Area Network Manager: Nathan Haley</addrLine>
									<settlement>Pittsburgh, Lawrence</settlement>
									<region>PA, Kansas</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Kansas</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">School of Economics and Political Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">London), Francis X. Diebold (University of Pennsylvania), Steven Durlauf (University of Wisconsin), Douglas Gale (New York University), Giancarlo Gandolfo (University of Rome), Roger Guesnerie (DELTA, Paris), Takatoshi Ito (University of Tokyo), Timothy Kehoe (University of Minnesota), Finn Kydland (Carnegie Mellon University), Lung-Fei Lee (Ohio State University), Adrian Pagan (Australian National University), Robert Townsend (Massachusetts Institute of Technology), Mark Watson (Princeton University), Kenneth West (University of Wisconsin), Michael Woodford (Columbia University), Randall Wright (University of Pennsylvania)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="institution">Washington University)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Jasmina Arifovic (Simon Fraser</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff10">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State University), Florin Bilbiie (Paris School of Economics), Volker Böhm (University of Bielefeld, Germany), Hafedh Bouakez (HEC Montreal, Canada), Raouf Boucekkine (Universite Catholique de Louvain, Belgium), Jeffrey Campbell (Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago), Shankha Chakraborty (University of Oregon), Marcelle Chauvet (University of California at Riverside), Rose-Anne Dana (Université Paris IX-Dauphine), Christophe Deissenberg (University d&apos;Aix-Marseille II), Huberto Ennis (Federal Reserve Bank of Richmond), Alvaro Escribano (Universidad Carlos III de Madrid, Spain), Emilio Espino (Buenos Aires, Argentina), George Evans (University of Oregon), Ester Faia (Goethe University of Frankfurt), Roger Farmer (UCLA), Alessandra Fogli (Minneapolis Federal Reserve Bank), Luisa Fuster (Madrid Institute of Advanced Studies, Spain), Oded Galor (Brown University and Hebrew University of Jerusalem), Marc Giannoni (Federal Reserve Bank of New York), Liam Graham (University College, London), Antonio Guarino (University College, London), Thorvaldur Gylfason (University of Iceland), Niels Haldrup (Aarhus University, Denmark), John Hassler (Stockholm University), Moshe Hazan (The Hebrew University of Jerusalem), Cars Hommes (University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands), Kevin Huang (Vanderbilt University), Leo Kass (University of Konstanz, Germany</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Todd Keister</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff11">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Keith Kuester (University of Bonn, Germany), Blake LeBaron (Brandeis University), Helmut Lütkepohl (European University Institute, Florence), Iourii Manovskii (University of Pennsylvania), David Marshall (Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago), Alfredo Medio (University of Udine, Italy), Jianjun Miao (Boston University), Kaushik Mitra (University of St. Andrews, UK), Omer Moav (The Hebrew University of Jerusalem), Cyril Monnet (University of Bern, Switzerland), José V. Rodriguez Mora (University of Edinburgh, UK), Lee Ohanian (UCLA), Patrick Pintus (Université de la Méditerranée &amp; GREQAM, France), Bruce Preston (Columbia University), Neil Rankin (University of York, UK), Francisco Ruge-Murcia (University of Montreal), Gilles Saint-Paul (Université de Toulouse, France), Argia M. Sbordone (Federal Reserve Bank of New York), Klaus Martin Schneider (Stanford University), Apostolos Serletis (University of Calgary, Canada), Tony Smith (Yale University), Stephen Spear (Carnegie Mellon University), Stephen Turnovsky (University of Washington), Farshid Vahid (Monash University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff12">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Reserve Bank of Chicago), Nicolaas Vriend (Queen Mary, University of London), Neng Wang (Columbia University), Ronald Wendner (University of Graz, Austria), Sevin Yeltekin (Carnegie Mellon</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">MDY volume 18 issue 1 Cover and Front matter</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Macroeconomic Dynamics</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Macroecon. Dynam.</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">1365-1005</idno>
						<idno type="eISSN">1469-8056</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Cambridge University Press (CUP)</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">01</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="f1" to="f4"/>
							<date type="published" when="2013-12-19" />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1017/s136510051300076x</idno>
					<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.cambridge.org/core/services/aop-cambridge-core/content/view/6B46CE5C63CC171132FDEA4D054E2CFB/S136510051300076Xa.pdf/div-class-title-mdy-volume-18-issue-1-cover-and-front-matter-div.pdf" />
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T22:30+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EDITORIAL POLICY</head><p>Macroeconomic Dynamics publishes research of the highest theoretical, empirical or quantitative sophistication. Papers of high quality are welcomed from all areas of advanced macroeconomics and allied fields, so long as the research is founded in a rigorous scientific approach. Major advances in macroeconomics without immediate policy applications also are accepted, if they show potential for application in the future. Occasional book reviews, software reviews, announcements, conference proceedings and interviews are published.</p><p>An electronic version of the journal is published just prior to the paper version at journals.cambridge.org/mdy. Access to the full-text articles of the electronic version will be limited to institutional subscribers of the hard copy version of the journal, with access available to all online users at that institution's registered domain. Tables of Contents, abstracts, searching and alerting services will remain free of charge. To view the full text of Macroeconomic Dynamics, you will need to use the Adobe Acrobat Reader software. If you do not have a copy already, you can get it free of charge. Just follow the link from our Cambridge Journals Online home page, download it, and install it as a plug-in helper application for your browser.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Jinli Zeng, Jie Zhang, and Michael Ka-Yiu Fung 1Davide Debortoli, Junior Maih, and Ricardo Nunes 175 Multiple Testing for Output Convergence Thomas Deckers and Christoph Hanck 199 MD SURVEY. Spear and Warren Young 215 NOTESTom Ahn, Jeremy Sandford, and Paul Shea 244</head><label></label><figDesc>MACROECONOMIC DYNAMICS Volume 18, Number 1, January 2014 Contents ARTICLES Patent Length and Price Regulation in an R&amp;D Growth Model with Monopolistic Competition Interest Rate Rules and Equilibrium Stability under Deep Habits June, July, September, October, and December. Annual subscription rates for Volume 18, 2014: Institutional rate is (print and electronic) $1018.00 in the USA, Canada, and Mexico, £614.00 + VAT elsewhere. Institutional rate (electronic only) $743.00 in the USA, Canada, and Mexico, £454.00 + VAT elsewhere. Institutional rate (print only) $944.00 in the USA, Canada, and Mexico, £560.00 + VAT elsewhere. Individual rate is (print and electronic) $236.00 in the USA, Canada, and Mexico, £134.00 + VAT elsewhere. Individual rate (print only) $229.00 in the USA, Canada, and Mexico, £131.00 + VAT elsewhere. Students (print only) $122.00 in the USA, Canada, and Mexico, £46.00 + VAT elsewhere. For members of the Econometric Society, the Society for the Advancement of Economic Theory, the Society for Nonlinear Dynamics and Econometrics, the Society for Computational Economics, and the Society for the Promotion of Economic Theory the rate is $100.00 in the USA, Canada, and Mexico, £62.00 + VAT elsewhere. Institutional access is via IP address range(s) or domain name(s); individual subscriber access is via a username and password. Prices include postage; airmail is extra. Write to Cambridge University Press, 32 Avenue of the Americas, New York, NY 10013-2473, or outside the USA, Canada, and Mexico to Cambridge University Press, The Edinburgh Building, Shaftesbury Road, Cambridge CB2 8RU, England. Claims for missing issues should be made immediately after receipt of the next issue. Philadelphia, PA 19104, USA is authorized to supply single copies of separate article for private use only. Article reprints are available from the authors. For orders of 50 or more reprints, contact Cambridge University Press.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">SUBSCRIPTION INFORMATION: Macroeconomic Dynamics (ISSN 1365-1005) is published</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Sarah Zubairy Estimated Thresholds in the Response of Output to Monetary Policy: Are Large Policy Changes Less Effective? Luiggi Donayre Can Capacity Constraints Explain Asymmetries of the Business Cycle? Malte Knüppel The Endogenous Determination of Retirement Age and Social Security Benefits Francisco Cabo and Ana García-González How Child Costs and Survival Shaped the Industrial Revolution and the Demographic Transition Holger Strulik and Jacob Weisdorf eight times a year in January, March, April, Macroeconomic Dynamics is indexed in EconLit; The Journal of Economic Literature (e-JEL and JEL on CD); ISI: 23 41 65 93 114 Current Contents/Social &amp; Behavioral Sciences; Social Sciences Citation Index; Research Alert; Mathematical</cell></row><row><cell>Which Inflation to Target? A Small Open Economy with Sticky Wages Reviews; MathSciNet; Zentralblatt fur Mathematik.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Alessia Campolmi</cell><cell>145</cell></row><row><cell>Loose Commitment in Medium-Scale Macroeconomic Models:</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Theory and Applications</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Optimum Savings and Optimal Growth: The Cass-Malinvaud-Koopmans</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Nexus</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Stephen EA Note on Bubbles, Worthless Assets, and the Curious Case of</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>General Motors</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>Periodicals postage pending at NewYork, NY and additional mailing offices. Postmaster: send address changes in the USA, Canada, and Mexico to: Macroeconomic Dynamics, Cambridge University Press, 100 Brook Hill Drive, West Nyack, NY 10994-2133. Send address changes elsewhere to: Macroeconomic Dynamics, Journals Dept., Cambridge University Press, The Edinburgh Building, Shaftesbury Road, Cambridge, CB2 8RU, U.K.c 2014 Cambridge University Press. Photocopying information for users in the USA: The Item-Fee Code for this publication indicates that copying for internal or personal use beyond that permitted by Section 107 or 108 of the US Copyright Law is authorized for users duly registered with the Copyright Clearance Center (CCC) Transactional Reporting Service, provided that the appropriate remittance of $18.00 per article is paid directly to: CCC, 222 Rosewood Drive, Danvers, MA 01923. Specific written permission must be obtained from the publisher for all other copying. The Item-Fee Code for this journal is 1365-1005/14 $18.00.ISI Tearsheet Service, 3501 Market Street,</note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S136510051300076X Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 17:02:46, subject to the Cambridge</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
