<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Weights and substitution degree in multidimensional well-being in China</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Emerald</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Emerald</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-03-30">30 March 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Esfandiar</forename><surname>Maasoumi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Emory University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>Georgia</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Emory University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>Georgia</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tong</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Emory University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>Georgia</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Emory University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<region>Georgia</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Weights and substitution degree in multidimensional well-being in China</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Journal of Economic Studies</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Economic Studies</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0144-3585</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Emerald</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="19"/>
							<date type="published" when="2018-03-30">30 March 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1108/jes-04-2014-0055</idno>
					<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/9f0d/90fdafa24982a8f37a5654b11720280f05a3.pdf" />
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T21:19+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>China</term>
					<term>Poverty</term>
					<term>Entropy metric</term>
					<term>Maasoumi&apos;s two-step measures of multivariate inequality</term>
					<term>Multidimensional well-being</term>
					<term>Urban Paper type Research paper</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Emerald is a global publisher linking research and practice to the benefit of society. The company manages a portfolio of more than 290 journals and over 2,350 books and book series volumes, as well as providing an extensive range of online products and additional customer resources and services. Emerald is both COUNTER 4 and TRANSFER compliant. The organization is a partner of the Committee on Publication Ethics (COPE) and also works with Portico and the LOCKSS initiative for digital archive preservation.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>It is now generally accepted that well-being and policy are best viewed in many dimensions, and related indices. However, there is an inevitable lack of consensus on which attribute dimensions to include, the relative weights for each, and the substitution between the attributes. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Decancq and Lugo's (2013)</ref> paper, a discussion is given of different approaches to determine the relative weights in multidimensional indices of welfare, one of 4 JES 42,1 which is to infer information on weights based on self-reported "happiness. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">" Nardo et al. (2005)</ref> proposed a regression of life satisfaction on various variables to derive the relative weights. However, this approach suffers from a number of disadvantages. First, there is over reliance on self-reported indicator of "happiness." Second, it is complex to take into consideration explicit non-linear relationships in regressions. Third, this approach does not handle the substitution relationship among different attributes in a satisfactory manner. In this paper we propose a different strategy. First, we adopt ideal aggregation functions that combine different attributes so as to minimize general entropic divergence between the aggregate's distribution, and the distributions of the constituent attributes. This procedure leaves the parameters of the aggregator function undetermined. But these parameters can be obtained to, again, minimize the entropic divergence between the distribution of the aggregates and the distribution of any desired measure of "happiness." A metric entropy measure is a proper measure of "distance" and suitable to compare two or more distributions, with a minimand that identifies weights and other parameters uniquely. This offers an aggregation formula, as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Maasoumi (1986)</ref>, which is extended in this paper by a numerical optimization routine to identify suitable numerical values for weights and other parameters. These numerically identified well-being measures provide a basis for multidimensional consideration of poverty and inequity.</p><p>The structure of this paper is as follows. In Section 2, we introduce Maasoumi's two-step measures of multivariate well-being and inequality; In Section 3, we introduce the two metric entropy measures; Section 4 describes the numerical optimization procedures; Section 5 contains the empirical results based on CHIPS; and Section 6 provides the conclusion and potential future research directions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Multivariate measure of well-being and inequality</head><p>It has been widely accepted that only using one attribute (usually income or GDP) to measure individuals' or countries' welfare is insufficient. We should incorporate more attributes (especially non-tradable ones) to obtain more comprehensive information. However, including more attributes brings in the problem of aggregation, that is how to aggregate different indicators of well-being to represent the welfare level. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Maasoumi (1986)</ref> proposed a two-step measure of multivariate inequality. In the first step, he used different attributes to construct a welfare aggregate or "average," and in the second step, he calculated the inequality index using each person's welfare evaluation obtained in the first step. We now describe this two-step measures of multivariate inequality method in detail.</p><p>In the first step, we address the aggregation problem using the generalized entropy measure to have a representation of the divergence between the multiple distribution of the attributes, on the one hand, and the distribution of the latent aggregator index, on the other. Let S i be the individual i's aggregate welfare, which can be seen as individual's utility evaluation or welfare assessment. Let X ij be individual i's amount of jth attribute. Then we can define the multivariate generalized entropy measure of closeness as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">D b S; X ; a ð Þ¼ X m j¼1 a j X n i¼1 S i S i =X ij À Á b À1 h i =b bþ 1 ð Þ ( )<label>(1)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5</head><p>Weights and substitution degree</p><p>where α j 's are the relative weights of each attributes ð P m j¼1 a j ¼ 1Þ. By minimizing the D β function regarding S i 's, which are subject to restriction that P n i¼1 S i ¼ 1, that is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">min S i f g D b S; X ; a ð Þmin S i f g X m j¼1 a j X n i¼1 S i S i =X ij À Á b À1 h i =b bþ 1 ð Þ ( ) (2) s:t: X n i¼1 S i ¼ 1</formula><p>we can get our welfare or aggregate function:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">S i p X m j¼1 a j X Àb ij ! À1=b</formula><p>; b a 0; À1;</p><p>(3)</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">S i p Y m j¼1 X a j ij ; b ¼ 0; (4) S i p X m j¼1 a j X ij ; b ¼ À1:<label>(5)</label></formula><p>These are different averages of the attributes for each person, and the elasticity of substitution between different attributes is 1/(1+β). By minimizing the "divergence measure" D β , we make the welfare vector S ¼ (S 1 , S 2 , …, S n ) as close to their corresponding multivariate attributes as possible. From Information Theory, the vector S absorbs all the objective information from data, and any deviation from S will cause some distortion. The underlying assumption in this step is that we know the exact weights for different attributes(α j 's) and substitution degree between attributes( β). However, in reality, we do not know. Finding out the parameters is one main issue in this paper, and we will discuss it later. There is also a welfare theoretic basis for this conundrum. Every scalar aggregator endows individual attributes with weights, and levels of substitution, that reflect social valuations. Arrow's impossibility theorems speak to the difficulty of reaching consensus. Generalized entropy measures are equivalent, up to monotonically increasing transformations, very flexible welfare functions. But this merely identifies a family of aggregator functions. The choice of a metric entropy which satisfies the triangularity property of distances resolves some of this indeterminacy, but not all. Here "calibrating" toward the distribution of observed "happiness" will find parameter values that would be required to "match" the underlying attributes and their valuations to the "happiness" observation. No more, and no less. In the second step <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Maasoumi, 1986)</ref>, adopted the generalized entropy index on inequality for the S i distribution as the measure of multidimensional inequality, that is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">M g S ð Þ ¼ X n i¼1 p i S n i =p i À Á 1 þ g À1 h i =g 1 þ g ð Þ; g a 0; À1 (6) M 0 S ð Þ ¼ X n i¼1 S n i log S n i =p i À Á ; Theil's first index (7) 6 JES 42,1 M À1 S ð Þ ¼ X n i¼1 p i log p i =S n i À Á ; Theil's second index (8)</formula><p>where p i is individual i's population share (usually ¼ 1/n), and S n i is normalized S i which is divided by the total K ¼ P n i¼1 S i .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Two metric entropy measures</head><p>The entropy measures of similarity or association we will introduce below are supported by a set of desirable axiomatic properties. These include invariance to non-linear (monotone) transformations, invariance to dimensionality, capability to reproduce correlation and other linear measures of linear association (when that is appropriate as for jointly Gaussian variables), metricness, normalization, and others. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Maasoumi and Racine's (2002)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Granger et al.'s (2004)</ref> paper, they proposed a metric entropy to test dependence of two univariate variable X and Y, which is "Matusita-Bhattacharya-Hellinger measure of dependence" (we call it metric entropy measure 1 later) given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">S r ¼ 1 2 Z þ 1 À1 Z þ 1 À1 f 1=2 x; y ð ÞÀf 1=2 1 x ð Þf 1=2 2 y ð Þ 2 dxdy (9)</formula><p>where f(x, y) is the joint pdf of X and Y, f 1 (x) is the marginal pdf of X, and f 2 (y) is the marginal pdf of Y. This metric is able to measure the non-linear dependence relationship between X and Y, with the range [0, 1). S ρ is zero when X and Y are independent variables and is positive but less than one otherwise. Because it is a metric, we can say the larger it is, the farther the two variables are from independence. For discrete or categorical variables, suppose X∈{x 1 , x 2 , …, x m }, Y∈{y 1 , y 2 , …, y n }, joint probability mass function is P xy (i, j) ¼ Prob(X ¼ x i , Y ¼ y j ) and the corresponding marginal probability mass functions are</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">P x (i) ¼ Prob(X ¼ x i ) and P y ( j) ¼ Prob(Y ¼ y j )</formula><p>, then we can rewrite (9) as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">S r ¼ 1 2 X m i¼1 X n j¼1 P 1=2 xy i; j ð ÞÀP 1=2 x i ð ÞP 1=2 y j ð Þ h i 2 :<label>(10)</label></formula><p>This metric can also be used to measure the distance between the distributions of X 1 and X 2 if we write it in the following form (we call it metric entropy measure 2 later):</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">S r ¼ 1 2 Z þ 1 À1 f 1=2 1 x ð ÞÀf 1=2 2 x ð Þ 2 dx:<label>(11)</label></formula><p>Equation (11) measures the closeness of random variables X 1 and X 2 's distributions. S ρ equals zero if they have identical distribution, and it is positive and less than one otherwise. Larger S ρ means that the difference between their distributions is larger. For discrete or categorical variables, suppose X 1 , X 2 ∈{x 1 , x 2 , …, x n }[1], and the corresponding probability mass functions are</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">P 1 (i) ¼ Prob(X 1 ¼ x i ) and P 2 (i) ¼ Prob (X 2 ¼ x i )</formula><p>, and then we can rewrite (11) as:  <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Shi (2009)</ref>. CHIPS2002 is a countrywide survey conducted in the year 2002, containing samples from urban residents, migrants, and rural residents. We treat urban residents, migrants (in cities) and rural residents as separate groups[3], and we only keep urban residents with local hukou and migrants with rural hukou. After deleting observations with missing values, the final sample contains 6,553 urban residents, 5,035 migrants, and 8,533 rural residents.</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">S r ¼ 1 2 X n i¼1 P 1 i ð Þ 1=2 ÀP 2 i ð Þ 1=2 h i 2 :<label>(12)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Variables</head><p>In attribute selection, we include five attributes proxying in four types. The first and second attributes are household per capita income (income for short later)[4] and household per capita net asset (net asset for short later), which represent "economic" conditions. For income, it is net income, and we adjust it for provincial CPI and household composition (children count as one half). In <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Maasoumi and Nickelsburg (1988)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Pasha et al.'s (2005)</ref> papers, they both used annual nominal income. And because in CHIPS there is information about assets and debts, we also choose household per capita net asset to capture "permanent income." For urban residents, CHIPS has information about annual personal income, and we calculate household per capita income by taking the average of personal incomes in the same household. For migrants, we calculate household per capita income by dividing the answer to "total household income from working in cities and family production in 2002" by the size of household. For rural residents, we use total annual household income divided by family size. For net asset, we first calculate the household net asset by total household financial asset (for rural residents, we also include fixed productive assets) minus total household debt and then divide it by household size. The third attribute is household per capita usable house area (house area for short later) <ref type="bibr">[5]</ref>, which reflect the housing conditions. In <ref type="bibr">Pasha et al.'s (2005)</ref> paper, they used building area. In this paper, we use usable house area for two reasons. First, usable house area reflects better how much space the person can use and live in. Second, most migrants cannot afford buying or renting a whole apartment in cities so they share apartments or rooms with other people. Thus, CHIPS only has data on usable house area for migrants. To calculate household per capita usable house area, we divide the usable house area by family size for urban residents and by the number of family members living together for migrants and rural residents. The fourth attribute is health. It is the answer to body conditions, which contains five categories, "Worst," "Worse," "Just so-so," "Good," and "Very good," and we assign number 1-5 to them, respectively. The fifth attribute is years of education (education for short later), which represent human capital <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Maasoumi and Nickelsburg, 1988)</ref>. Statistical summaries are in <ref type="table">Table I</ref>.</p><p>In calculating the individual's welfare S, the weights indicate the relative importance of different attributes. To eliminate the effects of the scale difference in attributes, we normalize them by calculating the "shares" of attributes to the total amount in their group, i.e. dividing individuals' attribute amount by the total amount in their group. This is also consistent with research in happiness, which finds that relative amount plays an important role in determining happiness or subjective well-being. One exception is net asset because for some observations the values of net asset are negative. We add the absolute value of the minimal net asset (which is negative) in the group to each person within the group and then calculate their share of net asset. Weights and substitution degree</p><p>Another variable we use is the happiness level. The question for interviewees is "Generally speaking, do you feel happy?" and their answers can be categorized into "very happy," "happy," "so-so," "not very happy," "not happy at all," and "don't know" <ref type="bibr">[6]</ref>. We keep observations with the first five answers and assign values 5, 4, 3, 2, and 1, respectively, to interviewees' reported happiness. <ref type="table">Table II</ref> shows the reported happiness distributions in the three groups.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Choosing parameters</head><p>In assessing the multidimensional welfare of individuals, one critical issue is to choose the parameters, i.e. weights for different attributes α j 's and the substitution degree β. Given the data, the choice of parameters determines everyone's welfare and then the distribution, which can be used to conduct some research on inequality or implement some policy analysis. However, there is no wide consensus on how to choose these parameters. In this paper, we will choose the parameters using a method similar to calibration, which can be included in the category "Hedonic Weights" in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Decancq and Lugo's (2013)</ref> paper. Simply speaking, we search the whole parameter space to find the set of parameters making the distance of reported happiness and objective measures of individual welfare smallest. To measure the distance between reported happiness and welfare, we adopt the two methods mentioned in Section 3. Given individuals' attributes and parameters, we can calculate individuals' welfare S i 's, which can be seen as continuous variables across observations. To compare the individuals' welfare with their reported happiness, we transform individuals' welfare into discrete variables. The procedure is as follows: first, we normalize S i into the range [0, 1] by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">normalized S i ¼ S i ÀS min S max ÀS min (13)</formula><p>where It is possible to be economical in searching the parameter space[7], we adopt algorithms to reduce the computation burden and time, as follows.</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">S</formula><p>4.3.1</p><p>Step 1: rough search. First, we go through the parameter space roughly and record 50 best parameter sets. Parameter sets are judged by the smallest distance between reported happiness and welfare given the parameter set in different measures. For the first measure of Section 3, that is (9) and (10), the larger the value the smaller the distance between reported happiness and calculated welfare because it indicates the dependence of reported happiness and welfare in the individual level. We call it "Metric entropy measure 1" and denote it as S 1 r. For the second measure of Section 3, that is (11) and (12), the smaller the value the smaller the distance between reported happiness and calculated welfare because it indicates the difference between reported happiness and individual welfare in the distribution level. We call it "Metric entropy measure 2" and denote it as S 2 r . In this rough search, we set the interval of weights α j 's as 0.05 <ref type="bibr">[8]</ref> and the interval of substitution degree β as 0.01, and we let α j 's change in {0, 0.05, 0.10, …, 0.95, 1.00} with P 5 j¼1 a j ¼ 1 and β change in {0, 0.01, 0.02, …, 0.99, 1.00}. Then we record 50 best-performed parameter sets in each measure for future use. 4.3.2</p><p>Step 2: refinement. After we get results from the rough search in the step 1, we conduct some refinement and obtain best parameter sets with α j s' change interval as 0.01. Due to the huge computation burden, we only make more accurate search around the best 50 results from step 1 <ref type="bibr">[9]</ref>. Let us denote any of the results from step 1 as b 1 ; a 1 1 ; a 1 2 ; a 1 3 ; a 1 4 ; a 1 5 À Á</p><p>. In the refinement step, we let β change in the range [ β 1 −0.01, β 1 +0.01] with interval 0.01 and each α j change in the range a 1 j À0:05; a 1 j þ 0:05 h i with interval 0.01, and α j 's also need to satisfy P 5 j¼1 a j ¼ 1. And after comparing the distances between happiness and different parameter sets, we record best-performed 100 parameter sets in this step.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.3.3</head><p>Step 3: bootstrap. In a sense, the best S 1 r and S 2 r can be regarded as an estimate based on a specific data sample. To report some degree of reliability, we bootstrap nonparametrically from the data set to test the performance of the 100 parameter sets recorded in step two. We record the percentage of each parameter set performing best in the bootstrap procedure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Numerical results</head><p>The main task above is to find out relative weights for different attributes and their degree of substitution. Then we can interpret the findings in two contexts. The first is welfare analysis, which focusses on multidimensional index of well-being and, we use certain parameter sets to investigate the inequality in different groups. The second examination is a form of utility analysis, which explains the relative weights as contributions to utility for each attribute. We consider some historical and family characteristics to shed light on findings that help policy decisions. <ref type="table">Table III</ref> shows the best parameter sets for metric entropy measures 1 and 2 in different groups after refinement. The second column is entropy metric S ρ , the third one is β, the fourth to the eighth columns are relative weights for income, net asset, house area, health, and education. However, the refinement results may be not robust in the statistical sense. We give the best parameter sets in bootstrap procedure (having the highest percentage to be the best parameter sets) in Weights and substitution degree percentage is not very high. The third to ninth columns are the same to the second to eighth columns in <ref type="table">Table III</ref>. And also we can see that the percentage in metric entropy measure 2 is higher than in metric entropy measure 1, which means parameter sets perform more stable in metric entropy measure 2. In addition, we can obtain the desired parameter sets by taking the percentageweighted average of the bootstrap results (in <ref type="table">Table V</ref>). In this way, how much weight we give to different parameter sets is the percentage they become the best parameter set in bootstrap procedure, so we give larger weights to parameter sets which perform better in the statistical sense.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Welfare analysis</head><p>Another way to calculate the relative weight from the data is using the (normalized) metric entropy measures between each attribute and happiness as their respective relative weights. The results are in <ref type="table">Table VI</ref> some evidence for the importance of adding attribute substitution into the multidimensional indices of well-being.</p><p>Next, we calculate the inequality based on the parameter sets we obtained above. Here we use the best and weighted average parameter sets in bootstrap to calculate individuals' welfare without discretizing them, and then we calculate Theil's first and second indices and generalized entropy index with γ ¼ −1/2 using R package "ineq." Here we use generalized entropy index with γ ¼ −1/2 because the metric entropy measure we use is the same entropy metric with γ ¼ −1/2. The results are in <ref type="table">Table VII</ref>. The second column is the inequality in reported happiness, where happiness is a discrete variable. The third and fourth columns are inequality of welfare S calculated through the best and weighted average parameter sets in the bootstrap, using metric entropy measure 1. The fifth and sixth columns are inequality of welfare S calculated through the best and weighted average parameter sets in the bootstrap, using metric entropy measure 2. The results for discrete individual welfare are in <ref type="table">Table VIII</ref>. When we analyze inequality results, we should focus more on results from metric entropy measure 2 because it focusses on the similarity of two distributions. It is interesting to note from Tables VII and VIII, that inequality in self-reported "happiness" is always higher than that in multidimensional welfare based on entropy metric 2. One possible explanation is that this is due to the </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>13</head><p>Weights and substitution degree substitution between different attributes. Individuals may report based on the most pressing needs and dimensions, as perceived by them at a moment in time. Even though our approach aggregates different dimensions "toward' this self-reported indicator, it still allows for formal consideration of other objective indicators. Another possible explanation is that there exist some hidden factors such as personality which affect happiness and are not captured by the variables used in this paper[10].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Utility analysis</head><p>The other way to interpret the best parameter sets we get is to explain them as the utility of different groups, and we can compare the difference across groups. In this sense, parameter sets obtained by metric entropy measure 1 may be more suitable, since using it implicitly imposes a correspondence relationship between reported happiness and aggregated welfare. Thus, we will mainly use the S 1 r 's results to represent the utilities in different groups. And because some parameter sets are very close in the results, we group them up. The principle is that substitution degree is within 0.1 from the group mean and the sum of distance of relative weights to group mean is &lt;0.2. The results are in <ref type="table">Table IX</ref>. For the weighted average parameter sets, the numbers in the parenthesis are the standard errors, and for grouped parameter sets, the numbers in the bracket are the ranges. To gain greater intuition, we plot the absolute value of β and α j 's in <ref type="figure">Figures 1 and 2</ref>.</p><p>By comparing the parameter values of the three groups, we find some similarities and differences. First, it seems the average substitution degrees across different attributes in different groups are relatively similar, and they are different from perfect substitution, which suggests that it may be problematical assuming perfect substitution (as in linear aggregators and regressions). Second, migrants' preference is very similar to urban residents other than for education. Education does not contribute to migrants' utility. A possible explanation is that this phenomenon is related to the Household Registration (Hukou) system in China. There are segregated labor markets in Chinese cities, and migrants are discriminated against for entry in mainly the "good" industries, where "good" means higher wages combined with higher demand for education and skills <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Chen et al., 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Chen et al., , 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Meng and Zhang, 2001)</ref>. Thus, the contribution of migrants' education to welfare is nearly zero. Third, compared with urban residents and migrants, rural residents put most of their weights on health and less on economic factors (income, net asset, and house area) and education. On the one hand, from happiness literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Clark et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Luttmer, 2005)</ref>, relative income matters a lot for happiness, which means people would like to compare their income and asset with others. Rural residents are less exposed to external world due to lack of media so they are less likely to compare their income or property with others <ref type="bibr">[11]</ref>. Thus, economic factors matter relatively less to their utility. On the other hand, the relatively poor medical conditions and lack of medical security in rural area may be another reason why rural residents care more about health <ref type="bibr">[12]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Control for marital status</head><p>One concern of the above method is that it only includes five attributes due to data limitations, and many other characteristics correlated with happiness are omitted, such Weights and substitution degree as age and marital status. Here we adopt cell decomposition method to address this issue <ref type="bibr">[13]</ref>. As is shown in <ref type="table">Table AI</ref> in the Appendix, the subgroup/cell differences in characteristics mainly come from marital status rather than age. This is based on summary statistics, including quantiles. Thus, we divide the sample further according to marital status within each group in order to isolate its potential impact. <ref type="table">Table X</ref> shows the weighted average parameter set for married and unmarried within each group, respectively. We can see that substitution degrees are different between the married and unmarried within each group, but especially for urban and rural residents. Although there also exist differences in weights for different marital status, the differences are not very large. It should be noted that migrant group is youngest and most single.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Conclusion</head><p>In this paper,with CHIPS2002 data, we combine multidimensional welfare analysis and entropy metrics to identify the best relative weights and substitution degree among five attributes which make individuals' welfare have the smallest distance to reported happiness for three social groups, urban residents, migrants, and rural residents. We use the obtained parameter sets to calculate inequality in the three groups. In addition, we compare the differences among the three groups and attempt to link them to institutional factors. Main findings in this paper are as follows: first, substitution among attributes matters for multidimensional indices of well-being; second, there are significant group differences in relative weights of attributes in China, which may be related to some social and institutional factors; third, inequality in calculated welfare from metric entropy measure 2 is less than reported happiness inequality. From this study, we learn that we should incorporate substitution among attributes and take into consideration group heterogeneity in multidimensional assessments of well-being and poverty. This would seem to suggest that one size-fits-all policies are not appropriate for China, and perceptions of well-being, objectively and as self-reported, reflect very different concerns, requiring very different approaches. For example, health issues dominate rural perceptions of well-being, whereas education and income are more prominent among other groups. Based on finite and different substitution values, it is safe to assume that different groups place very different monetary values on nonmonetary attributes. This is quite significant for policy analysis going forward.</p><p>There are several potential future research directions. First, we can search more precisely in our numerical algorithms. Second, we can further investigate the role of attribute substitution in multidimensional well-being. Third, we can adopt clustering techniques to identify unique attribute dimensions and reduce double counting <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Hirschberg et al., 1991</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Hirschberg et al., , 2001</ref>. Fourth, when CHIPS2007 releases specific data on asset and housing, we can investigate how the relative weights and substation degree change over time.</p><p>Notes 1. In this case, we need the two random variables in the same support.</p><p>2. We cannot use panel data to control individual fixed effect because CHIPS data is crosssectional. However, the focus of this paper is not on investigating the causality of happiness but on the methodology of constructing a mapping from self-reported happiness to a number of objectively measured attributes.</p><p>3. On the one hand, we expect the welfare functions of different groups to be different due to the great disparity in their living environment, opportunities, and life style <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Meng and Zhang, 2001</ref>), and we wish to compare their differences. On the other hand, if we combine all the groups into one, we will get a biased result for welfare function or distribution because we lack an accurate and reliable proportion of the three groups, most of which comes from the lack of exact data on migrants.</p><p>4. We use income rather than consumption for two reasons. First, consumption data are not available for CHIPS. Second, income is a generally broader indicator of economic opportunity.</p><p>5. Due to data limitation, we cannot impute housing expenses for people who live in their own houses. However, our computation is mainly based on each group (urban residents, migrants and rural residents) so it partly alleviates this problem.</p><p>6. We treat answers in the category "don't know" as missing values, and the fractions are &lt;1 percent in all the three samples.</p><p>7. In theory, it is very intensive to search all of the parameter space because it is continuous.</p><p>8. If we reduce the α j 's' interval to 0.01, the computation time will increase approximately 5 4 ¼ 625 times.</p><p>9. The implicit assumption is that there is continuity with respect to parameter intervals. We make some trials and find that this holds for well-performed parameters after refinement. With more powerful computation ability, we can let parameters change in smaller intervals, and then the continuity assumption is more plausible.</p><p>10. We thank anonymous referee for this explanation.</p><p>11. Another possible explanation is that rural residents conduct self-consumed production, and that is not included in the income variable. Thus, income is not relatively important for rural residents. We thank anonymous referee for pointing this out.</p><p>12. From <ref type="table">Table I</ref>, we can see that average age of rural residents is not larger than that of urban residents, so age should not be the reason why rural residents care more about health.</p><p>13. Another method is regression-or model-based method to adjust all the attributes for age and marital status. One problem is that it is hard to adjust category variables such as happiness and health with this method, another challenge is specification issues for proper modeling for each attribute, and jointly.  <ref type="table">Table AI</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Weights and substitution degree</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical description for attributes by cells</head><p>For instructions on how to order reprints of this article, please visit our website: www.emeraldgrouppublishing.com/licensing/reprints.htm Or contact us for further details: permissions@emeraldinsight.com</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>min and S max are the minimal and maximal values among S i 's; second, we assign values 1, 2, 3, 4, or 5 to individuals' welfare if their normalized S 's are in the range [0, 0.2], (0.2, 0.4], (0.4, 0.6], (0.6, 0.8], or (0.8, 1].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 2. Grouped parameter set</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table</head><label></label><figDesc>IV for different metrics with the bootstrap number 999. The second column is the percentage of performing best for the parameter sets. Because there are some very similar parameter sets, so the</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>S 1 r</cell><cell>β</cell><cell>Income</cell><cell>Net asset</cell><cell>House area</cell><cell>Health</cell><cell>Education</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Urban</cell><cell>0.01045</cell><cell>−0.23</cell><cell>0.19</cell><cell>0.15</cell><cell>0.10</cell><cell>0.55</cell><cell>0.01</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Migrant</cell><cell>0.00818</cell><cell>−0.23</cell><cell>0.29</cell><cell>0.26</cell><cell>0.11</cell><cell>0.34</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Rural</cell><cell>0.00950 S 2 r</cell><cell>−0.24 β</cell><cell>0.03 Income</cell><cell>0.09 Net asset</cell><cell>0.01 House area</cell><cell>0.87 Health</cell><cell>0.00 Education</cell><cell>Table III.</cell></row><row><cell>Urban</cell><cell>0.00418</cell><cell>−0.02</cell><cell>0.06</cell><cell>0.03</cell><cell>0.05</cell><cell>0.84</cell><cell>0.02</cell><cell>Best parameter set</cell></row><row><cell>Migrant Rural</cell><cell>0.00163 0.00089</cell><cell>−0.13 −0.63</cell><cell>0.01 0.00</cell><cell>0.00 0.00</cell><cell>0.10 0.00</cell><cell>0.86 0.76</cell><cell>0.03 0.24</cell><cell>in refinement for S 1 r and S 2</cell></row></table><note>r 11</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. However, this results are not consistent with other results. The possible reason is that this method does not take into consideration of substitution effects in different attributes, i.e. β. So it may provide</figDesc><table><row><cell>JES</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>42,1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>%</cell><cell>S 1 r</cell><cell>β</cell><cell>Income</cell><cell cols="2">Net asset</cell><cell>House area</cell><cell>Health</cell><cell>Education</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Urban</cell><cell>5.3</cell><cell>0.01028</cell><cell>0.00</cell><cell>0.24</cell><cell>0.13</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.02</cell><cell>0.38</cell><cell>0.23</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Migrant</cell><cell>9.7</cell><cell>0.00770</cell><cell>−0.20</cell><cell>0.20</cell><cell>0.28</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.13</cell><cell>0.39</cell><cell>0.00</cell></row><row><cell>Table IV.</cell><cell>Rural</cell><cell>12.0 %</cell><cell>0.00920 S 2 r</cell><cell>−0.51 β</cell><cell>0.05 Income</cell><cell cols="2">0.00 Net asset</cell><cell>0.01 House area</cell><cell>0.94 Health</cell><cell>0.00 Education</cell></row><row><cell>Best parameter set in bootstrap for S 1 r and S 2 r</cell><cell>Urban Migrant Rural</cell><cell>11.5 20.0 41.7</cell><cell>0.00441 0.00163 0.00089</cell><cell>−0.09 −0.13 −0.63</cell><cell>0.06 0.01 0.00</cell><cell>0.11 0.00 0.00</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.03 0.10 0.00</cell><cell>0.74 0.86 0.76</cell><cell>0.06 0.03 0.24</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>β</cell><cell></cell><cell>Income</cell><cell cols="2">Net asset</cell><cell cols="2">House area</cell><cell>Health</cell><cell>Education</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>S 1 r</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Urban</cell><cell cols="2">−0.170</cell><cell>0.209</cell><cell>0.164</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.075</cell><cell>0.490</cell><cell>0.062</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Migrant</cell><cell cols="2">−0.235</cell><cell>0.267</cell><cell>0.284</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.089</cell><cell>0.360</cell><cell>0.000</cell></row><row><cell>Table V. Weighted average parameter set in bootstrap for S 1 r and S 2 r</cell><cell>Rural S 2 r Urban Migrant Rural</cell><cell cols="2">−0.331 −0.032 −0.133 −0.587</cell><cell>0.044 0.058 0.005 0.016</cell><cell>0.038 0.052 0.006 0.001</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.015 0.047 0.105 0.000</cell><cell>0.899 0.813 0.848 0.815</cell><cell>0.004 0.030 0.036 0.167</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Income</cell><cell>Net asset</cell><cell cols="3">House area</cell><cell>Health</cell><cell cols="2">Education</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>S 1 r</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Table VI. Relative weights by calculating S 1 r and S 2 r between</cell><cell>Urban Migrant Rural S 2 r Urban</cell><cell cols="2">0.253 0.112 0.064 0.354</cell><cell>0.027 0.174 0.077 0.212</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.114 0.281 0.069 0.371</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.466 0.297 0.717 0.013</cell><cell>0.140 0.136 0.073 0.050</cell></row><row><cell>attributes and</cell><cell>Migrant</cell><cell cols="2">0.377</cell><cell>0.253</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.270</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.058</cell><cell>0.042</cell></row><row><cell>happiness</cell><cell>Rural</cell><cell cols="2">0.339</cell><cell>0.266</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.312</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.009</cell><cell>0.074</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Inf comes from the fact that some person's welfare equals to zero</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Happiness</cell><cell>Best in S 1 r</cell><cell>Average in S 1 r</cell><cell>Best in S 2 r</cell><cell>Average in S 2 r</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Theil's 1st index</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Urban</cell><cell>0.03310635</cell><cell>0.02096783</cell><cell>0.01882967</cell><cell>0.01938336</cell><cell>0.02362107</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Migrant</cell><cell>0.02997603</cell><cell>0.02424105</cell><cell>0.02820155</cell><cell>0.01788124</cell><cell>0.01882405</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Rural</cell><cell>0.0297519</cell><cell>0.02066842</cell><cell>0.01913168</cell><cell>0.01961511</cell><cell>0.01907011</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Theil's 2nd index</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Urban</cell><cell>0.03863011</cell><cell>Inf a</cell><cell>0.01963884</cell><cell>0.02109975</cell><cell>0.0265901</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Migrant</cell><cell>0.0335238</cell><cell>0.02364874</cell><cell>0.02687041</cell><cell>0.0197093</cell><cell>0.02074389</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Rural</cell><cell>0.03345007</cell><cell>0.02405269</cell><cell>0.02212287</cell><cell>0.022138</cell><cell>0.02167807</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="7">GE (γ ¼ −1/2) Urban Migrant Rural Note: a Table VII. 0.03546201 0.04373861 0.01915617 0.02013176 0.02487101 0.0314595 0.02378915 0.02732712 0.01866831 0.01965113 0.03133147 0.02212602 0.02042914 0.02071965 0.02021248 Inequality indices for happiness and original individual welfare S</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Happiness</cell><cell>Best in S 1 r</cell><cell>Average in S 1 r</cell><cell>Best in S 2 r</cell><cell>Average in S 2 r</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Theil's 1st index</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Urban</cell><cell>0.03310635</cell><cell>0.02214269</cell><cell>0.02716573</cell><cell>0.02494992</cell><cell>0.02496797</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Migrant</cell><cell>0.02997603</cell><cell>0.04447686</cell><cell>0.0621958</cell><cell>0.02500336</cell><cell>0.02569485</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Rural</cell><cell>0.0297519</cell><cell>0.02979672</cell><cell>0.02786803</cell><cell>0.02747622</cell><cell>0.02431393</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Theil's 2nd index</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Urban</cell><cell>0.03863011</cell><cell>0.02415579</cell><cell>0.02813996</cell><cell>0.02798481</cell><cell>0.02833565</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Migrant</cell><cell>0.0335238</cell><cell>0.04900813</cell><cell>0.0639305</cell><cell>0.02733607</cell><cell>0.02806306</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Rural</cell><cell>0.03345007</cell><cell>0.03405223</cell><cell>0.03188229</cell><cell>0.03125789</cell><cell>0.02858245</cell><cell>Table VIII.</cell></row><row><cell>GE (γ ¼ −1/2)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Inequality indices</cell></row><row><cell>Urban</cell><cell>0.03546201</cell><cell>0.02299552</cell><cell>0.02753501</cell><cell>0.02624043</cell><cell>0.02639708</cell><cell>for happiness and</cell></row><row><cell>Migrant</cell><cell>0.0314595</cell><cell>0.04646297</cell><cell>0.06276656</cell><cell>0.02599023</cell><cell>0.02670232</cell><cell>discrete individual</cell></row><row><cell>Rural</cell><cell>0.03133147</cell><cell>0.03159864</cell><cell>0.02957278</cell><cell>0.02909023</cell><cell>0.02613244</cell><cell>welfare S</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT)</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Who entered high-wage industries? The role of social network, hukou and labor productivities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economic Research Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Household registration, signal effects and happiness: empirical evidence from Shanghai and Shenzhen communities</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of World Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relative Income, Happiness, and Utility: An Explanation for the Easterlin Paradox and Other Puzzles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Frijters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Shields</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/jel.46.1.95</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://eprints.qut.edu.au/30738/1/30738_final.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Literature</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Economic Literature</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-0515</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="144" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-02" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Weights in Multidimensional Indices of Wellbeing: An Overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Koen</forename><surname>Decancq</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">María</forename><forename type="middle">Ana</forename><surname>Lugo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/07474938.2012.690641</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://lirias.kuleuven.be/bitstream/123456789/262767/1/DPS1006.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometric Reviews</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Econometric Reviews</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0747-4938</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1532-4168</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-01" />
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Dependence Metric for Possibly Nonlinear Processes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Granger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Maasoumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Racine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1467-9892.2004.01866.x</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-30492S0Q-9</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">673CE4C1CDC2EF3AD3CE60B834B271B3EB97AAD1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Time Series Analysis</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">J Time Series Analysis</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0143-9782</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1467-9892</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="649" to="669" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-09" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cluster analysis for measuring welfare and quality of life across countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hirschberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Esfandiar</forename><surname>Maasoumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Slottje</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0304-4076(91)90093-s</idno>
		<idno type="PII">0304-4076(91)90093-S</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-3HN8FTSS-K</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">B4BF24D04470EB024B83BBB4F214CA7F347A0DA8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Econometrics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Econometrics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-4076</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-10" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clusters of attributes and well-being in the USA</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hirschberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Esfandiar</forename><surname>Maasoumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Slottje</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/jae.605</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-P3LKJKSN-R</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">B6E0CC843AB635CF19F0D0A22D93B07EF5457A38</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Econometrics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">J. Appl. Econ.</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0883-7252</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1099-1255</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="445" to="460" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neighbors as Negatives: Relative Earnings and Well-Being</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Erzo</forename><forename type="middle">F P</forename><surname>Luttmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.571824</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www.nber.org/%7Eluttmer/relative.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SSRN Electronic Journal</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">SSRN Journal</title>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1556-5068</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="963" to="1002" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Measurement and Decomposition of Multi-Dimensional Inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Esfandiar</forename><surname>Maasoumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/1912849</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www.ophi.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/ssMaasoumi-1986.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Econometrica</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0012-9682</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">991</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986-07" />
			<publisher>JSTOR</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multivariate Measures of Well-Being and an Analysis of Inequality in the Michigan Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Esfandiar</forename><surname>Maasoumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gerald</forename><surname>Nickelsburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/1391884</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Business &amp; Economic Statistics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Business &amp; Economic Statistics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0735-0015</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">327</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988-07" />
			<publisher>JSTOR</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entropy and predictability of stock market returns</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Esfandiar</forename><surname>Maasoumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jeff</forename><surname>Racine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0304-4076(01)00125-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Econometrics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Econometrics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-4076</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="312" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-03" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The two-tier labor market in urban China: occupational segregation and wage differentials between urban residents and rural migrants in Shanghai</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Comparative Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="485" to="504" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Saisana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Saltelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tarantola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Tools for Composite Indicators Building</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ispra</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>European Comission</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multidimensional analysis of inequality in Iran</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pasha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zendedel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Maasoumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Institute of Mathematics and Computer Sciences (Mathematical Series)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Chinese Household Income Project, 2002</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Li</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3886/icpsr21741</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-05-28" />
			<publisher>Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research (ICPSR)</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI. Further reading</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multidimensioned Approaches to Welfare Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Esfandiar</forename><surname>Maasoumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-94-011-4413-1_16</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Income Inequality Measurement</title>
		<editor>Pesaran, M.H. and Schmidt, P.</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer Netherlands</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="484" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
