<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Report of the Committee on the Status of Women in the Economics Profession 2011</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright American Economic Association</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2012-05">2012-05</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Watts</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Report of the Committee on the Status of Women in the Economics Profession 2011</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">American Economic Review</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">American Economic Review</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0002-8282</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="691" to="696"/>
							<date type="published" when="2012-05" />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1257/aer.102.3.691</idno>
					<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles/pdf/doi/10.1257/aer.102.3.691" />
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T23:35+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The major new initiative of the Committee in 2011 was to launch an annual conference on teaching economics at the undergraduate and graduate levels, and research on economic education at all levels (including precollege). The first conference was an outstanding success, held June 1-3, 2011, at the Stanford Institute for Economic Policy Research. Plenary sessions featured Vernon Smith (Chapman), John Taylor (Stanford), and Douglas Bernheim (Stanford), with a dinner and fourth plenary session by John Williams at the San Francisco Federal Reserve Bank. There were 55 papers presented in concurrent sessions, plus six panel discussions and four workshops on teaching or research. Registrations were received from 174 individuals, including 20 from international participants from 10 different countries. The second annual conference will be held in Boston from May 30-June 1, 2012, featuring plenary sessions by Daron Acemoglu (MIT), Susan Athey (Harvard), Peter Diamond (MIT), Gregory Mankiw (Harvard), and a dinner and fifth plenary session by Jeffry Fuhrer at the Boston Federal Reserve Bank.</p><p>The annual conference is cosponsored by the Journal of Economic Education (JEE), and after the usual (but expedited) blind reviews some conference papers are selected for publication in JEE. At the Denver meetings in January of 2011, the AEA Executive Committee unanimously approved annual support for this conference of $25,000 starting with the 2012 conferencewith over 70 percent of those funds dedicated to reducing registration fees (especially for AEA members). A final report on the Stanford conference was provided to the Executive Committee for its January 2012 meeting, and a slightly modified version of that report will be published in JEE in 2012, titled "Changing the Landscape of Economic Education."</p><p>The annual report provided by the editor of JEE (William Walstad, NE-Lincoln) to the Committee is included as an attachment to this report.</p><p>The Committee sponsored the "Teaching Innovations Program" (TIP) for faculty members in economics from 2005-2010, funded</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Report of the Committee on Economic Education for 2011</head><p>by a $675,000 grant from the National Science Foundation, codirected by William Walstad (Nebraska-Lincoln) and Michael Salemi (North Carolina). In spring 2011 Edward Elgar published Teaching Innovations in Economics: Strategies and Applications for Interactive Instruction, edited by the TIP codirectors and featuring 11 chapters written by 29 TIP participants and staff. As a follow-up to the TIP project the Committee supported a proposal for a daylong "continuing education" session on the interactive teaching of economics at the January 2012 meetings of AEA in Chicago. That proposal was accepted, and the session will be conducted by Michael Salemi, William Walstad, KimMarie McGoldrick (Richmond), Tisha Emerson (Baylor), and Pat Conway (North Carolina).</p><p>Two projects were completed or nearing completion in 2011 as extensions of a Teagle Foundation grant awarded to the Committee in 2007, on the role of the undergraduate economics major in a liberal education. From the first extension project, with additional support from the Tobin Project and the American Institute of Economic Research, a paper by 11 PhD students in economics from seven universities (California-Berkeley, Chicago, Columbia, MIT, Northwestern, Pennsylvania, and Princeton) was published in the Fall 2011 issue of the JEE. The "creativity workshop" featured in this project was directed by David Colander (Middlebury), John Siegfried (Vanderbilt), and Avinash Dixit (Princeton). In the second Teagle extension project KimMarie McGoldrick (Richmond) and Robert Garnett (Texas Christian) developed two modules, one in microeconomics and one in macroeconomics, demonstrating how to teach enduring "big think" questions. Two manuscripts have been prepared describing the modules and the development process for the modules.</p><p>Four training modules on advanced econometric methods in economic education research have now been posted on the AEA CEE website for just over a year. The modules were developed by William Becker (Indiana), with William Greene (NYU) and John Siegfried (Vanderbilt) contributing on two modules. The modules deal with heteroskedasticity; endogenous regressors with natural experiments, instrumental variables, and two-stage estimators; panel data; and sample selection issues. Each module features "real-world" datasets and sample programs written in Stata, SAS, and Limdep. Information on website "hits" is now available for the period corresponding to the 2011 "spring semester" at most US schools, from January-May 2011. The monthly average over this period was 220 hits/ views, with more hits in early and middle months of the "term." It appears (as supported by anecdotal accounts) that the modules and datasets are being used in many econometrics classes as general teaching tools, not just to introduce research topics in economic education.</p><p>The Committee supports an NSF-funded project on "Teaching with Data" in undergraduate social science courses, directed by George Alter and Bill Frey (both at Michigan). Tisha Emerson (Baylor) is the Committee representative for the project's advisory board. A national survey of faculty across disciplines and Carnegie classifications of schools was completed and described in 2011 reports and found that instructors in economics are much more demanding about quantitative skills than instructors from other social sciences, while faculty at Associate schools and non-tenure track faculty are less likely to teach quantitative reasoning. A presentation on this project was included in the Committee's annual poster session at the Chicago meetings in January 2012.</p><p>The Committee supported an NSF-funded project on "Adapting Effective Outreach and Workshop Practices to Improve Community College Economics Instruction," directed by Mark Maier (Glendale Community College) and Cathryn Manduca (Carleton College). Participants in this program attended a workshop in Palo Alto for two days in May 2011, and many then attended the Committee's June 1-3 conference on teaching economics at Stanford, described above.</p><p>The Committee annually tracks the number of BA and BS degrees awarded at US colleges and universities. After three flat years, in 2008 the number of degrees awarded resumed the sharp increases seen from 1997-2004 (when they rose 56 percent). Over the past three years, the number of undergraduate degrees awarded rose by 16 percent. The percentage of undergraduate degrees in economics awarded to women declined slowly but steadily over the past six years, however, from a peak of 34 percent in 2003 to 30 percent in recent years. This occurred while the share of all bachelor's degrees earned by women remained constant at about 58 percent.</p><p>The Committee organized six sessions and two special events for the 2012 AEA meetings in Chicago. The six sessions were: The Committee hosted two special events at the Chicago meetings: For the seventh consecutive year the Committee hosted a continental breakfast for department directors of undergraduate studies in economics, to discuss issues of concern and share information (organized by Tisha Emerson at Baylor and Gail Hoyt at Kentucky); the annual reception for Friends of Economic Education (invitation only) was also hosted. The Committee Chair also makes an annual presentation on resources and programs the Committee offers at the breakfast for Chairs of economics departments.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">1. (AER Proceedings session) "</formula><p>Members of the Committee are called on to provide time and service each year, and they regularly and generously answer that call. Doug Bernheim completes his first term and begins a second. Other continuing members are Tisha Emerson, Ben Friedman, Gail Hoyt, Randy Kroszner, KimMarie McGoldrick, and Susan Rose. William Bosshardt will step down from the Committee in light of a new position he has taken with the Council for Economic Education in New York. New members joining the Committee in 2012 are Sam Allgood (Chair) and Steve Cobb.</p><p>Bill Greene and Mike Watts complete their second terms on the Committee at the Chicago meetings, which invokes the AEA's term limit policy for committee memberships. Greene set a record that may well never be equaled in reviewing papers and abstracts submitted in response to Committee calls for papers for sessions at the January AEA meetings, including the Committee's AER Papers and Proceedings session in 2009, which Greene organized. Watts served as Chair of the Committee for the past six years.</p><p>Current information and past reports about the Committee and its activities are available at http://www.vanderbilt.edu/AEA/AEACEE/ index.htm. 3. Publishing and Support a. The JEE is published by Taylor and Francis (www.taylorandfrancis.com).</p><p>The Taylor and Francis staff has been very timely and efficient in the production of journal issues. Taylor and Francis maintains a Web site for the JEE.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Report for the Journal of Economic Education Submitted to the Committee on Economic Education of the American Economic Association</head><label></label><figDesc>Paul Grimes, former JEE Associate Editor and now Business Dean at Pittsburg State University. b. Other additions to the Board are being considered.</figDesc><table><row><cell>January 6, 2012</cell><cell>b. The JEE Editor and Taylor and Francis</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>changed the cover, size, print style, and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>other internal features of the JEE start-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ing with Volume 41, Number 1 (January-March 2010). No further changes were</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>made in 2011 or are being considered.</cell></row><row><cell>William B. Walstad (JEE Editor) Chicago, IL</cell><cell>c. The JEE receives about 170 manu-Most manuscripts are published within scripts a year (average over 2008-2011).</cell></row><row><cell>1. Editors</cell><cell>a year of acceptance. Associate Editors</cell></row><row><cell>a. In January 2011 Paul Grimes stepped</cell><cell>have been very conscientious in seeking</cell></row><row><cell>down as Associate Editor for instruc-</cell><cell>quality reviews and in making thought-</cell></row><row><cell>tion after having served in this capac-</cell><cell>ful and timely recommendations to the</cell></row><row><cell>ity for the past three years (since 2008). The JEE greatly benefitted from Paul's</cell><cell>Editor. d. Manuscripts are submitted to the</cell></row><row><cell>thoughtful and effective service.</cell><cell>JEE in a Word file by e-mail with a</cell></row><row><cell>b. In January 2011 Tisha Emerson (Baylor University) and KimMarie McGoldrick</cell><cell>cover letter to jee@unl.edu. Taylor and Francis was willing to develop an</cell></row><row><cell>(University of Richmond) were appointed Associate Editors. They are primarily responsible for manuscripts</cell><cell>electronic submission and manuscript management system for the JEE (aka: Manuscript Central), but for now the</cell></row><row><cell>related to instruction.</cell><cell>Associate Editors prefer to use the use</cell></row><row><cell>c. Other JEE Associate Editors remain</cell><cell>the current e-mail system.</cell></row><row><cell>in place: David Colander (Middlebury College) for the Content section;</cell><cell>e. Sharon Nemeth, the JEE Editorial Assistant at Nebraska, provides invalu-</cell></row><row><cell>and Bill Goffe (SUNY-Oswego) for the Online section. Sam Allgood</cell><cell>able help with processing manuscripts, corresponding with authors and editors,</cell></row><row><cell>(University of Nebraska-Lincoln) is primarily responsible for the Research</cell><cell>and maintaining records. f. The JEE is published in cooperation with</cell></row><row><cell>section. Responsibility for the Features</cell><cell>the Council for Economic Education,</cell></row><row><cell>and Information section is shared</cell><cell>the Committee on Economic Education</cell></row><row><cell>among all editors.</cell><cell>of the American Economic Association,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and the Department of Economics at</cell></row><row><cell>2. Editorial Board</cell><cell>the University of Nebraska. The JEE is</cell></row><row><cell>a. The following people have joined the</cell><cell>sponsored by the Council for Economic</cell></row><row><cell>JEE board in 2011: (1) John Taylor, Professor of Economics at Stanford;</cell><cell>Education, and its financial support is greatly appreciated.</cell></row><row><cell>(2) Annamaria Lusardi, Professor of Economics at George Washington</cell><cell>4. Current and Future Publications</cell></row><row><cell>University (formerly at Dartmouth College); and (3)</cell><cell>a. A special section of the JEE in 2012 will be devoted to publication of a limited set of papers that were first presented</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>at the AEA-CEE and JEE-sponsored</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>conference at Stanford University in</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>summer 2011. All participants at this</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>conference were invited to submit their</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Respectfully submitted, presented papers. A total of 29 papers</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Michael Watts, Chair were submitted from which 10 have</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>been accepted for publication. The sub-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>mitted papers underwent the same peer</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and editorial review as all JEE pub-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>lished papers but using an expedited</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>schedule.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>AEA PAPERS AND PROCEEDINGS b. A call for papers was issued for a 2012 AEA-CEE session on "Research in Economic Education." Publication of these papers are being considered for the JEE after review. c. A special section of the JEE in 2013 will be devoted to selected papers presented at the AEA-CEE and JEEsponsored conference at the Boston Fed in summer 2012. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Editorial Statistics</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Howard</forename><surname>Cochran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marieta</forename><surname>Velikova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">both at Belmont); &quot;Don&apos;t Touch My Medicare</title>
		<editor>Elizabeth Peterson (Eastern Washington) and Charlotta Evans</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Utah</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using Peer Assessment to Improve Literative Reviews in Economics&quot; by Julie Smith (Lafayette)</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Promoting Active Learning through Online Undergraduate Economics Journals</title>
		<editor>Stephanie Davis-Kahl, Robert Leekley, and Michael Seeborg</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>all at Illinois Wesleyan</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Does Economic Instruction Vary in Community Colleges across Four Regions?&quot; by John Min (Northern Virginia Community College) and Amber Casolari (Riverside City College)</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Realm of Imperfection: Monopoly, Oligopoly and Monopolistic Competition</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using Macroeconomic Indicators in Managerial Decision-Making&quot; by Brian Sloboda (Phoenix); &quot;A Web-Based Interactive Macro-Econ Learning System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marilyn</forename><surname>Cottrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Is Your CFO Smarter Than a Sophomore? Applying Economics to University Managerial Decisions</title>
		<editor>Jinzhuo Zhao</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Brock; St. Thomas; Hampden-Sydney</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>TeachingWithData.org: Online Resources for Bringing Data into the Classroom. all at Michigan</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Utilizing Economic Modules for Undergraduate Teaching though Internship Programs&quot; by Maureen Dunne, Martha Meaney, and Fahlino Sjuib (all at Framingham State)</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Big Think: A Model for Critical Inquiry in Economics Courses</title>
		<editor>Robert Garnett (Texas Christian) and KimMarie McGoldrick</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Using Collective Action Experiments to Teach the Economics of Social Issues&quot; by James Bruehler, Linda Ghent (both at Eastern Illinois) and Alan Grant (Baker). Richmond</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
