<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The DataLab of the Australian Bureau of Statistics</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Wiley</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-11-30">2017-11-30</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Talei</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
							<email>&lt;talei.parker@abs.gov.au&gt;.</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Customised and Microdata Delivery Section</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dissemi-nation Branch</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Australian Bureau of Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Australian Capital Territory</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2617</postCode>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Commonwealth of Australia. Australian Economic Review°C</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Melbourne</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2017, 2017</postCode>
									<settlement>Ltd</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The DataLab of the Australian Bureau of Statistics</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Australian Economic Review</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Australian Economic Review</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0004-9018</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="478" to="483"/>
							<date type="published" when="2017-11-30" />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1467-8462.12246</idno>
					<ptr type="open-access" target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdfdirect/10.1111/1467-8462.12246" />
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-14T00:49+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Over and above the current multitude of licensed micro-level datasets that the Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS) provides for research purposes, the ABS has expanded its support to include the new DataLab protected research environment to allow unparalleled access to Australia&apos;s valuable micro-level research datasets. The environment is highly protected by multiple layers of data security but allows access to unprecedented levels of data detail in realtime to datasets such as the 2006-2011 linked census (ACLD), the ABS firm survey and tax panel (BLADE) and linked census and administrative data (MADIP).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Australia's official national statistical agency, the Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS), provides academics and researchers access to microdata by way of the widely known confidential unit record files (or CURFs) via CD-ROM, the Remote Access Data Laboratory (RADL) and the ABS Data Laboratory (ABSDL, onsite). The ABS also provides two TableBuilder products, online tools for creating tables, graphs and maps using ABS microdata. These microdata files are 'licensed', as opposed to 'public use', as each organisation, and its individual staff, is required to sign relevant undertakings assuring it will abide by prescribed conditions of use (under the Census and Statistics Act 1905 (Cwlth) and the Statistics Determination 1983). Recently the ABS has expanded its microdata product suite by offering the DataLab protected research environment, which for the first time allows researchers to have unparalleled access to protected ABS datasets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">The DataLab</head><p>Essentially, the DataLab is a data analysis solution for high-end data users who want to extract full value from ABS microdata in an interactive (real time) environment. All ABS microdata files, ranging from basic and expanded CURFs through to detailed and integrated files, are accessible via the DataLab, providing a more responsive and interactive environment than that offered by RADL and TableBuilder. The DataLab can be accessed securely on-site at ABS offices or as part of the virtual DataLab trial program.</p><p>The DataLab was designed in late 2015 to improve access to ABS microdata, enhance user experience and advance research outcomes to inform policy design and delivery, as well as increase the use of statistics within the research community. The development areas to be addressed included: the costs and security risks associated with the maintenance of ageing technologies (for example, RADL); the substantial changes in user requirements and the increased sophistication of researcher skills (for example, programming skills associated with SAS as opposed to improved 'point and click' functionality, and open source coding packages such as R and Python); and importantly the increased risk of re-identification posed by making more detailed as well as integrated microdata available.</p><p>While the RADL allows analysis of microdata in a secure and controlled environment, it does not allow 'remote' access as implied by its name. Instead it provides a remote execution service, whereby authorised users submit queries in SAS 9.1, SPSS 11.5 or Stata 10 analytical languages against expanded CURFs (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1)</ref>. A range of automated processes monitor data requests and either release or withhold results where there is a possible confidentiality/disclosure risk. The number of unit records that can be seen at any one point in time is restricted in the RADL.</p><p>In comparison, the DataLab environment provides users with their own virtual workspace within the secure ABS cloud (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>). These workspaces can be accessed remotely, using a two-factor authentication over an encrypted internet connection using Citrix. While the microdata files remain in the secure environment, users can view and analyse unit record information using the latest analytical software with no code restrictions. All analytical outputs are subject to a principles-based, manual vetting process to evaluate disclosure risks and apply confidentiality measures where required before being released.</p><p>The storage of files and running of analyses occurs on dedicated ABS servers housed in a secure data centre. The DataLab environment is a self-contained environment (that is, there is no email or internet connection, no copy and paste functionality in or out of the environment, no print facility and data cannot be copied to removable media). All file movement in and out of the DataLab is performed and managed by the ABS Customised and Microdata Delivery (CaMD) team through a dedicated administrative portal following a strict auditing and sign-off process. All sessions within the DataLab environment are recorded allowing for real-time monitoring and subsequent playback. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">DataLab Access and Approval Process</head><p>Access to the DataLab is managed under a 'Trusted Access' model using the principles from the 'Five Safes Framework' (FSF) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Desai, Ritchie and Welpton 2016)</ref>. The ABS has adopted this model in order to significantly improve and more effectively manage microdata access and disclosure risk. Users are at the core of this model, which is built on the value of partnerships, shared accountability and the mutual benefits that result from researcher access to data. By carefully assessing people, projects, settings, data and output, necessary controls can be put in place to increase public value from national statistics whilst protecting privacy and confidentiality. The FSF (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>) allows the ABS to better enable authorised users to work directly with the data without infringing on their academic independence.</p><p>Each of the 'five safes' is considered independently on a sliding scale, as well as jointly, to evaluate whether a particular method of data access meets these requirements. Once researchers are trained, authorised and have signed relevant undertakings to comply with privacy and confidentiality obligations, the level of direct treatment applied to the data can be reduced. Similarly, technology settings and output review further protect data access and results. The benefit of this approach is that steps taken to protect privacy and confidentiality are designed to be both reasonable collectively and adequate to minimise the overall risk of disclosure.</p><p>In order to use the DataLab, researchers must first be 'accredited'. The accreditation  (vi) Researchers must complete and submit a project proposal (Safe project). The proposal needs to outline the research objectives and any associated ethics/ grants approvals, the microdata products to be used, and any anticipated outcomes and project timeframes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Using the ABS DataLab</head><p>Once researchers have completed the accreditation process they are provided with a username and password. Researchers in the virtual DataLab trial are also supplied with a secure two-factor authentication Fortitoken 1 to enable access from their desktop in their own workplace environments. Once logged into the system, researchers are made aware that session recording is used in°C the system and they must indicate agreement to this. Session recording is a part of the required DataLab auditing process and all sessions are viewed by CaMD staff. The use of a virtual environment has been provided to enable the researcher complete flexibility in how they approach their analytical/project work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">DataLab Drives</head><p>A total of four drives are provided within the DataLab for each user in a Windows environment.</p><p>The H: drive is the researcher's personal drive. It contains an 'Application' folder and a 'Clearance' folder. The 'Application' folder is for the researcher to save and access any code, project information and output files in the course of their work. If the researcher has any pre-prepared code files, Word/PDF documents or public data files they may wish to use then these will be accessible in this folder once they have been cleared and loaded by CaMD. The 'Clearance' folder is where the researcher places analytical results that require vetting.</p><p>Those microdata files that the researcher has been given approval to use can be found in the V: drive. Project teams have access to a shared project space-the S: drive-within their individual virtual workspaces. The shared project spaces have been designed to facilitate collaboration and enable the team to complete their research/project end to end before requesting a release of outputs to be used for public dissemination.</p><p>The L: drive is a read-only drive designed to mimic 'Google' in a way. As the DataLab is a contained environment with no internet access, this drive has been created to house analytical reference material, publicly available code and any other material that researchers may routinely use or search for in the normal course of their work.</p><p>In relation to package add-ons, researchers can request for CaMD to have these loaded on their behalf. For example, a researcher who is using STATA may need an add-on, such as 'svr', that is not available in the ABS licensed package within the DataLab. A request can be made to CaMD to have this added into the DataLab environment and once loaded it will be available for all DataLab users via this drive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Clearance Process (Safe Outputs)</head><p>Output checking is standard practice in countries that use the FSF (for example, Stats NZ 2017 and Office for National Statistics 2017) and is a mechanism to protect against statistical disclosure, that is, the release of information that could lead to the identification of an individual, household or organisation in data. As microdata files in the DataLab have lower levels of 'confidentialisation' applied, they carry an increased risk of disclosure, compared to other products. Output checking helps to mitigate reasonably this risk and guard against mistakes.</p><p>Once researchers are ready to have an output file released, they save it to their 'Clearance' folder and CaMD team members will vet the request. The turn-around time for the vetting process is 1-2 business days.</p><p>CaMD uses a 'principles'-based approach to output checking <ref type="bibr">(Ritchie and Elliot 2015)</ref> and utilises 'rules of thumb'. Practical guidelines on adhering to the safe output standard are provided to users as part of the face-to-face DataLab training session. Once output has been cleared, it is released to the researcher via email.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Improved Microdata Offering</head><p>The full suite of basic and expanded CURFs (ABS 2017) are available in the DataLab, removing the need for researchers to use CD-ROMs (basic CURFs) and/or the RADL (expanded CURFs). With the implementation of the FSF and the development of the DataLab, the ABS now also offers access to detailed microdata files (ABS 2017). These files have been designed specifically for the DataLab, have direct identifiers removed and are confidentialised within the context of the DataLab's security features. The following are examples of such files. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Conclusion</head><p>The ABS DataLab research environment offers researchers greater flexibility in accessing and analysing unit record data whilst ensuring essential confidentiality processes are maintained. Up-to-date technology and trusted access based risk management mean the system is streamlined, responsive to user needs and provides microdata access in a reliable and safe manner. The DataLab delivers ease of use, enhanced opportunity for collaboration and a modernised approach to dissemination. Researchers can better inform public decisions and develop policy. These outcomes are achieved in a manner that respects privacy and confidentiality of those who provide their data.</p><p>September 2017 Endnote 1. See &lt;https://www.fortinet.com/products/identity-accessmanagement.html&gt;.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 RADL</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Login and Query Screens</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>DataLab Login and Home Screens</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(i) Australian Census Longitudinal Dataset (ACLD): The ACLD is a 5 per cent°C sample of data from the 2006 Census linked to the 2011 Census. It enables largesample longitudinal analysis of transitions in the economic and social conditions of Australians. (ii) Business Longitudinal Analysis Data Environment (BLADE): The BLADE is an integrated data environment and was developed by the ABS and the Department of Industry, Innovation and Science. It contains detailed information drawing on several years of ABS business survey data and administrative data from the Australian Tax Office (ATO), on the characteristics and finances of Australian businesses. This allows for longitudinal analysis of business and investigatory analyses of the 'microeconomic factors driving productivity, performance, innovation and job creation' in the Australian economy (ABS 2016-17) (iii) Multi-Agency Data Integration Project (MADIP): MADIP is an on-going partnership project that brings ABS Census data together with administrative data from the ATO, Department of Human Services, Department of Social Services, Department of Health and, most recently, the Department of Education. Currently in an evaluation phase, it creates a valuable data resource with significant potential for research and policy analysis (ABS 2016-17).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The Five Safes (FSF) Applied to Trusted Access</figDesc><table><row><cell>Principle</cell><cell>Criteria</cell><cell>In practical terms</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Safe People Appropriate personal authorisation</cell><cell>An undertaking on how the data will be used is signed after</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>to access and use the data</cell><cell>engagement with the researcher. Training is provided so</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>that users understand their responsibilities and are able to</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>use the microdata effectively.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Safe Projects Data to be used for an appropriate</cell><cell>Users demonstrate that they will use the data for legitimate</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>purpose</cell><cell>statistical research purposes.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Safe Settings The access environment prevents</cell><cell>The data cannot be exported from the environment.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>unauthorised use</cell><cell>The login is secure.</cell></row><row><cell>Safe Data</cell><cell>The data have been appropriately</cell><cell>Directly identifying information has been removed and the data</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and sufficiently protected</cell><cell>are treated appropriately with respect to the other four</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>'safes'.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Safe Outputs The statistical results do not disclose</cell><cell>Outputs are checked for disclosure risk and treated if deemed</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>identifying information</cell><cell>necessary°C</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2017">Commonwealth of Australia. Australian Economic Review°C 2017 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2017">Commonwealth of Australia. Australian Economic Review°C 2017 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">The Australian Economic Review December 2017</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2017">Commonwealth of Australia. Australian Economic Review°C 2017 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd Parker: The DataLab of the Australian Bureau of Statistics</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2017">Commonwealth of Australia. Australian Economic Review°C 2017 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Parker: The DataLab of the Australian Bureau of Statistics</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Forward Work Program, Cat. no. 1006.0, ABS, Canberra</title>
		<ptr target="&lt;http://www.abs.gov.au/ausstats/abs@.nsf/Lookup/by%20Subject/1006.0~2016-17~Main%" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-09" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Australian Bureau of Statistics</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<ptr target="&lt;http://www.abs.gov.au/websitedbs/D3310114.nsf/home/Expected+and+available+Micro-data&gt;" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Available Microdata</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-09" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Australian Bureau of Statistics</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Five Safes: Designing data access for research</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Desai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ritchie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Welpton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>no. 1601</idno>
		<ptr target="&lt;https://blog.ons.gov.uk/2017/01/27/the-five-safes-data-privacy-at-ons/&gt;" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of the West of England, Bristol. Office for National Statistics</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Economics Working Paper</note>
	<note>The &quot;Five Safes&quot; -Data privacy at ONS&apos;, ONS</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Principles- Versus Rules-Based Output Statistical Disclosure Control In Remote Access Environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Felix</forename><surname>Ritchie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mark</forename><surname>Elliot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.29173/iq778</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://iassistquarterly.com/index.php/iassist/article/view/778/770" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IASSIST Quarterly</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">IQ</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0739-1137</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015-12-11" />
			<publisher>University of Alberta Libraries</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Stats</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="&lt;http://www.stats.govt.nz/about_us/legisln-policies-protocols/microdata-access-protocols.aspx&gt;.°C" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Microdata Access Protocols</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
