<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">INFORMAL LABOR MARKETS AND ON-THE-JOB TRAINING: EVIDENCE FROM WAGE DATA</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Wiley</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-10-15">October 15, 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Javier</forename><surname>Cano-Urbina</surname></persName>
							<email>jcanourbina@fsu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Eco-nomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Florida State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tallahassee</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">INFORMAL LABOR MARKETS AND ON-THE-JOB TRAINING: EVIDENCE FROM WAGE DATA</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Economic Inquiry</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Econ Inq</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0095-2583</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="43"/>
							<date type="published" when="2015-10-15">October 15, 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/ecin.12279</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T22:02+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>This study examines whether informal sector jobs are a source of training for young less-educated workers. Controlling for worker and job characteristics, it is found that, in the early years of workers&apos; careers in Mexico, wage growth in the informal sector is higher than in the formal sector. This result is consistent with general human capital investment on-the-job if the informal labor market is more competitive than the formal labor market due to frictions generated by labor regulations. (JEL O17, J24, J310) I. INTRODUCTION This study explores the role of informal jobs in the formation of human capital among young less-educated workers. An informal job is a job that fails to comply with some or all of the labor regulations. 1 The set of all informal jobs constitute what is typically known as the informal sector. Due to the lack of compliance with the labor laws, informal jobs are not registered with the authorities. 2 However, it is often argued that compliance with these laws is of great significance in developing countries to ensure social justice for workers (Berg and Kucera 2008) and to protect them against the forces of reallocation in the labor market (Inter-American Development Bank 2003). In spite of these arguments, the lack of compliance with these mandates in developing countries is common practice, leading to the existence of sizable informal labor markets, especially among the youth and the less educated. 3 Hence, the importance of understanding what role the informal sector is playing in the lives of young less-educated workers.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>1. These regulations are usually designed to protect workers, for example, minimum wage, health insurance, severance pay, and retirement pension.</p><p>2. Nevertheless, it is important to note that the informal sector is not about the black or the illegal market.</p><p>3. According to the statistics of the Socio-Economic Database for Latin America and the Caribbean (published by CEDLAS and The World Bank), the proportion of male workers ages 15-24 years with informal jobs ranges from 30.6% in Chile to 90% in Bolivia (information obtained in September 2012). According to the same source, in Mexico, this proportion is 79%.</p><p>The traditional views of the informal sector in the literature are that of a sector that is the last resort for many workers who are rationed out of the protected and better paid jobs in the formal sector (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Ozorio de Almeida et al. 1995)</ref>, or that it is the disadvantaged sector in a segmented labor market (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fields 1975;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Harris and Todaro 1970)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">4</ref> The support for these views of the informal sector is mixed in the literature. The work of <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Maloney (1999)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Amaral and Quintin (2006)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Galiani and Weinschelbaum (2012)</ref> suggests that the existence of informal labor markets is not necessarily evidence of segmentation and that could be an equilibrium outcome in a competitive labor market. However, the work of <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Arias and Khamis (2008)</ref> presents some evidence that is consistent with the rationing of formal-salaried jobs and with segmentation in the labor market. 5 4. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Harris and Todaro (1970)</ref> were concerned with urban unemployment and explained this in the context of a model of labor markets with segmentation between rural and urban jobs. The full connection with the informal sector is in the model developed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fields (1975)</ref>. I would like to thank an anonymous referee from Economic Inquiry for pointing this out to me.</p><p>5. Also, the results from household surveys in Argentina, Bolivia, Colombia, and the Dominican Republic presented by <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Arias and Maloney (2007)</ref> appear to suggest that an important fraction of informal-salaried workers are rationed out of the better paid formal-salaried jobs (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>.9 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Arias and Maloney 2007</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ABBREVIATIONS</head><p>ENEU: Encuesta Nacional de Empleo Urbano ENOE: Encuesta Nacional de Ocupación y Empleo IMSS: Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social IPW: Inverse Probability Weights Despite the ongoing debate, informal jobs play an important role in the work lives of lesseducated workers. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Maloney (1999)</ref> argues that informal-salaried jobs serve as the main point of entry for young poorly educated workers into paid employment. The current study further explores this idea focusing on the group of young less-educated workers in Mexico. The study explores the extent to which less-educated workers in the informal sector experience wage growth and how wage growth in the informal sector compares with wage growth in the formal sector. The basic question is whether informal jobs offer wage growth and skill accumulation to less-educated workers, and how it compares with formal jobs.</p><p>The empirical analysis uses a household survey from Mexico, the ENOE (acronym in Spanish for Encuesta Nacional de Ocupación y Empleo). The panel structure of the survey allows the construction of measures of wage growth and continuing sector participation. The results indicate that young less-educated workers in the informal sector experience faster wage growth than their peers in the formal sector. Based on existing models of on-the-job training <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Acemoglu and</ref><ref type="bibr">Pischke 1999a, 1999b;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Becker 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Stevens 1994)</ref>, this result suggests that informal jobs offer valuable general training opportunities to young less-educated workers.</p><p>The literature provides little evidence on wage growth in the informal sector or on how it compares with wage growth in the formal sector. There is some evidence on the wage gain (or loss) from informality. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Maloney (1999)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Alcaraz et al. (2011)</ref> provide estimates of the wage change associated with transitions between the formal and informal sectors in Mexico. The results in both studies indicate that informal-toformal transitions are associated with positive wage changes, while transitions in the opposite direction are associated with negative wage changes. However, none of these two studies provide evidence on wage growth experienced by workers in the informal sector or how it compares to wage growth in the formal sector. The present study contributes to the literature on the informal sector by providing evidence and some suggestive ideas of the mechanisms behind these results.</p><p>The study is organized as follows. The following section describes the sample used for the analysis and the criteria used to classify employed respondents as formal or informal sector workers. Next, evidence from wage data is presented in Section III and the economic interpretations of this evidence are presented in Section IV. The last section concludes and discusses future research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. DATA</head><p>The empirical analysis is based on data from a household survey in Mexico called the Occupation and Employment Survey, ENOE. The ENOE is a rotating panel where households are visited five times over the course of a year, one visit every 3 months. <ref type="bibr">6</ref> The ENOE collects demographic data from each family member as well as job-related data for members who are 12 years of age or older. Job-related data include information on the individual's occupation, size of the firm and industry of occupation, earnings per hour, as well as work-related benefits. I used data from the ENOE from the first quarter of 2005 to the fourth quarter of 2012. Appendix A provides more details on this survey.</p><p>The sample used in the analysis includes male workers only. 7 Also, as the arguments made on this article are based on the employer-worker relationship and on who bears the cost of training, the sample is limited to workers who are employees. Self-employment is treated as a job category different from informal-salaried and formal-salaried as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Arias and Maloney (2007)</ref> or <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Arias and Khamis (2008)</ref>. I restrict the sample to individuals who have less than 12 years of education and did not attend school during the five visits to the household in an effort to focus on less-educated workers who are committed to the labor market. As this study focuses on young workers, the main sample used in the analysis only includes workers between the ages of 16 and 25 years. 8 However, to get a better understanding of the results, the analysis also considers samples of older workers.</p><p>6. For example, a household visited for the first time in January 2005 will be visited the second time in April 2005, the third time in July 2005, the fourth time in October 2005, and the fifth time in January 2006. Not all households are visited for the first time in January, they could be visited for the first time in any other month of the year. 7. Some authors have found that women may have different reasons for joining the informal sector, for example, job flexibility to balance work and child rearing <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Arias and Maloney 2007)</ref>.</p><p>8. Age 16 is the minimum age at which a worker can be hired according to Mexican Labor Law (see Articles 22, 173, and 174 of the Ley Federal del Trabajo). And so I set it as the lower bound for the sample. Age 26 is when the transition rate from informal to formal sector reaches a maximum (see <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>(b) below). And so I choose age 25 as the upper bound to focus on the first 10 years of the workers' careers.</p><p>Finally, because the informal sector is mainly an urban phenomenon, the sample is restricted to the urban areas. In principle, I include all the cities that are statistically self-represented in the sample of the ENOE. This includes 32 cities. In all of these cities, except for one, the population is larger than 100,000 people. 9 It is important to mention that there are communities in the sample with a population lower than 100,000 people, but that are assigned to a self-represented city. That is the case of small communities located in the outskirts of large cities. In those cases, I include observations from individuals living in the smaller communities even when the community where they live is not larger than 100,000 people. 10 Finally, I also include in the sample individuals who live in cities that are not selfrepresented in the sample but that are larger than 100,000 people.</p><p>During the period of observation, males account for 49.70% of the respondents with less than 12 years of education and not attending school. Among these less-educated males, 15.57% were between the ages of 16 and 25 years at the time of the first interview, and 91.70% of them were employed. 11 Among these young less-educated employed respondents, 79.38% worked as paid employees, while 8.67% were self-employed, 10.60% were unpaid employees, and 1.35% were employers. Finally, among these young less-educated workers working as paid employees, 28.98% attended primary school and no more (years 1-6), and 71.24% of those who attended graduated from primary school. Whereas 58.34% attended middle school but went no further, and 84.14% of those who attended graduated from middle school. The proportion of workers in the sample who attended high school but did not graduate is 10.09%. 12 9. The one self-represented city that is not larger than 100,000 people is the city of Tlaxcala. It is classified as a city with a population between 15,000 and 99,999 people. According to the INEGI, the Statistics Bureau in Mexico in charge of the Census (and the ENOE), in 2010 the population of the city of Tlaxcala was 89,795 people (see http://www3 .inegi.org.mx/sistemas/mexicocifras/default.aspx).</p><p>10. In those cases, these "smaller" communities will be very much urbanized as the larger city, or even attached to the larger city. And in many cases individuals may in fact work in the big city.</p><p>11. Note that 92.19% of the less-educated workers between the ages of 26 and 65 are employed. This proportion is very similar to the proportion of younger workers, suggesting that the vast majority of the young less-educated workers included in the sample are already committed to the labor market in spite of not having completed high school.</p><p>12. Notice that this low percentage is a result of only including workers with less than 12 years of education in the To determine informal sector status of a worker, I use the labor laws in Mexico. When a worker is hired in Mexico, labor regulations mandate that the employer register the worker in the Mexican Institute of Social Security, IMSS (acronym in Spanish for Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social). This institution provides a bundle of benefits to its affiliates, such as health insurance, day-care services for children, life insurance, disability pensions, work-risk pensions, sports and cultural facilities, retirement pensions, and housing loans <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Levy 2007)</ref>. Both the employer and the worker pay fees to fund this institution, but the employer fees are higher than the worker fees. If a firm is caught not complying with this regulation, it incurs a penalty. Once a worker is registered in the IMSS, the work relationship must abide by the labor regulation in Mexico. <ref type="bibr">13</ref> The questionnaire of the ENOE does not ask the individual whether he is a formal or an informal worker, but whether his job gives him access to medical services provided by IMSS or other institutions. 14 In this study, I consider a worker to belong to the formal sector if he is a paid employee and his job gives him access to any kind of medical services, and to belong to the informal sector if he is a paid employee and his job does not give him access to medical services. <ref type="bibr">15</ref> In the remainder of the study, I will focus on male workers with less than 12 years of education and employed as paid employees (salaried). Following the aforementioned definitions of informal and formal sectors, <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>(a) presents the proportion of workers employed sample. The proportion of workers who attend high school and went no further among male individuals between ages 16 and 25 years who were paid employees is 26.74%, where 64.09% graduated from high school. A bit more than 10% attended college.</p><p>13. A salient mandate of the labor laws in Mexico is the severance pay. Workers in Mexico are entitled to severance pay either when they are fired or when they resign. Firing a worker "with just cause," in order to avoid severance pay, is difficult; and even if the employer is able to fire the worker with just cause, the worker is still entitled to a reduced severance pay. The severance pay is mandatory even if the firm is closing its business (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Gordon and Williams 2002)</ref>.</p><p>14. Other institutions could be the ISSSTE, the military or navy hospital, or the PEMEX hospital. ISSSTE is an institution similar to IMSS but for State employees only. PEMEX is the state-owned petroleum company in Mexico. Given the link between the State and these institutions, all workers entitled to medical services from these institutions will be hired formally.</p><p>15. As mentioned before, self-employed and unpaid employees are not included in this definition of the informal sector. That is, they are neither formal nor informal sector workers. Notes: Author's calculations using ENOE from Q1:2005 to Q4:2012. The calculations for panel (a) of the figure use only the information at the time of the first interview. The calculations for panel (b) of the figure pool all the ENOE panels (28 panels) over the period of observation and used the transitions over the course of a quarter. The samples include employed males with less than 12 years of education and not attending school. Both graphs use statistics calculated using the ENOE sampling weights.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FIGURE 1 Less-Educated Salaried Workers in Mexico by Age</head><p>in the formal or informal sectors at the time of the first interview for different age groups. The figure shows that 90.42% of those aged 16 at the time of the first interview were informal salaried, while the rest were formal salaried. Notice that the proportion of informal salaried decreases with the age groups between the ages of 16 and 46 years. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>(b) presents, also for different age groups, the transitions between the informal and formal sectors as a fraction of the size of the initial sector. These are the transitions over the course of a quarter (from one interview to the next) and pool all panels from the ENOE that are available over the period of observation. The figure shows that the likelihood of moving from the informal into the formal sector increases from 3.51% for workers of age 16 to 13.99% for workers of age 26 and that the likelihood of moving in the opposite direction decreases monotonically by age between workers aged 16 and those aged 26.</p><p>Note that the U-shaped age profile presented in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>(a) could be contaminated by generational effects. More specifically, to the extent that the "older" workers in the ENOE's 2005-2012 belong to a different generation, it could be that the graph reflects a generational pattern rather than a life-cycle one. There is however evidence that such a pattern is indeed a lifecycle one. In particular, Duval-Hernández and Orraca-Romano (2011) show that after removing cyclical and cohort effects, the life-cycle participation of unskilled males as informal salaried workers is U-shaped (see their <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>-B).</p><p>The change in the proportion of formal and informal workers, presented in <ref type="figure">Figure 1(a)</ref>, and the increase in the likelihood of making a transition from the informal to the formal sector, presented in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>(b), are consistent with a pattern in which less-educated workers enter the labor market through the informal sector with a tendency to move to the formal sector as they grow older. These patterns suggest that young less-educated workers employed in the informal sector may have expectations of eventually moving to the formal sector.</p><p>The final sample used for the analysis below only includes individuals who do not have missing values in key variables used in the analysis below. These are: age, education, earnings, size of firm where the worker is employed, as well as the industry where the firm operates. <ref type="bibr">16</ref> Appendix A provides more details on the measure of earnings that I used. Also, as the analysis below focuses on wage growth, I drop the top and bottom 0.5 percentiles of wage growth in the formal and informal sectors. <ref type="bibr">17</ref> Table 1 presents the summary statistics for the individuals in the sample at the time of the first 16. In the analysis below, I also use geographical variables and minimum wage variables, because this information is provided for all respondents in the sample, no respondent is drop for missing this information.</p><p>17. In the analysis below, I will focus on measures of one-, two-, three-, and four-quarter wage growth. For each of these four measures, and separately for each sector, I locate the top 0.5 percentile and the bottom 0.5 percentile and drop observations that are above the top or below the bottom 0.5 percentiles separately for each sector. Notes: Sample statistics using the ENOE sampling weights. Male paid-employees with less than 12 years of education and not attending school, ages 16-25 years. Individual and job characteristics at the time of the first interview. Hourly earnings are in Mexican pesos as in the second half of December of 2010. The ranking of minimum wages by zone is: w A &gt; w B &gt; w C , where w k is the minimum wage in zone k.</p><p>interview. About 50% of the individuals in the sample were employed in the formal sector at the time of the first interview. Even though workers in the formal sector are, on average, older, more educated, and have higher hourly earnings than those in the informal sector, the differences in these individual characteristics are not extreme. The proportion of workers who are married, however, is bigger in the formal sector. Notice the stark difference in the distribution of workers by firm size in the formal and informal sectors. In the formal sector, most of the workers are employed in large firms, whereas in the informal sector, most of the workers are employed in small firms. Also notice the differences in the distribution of workers by industry. The proportion of workers employed in the construction industry is larger in the informal sector, whereas the proportion of workers employed in the manufacturing industry is larger in the formal sector. The services industry is important in both sectors, although the proportion of workers employed in that industry is slightly larger in the informal sector.</p><p>III. EVIDENCE FROM WAGE DATA <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>(a) presents the empirical distribution of log wages in the formal and informal sectors in the sample. Wages are in Mexican Pesos of the second half of December 2010. <ref type="bibr">18</ref> Both distributions are more or less symmetric around their means, but the distribution of log wages in the formal sector is to the right of the distribution of log wages in the informal sector. A Kolmogorov-Smirnov test indicates that the distribution of log wages in the formal sector first order stochastically dominates the distribution of log wages in the informal sector. <ref type="bibr">19</ref> This result is consistent with the study by , who finds that informal-salaried workers have an earnings disadvantage with respect to formalsalaried workers at all points of the pay scale in the case of Argentina and Bolivia. This feature appears to be true for less-educated workers in Mexico. Log-wage regressions by sector have been estimated time and again in different papers in the literature; hence, I defer this discussion to Appendix B.</p><p>Figure 2(b) shows the empirical distribution of the one-quarter wage growth for the formal and informal sectors, where one-quarter wage growth is defined as the exact percentage change in wages Δ 1 w it = [(w it − w it − 1 )/w it − 1 ] × 100, and t is in quarters. Wage growth in both sectors is right-skewed, but none of the distributions appear to first order stochastically dominate the other. A Kolmogorov-Smirnov test indicates that there is no ranking of any of these two distributions. 20</p><p>18. I used the Consumer Price Index base 2nd half Dec 2010 to deflate wages.</p><p>19. The p value associated with the hypothesis that the empirical distribution function of ln(w) in the formal sector is "smaller" is 0.448, whereas the p value associated with the hypothesis that the empirical distribution function of ln(w) in the informal sector is "smaller" is 0.000, indicating that the distribution of ln(w) in the formal sector first order stochastically dominates that distribution in the informal sector.</p><p>20. The p value associated with the hypothesis that the empirical distribution function of Δ 1 w in the formal sector is "smaller" is 0.000, whereas the p value associated with the hypothesis that the empirical distribution function of Δ 1 w in the informal sector is "smaller" is 0.000, indicating no ranking between these two distributions in terms of first order stochastic dominance. Notes: Author's calculations using ENOE from Q1:2005 to Q4:2012. The sample includes males with less than 12 years of education and not attending school. The sample includes all wage observations, and so it can include multiple observations for each respondent. For panel (b), the top and bottom 0.5% of the one-quarter wage growth is dropped from the sample.</p><p>However, the distribution of wage growth in the informal sector appears to be slightly more disperse than in the formal sector, suggesting that wages are more flexible in the informal sector, both for wage increases and wage decreases. A traditional variance ratio test rejects the hypothesis that the variance of Δ 1 w in the formal sector is equal to the variance of Δ 1 w in the informal sector in favor of an alternative that the variance of Δ 1 w in the formal sector is smaller. 21 However, this test is sensitive to the assumption that the data are drawn from a Normal distribution. Using a test for the equality of variances that is robust when dealing with skewed distributions <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Brown and Forsythe 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr">Levene 1960</ref>) also rejects the null hypothesis that the variances are equal. <ref type="bibr">22</ref> Next, I explore how wage growth in the informal sector compares to wage growth in the formal 21. For the variance ratio test, I used the Stata command sdtest. The null hypothesis of this test is that the ratio r = σ 2 FS ∕σ 2 IS equals 1, i.e. H 0 : r = 1. The calculated test statistic is f = 0.6605, which is distributed as F <ref type="bibr">(32172,</ref><ref type="bibr">27221)</ref> , where the degrees of freedom in the numerator and denominator are (n FS − 1) and (n IS − 1), respectively. This null is rejected against the alternative H 1 : r &lt; 1 with a p value of 0.0000, and against the alternative H 1 : r ≠ 1 with a p value of 0.0000, but cannot be rejected against the alternative H 1 : r &gt; 1 with a p value of 1.0000.</p><p>22. To test the hypothesis of equal variances, I used the Stata command robvar which provides three alternative test statistics that vary the measure of central tendency used to calculate the test. The first one uses the mean of each group under comparison, the second uses the median of each group, and the third uses the 10% trimmed mean of each group. The first variant of the test is the one proposed by <ref type="bibr">Levene (1960)</ref>, the other two are the ones proposed by Brown and sector conditional on individual and firm characteristics and for different time spans. To this end, I estimate the following wage-growth regressions:</p><p>(1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Δ k w it = β k IS k it + x ′ it γ k + ξ k it , for k = 1, 2, 3, 4 where t is defined in quarters and Δ k w it = [(w it − w it − k )/w it − k ] × 100, for k = 1, 2, 3, 4</formula><p>, that is, one-quarter, two-quarters, three-quarters, and four-quarters wage growth equations, respectively. For each of the four wage growth regressions in Equation (1), the variable IS k it is an indicator that equals 1 if the worker was employed (k + 1) consecutive quarters in the informal sector, and equals 0 if the worker was employed (k + 1) consecutive quarters in the formal sector. That is, let I it be an indicator variable equal to 1 if individual i is employed in the informal sector in quarter t and 0 otherwise, and let F it be an indicator variable equal to 1 if individual i is employed in the formal sector in quarter t and 0 otherwise. Then, for the one-quarter wage growth regression IS 1 it is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">IS 1 it = { 1 if I it = I it−1 = 1 0 if F it = F it−1 = 1 .</formula><p>Forsythe <ref type="formula">1974</ref>, and which are more robust than Levene's test when dealing with skewed distributions. The calculated test statistics are: W 0 = 603.806 for the mean, W 50 = 448.425 for the median, and W 10 = 481.202 for the 10% trimmed mean. In each case, the test statistic is distributed as F (1,59393) , where the degrees of freedom in the denominator are (n FS + n IS − 2), and in all three cases the p value is 0.0000. Notes: All regressions are weighted using the ENOE sampling weights. The samples include male paid-employees with less than 12 years of education and not attending school, ages 16-25 years. Primary School Grad = {E ≥ 6}, Middle School Grad = {E ≥ 9}. The ranking of minimum wages by zone is: w A &gt; w B &gt; w C , where w k is the minimum wage in Zone k. The omitted category for the minimum dummy is Z one A. All specifications include year dummies, city dummies, and city-size dummies, and a dummy equal to 1 if the measure of hourly earnings was imputed using the minimum wage in the zone. Huber-White robust standard errors clustered at the individual level are in parenthesis.</p><p>Similarly, for the two-, three-, and four-quarter wage growth regression IS k it is defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">IS k it = { 1 if I it = • • • = I it−k = 1 0 if F it = • • • = F it−k = 1 for k = 2, 3, 4.</formula><p>Notice that the definition of the indicator variables IS k it implies that, in the estimation of Equation (1) for each of the four time spans (k = 1, 2, 3, 4) I can only use the observations from individuals that were employed in the formal or informal sectors for at least (k + 1) consecutive quarters. For example, consider the one-quarter wage growth of a worker who was employed in the informal sector in quarters t and (t + 1), but employed in the formal sector in quarters (t + 2), (t + 3), and (t + 4). The estimation sample will include the one-quarter wage growth between quarters t and (t + 1) as informal sector wage growth, but will not include the onequarter wage growth between quarters (t + 1) and (t + 2) because this is neither informal sector nor formal sector wage growth, it is the wage growth associated with the transition from informal to formal sectors. Then, the sample will also include the one-quarter wage growth between quarters (t + 2) and (t + 3) and between quarters (t + 3) and (t + 4) as formal sector wage growth. Now, consider the same individual for the two-quarter wage growth. The sample will not include a measure of two-quarter wage growth for this particular worker because the worker does not have a two-quarter wage growth in the informal sector. However the sample will include the twoquarter wage growth between quarters (t + 2) and (t + 4) as formal sector wage growth.</p><p>This restriction in the sample is to avoid β k from picking up the wage gains (or losses) associated with switching sectors. Then, the sample used for estimation can include "switchers," but will not include the wage growth of the period when the worker switches sectors. A similar procedure would be applied for threeand four-quarters wage growth and for consecutive formal sector employment. In this way, the parameter of interest, β k , summarizes how wage growth of an individual employed in the informal sector compares with wage growth of an individual employed in the formal sector conditional on x it .</p><p>Tables 2 and 3 present the results from estimation of Equation (1) for the different spans of wage growth.  Notes: All regressions are weighted using the ENOE sampling weights. The samples include male paid-employees with less than 12 years of education and not attending school, ages 16-25 years. Primary School Grad = {E ≥ 6}, Middle School Grad = {E ≥ 9}. The ranking of minimum wages by zone is: w A &gt; w B &gt; w C , where w k is the minimum wage in zone k. The omitted categories for the dummy variables are: minimum wage zone A, Construction industry, and firm size 2-5 employees. All specifications include year dummies, city dummies, and city-size dummies, and a dummy equal to 1 if the measure of hourly earnings was imputed using the minimum wage in the zone. Huber-White robust standard errors clustered at the individual level are in parenthesis. and firm size, whereas <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref> presents estimation results including these firm characteristics. From the perspective of a worker maximizing intertemporal earnings, the wage growth that matters is the wage growth unconditional on firm characteristics, hence the estimation in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref> does not control for them. <ref type="bibr">23</ref> Then for <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref> the vector of covariates includes: education dummies, labor market experience, minimum-wage zone dummies, year dummies, city dummies, and a dummy variable that indicates whether the individual wage used to compute wage growth was imputed (see Appendix A). For <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref>, the vector of covariates includes in addition dummies for the industry in which the worker is 23. An unskilled young worker choosing among jobs would look across industries and firm sizes to find the one that maximizes his expected discounted income. Hence, the wage growth that he would be looking at is the one for which there are no controls. employed, and dummies for the size of the firm where the worker is employed. These indicators refer to the industry and size of the firm in the final period used to compute the wage growth. <ref type="bibr">24</ref> The first column of <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Tables 2 and 3</ref> presents estimation results for one-quarter wage growth. In this case, the dependent variable is Δ 1 w it = [(w it − w it − 1 )/w it − 1 ] × 100, and the indicator for informal-sector participation is IS 1 it as defined above. The positive estimate for the coefficient of IS 1 it in both tables indicates that one-quarter wage growth is faster in the informal sector than in the formal sector.</p><p>Notice the important role played by the industry and firm size controls in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref>. If firms of 24. To compute wage growth Δ k w it two periods are involved, an initial period (t − k) and a final period t. The industry and firm size indicators are those of period t, which is the final period used to compute the wage growth. different sizes, or operating in different industries, are systematically different with respect to productivity, then these differences in productivity may lead to differences in wage growth as well as wage levels. For instance, larger firms invest more in technology than small firms, which may require more worker training, in turn resulting in higher wage growth. Similarly, one could argue that firms in industries with higher opportunities for human capital accumulation for young less-educated workers will experience on average faster wage growth than other industries. <ref type="bibr">25</ref> Recall that formal sector workers are mostly employed in large firms, whereas informal sector workers are mostly employed in small firms (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). Similarly, the fraction of workers employed in the manufacturing and commerce industries is higher among formal sector workers, whereas the fraction of workers employed in the construction and services industries is higher among informal sector workers (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). Then, however, not including firm-size controls would result in a downward-biased estimate of β k because wage growth is faster in larger firms and working in a large firm is negatively correlated with being informal salaried worker. However, not including industry controls would result in an upward-biased estimate of β k because workers in the construction industry experience faster wage growth than those in other industries, and working in the construction industry is positively correlated with being informal salaried worker. The opposite directions of the biases are reflected in the estimates of <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref> that are larger than the estimates in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref> but the differences are not large and the conclusion is the same.</p><p>Note that <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref> indicates higher wage growth in the construction industry than in the manufacturing industry. This suggests that those workers who stayed in the construction industry and those who moved from another industry into construction experienced a higher wage growth than those who stayed in manufacturing or moved into manufacturing. The log-wage regressions in Appendix B indicate that lesseducated workers in the construction industry 25. Even though the sample excludes the wage growth associated with sector switching, the sample can include wage growth associated with employer switching within the same sector. The economic interpretations presented below refer to general human capital and the degree of competitiveness of the labor market. As general human capital is portable and difficulties finding jobs are related with labor market frictions, I decided not to restrict the sample to those workers who would stay with the same employee. have on average higher wages than those in any of the other three industries which helps explain part of these estimation results.</p><p>Finally, notice that neither education nor experience appear to have a significant effect on wage growth. The log-wage regressions presented in Appendix B indicate that these variables are important to determine wages in both the formal and informal sectors. However, it appears that once the market accounts for differences in these individual features in the wage determination, wage growth is not greatly affected by them.</p><p>The second, third, and fourth columns of Tables 2 and 3 present the estimation results for two-, three-, and four-quarter wage growth regressions, respectively. That is, the second column presents the estimation results when the dependent variable is Δ 2 w it = [(w it − w it − 2 )/w it − 2 ] × 100, and the indicator of informal sector participation is IS 2 it as defined above. Similarly for the third and fourth columns. In all three regressions, the conclusion is the same. That is, wages in the informal sector grow at a faster rate than wages in the formal sector.</p><p>Notice that in the analysis presented above, there is no explicit treatment of unobserved heterogeneity or selection, and so the estimates on the indicator of informal sector participation could be biased. However, if unobserved heterogeneity, or "ability," has a similar effect on wage levels in two or three consecutive quarters, then its effect should cancel out when looking at wage growth. <ref type="bibr">26</ref> Also, recall that educational achievement does not have a significant effect on wage growth (as indicated by the estimates in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3)</ref>, and so it appears unlikely that unobserved heterogeneity would have a crucial role, given the strong correlation between education and ability. With respect to worker selection, one can argue that those workers continuously employed in the informal sector are negatively selected, and so, if high-ability workers experience faster wage growth than low-ability workers, the estimate of the coefficient of IS k it would be downward-biased. If this is the case, then we can consider the estimate of β k provided in this study as a lower bound for the true value, and so the conclusion 26. Suppose that log-wages are given by: ln w it = z ′ it δ + μ i + ε it where z it is a vector of individual and firm observed characteristics, μ i represents a worker's unobserved ability, and ε it is a well-behaved error term. Wage-growth is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Δ k w it = [(w it − w it − k )/w it − k ] × 100, where w it = exp { z ′ it δ + μ i + ε it }</formula><p>, and exp{•} is the exponential function. Then, it is easy to see that the worker's unobserved ability, μ i , will cancel out. would be the same, that is informal sector workers experience faster wage growth than formal sector workers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Attrition</head><p>It is important to note that by looking at wage growth, nonrandom sample attrition in the panel may grow for longer spans. Based on the results from <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref>, this could represent a problem if most of the attriters are individuals employed in the informal sector with low wage growth or employed in the formal sector with high wage growth. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Antman and McKenzie (2007)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Duval-Hernández (2007)</ref> highlight the problem of attrition in the ENEU (Encuesta Nacional de Empleo Urbano), which is the predecessor of the ENOE and had the same sampling structure. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Antman and McKenzie (2007)</ref> find that for the period 1987-2001, 10% of the households in the ENEU were observed for only one quarter, and approximately 65% of the households could be followed for all five quarters. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Duval-Hernández (2007)</ref> finds that for the period 1987-2002, 50% of the sample of interest in the ENEU was missing from the panel, most of them due to attrition. Hence, the concern is that the ENOE may also suffer from attrition. <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 4</ref> presents the pattern of attrition in the ENOE during the period of 2005-2012. <ref type="bibr">27</ref> As <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 4</ref> indicates, the problem of attrition appears less serious in the ENOE compared to the ENEU. For example, the attrition rate after the first interview is only 1.13%, and some of these individuals may come back from nonresponse at later interviews. The attrition rate is higher between the third and fourth interviews, but by the fifth interview 84.19% of the individuals who started are still in the sample. Next, <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">Table 5</ref> 27. <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Tables 3 and 4</ref> are motivated by the work of <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Fitzgerald et al. (1998)</ref>. presents the characteristics in the first interview by attrition status. There are some small but clear differences between those who were always in the sample and those who ever came out, almost all of these differences are statistically significant. For example, those who were always in the sample have less hours of work, lower hourly earnings, and are older than those who were ever out. Equally important for this study are the differences in the distribution by industry of occupation and firm size. Overall, the numbers in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 5 suggest that sample attrition could  bias the regression results presented in Table 3</ref>.</p><p>To have a more precise idea about the problem of attrition bias, I performed a variable addition test as suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Verbeek and Nijman (1992)</ref>. The test consists in building a variable that summarizes the pattern of attrition, adding this variable to the regression being estimated and testing for its significance. Following the implementation of this test by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Jones et al. (2013)</ref>, I construct three variables: (1) an indicator of whether the individual is in the next interview, <ref type="bibr">28</ref> (2) an indicator of whether the individual is in the balanced panel, and (3) a variable measuring the number of interviews each individual is in the sample. Intuitively, if attrition is random, then conditional on the covariates, none of these variables should be correlated with the outcome variable, that is, with Δ k w it for k = 1, 2, 3. Note that I cannot perform this test on the four-quarter wage growth regression, Δ k w it for k = 4, because the variable for consecutive informal sector participation IS 4 it equals one if the individual is informal salaried for all five interviews and zero if he is formal salaried for all five interviews. Hence, for all observations with IS 4 it = 1 or IS 4 it = 0 the three additional variables have no variance at all.</p><p>In the process of building each of these three variables, I follow <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wooldridge (2002)</ref> and I assume that attrition is an absorbing state, that is, once the individual is out of the sample he never comes back. The results for this test are presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table 6</ref>. The numbers in the table are the estimated coefficient and standard error for the additional variable the same sample and the specifications as those used in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref>. Each number in the table is taken from a separate regression. Except for one case, the additional variable is significant, which suggests that nonresponse is not random.</p><p>28. Recall that the dependent variable is wage growth. Let t = 1 be the time period for the first interview, t = 2 for the second interview, and so on. If individual i is in all five interviews, we have five wage measures w i1 , … , w i5 , but only four one-quarter wage growth measures Δ 1 w i2 , … , Δ 1 w i5 . Then, the indicator variable for whether individual i is in the next interview is irrelevant for t = 1, takes the value 1 for t = 2, t = 3, and t = 4 and it is irrelevant for t = 5. If individual i is only in the first four interviews, then, the indicator variable is irrelevant for t = 1, takes the value 1 for t = 2 and t = 3, takes the value 0 for t = 4, and is irrelevant for t = 5. An analogous explanation can be applied for the two-and threequarter wage growth. Notes: All regressions are weighted using the ENOE sampling weights. The table presents the estimated coefficient on the additional variable and its standard error in parenthesis. Each estimated coefficient is obtained from a separate regression. The samples and the regressions are comparable to the samples and regressions in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref>.</p><p>To gage the effect of sample attrition in the estimates of <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref>, I re-estimate the wage-growth regressions for one-, two-, and three-quarters wage growth, using an inverse probability weight estimation as suggested by <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wooldridge (2002)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Jones et al. (2013)</ref>. The inverse probability weighting is based on the assumption of selection on observables introduced by <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Fitzgerald et al. (1998)</ref>. The inverse probability weights are computed separately for each of the three wage-growth regressions, the details of the calculation are given in Appendix C.</p><p>The results are presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">Table 7</ref>. From the results in <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table 6</ref>, it was expected that the estimate on the consecutive informal sector participation was going to be lower, but the drop in the estimated coefficient is moderate. Moreover, the estimates for the one-quarter, two-quarters, and three-quarters wage growth regressions are all statistically significant and suggest the same conclusions as the results in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref>, that is, informal sector workers experience faster wage growth. Given these estimates for the one-, two, and threequarter wage growth regressions, it appears plausible that the estimate in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref> for four-quarter wage growth is not severely affected by attrition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Evidence for Older Workers</head><p>The findings on wage growth for the group of young less-educated workers suggest that workers in the informal sector experience, on average, faster wage growth than formal-sector workers conditional on observable individual and Notes: All regressions are weighted using the inverse probability weight. The samples include male paid-employees with less than 12 years of education and not attending school, ages 16-25 years. Primary School Grad = {E ≥ 6}, Middle School Grad = {E ≥ 9}. The ranking of minimum wages by zone is: w A &gt; w B &gt; w C , where w k is the minimum wage in Zone k. The omitted categories for the dummy variables are: minimum wage zone A, Construction industry, and firm size 2-5 employees. All specifications include a time trend, year dummies, city dummies, and city-size dummies, and a dummy equal to 1 if the measure of hourly earnings was imputed using the minimum wage in the zone. Huber-White robust standard errors clustered at the individual level are in parenthesis. job characteristics. At this point, it is natural to ask whether faster wage growth in the informal sector would also hold for older age groups. If older workers employed in the informal sector also experience faster wage growth than similar workers employed in similar jobs in the formal sector, then one can argue that workers would never want to leave their informal sector jobs, and that the formal sector would eventually disappear. On the contrary, the data suggest that for the group of young less educated workers, the number of workers (and the proportion of workers) employed in the formal sector increases with age (see <ref type="figure">Figure 1)</ref>.</p><p>How does wage growth in the informal sector compare with wage growth in the formal sector for older groups? <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">Table 8</ref> presents the estimate of β k for k = 1, 2, 3, 4, the coefficient on consecutive informal sector participation, for different age groups and for different wage-growth spans.</p><p>For ease of comparison, the first column of the table replicates the first row of <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref>, which are the estimates for young workers, those aged 16-25 years. The estimation results indicate that informal sector workers experience significantly faster one-quarter wage growth in all age groups, but the same is not true for two-, three-, and four-quarter wage growth, with a few exceptions. The second youngest group, aged 26-35 years, experiences significantly faster wage growth for one-, two-, and three-quarters. Overall, the results indicate that the faster wage growth of informal sector workers is concentrated in the younger groups both in terms of the magnitude of wage growth and its statistical significance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. ECONOMIC INTERPRETATIONS OF EVIDENCE</head><p>This section argues that the evidence from wage data is consistent with general human Notes: All regressions are weighted using the ENOE sampling weights. The samples include male paid-employees with less than 12 years of education and not attending school. All specifications include all the covariates used in the regressions of <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref>. That is, dummies for education, a variable for labor market experience, dummies for the different minimum wage zones, dummies for industry, dummies for firm size, a time trend, year dummies, city dummies, and city-size dummies, and a dummy equal to 1 if the measure of hourly earnings was imputed using the minimum wage in the zone. Huber-White robust standard errors clustered at the individual level are in parenthesis.</p><p>capital investment on-the-job. <ref type="bibr">29</ref> First, consider the model of general on-the-job training in a competitive labor market provided by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Becker (1993)</ref>. In this model, the wage is determined by the worker's productivity in the current firm but also by the productivity in other firms. A distinctive feature of a competitive labor market is that productivity increases with general training equally in the firm providing it as well as in other firms. Consequently, firms cannot capture any of the returns from the investment in general training because the worker can move freely to another firm once training is finished. As a result, in a competitive labor market, workers capture all the returns from investment in general skills and bear the cost of general training through lower wages. Which implies a substantial wage growth after training is over. <ref type="bibr">Acemoglu and Pischke (1999b)</ref> argue that because of labor market imperfections, worker's productivity in the current firm increases more with training than in other firms. Hence, when workers change jobs, they do not get paid their full marginal product, and as a result productivity increases faster with training than wages. Consequently, firms' profits increase with training, and for this reason firms are willing to sponsor general training. As a result, wage growth after training is over is not as substantial as in the case in which the workers bear all the costs of training. Acemoglu and Pischke also provide mechanisms 29. General training increases a worker's productivity at any firm, contrary to firm-specific training, which increases productivity more in firms providing it. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Becker (1993)</ref>, chapter III. that produce this distorted structure of wages as an equilibrium outcome of the model. Two of these mechanisms are: job-search frictions, and labor market institutions, such as minimum wages and unions. Furthermore, Acemoglu and Pischke show that the higher the distortion on the wage structure due to the labor market frictions, the more the firm will sponsor general training.</p><p>The models of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Becker (1993)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Acemoglu and Pischke (1999b)</ref> can be used together with the institutional differences that exist between the formal and the informal labor markets to interpret the evidence from wage data presented in the previous section. The features of the informal and the formal labor markets suggest that the informal labor market operates like a competitive labor market whereas the formal labor market operates like a frictional labor market. First, the informal labor market is not directly affected by labor market institutions, whereas, by definition, the formal labor market is affected by these institutions. Second, job search frictions are likely to be higher in the formal labor market than in the informal labor market. A market friction is defined as "the costly delay in the process of finding trading partners and determining the terms of trade … " (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Mortensen and</ref><ref type="bibr">Pissarides 1999, 2571)</ref>. The institutional features of the formal labor market, such as unions or hiring and firing costs, generate frictions that delay the process of job matching. Because the informal labor market, by definition, is not subject to these institutional features, job matching in the informal sector, while not perfect, is less complicated than in the formal sector. According to the model of <ref type="bibr">Acemoglu and Pischke (1999b)</ref>, frictions in the labor market allow firms to reap some of the returns from general training which leads firms to pay at least part for the costs of training. And so, if the formal labor market is a frictional labor market, firms in the formal sector will pay at least part of the costs of training, so that wages are not heavily discounted during the training period. However, according to the model of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Becker (1993)</ref>, in a competitive labor market, workers reap the returns from training but also bear the costs of training. And so, if the informal labor market is a competitive labor market, wages are discounted more heavily during the training period. As a consequence, even if both sectors have the same amount of investment on training, wage growth in the informal sector should be faster than wage growth in the formal sector. Which is the result found in the previous section? <ref type="bibr">30</ref> The notion that the informal labor market is competitive while the formal labor market is frictional has been used in previous studies. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Zenou (2008)</ref> develops an equilibrium model of the informal and formal sectors to evaluate various policies to reduce unemployment. In Zenou's model, the formal labor market is characterized by search frictions, whereas the informal labor market is competitive. Equally important is the fact that labor market institutions generate frictions, and that labor market institutions are directly related with the existence and the level of informality in the labor market. In fact, one of the most cited causes of large informal sectors is the existence of rigidities in the labor market due to excessive regulation (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Schneider and Enste 2000)</ref>. This link between labor regulations and the existence of informal sectors has been studied and documented. For example, Rauch (1991) develops a model in which the size of the informal sector is directly related to the degree of labor regulation. <ref type="bibr">31</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Bosch et al. (2007)</ref> find 30. It is natural to ask if 3-12 months (one-to fourquarters) are enough for a worker to accumulate the skills necessary for work. Employers' reports in the surveys for the Employer Opportunity Pilot Projects (EOPP) for year 1982, and the survey funded by the Small Business Administration (SBA) for 1992, suggest that the unconditional mean length of time for a worker "to become fully trained and qualified" is about 21 weeks, and that the median is about 6 weeks (see <ref type="bibr">Barron et al. 1997, Table 3</ref>.4).</p><p>31. Labor regulation by <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Rauch (1991)</ref> is implemented as a minimum wage. <ref type="bibr">Acemoglu and Pischke (1999b)</ref> argue that this is one of the mechanisms that result in the structure of wages in which productivity increases faster with training than wages, and that leads to firm-sponsored general training. that the main driving force behind the increase in informality in Brazil during the 1990s was the reduction of formal sector hirings mainly explained by changes in labor market legislation. More recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Albrecht et al. (2009)</ref> built an equilibrium search and matching model to study the effects of changes of severance and payroll taxes; their simulations suggest that increases in both severance and payroll taxes shift employment from the formal to the informal sector.</p><p>Once agreed that it is possible that human capital accumulation takes place while workers are employed in the informal sector, one could also say that it is possible that informal sector workers invest more in human capital than formal sector workers. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> shows that, on average, wages in the informal sector are lower than in the formal sector. The difference in intercepts in the log-wage regressions presented in Appendix B suggests that there is still a gap after controlling for worker and firm observable characteristics. Finally, <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> suggests that, during the first years of the workers' careers, workers are more likely to move from the informal to the formal sector as they age. If wages and productivity are lower in the informal sector and informal sector workers expect to move to the formal sector eventually, investment in human capital may be greater in the informal sector than in the formal sector. That is, if workers face a lower price for their skills in the informal sector in the present, and expect a higher price for their skills when they move to the formal sector in the future, then the opportunity cost of human capital investment is lower in the informal sector, which will induce informal sector workers to invest more in human capital. Formal sector workers, however, do not face this lower opportunity cost.</p><p>Faster wage growth in the informal sector could also arise in a model of on-the-job training with different levels of specificity of training in the formal and informal sectors. In the study by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Becker (1993)</ref>, when firms provide firm-specific on-the-job training, firms bear the cost of training because if the worker moves to another firm, all productivity gains from training will be lost. If most of the training in the formal sector involves firm-specific human capital, whereas most of the training in the informal sector involves general human capital, wages in the informal sector will exhibit greater growth than wages in the formal sector.</p><p>Finally, recall that <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">Table 8</ref> indicates that faster wage growth in the informal sector is concentrated in the youngest groups, mainly ages 16-25 years, but also ages 26-36 years. This is also consistent with theories of human capital accumulation, because it is mostly young workers who invest in accumulating skills on the job (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ben-Porath 1967;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Rosen 1972)</ref>. If most training takes place during the early stages of workers' careers, and if informal sector workers invest in human capital just as formal sector workers, or perhaps more, then we should only observe faster wage growth in the informal sector during the early stages of the workers' careers. This is what the evidence presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">Table 8</ref> suggests.</p><p>Evidently there are alternative explanations to the result that wages grow faster in the informal than in the formal sector presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref>. Two alternative explanations are wage flexibility and job switching. It is possible that the results in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref> just reflect the fact that wages are more flexible in the informal sector than in the formal sector, particularly since previous studies have found that it is common that nominal wages remain constant from year to year in IMSS-registered firms <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Castellanos et al. 2004)</ref>. However, the results presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">Table 8</ref> indicate that change in wages is not consistent across age groups, which does not support the wage flexibility explanation. That is, if the finding that wage growth is faster in the informal sector due to wage rigidity in IMSS-registered firms, this should be true for older workers too. <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">Table 8</ref> indicates that while this is true for one-quarter wage growth, it is not true for two-, three-, and four-quarter wage growth. Hence, the results in <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">Table 8</ref> discard this possibility.</p><p>Similarly, it is possible that the results in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref> are due to informal sector workers switching jobs more frequently than formal sector workers. That is, if informal sector workers switch jobs very frequently and the wide range of informal sector job opportunities induce them to have higher reservation wages, then we could observe wages growing faster in the informal than in the formal sector. However, the range of hourly wage changes in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> is very large for both informal and formal sector wages, and for both wage increases and wage decreases. This suggests that some workers are not staying with the same employer both in the informal and formal sectors, hence it is not very likely that the results in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref> are driven by more job switching in the informal sector.</p><p>The ENOE allows for a more careful analysis of this competing hypothesis. <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">Table 9</ref> presents the number of individual changes in job-related characteristics for the sample used in the estimation of <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 3</ref>. I consider three job-related characteristics: occupation (job position), industry, and firm size. Changes in these characteristics are considered separately for the four different time spans: one-, two-, three-, and four-quarters. The table also shows, in parenthesis, the proportion of individual changes relative to the total number of observations by sector, presented in the first row. Recall that there can be multiple wage growth observations by individuals, and so there can also be multiple changes by individuals for each of the three categories. The results are mixed: there is a larger proportion of workers switching job position and firm size within the formal sector, but there is a larger proportion of workers switching industry within the informal sector. The last two rows present the number of changes in "at least one" category without double counting switchers and, in parenthesis, the proportion of these changes relative to the total number of observations in each sector. That is, if a worker changes both occupation and industry this is only counted as one change. In this case, the numbers show that the proportion of changes in the formal sector is larger than in the informal sector. Overall the table suggests that workers in these age and education categories employed in the informal sector are not more likely than formal sector workers in the same categories to change jobs.</p><p>A third possible explanation is that formal sector workers in small firms are hired at the minimum wage, which would be above their market clearing wage, and that informal salaried catch up over time. However, this implies that wages in the informal sector grow, because they are catching up, and that the wage growth is due to the accumulation of human capital. That is, if employers behave optimally, they would only increase a worker's wage if there is an increase in that worker's productivity, and worker productivity increases because workers accumulate human capital.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. FINAL REMARKS</head><p>The traditional view of the informal sector assumes that jobs in this sector offer little beyond a make-shift or temporary job for workers that are waiting for a "better" formal sector job. However, this study shows that informal jobs are not dead end jobs, and that these jobs appear to offer wage growth similar to formal sector jobs for young less-educated workers entering the labor market. Notes: FS, formal sector; IS, informal sector. Number of workers who switch job position, industry, or firm size between interviews. The row "Any Change" avoids double counting of switchers for the three categories. The numbers in parenthesis are the proportion of switchers with respect to the total number of observations by sector presented in the first line. The One-Quarter columns correspond to workers who switched between interviews in t and t + 1. The Two-Quarter columns correspond to workers who switched between interviews in t and t + 2. The Three-Quarter columns correspond to workers who switched between interviews in t and t + 3. The Four-Quarter columns correspond to workers who switched between interviews in t and t + 4. The samples include male paid-employees with less than 12 years of education and not attending school, ages 16-25 years.</p><p>The present study provides an analysis of the informal and formal sectors using data from 2005 to 2012 from a longitudinal household survey from Mexico, the ENOE. The analysis suggests that less-educated workers start their careers in the informal sector, and move to the formal sector as they grow older. More important, it is found that for young less-educated workers, wages in the informal sector grow faster than wages in the formal sector, conditional on worker and firm observable characteristics.</p><p>If the labor market in the informal sector is a competitive labor market whereas the formal sector is a frictional labor market, models of on-the-job training in competitive and in noncompetitive labor markets predict that formal sector employers sponsor at least part of the training costs, while informal sector employers pass these costs onto the workers. The evidence from wage growth data presented in this study is consistent with these theories of human capital accumulation, which, in turn, supports the possibility that young less-educated workers accumulate skills while employed in the informal sector.</p><p>Informal-salaried workers may even invest more in human capital than formal-salaried workers. This is because informal-salaried workers have lower wages and expect to eventually move to a formal-salaried job. Another mechanism consistent with the evidence on wage data is based on systematic differences in the specificity of training between the informal and the formal sectors. Even though all these mechanisms lead to the same conclusion in terms of investment in human capital in the informal sector, they may have different implications for the design of labor market policies, and so ideally one could distinguish between them. That exercise would require more than just analyzing wage data.</p><p>If informal jobs do indeed provide training to young less-educated workers, those who start in the informal sector and move to the formal sector later on in their careers, will have a career path different from the career path of less-educated workers who start in the formal sector. These differences could be used to distinguish between the proposed mechanisms discussed above. However, to study these differences, it is necessary to have access to a longer panel than the one used in this study, which only follows individuals during 12 months.</p><p>Equally important, if informal jobs provide training opportunities to young less-educated workers, then it is possible that these workers opt for an informal job instead of queuing longer for a formal job, in order to accumulate skills. Given the arguments provided before, it could also be possible that training costs could help in closing the gap between earnings in the formal and informal sectors, which appear to persist after controlling for observable characteristics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A: THE ENOE</head><p>The ENOE is a rotating panel where households are visited five times during 12 months, one visit every 3 months.</p><p>After the fifth visit, the household is replaced with another household that is also visited five times in the course of a year. The ENOE collects demographic data of each family member as well as job-related data for members who are 12 years of age or older. Job-related data include working hours, earnings, benefits, firm size, job position, and industry of occupation. These data refer to the job held by the individual the week prior to the interview. I used data from the first quarter of 2005 to the fourth quarter of 2012. During this period, it is possible to identify 28 different panels of individuals.</p><p>Hourly earnings are obtained from a variable constructed by the ENOE called "ING_X_HRS" which provides average earnings per working hour. <ref type="bibr">32</ref> To construct this variable, the ENOE records (1) how often the respondent receives his or her income (i.e., daily, weekly, monthly, etc.) and <ref type="formula">2</ref>what is the amount of money received. With these two pieces, the ENOE computes a measure of monthly income. Income reported by the respondent is only net income, that is, income received by the worker after paying taxes, social security fees, or union fees. All this information is with respect to the job held by the individual the week prior to the interview.</p><p>In a separate sequence of questions, the ENOE collects the days of the week prior to the interview in which the worker attended his or her job and the number of hours worked on each day. With this information, a measure of monthly hours is constructed which is then used to obtain the average earnings per working hour provided by the variable "ING_X_HRS." Finally, I used the CPI base second half of December 2010 to deflate nominal hourly wages.</p><p>The ENOE also indicates the minimum-wage zone in which an individual in the survey is located and the corresponding minimum wage in that zone. In Mexico, there are three different minimum-wage zones: zones A, B, and C. Zone A pays the highest minimum wage, and zone C pays the lowest minimum wage. As this information is determined by the geographical location of the individual, it is provided for all individuals in the survey and so it can be used to impute individual earnings when this information is missing in the ENOE variable ING_X_HRS. The ENOE asks the individual if his or her earnings are between: (1) 0 and 1 minimum wage, (2) 1 and 2 minimum wages, (3) 2 and 3 minimum wages, (4) 3 and 5 minimum wages, and (5) more than 5 minimum wages. I used this information to impute earnings of workers who reported having worked but for whom the information on the ENOE variable ING_X_HRS is missing. Let w k be the minimum wage in zone k ∈ {A, B, C}. The following table describes the imputation procedures:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TABLE A1 Imputation Procedures</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Range of Minimum Wage Imputation</head><p>0-1 0.5 × w k 1-2 1.5 × w k 2-3 2.5 × w k 3-5 4 × w k 5 or more 5.5 × w k I also create an indicator variable for the observations for which earnings are imputed and include this variable in the 32. I constructed a similar variable using the information on the questions of the ENOE related to income and working hours and following standard procedures and obtained the same results. Hence, I decided to use the variable already constructed by the ENOE. regression analysis below. In the final sample, only 4.77% of the earnings were imputed. <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 10</ref> presents log-wage regressions for each salaried sector on a set of worker and firm observable characteristics. The estimation results indicate that graduation from primary school is an important factor to explain differences in earnings in the informal sector, but not in the formal sector. The effect of middle school graduation, however, is an important factor to explain differences in earnings in both sectors as well as labor market experience. Note that the indicators for the minimum wage zones are only significant in the formal sector. On average, those workers employed in cities with the highest minimum wage have higher earnings than those employed in cities in the minimum wage zones B and C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX B: LOG-WAGE REGRESSIONS</head><p>In both sectors, the industry of occupation is very important in explaining differences in earnings. In both the formal and informal sectors, workers employed in manufacturing, Notes: Both regressions are weighted using the ENOE sampling weights. The samples include male paid-employees with less than 12 years of education and not attending school, ages 16-25 years. Primary School Grad = 1{E ≥ 6}, Middle School Grad = 1{E ≥ 9}. The ranking of minimum wages by zone is: w A &gt; w B &gt; w C , where w k is the minimum wage in Zone k. The omitted categories for the dummy variables are: minimum wage zone A, Construction industry, and firm size 2-5 employees. Both specifications include a time trend, year dummies, city dummies, city-size dummies, and a dummy equal to 1 if the measure of hourly earnings was imputed using the minimum wage in the zone. Huber-White robust standard errors clustered at the individual level are in parenthesis.</p><p>commerce, or services have on average lower earnings than those employed in the construction industry. Interestingly, the estimates in both sectors are fairly similar and have a similar pattern. Also, those employed in larger firms earn on average higher wages than those in smaller firms. The differences in firm size are more important to explain wages in the informal sector than in the formal sector, as indicated by the statistical significance of the estimated coefficients. Both specifications include a time trend, year dummies, city dummies, city-size dummies, and a dummy equal to one if the measure of hourly earnings was imputed using the minimum wage in the zone, as I explained in the previous section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX C: COMPUTING THE INVERSE PROBABILITY WEIGHTS</head><p>The inverse probability weights (IPW) are calculated following the procedure described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Wooldridge (2002)</ref>. A detailed implementation of this procedure is provided by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Jones et al. (2013)</ref>. See <ref type="bibr">Wooldridge (2002, 587-88)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Jones et al. (2013, 283-87)</ref> for the details. For individual i define an indicator variable s ik as: s ik = 1 { In Sample at Interview k } , k = 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IPW FOR ONE-QUARTER WAGE GROWTH</head><p>For the one-quarter wage growth regression, the first relevant interview is the second interview, that is, k = 2, because at the first interview there is no measure of wage growth. For individual i, define the vector of characteristics z i0 as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">z ′ i0 = ( Δ 1 w ik , x ′ ik ) , k = 2,</formula><p>where x ik is the vector of covariates used in the estimation of the wage growth regressions presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref>. That is, z i0 is the value of wage growth and of the covariates at the first relevant interview, which is the second interview. To compute the IPW for the one-quarter wage growth, I estimate three separate probit models for the indicator variable s ik for k = 3, 4, 5 and from each estimation I obtain the predicted probability of being in the sample at interview k. The inverse of this predicted probability is the IPW for each interview. The following diagram describes the estimation of the IPW:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Probit of s i3 on z i0 ⇒ Obtainp ⇒ IPW i3 = 1∕p i3 Probit of s i4 on z i0 ⇒ Obtainp ⇒ IPW i4 = 1∕p i4 Probit of s i5 on z i0 ⇒ Obtainp ⇒ IPW i5 = 1∕p i5</formula><p>Then, the IPW i3 is used to weight the observations of individual i at the third interview, the IPW i4 is used to weight the observations of individual i at the fourth interview, and the IPW i5 is used to weight the observations of individual i at the fifth interview. Observations for individual i at the second interview have a weight of 1. The same weighting is done for all individuals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IPW FOR TWO-QUARTER WAGE GROWTH</head><p>For the two-quarter wage growth regression, the first relevant interview is the third interview, that is, k = 3, because at the first and second interviews there is no measure of wage growth. Similar to what I did for the one-quarter wage growth, define the vector of characteristics z i0 as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">z ′ i0 = ( Δ 2 w ik , x ′ ik )</formula><p>, k = 3.</p><p>To compute the IPW for the two-quarter wage growth, I estimate two separate probit models for the indicator variable s ik for k = 4, 5 and from each estimation I obtain the predicted probability of being in the sample at interview k as in the diagram presented above. The inverse of this predicted probability is the IPW for each interview. The IPW i4 is used to weight the observations of individual i at the fourth interview, and the IPW i5 is used to weight the observations of individual i at the fifth interview. Observations for individual i at the third interview have a weight of 1. The same weighting is done for all individuals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IPW FOR THREE-QUARTER WAGE GROWTH</head><p>Finally, for the three-quarter wage growth regression the first relevant interview is the fourth interview, that is, k = 4, because at the first, second, and third interviews there is no measure of wage growth. Similar to what I did above, define the vector of characteristics z i0 as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">z ′ i0 = ( Δ 3 w ik , x ′ ik )</formula><p>, k = 4.</p><p>To compute the IPW for the three-quarter wage growth, I estimate one probit model for the indicator variable s ik for k = 5 and from this estimation I obtain the predicted probability of being in the sample at interview k as in the diagram presented above. The inverse of this predicted probability is the IPW for each interview. The IPW i5 is used to weight the observations of individual i at the fifth interview, and the weight at the fourth interview is 1. The same weighting is done for all individuals.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>FIGURE 2 Distribution of Log Hourly Earnings and Wage Growth by Sector</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 1 Sample</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">Descriptive Statistics by Sector: Mean</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">(Standard Error)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Formal Sector</cell><cell>Informal Sector</cell></row><row><cell>Age</cell><cell>21.853</cell><cell>20.887</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.034)</cell><cell>(0.043)</cell></row><row><cell>Years of education</cell><cell>8.708</cell><cell>7.842</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.024)</cell><cell>(0.033)</cell></row><row><cell>Married</cell><cell>0.233</cell><cell>0.135</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.006)</cell><cell>(0.005)</cell></row><row><cell>Hourly earnings</cell><cell>22.593</cell><cell>20.282</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.141)</cell><cell>(0.247)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Minimum wage (proportion)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zone A</cell><cell>0.381</cell><cell>0.429</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.008)</cell><cell>(0.009)</cell></row><row><cell>Zone B</cell><cell>0.232</cell><cell>0.141</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.005)</cell><cell>(0.004)</cell></row><row><cell>Zone C</cell><cell>0.387</cell><cell>0.430</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.006)</cell><cell>(0.007)</cell></row><row><cell>Industry (proportion)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Construction</cell><cell>0.077</cell><cell>0.268</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.004)</cell><cell>(0.007)</cell></row><row><cell>Manufacturing</cell><cell>0.399</cell><cell>0.192</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.006)</cell></row><row><cell>Commerce</cell><cell>0.221</cell><cell>0.175</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.006)</cell><cell>(0.006)</cell></row><row><cell>Services</cell><cell>0.302</cell><cell>0.365</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.008)</cell></row><row><cell>Firm size (proportion)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1−5</cell><cell>0.056</cell><cell>0.662</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.003)</cell><cell>(0.008)</cell></row><row><cell>6−50</cell><cell>0.387</cell><cell>0.296</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.007)</cell></row><row><cell>51+</cell><cell>0.556</cell><cell>0.042</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.007)</cell><cell>(0.003)</cell></row><row><cell>No. of observations</cell><cell>12,664</cell><cell>12,203</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>One-, Two-, Three-, and Four-Quarters Wage Growth Regressions Excluding Firm Characteristics</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>One-Quarter</cell><cell>Two-Quarters</cell><cell>Three-Quarters</cell><cell>Four-Quarters</cell></row><row><cell>IS</cell><cell>5.6786</cell><cell>7.1109</cell><cell>9.3467</cell><cell>7.3511</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.8966)</cell><cell>( 1.4177)</cell><cell>( 1.9904)</cell><cell>( 3.2308)</cell></row><row><cell>Primary School Grad</cell><cell>0.3394</cell><cell>1.5640</cell><cell>3.1785</cell><cell>0.6612</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.7987)</cell><cell>( 3.1738)</cell><cell>( 3.4110)</cell><cell>( 5.3259)</cell></row><row><cell>Middle School Grad</cell><cell>−0.1910</cell><cell>0.5542</cell><cell>3.3316</cell><cell>2.5878</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.9484)</cell><cell>( 3.2717)</cell><cell>( 3.7138)</cell><cell>( 5.4214)</cell></row><row><cell>Experience</cell><cell>−0.1255</cell><cell>−0.3178</cell><cell>−0.4230</cell><cell>−0.2658</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.1572)</cell><cell>( 0.2374)</cell><cell>( 0.2813)</cell><cell>( 0.4294)</cell></row><row><cell>Minimum wage zone</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zone B</cell><cell>5.9182</cell><cell>9.0389</cell><cell>−16.9915</cell><cell>17.1680</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(6.2530)</cell><cell>( 12.5428)</cell><cell>( 12.2333)</cell><cell>( 14.9479)</cell></row><row><cell>Zone C</cell><cell>16.3610</cell><cell>17.9894</cell><cell>−21.0586</cell><cell>31.5773</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(9.2845)</cell><cell>( 17.7632)</cell><cell>( 14.0026)</cell><cell>( 17.2688)</cell></row><row><cell>No. of observations</cell><cell>61,211</cell><cell>35,322</cell><cell>19,074</cell><cell>7,977</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.0254</cell><cell>0.0292</cell><cell>0.0411</cell><cell>0.0827</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>presents estimation results</cell></row><row><cell>excluding firm characteristics, mainly industry</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>TABLE 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>One-, Two-, Three-, and Four-Quarters Wage Growth Regressions Including Firm Characteristics</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>One-Quarter</cell><cell>Two-Quarters</cell><cell>Three-Quarters</cell><cell>Four-Quarters</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(k = 1)</cell><cell>(k = 2)</cell><cell>(k = 3)</cell><cell>(k = 4)</cell></row><row><cell>IS</cell><cell>6.4348</cell><cell>10.1931</cell><cell>10.9430</cell><cell>8.6221</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.3510)</cell><cell>( 2.1342)</cell><cell>( 2.5570)</cell><cell>( 3.9360)</cell></row><row><cell>Primary School Grad</cell><cell>−0.4403</cell><cell>0.6469</cell><cell>0.7347</cell><cell>0.0085</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.9068)</cell><cell>( 3.3122)</cell><cell>( 3.4873)</cell><cell>( 5.5391)</cell></row><row><cell>Middle School Grad</cell><cell>−1.3726</cell><cell>−0.6968</cell><cell>0.6823</cell><cell>2.8297</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(2.0377)</cell><cell>( 3.4458)</cell><cell>( 3.7914)</cell><cell>( 5.7344)</cell></row><row><cell>Experience</cell><cell>−0.1991</cell><cell>−0.3757</cell><cell>−0.4433</cell><cell>−0.4033</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.1624)</cell><cell>( 0.2482)</cell><cell>( 0.2893)</cell><cell>( 0.4393)</cell></row><row><cell>Minimum wage zone</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zone B</cell><cell>7.2470</cell><cell>10.8565</cell><cell>−17.0079</cell><cell>17.1709</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(6.2222)</cell><cell>( 12.5631)</cell><cell>( 11.9502)</cell><cell>( 15.6764)</cell></row><row><cell>Zone C</cell><cell>19.5064</cell><cell>20.9731</cell><cell>−18.4204</cell><cell>26.2562</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(9.5167)</cell><cell>( 19.3186)</cell><cell>( 13.4798)</cell><cell>( 17.6474)</cell></row><row><cell>Industry</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Manufacturing</cell><cell>−4.0296</cell><cell>−3.5441</cell><cell>−2.3396</cell><cell>−15.0508</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.4744)</cell><cell>( 2.3128)</cell><cell>( 2.7794)</cell><cell>( 5.4999)</cell></row><row><cell>Commerce</cell><cell>−1.9194</cell><cell>−3.8126</cell><cell>−3.1344</cell><cell>−14.4347</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.5668)</cell><cell>( 2.3592)</cell><cell>( 2.7493)</cell><cell>( 5.4577)</cell></row><row><cell>Services</cell><cell>1.4914</cell><cell>−0.3148</cell><cell>2.4452</cell><cell>−12.0859</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.4428)</cell><cell>( 2.4641)</cell><cell>( 2.5989)</cell><cell>( 5.5296)</cell></row><row><cell>Firm size</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>6−50</cell><cell>0.4679</cell><cell>4.5489</cell><cell>2.2367</cell><cell>0.0441</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.3709)</cell><cell>( 2.1889)</cell><cell>( 2.5570)</cell><cell>( 3.6977)</cell></row><row><cell>51+</cell><cell>3.8702</cell><cell>6.8607</cell><cell>5.5254</cell><cell>6.1962</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.6909)</cell><cell>( 2.4795)</cell><cell>( 2.8157)</cell><cell>( 4.3931)</cell></row><row><cell>No. of observations</cell><cell>57,480</cell><cell>33,188</cell><cell>17,890</cell><cell>7,476</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.0275</cell><cell>0.0332</cell><cell>0.0442</cell><cell>0.0944</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>TABLE 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Pattern of Sample Attrition in ENOE, 2005-2012 ENOE 2005-2012. Males ages 16-65 years living in urban areas.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Number in</cell><cell>As Percentage of</cell><cell>Number of</cell><cell>Attrition</cell><cell>Number Back</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Sample</cell><cell>Interview 1</cell><cell>Attritors</cell><cell>Rate</cell><cell>from Nonresponse</cell></row><row><cell>Interview 1</cell><cell>343,519</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Interview 2</cell><cell>339,653</cell><cell>98.87</cell><cell>3,866</cell><cell>1.13</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Interview 3</cell><cell>316,925</cell><cell>92.26</cell><cell>26,057</cell><cell>7.67</cell><cell>3,329</cell></row><row><cell>Interview 4</cell><cell>301,391</cell><cell>87.74</cell><cell>19,452</cell><cell>6.14</cell><cell>3,918</cell></row><row><cell>Interview 5</cell><cell>289,213</cell><cell>84.19</cell><cell>15,818</cell><cell>5.25</cell><cell>3,640</cell></row><row><cell>Notes:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>TABLE 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Characteristics in First Interview by Attrition Status Sample statistics using the ENOE sampling weights. ENOE 2005-2012. Males ages 16-65 years living in urban areas. Hourly earnings are in Mexican pesos as in the second half of December of 2010. The ranking of minimum wages by zone is: w A &gt; w B &gt; w C , where w k is the minimum wage in zone k.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Always In</cell><cell>Ever Out</cell></row><row><cell>Working hours per week</cell><cell>48.55</cell><cell>49.30</cell></row><row><cell>Hourly earnings</cell><cell>34.82</cell><cell>35.62</cell></row><row><cell>Age</cell><cell>36.41</cell><cell>32.19</cell></row><row><cell>Married (%)</cell><cell>56.28</cell><cell>44.08</cell></row><row><cell>Informal salaried (%)</cell><cell>31.60</cell><cell>35.00</cell></row><row><cell>Attending school (%)</cell><cell>4.54</cell><cell>5.10</cell></row><row><cell>Education (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>0 years</cell><cell>1.69</cell><cell>1.26</cell></row><row><cell>Elementary: 1-6 years</cell><cell>18.92</cell><cell>17.38</cell></row><row><cell>Middle school: 7-9 years</cell><cell>31.95</cell><cell>32.79</cell></row><row><cell>High school: 10-12 years</cell><cell>24.87</cell><cell>23.97</cell></row><row><cell>College+: 13+</cell><cell>22.45</cell><cell>24.44</cell></row><row><cell>Missing</cell><cell>0.13</cell><cell>0.18</cell></row><row><cell>Minimum wage zone (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zone A</cell><cell>45.37</cell><cell>45.11</cell></row><row><cell>Zone B</cell><cell>15.95</cell><cell>15.64</cell></row><row><cell>Zone C</cell><cell>38.68</cell><cell>39.25</cell></row><row><cell>Industry (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Construction</cell><cell>10.51</cell><cell>12.30</cell></row><row><cell>Manufacturing</cell><cell>24.78</cell><cell>22.12</cell></row><row><cell>Commerce</cell><cell>16.31</cell><cell>17.73</cell></row><row><cell>Services</cell><cell>48.40</cell><cell>47.85</cell></row><row><cell>Firm size (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1−5</cell><cell>2 3 .13</cell><cell>23.90</cell></row><row><cell>6−50</cell><cell>32.83</cell><cell>35.00</cell></row><row><cell>51+</cell><cell>44.04</cell><cell>41.10</cell></row><row><cell>No. of observations</cell><cell>148,713</cell><cell>35,616</cell></row><row><cell>Notes:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>TABLE 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Additional Variable Test for Attrition<ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Verbeek and Nijman 1992)</ref> </figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Wage Growth Span</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>One-</cell><cell>Two-</cell><cell>Three-</cell></row><row><cell>Additional Variable</cell><cell>Quarter</cell><cell>Quarters</cell><cell>Quarters</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(k = 1)</cell><cell>(k = 2)</cell><cell>(k = 3)</cell></row><row><cell>In next interview</cell><cell>−2.3637</cell><cell>−2.0769</cell><cell>−4.2058</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.0227)</cell><cell>(1.7424)</cell><cell>(2.5778)</cell></row><row><cell>In balanced panel</cell><cell>−0.5454</cell><cell>−1.3227</cell><cell>−2.7628</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.2479)</cell><cell>(0.5821)</cell><cell>(1.2918)</cell></row><row><cell>Total number of</cell><cell>−1.5464</cell><cell>−3.4012</cell><cell>−4.0960</cell></row><row><cell>interviews</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.7524)</cell><cell>(1.3114)</cell><cell>(1.9483)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>TABLE 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>One-, Two-, and Three-Quarters Wage Growth Regressions Using the Inverse Probability Weight</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>One-Quarter</cell><cell>Two-Quarters</cell><cell>Three-Quarters</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(k = 1)</cell><cell>(k = 2)</cell><cell>(k = 3)</cell></row><row><cell>IS</cell><cell>5.8731</cell><cell>7.6472</cell><cell>8.0878</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.9183)</cell><cell>(1.3279)</cell><cell>(1.8228)</cell></row><row><cell>Primary School Grad</cell><cell>−0.8325</cell><cell>−0.9636</cell><cell>−5.5755</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.4968)</cell><cell>(2.0654)</cell><cell>(3.0870)</cell></row><row><cell>Middle School Grad</cell><cell>−2.0440</cell><cell>−2.8833</cell><cell>−7.1254</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.5320)</cell><cell>(2.1588)</cell><cell>(3.1965)</cell></row><row><cell>Experience</cell><cell>−0.2927</cell><cell>−0.5863</cell><cell>−0.8307</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.1078)</cell><cell>(0.1514)</cell><cell>(0.2021)</cell></row><row><cell>Minimum wage zone</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zone B</cell><cell>9.8894</cell><cell>28.0627</cell><cell>−23.1000</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(14.6395)</cell><cell>(6.0677)</cell><cell>(10.9884)</cell></row><row><cell>Zone C</cell><cell>12.6085</cell><cell>29.1531</cell><cell>−24.8511</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(16.4483)</cell><cell>(18.0704)</cell><cell>(13.3383)</cell></row><row><cell>Industry</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Manufacturing</cell><cell>−2.2855</cell><cell>−3.1559</cell><cell>−2.1271</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.0331)</cell><cell>(1.4326)</cell><cell>(1.9525)</cell></row><row><cell>Commerce</cell><cell>−0.8760</cell><cell>−2.5495</cell><cell>−2.2613</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.0599)</cell><cell>(1.4873)</cell><cell>(2.0169)</cell></row><row><cell>Services</cell><cell>1.5879</cell><cell>0.0611</cell><cell>1.7940</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.0194)</cell><cell>(1.3904)</cell><cell>(1.9100)</cell></row><row><cell>Firm size</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>6−50</cell><cell>0.6421</cell><cell>4.0280</cell><cell>2.2988</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.9885)</cell><cell>(1.3128)</cell><cell>(1.6873)</cell></row><row><cell>51+</cell><cell>2.3657</cell><cell>5.3698</cell><cell>5.9189</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.1068)</cell><cell>(1.4962)</cell><cell>(1.9945)</cell></row><row><cell>No. of observations</cell><cell>44,390</cell><cell>26,984</cell><cell>15,701</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.0221</cell><cell>0.0195</cell><cell>0.0287</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>TABLE 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>One-, Two-, Three-, and Four-Quarters Wage Growth Regressions for Different Age Groups (Coefficient of Consecutive Informal Sector Participation)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Wage Growth</cell><cell>Age 16-25</cell><cell>Age 26-35</cell><cell>Age 36-45</cell><cell>Age 46-55</cell><cell>Age 56-65</cell></row><row><cell>One-quarter</cell><cell>6.4348</cell><cell>3.6825</cell><cell>5.2406</cell><cell>4.1891</cell><cell>8.5961</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(1.3510)</cell><cell>( 1.1655)</cell><cell>( 1.2763)</cell><cell>( 1.8945)</cell><cell>( 2.6211)</cell></row><row><cell>Two-quarters</cell><cell>10.1931</cell><cell>6.7597</cell><cell>3.1237</cell><cell>6.6653</cell><cell>3.2306</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(2.1342)</cell><cell>( 1.8116)</cell><cell>( 1.7116)</cell><cell>( 2.5365)</cell><cell>( 3.4138)</cell></row><row><cell>Three-quarters</cell><cell>10.9430</cell><cell>6.9986</cell><cell>2.6828</cell><cell>2.2499</cell><cell>0.0209</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(2.5570)</cell><cell>( 2.5206)</cell><cell>( 2.5336)</cell><cell>( 3.7573)</cell><cell>( 4.9094)</cell></row><row><cell>Four-quarters</cell><cell>8.6221</cell><cell>9.0234</cell><cell>4.7516</cell><cell>9.9983</cell><cell>1.9499</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(3.9360)</cell><cell>( 4.7700)</cell><cell>( 3.7452)</cell><cell>( 6.2769)</cell><cell>( 6.1229)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>TABLE 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Workers Switching Job Position, Industry, and Firm Size by Sector</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">One-Quarter</cell><cell cols="2">Two-Quarter</cell><cell cols="2">Three-Quarter</cell><cell cols="2">Four-Quarter</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>FS</cell><cell>IS</cell><cell>FS</cell><cell>IS</cell><cell>FS</cell><cell>IS</cell><cell>FS</cell><cell>IS</cell></row><row><cell>Total observations by sector</cell><cell>35,627</cell><cell>30,223</cell><cell>21,831</cell><cell>16,905</cell><cell>12,318</cell><cell>8,768</cell><cell>5,281</cell><cell>3,520</cell></row><row><cell>Switchers by:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Job position</cell><cell>8,613</cell><cell>5,996</cell><cell>5,645</cell><cell>3,541</cell><cell>3,344</cell><cell>1,859</cell><cell>1,501</cell><cell>756</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.24)</cell><cell>(0.20)</cell><cell>(0.26)</cell><cell>(0.21)</cell><cell>(0.27)</cell><cell>(0.21)</cell><cell>(0.28)</cell><cell>(0.21)</cell></row><row><cell>Industry</cell><cell>4,959</cell><cell>5,511</cell><cell>3,222</cell><cell>3,282</cell><cell>1,896</cell><cell>1,753</cell><cell>813</cell><cell>737</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.14)</cell><cell>(0.18)</cell><cell>(0.15)</cell><cell>(0.19)</cell><cell>(0.15)</cell><cell>(0.20)</cell><cell>(0.15)</cell><cell>(0.21)</cell></row><row><cell>Firm size</cell><cell>25,111</cell><cell>11,864</cell><cell>15,283</cell><cell>6,529</cell><cell>8,626</cell><cell>3,312</cell><cell>3,713</cell><cell>1,372</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.70)</cell><cell>(0.39)</cell><cell>(0.70)</cell><cell>(0.39)</cell><cell>(0.70)</cell><cell>(0.38)</cell><cell>(0.70)</cell><cell>(0.39)</cell></row><row><cell>Any change</cell><cell>27,712</cell><cell>16,116</cell><cell>16,969</cell><cell>9,023</cell><cell>9,587</cell><cell>4,677</cell><cell>4,142</cell><cell>1,917</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.78)</cell><cell>(0.53)</cell><cell>(0.78)</cell><cell>(0.53)</cell><cell>(0.78)</cell><cell>(0.53)</cell><cell>(0.78)</cell><cell>(0.54)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>TABLE 10</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Log-Wage Regressions by Sector</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Formal Sector Informal Sector</cell></row><row><cell>Primary School Grad</cell><cell>0.0451</cell><cell>0.1390</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0254)</cell><cell>( 0.0213)</cell></row><row><cell>Middle School Grad</cell><cell>0.1329</cell><cell>0.2064</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0263)</cell><cell>( 0.0225)</cell></row><row><cell>Experience</cell><cell>0.0189</cell><cell>0.0240</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0014)</cell><cell>( 0.0017)</cell></row><row><cell>Minimum wage zone</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zone B</cell><cell>−0.1349</cell><cell>−0.0763</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.1523)</cell><cell>( 0.1629)</cell></row><row><cell>Zone C</cell><cell>−0.0878</cell><cell>0.0329</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.1673)</cell><cell>( 0.1763)</cell></row><row><cell>Industry</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Manufacturing</cell><cell>−0.2085</cell><cell>−0.1492</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0127)</cell><cell>( 0.0121)</cell></row><row><cell>Commerce</cell><cell>−0.2489</cell><cell>−0.2338</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0133)</cell><cell>( 0.0125)</cell></row><row><cell>Services</cell><cell>−0.1712</cell><cell>−0.1318</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0133)</cell><cell>( 0.0120)</cell></row><row><cell>Firm size</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>6−50</cell><cell>0.0167</cell><cell>0.1104</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0118)</cell><cell>( 0.0105)</cell></row><row><cell>51+</cell><cell>0.0378</cell><cell>0.1218</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.0124)</cell><cell>( 0.0218)</cell></row><row><cell>Const</cell><cell>2.9510</cell><cell>2.5670</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(0.1716)</cell><cell>( 0.1794)</cell></row><row><cell>Number of obs.</cell><cell>49,110</cell><cell>45,403</cell></row><row><cell>R 2</cell><cell>0.1697</cell><cell>0.2063</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beyond Becker: Training in Imperfect Labour Markets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Daron</forename><surname>Acemoglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jorn-Steffen</forename><surname>Pischke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1468-0297.00405</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-DWQGTV97-0</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">628E792653988F5B561C93A63FA17C0A51664DFF</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://econ-www.mit.edu/files/3810/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Economic Journal</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Economic Journal</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0013-0133</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1468-0297</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">453</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="112" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-02" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Structure of Wages and Investment in General Training</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Effects of Labour Market Policies in an Economy with an Informal Sector</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Albrecht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lucas</forename><surname>Navarro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Susan</forename><surname>Vroman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1468-0297.2009.02268.x</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-BQB9CTQJ-3</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">B47BFD5A28FE310313A8BFDD88B5319D857C671F</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://fen.uahurtado.cl/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/inv208.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Economic Journal</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0013-0133</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1468-0297</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">539</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1105" to="1129" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-07" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wage Differentials in Mexico&apos;s Urban Labor Market</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Alcaraz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chiquiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ramos-Francia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economics Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2500" to="2508" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A competitive model of the informal sector</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pedro</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Amaral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Erwan</forename><surname>Quintin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jmoneco.2005.07.016</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Monetary Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Monetary Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-3932</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1541" to="1553" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-10" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Earnings Mobility And Measurement Error : A Pseudo-Panel Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Francisca</forename><surname>Antman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mckenzie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1596/1813-9450-3745</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2005/10/06/000016406_20051006104727/Rendered/PDF/wps3745.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-10" />
			<publisher>The World Bank</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="61" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Economic Development and Cultural Change</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Arias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Earnings</forename><surname>Informality</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Welfare</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Informality: Exit and Exclusion</title>
		<editor>G. E. Perry, W. F. Maloney, O. S. Arias, P. Fajnzylber, A. D. Mason, and J. Saavedra-Chanduvi</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>The World Bank</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="100" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Comparative Advantage, Segmentation and Informal Earnings: A Marginal Treatment Effects Approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Arias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Khamis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<pubPlace>Bonn, Germany</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>The Institute for the Study of Labor</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Discussion Paper No. 3916</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Razón de Ser of the Informal Worker</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Arias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Maloney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Informality: Exit and Exclusion</title>
		<editor>G. E. Perry, W. F. Maloney, O. S. Arias, P. Fajnzylber, A. D. Mason, and J. Saavedra-Chanduvi</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>The World Bank</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="78" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On-the-Job Training</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Barron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Black</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<pubPlace>Kalamazoo, MI</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Upjohn Institute for Employment Research</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Human Capital: A Theoretical and Empirical Analysis, with Special Reference to Education</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Production of Human Capital and the Life Cycle of Earnings</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yoram</forename><surname>Ben-Porath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/259291</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/de15/d20a2bf1061b3bec90159f023989921996df.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Political Economy</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-3808</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1537-534X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4, Part 1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="352" to="365" />
			<date type="published" when="1967-08" />
			<publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Berg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kucera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1468-5922.2008.00713.x</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">18352943</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-P5Z12JL2-X</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">AA89AF50922EAC744AC12DE53BEE50A68CC3ACB0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Analytical Psychology</title>
		<editor>J. Berg and D. Kucera</editor>
		<idno type="ISSN">0021-8774</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-03-18" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Determinants Of Rising Informality In Brazil : Evidence From Gross Worker Flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mariano</forename><surname>Bosch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Edwin</forename><surname>Goni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">William</forename><surname>Maloney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1596/1813-9450-4375</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/bitstream/2027.42/55757/4/IPC-working-paper-043-BoschGoniMaloney.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007-11-09" />
			<publisher>The World Bank</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Working Paper</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust Tests for the Equality of Variances</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Morton</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alan</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Forsythe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/01621459.1974.10482955</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0162-1459</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1537-274X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">346</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="367" />
			<date type="published" when="1974-06" />
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nominal wage rigidities in Mexico: evidence from social security records</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sara</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Castellanos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rodrigo</forename><surname>García-Verdú</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kaplan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jdeveco.2004.06.008</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www.nber.org/papers/w10383.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-3878</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="507" to="533" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-12" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Working Paper No. 10383</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamics of Labor Market Earnings in Urban Mexico</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Duval-Hernández</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Centro de Investigación y Docencia Económicas (CIDE)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>México, DF</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">401</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Análisis por cohortes de la participación laboral en México (1987-2009)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Duval Hernández</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pedro</forename><surname>Orraca Romano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.20430/ete.v78i310.37</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://132.248.10.25/trimestre/index.php/te/article/download/37/39" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">El Trimestre Económico</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">El Trimestre</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0041-3011</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">310</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">343</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011-04-01" />
			<publisher>Fondo de Cultura Economica</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rural-urban migration, urban unemployment and underemployment, and job-search activity in LDCs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gary</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fields</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0304-3878(75)90014-0</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">12265914</idno>
		<idno type="PII">0304-3878(75)90014-0</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-PQ5GL84B-Z</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">8C9CFC8276FB445E8A1288617B877BE7ED9CF408</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-3878</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="187" />
			<date type="published" when="1975-06" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Analysis of Sample Attrition in Panel Data: The Michigan Panel Study of Income Dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Fitzgerald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Gottschalk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Moffitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/146433</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://fmwww.bc.edu/EC-P/wp394.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Human Resources</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Journal of Human Resources</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-166X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">251</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<publisher>JSTOR</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling Informality Formally: Households and Firms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sebastian</forename><surname>Galiani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Federico</forename><surname>Weinschelbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.957329</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://sedici.unlp.edu.ar/bitstream/handle/10915/3606/Documento_completo.pdf?sequence=1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SSRN Electronic Journal</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">SSRN Journal</title>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1556-5068</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="821" to="859" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Doing Business in Mexico: A Practical Guide</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<publisher>Best Business Books</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York; Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Migration, Unemployment and Development: A Two-Sector Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Todaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="168" />
			<date type="published" when="1970" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Good Jobs Wanted: Labor Markets in Latin America</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Inter-American Development</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Bank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Applied Health Economics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Rice</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bago-D'uva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Balia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4324/9780203102411</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-05-07" />
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust Tests for Equality of Variances</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Levene</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Contributions to Probability and Statistics: Essays in Honor of Harold Hotelling</title>
		<editor>I. Olkin, S. G. Ghurye, W. Hoeffding, W. G. Madow, and H. B</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Stanford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1960" />
			<publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="278" to="92" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Can Social Programs Reduce Productivity and Growth? A Hypothesis for Mexico</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Levy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<publisher>Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy</publisher>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Michigan</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Working Paper No. 37, International Policy Center</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does Informality Imply Segmentation in Urban Labor Markets? Evidence from Sectoral Transitions in Mexico</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Maloney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/wber/13.2.275</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-FD2T03NF-Z</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">62A271F3871A415E4C161E9802C036E92C60E820</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/05/16/000333037_20130516124409/Rendered/PDF/772950JRN019990Box0377302B00PUBLIC0.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The World Bank Economic Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The World Bank Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0258-6770</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1564-698X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="302" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-05-01" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chapter 39 New developments in models of search in the labor market</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dale</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mortensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pissarides</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s1573-4463(99)30025-0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Labor Economics</title>
		<editor>O. C. Ashenfelter, and D. Card</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Amsterdam, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2567" to="2627" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Poverty, Deregulation, and Employment in the Informal Sector of Mexico</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ozorio De Almeida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Alves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E M</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ESP Discussion Paper</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">54</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Education and Social Policy Department, World Bank</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modelling the informal sector formally</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rauch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0304-3878(91)90065-4</idno>
		<idno type="PII">0304-3878(91)90065-4</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-5R40QCTQ-K</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">B4302803E214026561CD4843A41FC19E8FA00F90</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-3878</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-01" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning and Experience in the Labor Market</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sherwin</forename><surname>Rosen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/145087</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Human Resources</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Journal of Human Resources</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-166X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">326</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1972" />
			<publisher>JSTOR</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shadow Economies: Size, Causes, and Consequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Friedrich</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dominik</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Enste</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/jel.38.1.77</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/dfc1/476b306e5d0426754509c5343f3a91bf9696.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Literature</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Economic Literature</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-0515</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-03" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A THEORETICAL MODEL OF ON-THE-JOB TRAINING WITH IMPERFECT COMPETITION</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Margaret</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/oxfordjournals.oep.a042147</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-LZ96XRQ9-F</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">788989B67F155518398E18D8E5561D5858AB600F</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oxford Economic Papers</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0030-7653</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1464-3812</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="537" to="562" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-10" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Testing for Selectivity Bias in Panel Data Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marno</forename><surname>Verbeek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Theo</forename><surname>Nijman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2527133</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/1bc8/d14e7f9d6d5fd0a62f002934e0fc6535087e.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Economic Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">International Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0020-6598</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">681</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1992-08" />
			<publisher>JSTOR</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Econometric Analysis of Cross Section and Panel Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wooldridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Job search and mobility in developing countries. Theory and policy implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yves</forename><surname>Zenou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jdeveco.2007.06.009</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Development Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-3878</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="336" to="355" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-06" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
