<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">THE EFFECTS OF YOUNG ADULT-DEPENDENT COVERAGE AND CONTRACEPTION MANDATES ON YOUNG WOMEN</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Wiley</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-03-16">2017-03-16</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><surname>Trudeau</surname></persName>
							<email>trudeauj@sacredheart.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Karen</forename><forename type="middle">Smith</forename><surname>Conway</surname></persName>
							<email>karen.conway@unh.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Eastern Economics Association Meetings</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Connecticut</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Bowdoin College</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Business Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sacred Heart University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>06825., 203</postCode>
									<settlement>Fairfield, Phone</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of New Hampshire</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>03824., 603</postCode>
									<settlement>Durham, Phone</settlement>
									<region>NH</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">THE EFFECTS OF YOUNG ADULT-DEPENDENT COVERAGE AND CONTRACEPTION MANDATES ON YOUNG WOMEN</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Contemporary Economic Policy</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Contemp Econ Policy</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">1074-3529</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="92"/>
							<date type="published" when="2017-03-16" />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/coep.12223</idno>
					<ptr type="open-access" target="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdfdirect/10.1111/coep.12223" />
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T23:12+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>BRFSS</term>
					<term>Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System CDC</term>
					<term>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention CM</term>
					<term>Contraception Mandate CPS</term>
					<term>Current Population Survey DD</term>
					<term>Difference-in-Difference DDD</term>
					<term>Triple Difference EPICC</term>
					<term>Equity in Prescription Insurance and Contraception Coverage Act ERISA</term>
					<term>Employee Retirement Income Security Act ESI</term>
					<term>Employer-Sponsored Insurance FDA</term>
					<term>Food and Drug Administration HRSA</term>
					<term>Health Resources and Services Administration MEPS</term>
					<term>Medical Expenditure Survey NCSL</term>
					<term>National Conference of State Legislatures YAD</term>
					<term>Young Adult-Dependent Coverage</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>This research investigates two features of the Affordable Care Act that especially affect young adults, the young adult-dependent coverage (YAD) mandate and the requirement to cover contraception (CM). Both mandates were first enacted at the state level but have been studied only in isolation. We estimate a wide range of models allowing these mandates to have joint effects on insurance coverage, health-care access, health outcomes and fertility. We provide new evidence that helps settle the mixed findings from past state-level YAD and CM research and suggests the two mandates may combine to improve the well-being of young adults. (JEL I18, I12, H75) * We would like to thank Elizabeth Nash from the Guttmacher Institute for providing information on state contraception policies, Joel Cantor for research on dependent coverage mandates, and Philip Levine for CPS data on health insurance. This paper has also benefited from the comments of</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>Young adults are typically low-risk/low-cost users of health insurance who are also among the most likely to be uninsured. The Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act of 2010 (ACA) targeted this group and contains two key mandates of particular benefit to young adults: (1) extending the provision of young adult-dependent coverage (YAD) on family insurance plans to age 26 and (2) requiring all Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved contraceptive methods to be available to women with no cost sharing <ref type="bibr">(HRSA 2015)</ref>. Both of these provisions were enacted at the state level prior to the national reform, thus providing a natural setting for researchers to test their effects (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Depew 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Levine, McKnight, and Heep 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Monheit et al. 2011</ref> for YAD; Mulligan 2015; Raissian and Lopoo 2015 for contraception mandates <ref type="bibr">[CMs]</ref>). However, the key findings from this research are decidedly mixed. Moreover, no research has taken a comprehensive approach to studying these two mandates in tandem.</p><p>Our research seeks to close this gap by studying the effects of both mandates on health insurance coverage, access to care, general health outcomes, and reproductive outcomes using a variety of datasets and empirical approaches. We make three contributions. First, ours is the first study to investigate the effects of both mandates. Our approach not only avoids the possible bias caused by ignoring a related health insurance policy but allows for the mandates to reinforce (or diminish) each other's effects. Such an interaction between the mandates appears plausible for young women. Given their typically low risk of serious health problems yet higher fertility, the costs because of pregnancy likely loom large.</p><p>Moreover, the cost of prescription contraception is relatively expensive, especially for young adults whose incomes tend to be lower than other groups. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Trussell et al. (2013)</ref> estimates the average annual cost of short-acting prescription contraception to be $390.53 for injections, $654.30 for the birth control pill, and $1,023.86 for the birth control patch. <ref type="bibr">1</ref> The reported spike in requests and Google searches for intrauterine devices immediately after the 2016 election is strong, although admittedly anecdotal, evidence of the importance women place on having the cost of their contraception covered <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Ross 2016)</ref>.</p><p>Health insurance policies that include contraception coverage are likely valued more highly by young women than policies that do not, which in turn may lead to greater take-up and strengthens the effects of a YAD mandate. Similarly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Raissian and Lopoo (2015)</ref> note that CMs only help those women who have insurance; thus, a CM may have stronger effects in states where young women have better access to health insurance, such as provided by a YAD mandate. Even if these mandates do not combine to increase health insurance coverage, they could still combine to affect the care women receive and their health outcomes. For example, a woman covered by a YAD may not bother going to the doctor for routine care if she is using nonprescription contraception (e.g., condoms, spermicide); the addition of a CM may encourage her to seek prescription contraception and lead her to get such routine care, care which could potentially diagnose, treat, or prevent other health conditions (like depression).</p><p>There are other, more indirect mechanisms too. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Depew (2015)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Colman and Dave (2015)</ref> find that YADs reduce labor supply; the latter also find a decrease in time spent waiting for or receiving health care and an increase in "socializing." Such second-order effects could lead YADs to affect both care received and health outcomes (indeed, Colman and Dave 2015, find an increase in subjective well-being) as well as influence reproductive behavior and the desire for contraception. These scenarios suggest that the effects of these mandates can operate through 1. These estimates contain an initial physician visit cost of $41.45 taken from the 2011 Medicare fee schedule; however, other evidence from the Medical Expenditure Survey (MEPS) by <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Davis and Carper (2012)</ref> suggests that the average expense for a visit to a primary physician is closer to $145, or for an OB-GYN $235. For context, note that the average earnings for 18-24-year-old women in 2009 was $24,117 according to the U.S. Census <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Bureau (2012)</ref>. multiple avenues and may be influenced by whether the other mandate exists, an interaction effect we model explicitly.</p><p>A second contribution is the comprehensive set of outcomes we investigate in studying these two mandates. This approach allows us to both fill in the gaps left by existing research and bring new evidence to key outcomes for which past findings are mixed. Research on state-level YAD mandates (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Levine, McKnight, and Heep 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Monheit et al. 2011</ref>) focuses on insurance coverage. <ref type="bibr">2</ref> In contrast, research on CMs primarily focuses on sexual activity and contraception use <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Atkins and Bradford 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Magnusson et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Raissian and Lopoo 2015)</ref> and birth and abortion rates <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Dills and Cotet-Grecu 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mulligan 2015)</ref>. Possible effects on insurance coverage or on more general health-care utilization and health outcomes that may arise out of the complementary consumption of health services have been mostly ignored. <ref type="bibr">3</ref> Our study investigates the effects of both mandates, first in isolation and then allowing for joint effects, for health insurance coverage; health-care access; general health outcomes; and pregnancies, births, and abortions. Drawing from several data sources also allows us to explore multiple independent measures of insurance coverage, general health, and reproductive outcomes, bringing new evidence and a different kind of robustness check to past work.</p><p>Finally, our study provides data and methodological updates to existing research on statelevel mandates. Six states adopted YADs in 2009 alone, yet the two key studies observing their effect on coverage end in 2008 <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Levine, McKnight, and Heep 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Monheit et al. 2011)</ref>. Some recent YAD research emphasizes including narrower, more targeted age groups (e.g., Slusky 2015), while <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Depew (2015)</ref> advocates for a wider age range such that eligibility can be based on age rather than marital or student status, which may be endogenous. Recent work also explores sensitivity to including location-specific time trends and emphasizes the need to test for pretrends and conduct placebo tests (e.g., Depew 2015; Dills and Cotet-Grecu 2016; Mulligan 2015; Slusky 2. Studies that investigate the broader effects of YAD reform on coverage, health-care utilization, and general health outcomes all consider only the ACA's mandate <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Antwi, Moriya, and Simon 2015a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Antwi et al. 2015b</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Barbaresco, Courtemanche, and Qi 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chua and Sommers 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Sommers et al. 2013)</ref>.</p><p>3. An exception is <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Raissian and Lopoo (2015)</ref>, which investigates the effect of state-level CMs on private insurance and preventive care services. To our knowledge, no published study has investigated the causal effects of the ACA CM. 2015). We estimate every outcome with several difference-in-difference (DD) and triple difference (DDD) models and subject each one to sensitivity and robustness checks. These exercises lend support to the emerging view that YADs did not significantly increase insurance coverage and, instead, led to a switch in the source of coverage. Our analyses also bring new evidence to the mixed findings regarding CMs' effects on fertility by finding that they reduce reported pregnancies. Finally, our joint models yield suggestive evidence that the two mandates combine to improve the general well-being of young adults, although the precise mechanism for the effect is not clear.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. BACKGROUND</head><p>In 1994, Utah adopted a provision for extended parental coverage of young adult dependents, allowing unmarried children under the age of 26 to enroll under their parents' insurance plan. 4 By 2009, more than 30 states had implemented their own variations of the YAD mandates, limiting dependency by age, student status, marital status, and whether or not the young adult has their own dependents. The 2010 ACA extended parental coverage of health insurance to all young adults, without exceptions, under the age of 26 as of September 23, 2010.</p><p>During the same time period, federal and state legislation began to challenge the equity of insurance coverage that does not provide free access to contraception. The issue first received national attention in the form of the Equity in Prescription Insurance and Contraception Coverage Act (EPICC) in 1997, yet Congress failed to enact the bill. States, however, seized the opportunity to establish their own initiatives, starting with Maryland in 1998, extending contraception coverage to women with insurance plans that covered other prescription drug benefits. By 2009, more than 25 states had enacted similar CMs. The ACA extended outpatient contraceptive services and prescription drug benefits to all insured women starting August 1, 2012 at zero cost sharing (HRSA 2015).</p><p>One complication in studying the effects of state-level mandates is that not all firms are subject to the mandates' reforms. In 1974, the Employee Retirement Income Security Act (ERISA) set the minimum standards for firms extending employer-sponsored insurance (ESI) benefits to their employees and exempted self-insured firms from state-level insurance mandates. In 2009, 59% of ESI plans were issued by self-insured firms <ref type="bibr">(Henry J. Kaiser Family Foundations and Health Research and Educational Trust [HRET]</ref> 2010), such that they are not covered by the mandates. 5 A second complication is that the increased cost of the newly mandated benefits may decrease ESI offers. Unfortunately, data sources that have measures of care utilization and health outcomes, including those we employ here, do not have information on ESI offers or ERISA status.</p><p>Research on these mandates, both at the state level and via the ACA, has exploded in recent years, and an expanded discussion of this research is available upon request. For the sake of brevity, <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> summarizes the research on each state-level mandate (two columns) across the three effects of interest (three rows)-coverage, care utilization, and health outcomes. <ref type="bibr">6</ref> We briefly summarize the key insights and note that our study requires an additional column as it considers the effects of both mandates on all three types of outcomes for the first time.</p><p>Research into state-level YAD mandates (left column of <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>) focuses on the effects on insurance coverage (top panel); care utilization (middle panel) and health outcomes (bottom panel) are much less explored. Most studies examine the effect of state-level YAD mandates across all or most states, although a few focus only on the Massachusetts Health Reform in 2006. Each employs quasiexperimental, DD, or DDD frameworks, using young adults not eligible for the mandates and/or living in states without mandates as control groups. The majority of studies of coverage use the Current Population Survey (CPS), which allows the identification of the source of coverage (own, dependent) and, for young adults living with their parents, whether the policy holders work for small employers who 5. Nonetheless, evidence provided by <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Sonfield et al. (2004)</ref> suggests that CMs led to an increase of insurance plans including contraception coverage. 6. We provide a similar summary table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">(Table S1</ref>) for ACA mandate research. However, it only has one column (for YAD) because, to our knowledge, no research yet exists with respect to the contraception mandate with the exception <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Finer, Sonfield, and Jones (2014)</ref>, a descriptive study that reports that the percentage of privately insured women paying zero out-of-pocket expenses for contraception increased after the ACA.  <ref type="bibr">2002-2004 vs. 2008-2009)</ref> Descriptive 1 st <ref type="bibr">Study,</ref><ref type="bibr">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr">3</ref>    <ref type="bibr">2002-2004 vs. 2008-2009)</ref> Descriptive 1 st <ref type="bibr">Study,</ref><ref type="bibr">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr">3</ref>   <ref type="bibr">(NSFG 1995</ref><ref type="bibr">(NSFG , 2002</ref><ref type="bibr">(NSFG , 2006</ref><ref type="bibr">(NSFG -2010</ref> DD, 15-44 privately insured only, includes indicator for mandates that cover services and supplies or suppliers: no effect on contraception use, 8% increase in pill use by women with low education, driven by supply mandates. are therefore more likely affected by state-level reforms (because of ERISA). There remains some debate about whether the overall uninsured rate decreases <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Levine, McKnight, and Heep 2011)</ref> or is unaffected because of reverse crowdout from own to parent coverage <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Monheit et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Depew 2015</ref>, who also finds a decrease in young adult labor supply). These differences stem from differences in definition of controls <ref type="bibr">(19-24 vs. 19-29)</ref> and identification of eligibility. Using CPS data and DD as well as the alternative DDD strategies of <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011)</ref> versus Depew (2015), we attempt to replicate past results, compare approaches, and explore the role that CMs may play. We also estimate these models using a health insurance measure from a different data source, the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System (BRFSS).</p><p>Because the CPS has no information on care utilization and is limited to one measure of self-reported health status, research that investigates health care or outcomes typically uses the BRFSS. To our knowledge, only one study <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Blum et al. 2012)</ref> considers the effect of state-level YADs on care utilization, and no study examines outcomes. 7 <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> makes it clear that several gaps exist in studying the effects of CMs as well. These studies focus on contraceptive use (care utilization) and fertility and birth outcomes (reproductive health outcomes), with most finding a positive effect on contraceptive use. This research typically takes a DD approach and considers broader age groups than YAD research as all women of childbearing age may be potentially affected by CMs. Only <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Raissian and Lopoo (2015)</ref> consider more general types of health care, finding an increase in pap smears for states that mandate contraceptive services and supplies. We consider a still broader set of care utilization variables that have not yet been investigated in CM research. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Raissian and Lopoo (2015)</ref> also make the point that CMs may not have much impact because they only affect women with health insurance-which is precisely why we believe it is critical to investigate the joint effects of contraceptive and YAD mandates. To our knowledge, only two economic studies address the direct effect of CMs on health outcomes, and both investigate only reproductive outcomes with contradicting findings. Mulligan (2015) uses state-level Vital Statistics data on fertility outcomes (births and abortions) and individual-level CPS Fertility Supplement data and finds a decline in both births and abortions, although the former is sensitive to including state-specific time trends. Dills and Cotet-Grecu (2016) conduct a similar analysis using the restricted-use Vital Statistics data but incorporate a more extensive set of individual-and state-level characteristics and policies. They find no robust effects on overall births with the exception of one subgroup, Hispanic teens (&lt;19), who experience a decline in births.</p><p>Taken together, the research summarized in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> reveals that CMs appear to increase contraceptive use but that evidence for the rest of the outcomes is lacking and/or mixed. Moreover, no study has considered the effects of both mandates together. Our analysis fills this gap and, as such, informs ACA research by providing the first evidence of how these two mandates combine to affect outcomes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. EMPIRICAL STRATEGY</head><p>We apply a quasiexperimental framework that takes advantage of variation in each mandate within states over time to two individual-level datasets (the CPS and the BRFSS) as well as state-level Vital Statistics data on births and abortions (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 2</ref> and Section IV for details). We begin with a DD framework because all women are potentially affected by a state's CM, so its variation is limited to the state level. We estimate a DD model for each mandate separately and for one that allows for a joint effect. However, because most YAD studies exploit the fact that not all young adults are eligible and so employ a DDD approach, we also estimate two alternative DDD models that rely on different identification strategies. This comparison allows us to see if (1) our DD findings stand up to a DDD approach and (2) if controlling for CMs and addressing more recent methodological concerns affect existing YAD-DDD findings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. DD Models</head><p>Because CMs potentially apply to all women of childbearing age, past CM research has relied on variation over time and across states only, (1)</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">+ πZ st + β CM CM st + ε iast ,</formula><p>where the state (θ s ) and year (θ t ) fixed effects capture the "treatment" and "after" effects included in the most basic DD model. CM is a dummy variable equal to one if the state has a CM in that year (and thus equals the standard "treatment*after" variable of interest). θ a , X, and Z are age fixed effects, other individual characteristics, and state characteristics, respectively. The effects of a YAD mandate can be estimated in a similar way:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">YAD Model ∶ Y iast = α + θ s + θ t + θ a + γX iast (2) + πZ st + β YA YAD st + ε iast ,</formula><p>where all variables are as defined above, and YAD is a dummy variable equal to one if the state has a YAD mandate in that year. We combine these two models to allow for both effects, thus eliminating the potential omitted variable bias from focusing only on one mandate, and we also include an interaction term to capture any joint effects the mandates may have 8 :</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Full Model ∶ Y iast = α + θ s + θ t + θ a + γX iast (3) + πZ st + β CM CM st + β YA YAD st + β CM * YA ( YAD st * CM st ) + ε iast .</formula><p>8. We also specify a simpler model that drops the interaction term and so focuses only on the possible omitted variable bias created by considering each mandate in isolation; that is, we see how the estimates of β CM and β YA are affected by controlling for the other mandate. As a practical matter, however, the conclusions are similar to those drawn by comparing models 1-3, and so, we do not report them.</p><p>The CM and YAD models commonly estimated often include different controls (i.e., X and Z); as described in Section IV and <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 2</ref>, we include a broad set of controls that are representative of both. Likewise, CM models are typically estimated on a wider set of ages, whereas YAD models are limited to young adults. To be comparable across models and have a homogeneous sample, we limit all DD analyses to women aged 19-24, the age group to which most YADs apply.</p><p>A concern with DD models is that the trends in treatment and control groups/states may be different in the periods preceding the law. In our case, with two potentially interacting laws occurring over a short time frame (13 years), the typical approaches (plotting trends before and after the law, estimating the pre-and post-effects of the law) greatly strain the data. 9 To our knowledge, no one has attempted these approaches in such a setting. Furthermore, these approaches become even more untenable-and less necessary-in the DDD models we consider next. <ref type="bibr">10</ref> We instead address this concern in two ways, both of which can be applied to all models we estimate (single mandate and the full models, DD and DDD models alike). First, we subject all models to a placebo test in which each mandate variable is replaced with a dummy of whether the mandate was in place 3 years in the future. This test is a more parsimonious way of seeing if the different "treatment" states behaved differently even before the mandate(s) was passed. It is also straightforward to apply to our more complicated DDD models. We are further reassured that, for our simpler onemandate DD models, estimating a dynamic specification with a full set of leads and lags of the policy typically yields similar conclusions to our 3-year lead placebo. 11 Second, we estimate all DD models both with and without state-specific 9. To illustrate, consider an event time plot where there are now five potential types of treatment states: (1) those that only adopt a YAD, (2) those that only adopt a CM, (3) those that first adopt a YAD then a CM, (4) those that adopt a CM and then a YAD, and (5) those that adopt both at the same time. Not only does that split the data into six groups (five treatment + one control), but there are also two events ("time zero") to consider. Similarly, a dynamic regression, such as that estimated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bellou and Bhatt (2013)</ref>, would include thrice the number of lead and lag coefficients (one set for each mandate plus their interaction).</p><p>10. As <ref type="bibr">Depew (2015, 127)</ref> notes, the assumptions required for identification in DDDs are considerably weaker.</p><p>11. Testing the joint statistical significance of the leads of the policy in these models yields a different conclusion from our placebo (3-year lead instead of current) less than 25% of the time. More importantly, these differences never occur in models that yield a key finding. time trends and estimate DDD models that do and do not include state-specific time effects.</p><p>Because many young adults in YAD states are not eligible for the mandate by virtue of their age, marital status, or student status, most YAD studies take a DDD approach, where eligible and ineligible young adults in both states are further compared. To be comparable to this past research, we adapt the above models to two alternative DDD approaches, described next. 12</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. DDD Models</head><p>To estimate a YAD-DDD model, we must identify a group of young adults who are not eligible for the YAD enacted in their state. Past YAD work differs on using age and/or marital/student status to identify eligibility, and both approaches have drawbacks. If one relies on age only, then to obtain a reasonable number of ineligible individuals, the age range of the sample must be sizable; typically, ages 19-29 are included <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Depew 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Monheit et al. 2011)</ref>. This approach pools together young adults at potentially very different points in their lives and has been subject to strong criticism in studies of the ACA (which must rely on age; e.g., Slusky 2015). Put simply, adults aged 25-29 (who are ineligible in most YAD states) may not be an appropriate control group for those aged 19-24. If the analysis is instead limited to that narrower, more homogeneous age group, as <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011)</ref> does, then other, arguably endogenous, eligibility criteria such as marital and student status must be used. Depew (2015) makes this point and provides evidence of possible endogeneity.</p><p>We therefore estimate two different DDD models, one that is limited to 19-24 year olds and uses marital and student status (as well as age) to identify eligibility and another that includes 19-29 year olds and uses only age to identify eligibility. The first follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011)</ref>, and the second follows Depew (2015). <ref type="bibr">13</ref> These two studies also differ in controlling for location-specific time 12. We also try modifying our DD models by replacing the YAD dummy variable with a measure of the intensity of the law. Specifically, we re-estimate Equations (2) and (3) using the percentage of young adults aged 19-24 in a national CPS sample who would be eligible for the state's mandate (on the basis of age, marital status, and student status). The estimates are quite similar to those from the above equations and are available upon request.</p><p>13. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Monheit et al. (2011)</ref> is a hybrid of the two approaches, including 19-29-year-olds in many analyses but also using student and marital status as criteria as well.</p><p>effects. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011)</ref> take a more restrictive approach and do not include state-specific time trends or effects, whereas <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Depew (2015)</ref> includes the full set of state*year fixed effects (as well as age*year and age*state fixed effects). As such, we view these two approaches as ideal bookends to the range of possible DDD approaches one could take, and we try to follow each one as closely as possible.</p><p>Our "Levine" model continues with the 19-24-year-old samples from the DD approach and defines Eligible as <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011)</ref> do: as a dummy variable equal to one if the individual, i, would be eligible for the YAD enacted (at some point in the sample) in their state, s, on the basis of age a, and marital/student status, m, e; for those living in a state without a YAD, it is equal to one if they are unmarried. Eligible is then interacted with every variable included in the model,</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">YAD-DDD Model ∶ Y iamest = α + θ s + θ t + θ a + γX iamest + πZ st + β YA YAD st + α ′ Eligible iames (2a) + θ ′ s Eligible iames + θ ′ t Eligible iames + θ ′ a Eligible iames + γ ′ X iamest Eligible iames + π ′ Z st Eligible iames + β ′</formula><p>YA YAD st Eligible iames + ε iamest , and the DDD "treatment" effect is the coefficient on Eligible*YAD, or β ′ YA . This approach is akin to splitting the sample into eligible ("treated") and ineligible ("control") observations and estimating the difference in the effects of the YAD mandate being implemented. Modifying this model to include CM's effects as well yields</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Full-DDD Model ∶ Y iamest = α + θ s + θ t + θ a + γX iamest + πZ st + β CM CM st + β YA YAD st (3a) + β CM * YA ( YAD st * CM st ) + α ′ Eligible iames + θ ′ s Eligible iames + θ ′ t Eligible iames + θ ′ a Eligible iames + γ ′ X iamest Eligible iames + π ′ Z st Eligible iames + β ′ CM CM st Eligible iames + β ′ YA YAD st Eligible iames + β ′ CM * YA ( YAD st * CM st ) Eligible iames + ε iamest .</formula><p>The baseline effect of a CM is β CM as before, and the special effect of having both mandates when one is YAD-eligible is now β ′ CM * YA . Depew (2015) uses only age to determine eligibility and expands the ages considered to 29. Depew (2015) also includes the full set of state-by-year, state-by-age, and year-by-age fixed effects. This full set of fixed effects allows the treatment and control groups to differ with respect to other factors in a very flexible way. It also includes location-specific time effects in an even less restrictive manner than statespecific time trends. We adapt this specification to our three models (Equations (1)-(3)) by first expanding our sample to ages 19-29; note that this means that our "CM-only" model results are different for the "Depew" model because of the wider age group and richer set of fixed effects included. In contrast, the "Levine" CMonly model is identical to the DD model without state-specific time trends. Second, eligibility is now equal to one if the individual is below the cut-off age for the YAD in the individual's state. Equations (1b)-(3b) (next page) reflect this distinction, with eligibility indexed by a and s, age and state, respectively, only. Finally, this model requires adding the full set of age*state, age*year, and state*year fixed effects. However, the effect of a CM will be completely subsumed in the stateby-year fixed effects. We therefore adapt our "Depew" model to include state-specific time trends instead. To explore the impact of this restriction, we also try including state-specific quadratic time trends, and we re-estimate the YAD-only model including the full set of state*year fixed effects. The results are reasonably similar, lending support to our approach.</p><p>Using our adapted "Depew" approach, the three models we estimate are then: Our analyses use data from several datasets combined with information on state-level insurance mandates and other characteristics. We first examine the variation in state-level insurance mandates and then discuss the different datasets we use: the CPS (coverage and health status), the BRFSS (coverage, care, and health and reproductive outcomes), and the Vital Statistics (reproductive outcomes). We conclude by discussing the individual-and state-level controls we include, as well as robustness checks and placebo tests.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table S2</ref> and reveals several discrepancies across the different sources. For CMs, the differences are fairly minor 14 ; for YADs, however, they are much more widespread, and no two studies use the exact same list, a point also noted in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Burgdorf (2014)</ref>. The differences appear to be because of the use of implementation versus effective dates, states with multiple changes to extended coverage eligibility criteria, and the censoring of most samples in 2008. We arrive at our final list by cross-referencing the discrepancies with state legislation recorded in WestLaw. As is the convention, we omit Massachusetts from our analyses because of its personal mandate. <ref type="figure">Figure S1</ref>, Supporting Information, summarizes the adoption of these mandates over time, as well as the state-specific requirements for YAD eligibility, and <ref type="figure">Figure S2</ref> shows the geographic variation over time. While both reveal the accelerating adoption of both mandates during this short time period, they also suggest substantial independent variation in each one. We explore their correlation formally by estimating stateyear panel models in which the presence/absence of each mandate is regressed on the other as well as state and year fixed effects. This exercise reveals a statistically significant positive relationship between the two, which suggests that considering each mandate in isolation could lead to bias. <ref type="bibr">15</ref> At the same time, there appears to be sufficient independent variation to identify the separate and joint effects of each mandate. 16</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">CM Model ∶ Y iast = α + θ s + θ t + θ a + θ</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. State Mandates</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. CPS-Health Insurance Coverage and General Health</head><p>The March Supplement of the CPS, also known as the Annual Social and Economic Supplement (ASEC), provides measures of health insurance status and source of coverage: private, 14. Dills and Cotet-Grecu (2016) differ by excluding states in which legislation is enacted by Attorney General opinion in Michigan and Montana; the differences with Mulligan (2015, Table 1) are almost all 1 year or less. When different, Mulligan (2015) tends to use the year prior to implementation. However, these differences may be compounded by combining these earlier dates with the year of birth rather than year of conception, as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Dills and Cotet-Grecu (2016)</ref> and in our analyses.</p><p>15. A Chi-squared test of independence on whether each state eventually adopts each mandate similarly rejects the null hypothesis of independence.</p><p>16. The R-squares of 0.608 and 0.703 obtained from the state-year panel models suggest that 29-39% of the variation remains even after controlling for the other mandate and for state and year fixed effects. public, group, and nongroup. As noted above, it is the main data source for past YAD studies of insurance coverage. While the CPS contains no information on health-care access, it does have a general self-reported health measure as well as other individual characteristics, including age, marital, and student status. We employ <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011)</ref>'s dataset and code submitted for publication in the AEJ: Economic Policy 17 to replicate and expand their analyses by (1) including state CMs; (2) using the revised list of YAD mandates; and (3) adding data for 1997-1999 and post-2008, 18 more ages (25-29), and the self-reported health measure. The year 2009, in particular, could be influential both because six states adopted YAD mandates in that year and because of the potentially widereaching effects of the Great Recession. As discussed shortly, one robustness check is to drop 2009 from our analyses. The CPS sample spanning 1997-2009 is comprised of 85,929 females aged 19-24 and 75,674 females aged 25-29. <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 2</ref> provides the summary statistics for each of our outcome variables across all three data sources; it also lists the control variables included. 19</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. BRFSS-Insurance Coverage, Care Access, Health Outcomes, and Pregnancy</head><p>The BRFSS is an annual telephone survey on personal health behaviors administered by the states that includes measures of all four outcomes of interest here-if the individual has health insurance; their access to health care; their selfreported general, physical, and mental health; and their reproductive outcomes (if they are currently pregnant). 20 As such, it allows us to explore, with one data source, the full range of outcomes shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>. It also allows us to bring 17. The dataset "maindata.dta" is available at http://www .aeaweb.org/articles.php?doi=10.1257/pol.3.1.129.</p><p>18. The CPS questions often refer to the previous calendar year; therefore, while <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011</ref><ref type="bibr">) use 2001</ref><ref type="bibr">-2009</ref> CPS data, their analyses actually refer to the years 2000-2008. However, the self-reported health measure refers to the current year (year of the survey), and so, we adjust the data accordingly for those analyses.</p><p>19. All summary statistics and regression analyses include sample weights. 20. Concern over the response rates of a landline survey, especially for young adults, led the BRFSS to include a cell phone survey in 2008 and modify its weighting procedures. Testing for raking began in 2007 and replaced poststratification entirely in 2011. These issues likely do not play a substantial role in our analyses as they end in 2009 <ref type="bibr">(and in robustness checks, 2008)</ref>.</p><p>new evidence for the two most heavily studied outcomes-health insurance coverage for YADs and reproductive outcomes for CMs. These two outcomes, as well as a self-reported general health status (similar to the one in the CPS), are available in every year. <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 2</ref> shows that health insurance and general health are reasonably similar across the CPS and the BRFSS, although the CPS respondents consistently report lower insurance rates and better health. It also shows that about 8% of young women report being pregnant at the time of the survey.</p><p>However, other access and health outcome measures are not reported in every year, as shown in <ref type="table">Table S3</ref>. Not Afford (whether the individual had to forego care because they could not afford to see the doctor) is the most available access measure, missing only in 2002. Especially unfortunate for our purposes is that routine care targeting females (pap smears and breast exams) and reported use of contraception methods are missing in too many years and/or states to be useful. <ref type="bibr">21</ref> Our health-care access measures are therefore limited to Not Afford and whether the woman had a routine physician visit in the last year (Check up, missing for most states in <ref type="bibr">[2001]</ref><ref type="bibr">[2002]</ref><ref type="bibr">[2003]</ref><ref type="bibr">[2004]</ref>. Finally, in all years but 2002, the BRFSS contains two measures indicating the number of days in the previous month in which the respondent's physical or mental health was "not good," which we also investigate in our analyses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Vital Statistics and Abortion Surveillance-Reproductive Outcomes</head><p>Past CM research relies primarily on Vital Statistics data to investigate reproductive outcomes, and we do as well, using the birth and abortion rates from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) aggregated to the state-year level. <ref type="bibr">22</ref> The restricted-use Vital Statistics records contain information on maternal and infant characteristics, including demographic and health indicators as well as geographic identifiers 21. Pap Smear and Breast Exam are missing for the vast majority of states for five of the more recent years <ref type="bibr">(2001, 2003, 2005, 2007, and 2009)</ref>, leading to relatively small sample sizes and less observed variation in the post mandate periods. The contraception questions are asked by all states in only 2002 and 2004 and by a very small number of states, if at all, in the remaining years.</p><p>22. Our abortion data is the same as that used in Mulligan (2015). Our conception year, state-level births data are similar; Mulligan (2015) uses birth year and state-level births, whereas <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Dills and Cotet-Grecu (2016)</ref> use conception year (estimated using date of last menstrual period) and countylevel births.</p><p>for state and county. Using the estimated length of gestation and counting back from the month of birth, pregnancies resulting in live births are aggregated to the state level by conception year and reported as the annual birth rate per 1,000 women. The full sample of live births between 1997 and 2009 is 19,457,946 births aggregated into 686 state-year observations. Abortion statistics by state are reported annually in the CDC's "Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report: Abortion Surveillance" by age bracket <ref type="bibr">(&lt;15, 15-19, 20-24, 25-29, 30-34, 35-39, 40+)</ref>.</p><p>These aggregate fertility measures preclude estimation of most DDD models. Neither the births nor abortion data contain the information needed to determine "Levine" eligibility (e.g., student status). In addition, the abortion data are already aggregated into broad age groups, and so, determining eligibility based solely on age (i.e., "Depew") is not possible either. This limitation highlights the benefits of the Pregnant variable we investigate from the BRFSS; to our knowledge, we are the first to do so in this kind of research. At the same time, we note that Pregnant differs from these fertility measures because (1) it captures whether the woman is pregnant and knows it at the time of the survey (and so misses many pregnancies over the course of a year), and (2) it captures some eventual miscarriages (which are missed in aggregate fertility measures). <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 2</ref> suggests that the former is larger than the latter as the 8% reported pregnancy rate in the BRFSS is substantially lower than the birth + abortion rates per 1,000 women observed in the Vital Statistics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. Other Data Choices and Robustness Checks</head><p>One challenge is choosing a set of control variables that are representative of both CM and YAD research. At the individual level, our choice is limited by what is available in the CPS versus the BRFSS; recall that our Vital Statistics analyses (state-level births and abortions) contain no individual-level variables. An additional complication is that studies vary in the state-level variables they include. Most include the unemployment rate and Medicaid eligibility levels, and CM studies emphasize controlling for emergency contraception availability. To be comparable across mandates and outcomes, we include all three state-level variables as well as the percent reporting ESI and percent receiving Medicaid; we also choose a broad set of individual-level variables (see panel B of <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 2</ref>).</p><p>Recent CM research <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Dills and Cotet-Grecu 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mulligan 2015)</ref> shows that the effects are sensitive to the inclusion of state-specific time trends. As noted in Section III, we estimate our DD models both with and without state-specific time trends and choose one DDD approach that does control for state-specific time effects ("Depew") and one that does not ("Levine"). <ref type="bibr">23</ref> We also re-estimate all models excluding 2009 as it was an unusual year because of the Great Recession and the large number of states enacting YADs; the results are quite similar. Finally, we subject every model to a placebo test in which the current mandate variables are replaced with a 3-year lead-that is, whether or not they were enacted 3 years in the future. In the full model, this process involves four separate tests-the individual statistical significance of each mandate coefficient (β CM , β YA , and β CM * YA ) as well as their joint statistical significance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. RESULTS</head><p>Our empirical analyses include three models (Equations (1)-(3) above) estimated with four different approaches (two DD and two DDD) on a wide set of outcomes from three different data sources. We also subject every model to a placebo test. We therefore report only the key coefficients from each of the models/approaches, and at the bottom of each one, we summarize whether the model "passed" the placebo test(s) at a 10% level. For the models including both mandates, we also report the p value for the joint test of the three key coefficients (for YAD, CM, and YAD*CM). To facilitate comparisons, we group the results by outcome rather than data source. <ref type="table">Table 3</ref> reports the results for health insurance coverage using data from both the CPS and the 23. Because the BRFSS data is gathered monthly, we include month fixed effects as well as year and state fixed effects in those models; their inclusion has no substantive impact on the results. Other sensitivity analyses explored but not reported include lagging the mandate indicators by 1 year (to allow for a delayed effect and/or variables that may capture behavior over more than one calendar year), including agespecific time trends, reducing the individual-and state-level controls included, and estimating the dichotomous outcomes with probit and the count outcomes (i.e., days not healthy) with a negative binomial. None of these analyses affect the conclusions drawn from the core set of exercises. All results discussed are available upon request.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Health Insurance and Health-Care Access</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TABLE 3</head><p>Results  BRFSS. Using the CPS measure and the "Levine" YAD-DDD model, our results are close to those of <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011)</ref>, despite including more years <ref type="bibr">(1997-1999 and 2009)</ref>, using slightly different mandate dates, and limiting our analyses to women. 24 However, the rest of our analyses provide very little evidence that either mandate increased insurance coverage. Using the BRFSS insurance measure instead is especially damaging, often leading to estimated negative effects. Our results are therefore consistent with the conclusion drawn by <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Depew (2015)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Monheit et al. (2011)</ref>, which state that YADs did little to increase overall insurance coverage and may have instead simply caused a shifting between group versus individual, parent versus own, and/or private versus public. The results for CMs and the joint effect of CM and YAD likewise suggest little consistent effect, although it is somewhat surprising that they are found to be positive and significant about as often as the much more heavily studied YAD. The health-care access measures from the BRFSS, Not Afford and Checkup, likewise yield no consistent evidence that either mandate expanded young women's access to general health care, and in fact, the estimated effects are just as likely to be detrimental as beneficial (see <ref type="table">Table S4</ref>). Given that we find no evidence that these mandates expanded insurance coverage, it is not surprising to find little effect on these general measures of care received. It nonetheless remains possible that switching types of coverage (à la YADs) could affect access in subtler ways, such as the quality or convenience of care received. If YADs lead young adults to switch to their parents' insurance, then that new insurance may differ in its coverage of contraception if the state also has a CM. Likewise, as <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Depew (2015)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Colman and Dave (2015)</ref> find, the switch in health insurance may have been accompanied by other changed behaviors. Such subtle mechanisms suggest that these mandates could still have effects on general health, and the avenue for CMs to affect reproductive outcomes-by expanding contraceptive use among the insured-remains. <ref type="table">Table 4</ref> reports results for several measures of general health. The first two panels 24. Specifically, <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011)</ref> find a statistically significant increase of 0.033 <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">(Table 5</ref>, Panel A, column 2 on p. 148), while ours suggests a 0.028 increase.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. General and Reproductive Health Outcomes</head><p>are the standard self-reported health variable (1 = poor to 5 = excellent) from the CPS and BRFSS, transformed to Very Good plus (=1 if excellent or very good, 0 otherwise) as commonly constructed. Neither mandate in isolation appears to have a consistent effect on Very Good plus, but the effect of having both mandates is consistently positive and, in the BRFSS data, almost always statistically significant. Moreover, while the individual coefficients vary, the estimated total effect of having both mandates is surprisingly close across the two very different datasets and DDD models, ranging from 0.023 to 0.046.</p><p>We explore this finding further by estimating the same models using the number of days out of the last 30 that physical (mental) health was "not good" from the BRFSS (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_10">Table 5</ref>). These analyses suggest no effect of either mandate on physical health, with the exception of the "Depew" model, which suggests that YADs reduce the number of "not good" days. The results are marginally more suggestive for mental health, but the mechanisms appear to differ. The "Depew" model once again finds that YADs are beneficial and that CMs may be as well, although the latter is not statistically significant. The "Levine" model finds it is CMs and perhaps the joint effect (CM*YAD) that are beneficial and that YADs are harmful if anything. However, the net total effect is again quite similar across the two DDD models; both suggest that having both mandates reduces the number of "not good" mental health days by 0.546-0.584 days.</p><p>Taken together with the results for Very Good plus, a broad measure of health, we conclude that there is some weakly suggestive evidence that these mandates are improving the subjective well-being of young women, although the pathways are not clear. Our findings therefore echo those of <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Colman and Dave (2015)</ref> for the ACA's YAD mandate; perhaps they derive from the same mechanisms (decreased time spent working and waiting for or receiving care, increased time socializing). It is also intriguing to link our "Depew" findings with the reductions in labor supply caused by YADs found by <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Depew (2015)</ref>; perhaps that reduced labor supply is associated with improvements in health.</p><p>Finally, we turn to reproductive outcomes, reported in <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">Table 6</ref>. The top two panels report estimates from the aggregate Vital Statistics measures typically used. Here, we find similar results to <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mulligan (2015)</ref> that CMs appear to reduce fertility until location-specific time effects         are included, which eliminate all significant effects. <ref type="bibr">25</ref> Moreover, our placebo tests suggest that including those effects are necessary. We augment these previously studied measures with whether the young woman reports being pregnant (via the BRFSS), included in the bottom panel. These individual-level data allow us to estimate all four DD and DDD approaches, as we have for all of the other outcomes. These results are consistent with the aggregate data, suggesting that CMs have a negative effect on pregnancy. Now, however, including location-specific time effects appears less necessary, and their inclusion strengthens the impact of CMs. These analyses are also weakly suggestive that YADs may increase pregnancy, which is not implausible, especially if YADs make it easier for women to get insurance from a source other than their employers and reduces their labor supply.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUDING REMARKS</head><p>This research takes a comprehensive approach to studying the effects of insurance mandates on young adults by using contrasting empirical methodologies to estimate the individual and possibly joint effects of both YAD and contraception insurance mandates on a wide set of outcomes spanning several different datasets. Our approach helps settle conflicting past findings as well as uncovers more complicated pathways for these mandates to have an effect. For YADs, our results support the more tepid findings of <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Depew (2015)</ref> and others that such mandates do not significantly increase overall insurance coverage. Rather, the strong effects of <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011)</ref> appear unique to their methodology and data source (the CPS). Using an alternative methodology (e.g., a DDD based on age only) or dataset (BRFSS) overturns the positive results we find using the CPS and their approach.</p><p>Past research on the effect of CMs on fertility outcomes (as measured with aggregate births and abortions) has also been mixed, whereby strong negative effects are greatly diminished by the inclusion of location-specific time trends (e.g., Mulligan 2015). We use similar-yet not identical-aggregate data as this past work and find the same mixed results. However, we also 25. Recall that the "Depew" model includes state-specific time trends. Also recall that these aggregate Vital Statistics datasets have no individual characteristics (precluding "Levine") and that the abortion data are already aggregated by broad age groups (precluding "Depew").</p><p>bring new evidence by estimating the effects one or both mandates have on reported pregnancy using data from the BRFSS. These analyses also yield a negative effect of CMs on fertility, an effect that is stronger when location-specific time effects are included. When combined with the aggregate evidence, it strengthens the case that CMs reduce fertility.</p><p>These findings for insurance coverage and reproductive outcomes are largely unaffected by allowing the other mandate to have an effect as well, despite the fact that we find the two mandates' enactments are positively correlated. We do find some evidence, however, that the two mandates combine to affect the general health and well-being of young adults, an effect that is mostly obscured if each mandate is considered in isolation. Such effects are plausible in light of past work that finds other pathways for YADs to have an effect (through a change in coverage type or reducing labor supply) and our results here that CMs appear likely to have an effect on reproductive behavior.</p><p>This research is not without its shortcomings. Our results are not as definitive as we would like and are instead mostly suggestive. Our analyses face the difficulty of identifying the unique and joint effects of two mandates using the relatively small number of years and states in which policy changes take place. This challenge is compounded by the fact that these mandates likely fail to reach a significant proportion of young women; that is, the gap between intent-to-treat (what we estimate) and treatment-on-the-treated estimates is large. This is especially true for our DD and age-based DDD YAD models because many young adults do not satisfy other eligibility requirements. More broadly, neither mandate is binding for those young adults who get their insurance from self-insured firms (because of ERISA) or who already receive such coverage prior to the law. As noted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Depew (2015)</ref>, such attenuation bias is likely to lead to insignificant results and is why he uses the American Community Survey to study labor supply, a very large dataset that is nearly 20 times bigger than the CPS or BRFSS. While these challenges extend to all studies of state-level YADs and CMs, studying both in tandem and subjecting them to such substantial robustness checks (different data sources and empirical methodologies) appears almost certain to exacerbate them and makes the consistent findings that do emerge compelling.</p><p>The ACA, with its much wider reach and fewer exemptions, avoids some of these limitations and has led to an explosion of research studying the effects of its YAD. As the full potential of the ACA's impact grows, with the CM and other mandates firmly in place, future work should consider the dual effects of both of these mandates on the coverage, care, and well-being of young adults. At the same time, the possible repeal of the ACA, an outcome that appears more likely with the 2016 elections, suggests that these state-level mandates may once again become relevant and therefore so too the estimated effects we explore here.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUPPORTING INFORMATION</head><p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the online version of this article: <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table S1</ref>. Summary of Studies on the ACA-YAD mandate on insurance, care, and health <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table S2</ref>. Comparison of timing of state mandates across studies <ref type="table">Table S3</ref>. State level sampling of care utilization and health measures in the BRFSS <ref type="table">Table S4</ref>. Results of the effect of state mandates on healthcare utilization <ref type="figure">Figure S1</ref>. Timing of individual state mandates on young adult-dependent coverage and contraception coverage <ref type="figure">Figure S2</ref>. Growth in state-level YADs and CMs over time <ref type="bibr">(1997)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1998)</ref><ref type="bibr">(1999)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2000)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2001)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2002)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2003)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2004)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2005)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2006)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2007)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2008)</ref><ref type="bibr">(2009)</ref> </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>7.</head><label></label><figDesc>Using the BRFSS,<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Blum et al. (2012)</ref> provide descriptive evidence of increased insurance coverage and care utilization of individuals living in 3 treatment (YAD) states relative to those living in 17 control states. Additionally, two studies investigate the effects of the MA Health Reform on health care<ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Kolstad and Kowalski 2012)</ref> and outcomes<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Courtemanche and Zapata 2014)</ref>, but neither focuses on young adults nor the YAD.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>The</head><label></label><figDesc>National Conference of State Legislatures (NCSL) website (National Conference of State Legislatures 2012) contains information on both the extended parental coverage and CMs. We cross-reference the NCSL indicators for YADs with Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011), Monheit et al. (2011), Hahn and Yang (2014), Depew (2015), and Cantor et al. (2012), and the CM indicators with the Guttmacher Institute (2014), Raissian and Lopoo (2015), Dills and Cotet-Grecu (2016), and Mulligan (2015). This exercise is summarized in</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>of the Effect of State Mandates on Having Any Insurance Coverage in the Last Year or Current Health Plan a sample weights and controls for state-level characteristics reported in</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>4</head><label></label><figDesc>Results of the Effect of State Mandates on Measures of Self-Reported Health a sample weights and controls for state-level characteristics reported in</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>sample weights and controls for state-level characteristics reported in</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>sample weights and controls for state-level characteristics reported in</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE 1 and Health YAD Mandate Contraception Mandate Coverage Long, Yemane, and Stockleyet al. (2012)-State Level (BRFSS</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Summary of Studies on the Independent Effects of State-Level YAD and Contraception Mandates on Insurance, Care,</figDesc><table><row><cell>(2010)-MA Health Reform (CPS</cell><cell>2006-2009)</cell><cell>DD, 19-26 vs. all 27-33, minorities 27-33, childless 27-33 in</cell><cell>MA: decreases uninsured rate by 5.0-6.5 pp.</cell><cell>DDD, compare against NY: decrease uninsured rate 5.4-7.5 pp.</cell></row></table><note>a Blum</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>et al. (2011)-State Level</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Raissian and Lopoo (2015) (CPS 1989-2009)</cell><cell>DD, 15-44, includes indicator for mandates that cover services and</cell><cell>supplies or suppliers only: no effect on probability of having private</cell><cell>insurance coverage</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>treatment states CO, NJ, SD v. 17 controls</cell><cell>0.2% increase in any insurance coverage.</cell><cell>Descriptive 2 nd Study, nonstudents 19-23 v. 26-29 in CO and SD only</cell><cell>4.2% increase in coverage for 19-23-year-olds.</cell><cell>Depew (2015)-State Level (CPS 2001-2010)</cell><cell>DDD, 19-29, 2.3 pp increase in likelihood of dependent insurance</cell><cell>coverage. Subsamples: 14.4% increase for females, 10% increase males</cell><cell>relative to mean.</cell><cell>Hahn and Yang (2014)-State Level (CPS 2001-2010)</cell><cell>DD, 19-24 in expansion states: 4.8 pp increase in dependent coverage,</cell><cell>more than half because of decreases in own private insurance.</cell><cell>b Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011)-State Level (CPS 2001-2009)</cell><cell>DDD, 19-24: 3.3 pp increase in any coverage, 4.4 pp increase in</cell><cell>private insurance. Subsample, nonstudents: 5.1 pp increase in any</cell><cell>insurance coverage.</cell><cell>DD, 19-24 and live with parents: 1.6 pp increase in any insurance</cell><cell>(2.9 pp private).</cell><cell>(CPS 2001-2009)</cell><cell>DD, 19-29: No effect on overall uninsured, private or public coverage.</cell><cell>Subsamples, by residence with parents and/or ages 19-25: decreases</cell><cell>in own ESI from 2.11 to 3.33 pp offset by increases in parents' coverage</cell><cell>of 2.58-3.84 pp.</cell></row></table><note>ab Monheit</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE 1 Continued YAD Mandate Contraception Mandate Care Utilization a Blum et al. (2012)-State Level (BRFSS</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Indicates that the study spans more than one row of the matrix.</figDesc><table><row><cell>DDD, 15-44, privately insured v. not privately insured: no differential effect on</cell><cell>contraception use overall or among low educated; 15.9% (12.8%) increase</cell><cell>in pap smears (pelvic exams), driven by low-educated privately insured women.</cell><cell>Health Outcomes Dills and Cotet-Grecu (2016) (Vital Statistics 1998-2008)</cell><cell>DD for 18-19, 20-34, 35-44 by race: 4% decrease in births to Hispanic teens</cell><cell>robust to inclusion of state-specific time trends and event-study specification.</cell><cell>Other Outcomes: No effect on meconium release, precipitous labor, induced</cell><cell>labor, or C-section.</cell><cell>Mulligan (2015) (Vital Statistics 1993-2007, NSLY, CPS)</cell><cell>DD, 15-44: 6% decrease in state annual abortion rate, moderated by inclusion</cell><cell>of state time trends; effects do not persist in long run for flexible time</cell><cell>specification model. Births: 3% decline in state-and individual-level analyses,</cell><cell>not robust to state trends.</cell><cell>Notes: Studies typically follow a DD/DDD approach, identifying the effect of each mandate using variation across states and over time. For DDD specifications, the treatment and control</cell><cell>groups are also indicated.</cell><cell>Burgdorf (2014) conducts a sensitivity analysis of Monheit et al. 2011 and Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011), incorporating a distinction between the source of dependent coverage</cell><cell>(spouse or parent). See also Monheit, Cantor, and DeLia (2015)'s commentary and Burgdorf (2015)'s reply.</cell></row></table><note>aab</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>TABLE 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Description of the Data Used: (A) Summary Statistics for Outcomes Studied and Eligibility Status by Age Group and (B) Description of Other Variables Included in the Models Control for race, marital status, student status, and income bracket CPS: Control for marital status, student status, and a quadratic measure of the income to poverty ratio. Regressions useLevine, McKnight, and   Heep's (2011) data, "maindata.dta," limited to women and expanded to include 2009. Vital Statistics/Abortion Surveillance: Control for fraction of state population that is married, non-White, that earned a high school diploma, that earned a college degree as well as log median income, average age, average number of children under 5 per household, average number of children under 18 per household by state, as in<ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Mulligan (2015)</ref>. CPS measures VeryGood + and Insured have different sample sizes because of survey questionnaire referencing current vs. prior year (see footnote 18). Sample from Abortion Surveillance excludes AK, CT, FL, NH, and WY because of missing information.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ages 19-24</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ages 25-29</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(A) Summary Statistics</cell><cell>N</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>N</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>Source</cell></row><row><cell>1. Insurance Coverage</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Insured a</cell><cell>85,929</cell><cell>0.72</cell><cell>0.45</cell><cell>75,674</cell><cell>0.75</cell><cell>0.43</cell><cell>CPS</cell></row><row><cell>HlthPlan</cell><cell>77,841</cell><cell>0.75</cell><cell>0.43</cell><cell>111,390</cell><cell>0.81</cell><cell>0.40</cell><cell>BRFSS</cell></row><row><cell>2. Care Utilization</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>NotAfford</cell><cell>64,857</cell><cell>0.22</cell><cell>0.41</cell><cell>95,522</cell><cell>0.20</cell><cell>0.40</cell><cell>BRFSS</cell></row><row><cell>Checkup</cell><cell>50,291</cell><cell>0.70</cell><cell>0.46</cell><cell>76,126</cell><cell>0.70</cell><cell>0.46</cell><cell>BRFSS</cell></row><row><cell>3. Health Outcomes</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>General</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Very Good + [CPS] a</cell><cell>79,579</cell><cell>0.74</cell><cell>0.44</cell><cell>70,069</cell><cell>0.71</cell><cell>0.45</cell><cell>CPS</cell></row><row><cell>Very Good + [BRFSS]</cell><cell>78,019</cell><cell>0.61</cell><cell>0.49</cell><cell>111,330</cell><cell>0.65</cell><cell>0.48</cell><cell>BRFSS</cell></row><row><cell>PhysHlth</cell><cell>73,335</cell><cell>2.37</cell><cell>5.42</cell><cell>105,788</cell><cell>2.37</cell><cell>5.67</cell><cell>BRFSS</cell></row><row><cell>MentalHlth</cell><cell>73,350</cell><cell>4.82</cell><cell>8.07</cell><cell>105,602</cell><cell>4.32</cell><cell>7.91</cell><cell>BRFSS</cell></row><row><cell>Reproductive</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Birth Rate [DD]</cell><cell>686</cell><cell>104.76</cell><cell>18.80</cell><cell></cell><cell>NA</cell><cell></cell><cell>Vital Stats</cell></row><row><cell>Birth Rate [DDD]</cell><cell>3,822</cell><cell>103.16</cell><cell>24.75</cell><cell>3,185</cell><cell>120.09</cell><cell>19.15</cell><cell>Vital Stats</cell></row><row><cell>Abortion Rate [DD] b</cell><cell>546</cell><cell>30.51</cell><cell>12.81</cell><cell></cell><cell>NA</cell><cell></cell><cell>Abortion Surveil.</cell></row><row><cell>Pregnant</cell><cell>77,243</cell><cell>0.08</cell><cell>0.26</cell><cell>102,057</cell><cell>0.08</cell><cell>0.27</cell><cell>BRFSS</cell></row><row><cell>4. Eligibility Used for DDDs</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>"Levine" [CPS]</cell><cell>85,929</cell><cell>0.75</cell><cell>0.44</cell><cell></cell><cell>NA</cell><cell></cell><cell>CPS</cell></row><row><cell>"Levine" [BRFSS]</cell><cell>78,115</cell><cell>0.66</cell><cell>0.48</cell><cell></cell><cell>NA</cell><cell></cell><cell>BRFSS</cell></row><row><cell>"Depew" [CPS]</cell><cell>85,929</cell><cell>0.60</cell><cell>0.49</cell><cell>75,674</cell><cell>0.21</cell><cell>0.41</cell><cell>CPS</cell></row><row><cell>"Depew" [BRFSS]</cell><cell>78,115</cell><cell>0.56</cell><cell>0.50</cell><cell>111,479</cell><cell>0.09</cell><cell>0.28</cell><cell>BRFSS</cell></row></table><note>(B) Other Variables 1. State-level Controls [Z] Medicaid eligibility, fraction of state receiving Medicaid assistance, receiving employer-sponsored insurance (ESI), state unemployment rate, indicator for availability of over-the-counter emergency contraception 2. Sample-specific Controls [X, Z] BRFSS:abthat is, a DD approach. The typical CM model estimated is CM Model ∶ Y iast = α + θ s + θ t + θ a + γX iast</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>+ θ s * time + γX iast + πZ st+ β CM CM st + ε iast , YAD-DDD Model ∶ Y iast = α + θ s + θ t + θ a + θ s * time + γX iast + πZ st + β CM CM st + β YA YAD st + β ′ YA YAD st Eligible as + β CM * YA CM st YAD st + β′ CM * YA CM st YAD st Eligible as + ε iast ,where the DDD estimate of YAD's effect is β ′ YA , and the joint effect of having both a YAD and a CM is β ′ CM * YA .</figDesc><table><row><cell>(1b)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>a * s</cell></row><row><cell>+ θ a * t (2b)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">+ θ a * s + θ a * t + θ s  *  time + γX iast + πZ st</cell></row><row><cell>+ β YA YAD st + β ′</cell><cell>YA YAD st Eligible as + ε iast ,</cell></row><row><cell>and</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(3b)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Full-DDD Model ∶ Y iast = α + θ s + θ t + θ a</cell></row><row><cell>+ θ a * s + θ a * t</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>IV. DATA</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 2 ,</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Panel B as well as age, year, and state fixed effects. Standard errors are clustered by state; corresponding t-statistics are reported in parentheses, and *, **, *** indicate 10, 5, and 1% significance levels, respectively.The placebo test replaces each mandate variable with a dummy for whether the mandate is in place 3 years in the future. P indicates whether the estimated coefficient passes, that is, is not statistically significant at the 10% level; F indicates fails. The fourth indicator for the YAD*CM model is the joint test of β</figDesc><table><row><cell>* YA from the placebo regression.</cell></row><row><cell>CM , β YA , and β CM</cell></row></table><note>b</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>TABLE</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 2 ,</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Panel B as well as age, year, and state fixed effects. Standard errors are clustered by state; corresponding t-statistics are reported in parentheses, and *, **, *** indicate 10, 5, and 1% significance levels, respectively.The placebo test replaces each mandate variable with a dummy for whether the mandate is in place 3 years in the future. P indicates whether the estimated coefficient passes, that is, is not statistically significant at the 10% level; F indicates fails. The fourth indicator for the YAD*CM model is the joint test of β</figDesc><table><row><cell>* YA from the placebo regression.</cell></row><row><cell>CM , β YA , and β CM</cell></row></table><note>b</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>TABLE 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>BRFSS Results of the Effect of State Mandates on Measures of Self-Reported Physical and Mental Health a</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 2 ,</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Panel B as well as age, year, and state fixed effects. Standard errors are clustered by state; corresponding t-statistics are reported in parentheses, and *, **, *** indicate 10, 5, and 1% significance levels, respectively.The placebo test replaces each mandate variable with a dummy for whether the mandate is in place 3 years in the future. P indicates whether the estimated coefficient passes, that is, is not statistically significant at the 10% level; F indicates fails. The fourth indicator for the YAD*CM model is the joint test of β</figDesc><table><row><cell>* YA from the placebo regression</cell></row><row><cell>CM , β YA , and β CM</cell></row></table><note>b</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>TABLE 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Results of the Effect of State Mandates on Birth and Abortion Rates and Reported Pregnancies a</figDesc><table><row><cell>DD Models</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table 2 ,</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Panel B as well as age, year, and state fixed effects. Standard errors are clustered by state; corresponding t-statistics are reported in parentheses, and *, **, *** indicate 10, 5, and 1% significance levels, respectively.The placebo test replaces each mandate variable with a dummy for whether the mandate is in place 3 years in the future. P indicates whether the estimated coefficient passes, that is, is not statistically significant at the 10% level; F indicates fails. The fourth indicator for the YAD*CM model is the joint test of β</figDesc><table><row><cell>* YA from the placebo regression.</cell></row><row><cell>CM , β YA , and β CM</cell></row></table><note>b</note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4">. Although Utah is commonly cited as the first adopter of YAD legislation, in our reading, we observe that North Dakota extended family coverage to students up to age 23 and nonstudents cohabitating with a parent through age 19 in 1985 and then increased both age thresholds in 1995. SeeTable S2, Supporting Information.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Access to Health Insurance and the Use of Inpatient Medical Care: Evidence from the Affordable Care Act Young Adult Mandate</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yaa</forename><forename type="middle">Akosa</forename><surname>Antwi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Asako</forename><surname>Moriya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kosali</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3386/w20202</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://doi.org/10.3386/w20202" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Health Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-06" />
			<publisher>National Bureau of Economic Research</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in Emergency Department Use among Young Adults after the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act&apos;s Dependent Coverage Provision</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Antwi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Moriya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sommers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Emergency Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="664" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in State Prescription Contraceptive Mandates For Insurers: The Effect on Women&apos;s Contraceptive Use</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Danielle</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Atkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">David</forename><surname>Bradford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1363/46e0314</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">24433431</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-LV3035QB-N</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">3D710698EE3FAD5ECA78D9B4B42E362C5AEEC1A2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Perspect Sex Repro H</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1538-6341</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-01-16" />
			<publisher>Guttmacher Institute</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impacts of the Affordable Care Act Dependent Coverage Provision on Health-Related Outcomes of Young Adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Silvia</forename><surname>Barbaresco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Charles</forename><surname>Courtemanche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yanling</forename><surname>Qi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3386/w20148</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://doi.org/10.3386/w20148" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Health Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-05" />
			<publisher>National Bureau of Economic Research</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reducing underage alcohol and tobacco use: Evidence from the introduction of vertical identification cards</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andriana</forename><surname>Bellou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rachana</forename><surname>Bhatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jhealeco.2012.12.001</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">23333955</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.econstor.eu/bitstream/10419/67209/1/72930017X.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Health Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Health Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0167-6296</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="353" to="366" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-03" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of State Laws That Extend Eligibility for Parents&apos; Health Insurance Coverage to Young Adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Blum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kleinman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Starfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1542/peds.2011-1505</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22331339</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC3356137</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://europepmc.org/articles/pmc3356137?pdf=render" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PEDIATRICS</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">PEDIATRICS</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0031-4005</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1098-4275</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="426" to="432" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-02-13" />
			<publisher>American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Young Adult Dependent Coverage: Were the State Reforms Effective? A Critique and a Response</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">Richard</forename><surname>Burgdorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1475-6773.12314</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">25994071</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC4450922</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-MWFR3Q6C-M</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">2850662F5F77D6243F04CCF8D83803BB175B95EA</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://europepmc.org/articles/pmc4450922?pdf=render" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Services Research</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Health Serv Res</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0017-9124</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="637" to="641" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-05-20" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Health Services Research</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Early Impact of the Affordable Care Act on Health Insurance Coverage of Young Adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joel</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cantor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alan</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Monheit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Derek</forename><surname>Delia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kristen</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1475-6773.2012.01458.x</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22924684</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC3513605</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-B6912G9D-J</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">B23E46FEBB81B95601C29F3114E643D5F8C80D28</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://europepmc.org/articles/pmc3513605?pdf=render" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Services Research</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Health Serv Res</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0017-9124</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1773" to="1790" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-08-27" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in Health and Medical Spending Among Young Adults Under Health Reform</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kao-Ping</forename><surname>Chua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Benjamin</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sommers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jama.2014.2202</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">24938568</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/articlepdf/1881299/jld140006.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JAMA</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">JAMA</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0098-7484</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">311</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2437</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014-06-18" />
			<publisher>American Medical Association (AMA)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IT&apos;S ABOUT TIME: EFFECTS OF THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT DEPENDENT COVERAGE MANDATE ON TIME USE</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gregory</forename><surname>Colman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dhaval</forename><surname>Dave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/coep.12242</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www.nber.org/papers/w21725.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contemporary Economic Policy</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Contemp Econ Policy</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1074-3529</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-07-20" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does Universal Coverage Improve Health? The Massachusetts Experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Charles</forename><surname>Courtemanche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Daniela</forename><surname>Zapata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3386/w17893</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://doi.org/10.3386/w17893" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Policy Analysis and Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-03" />
			<publisher>National Bureau of Economic Research</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Use and Expenses for Office-Based Physician Visits by Specialty, 2009: Estimates for the U.S. Civilian Noninstitutionalized Population</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Carper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.meps.ahrq.gov/mepsweb/data_files/publications/st381/stat381.shtml" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-08" />
			<pubPlace>Rockville, MD</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of state dependent mandate laws on the labor supply decisions of young adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Briggs</forename><surname>Depew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jhealeco.2014.11.008</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">25497756</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Health Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Health Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0167-6296</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-01" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of state contraceptive insurance mandates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Angela</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Dills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Anca</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Grecu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ehb.2016.11.004</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">27889633</idno>
		<ptr target="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2767094" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economics &amp; Human Biology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Economics &amp; Human Biology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1570-677X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-02" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in out-of-pocket payments for contraception by privately insured women during implementation of the federal contraceptive coverage requirement</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lawrence</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Finer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Adam</forename><surname>Sonfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rachel</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.contraception.2013.11.015</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">24332745</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contraception</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Contraception</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0010-7824</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-02" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Guttmacher</forename><surname>Institute</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://kaiserhealthnews.files.wordpress.com/2012/02/spib_icc.pdf" />
		<title level="m">State Policies in Brief: Insurance Coverage of Contraceptives</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do Work Decisions among Young Adults Respond to Extended Dependent Coverage?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Youjin</forename><surname>Hahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hee-Seung</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0019793915610308</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/fc29/ecf4e444af86ad098badf219ee4690456def.pdf" />
		<ptr target="http://ssrn.com/abstract=2101939" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ILR Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">ILR Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0019-7939</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">2162-271X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="737" to="771" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-10-12" />
			<publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Women&apos;s Preventive Services Guidelines: Affordable Care Act Expands Prevention Coverage for Women&apos;s Health and Well-Being</title>
		<ptr target="https://www.hrsa.gov/womensguidelines/" />
		<editor>Health Resources and Services Administration. U.S</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-07-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Department of Health and Human Services</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Kaiser Family Foundations and Health Research and Educational Trust (HRET)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://kaiserfamilyfoundation.files.wordpress.com/2013/04/8085.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-02-20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Employer Health Benefits: 2010 Annual Survey</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of health care reform on hospital and preventive care: Evidence from Massachusetts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kolstad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amanda</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kowalski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jpubeco.2012.07.003</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">23180894</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC3501746</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://europepmc.org/articles/pmc3501746?pdf=render" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Public Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Public Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0047-2727</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11-12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="909" to="929" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-12" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Effective are Public Policies to Increase Health Insurance Coverage Among Young Adults?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Phillip</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robin</forename><surname>Mcknight</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Samantha</forename><surname>Heep</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/pol.3.1.129</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Journal: Economic Policy</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">American Economic Journal: Economic Policy</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1945-7731</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1945-774X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-02" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disentangling the Effects of Health Reform in Massachusetts: How Important Are the Special Provisions for Young Adults?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sharon</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alshadye</forename><surname>Yemane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Karen</forename><surname>Stockley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/aer.100.2.297</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/1115/857b09179377a39441ce9c325a61f94fe76b.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">American Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-8282</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="302" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-05" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contraceptive Insurance Mandates and Consistent Contraceptive Use Among Privately Insured Women</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Brianna</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Magnusson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lindsay</forename><surname>Sabik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Derek</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Saba</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Masho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><forename type="middle">Elston</forename><surname>Lafata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Cathy</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kate</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lapane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/mlr.0b013e318254331c</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22688787</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medical Care</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Medical Care</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0025-7079</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="562" to="568" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-07" />
			<publisher>Ovid Technologies (Wolters Kluwer Health)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Have State Policies to Expand Dependent Coverage Affected the Health Insurance Status of Young Adults?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alan</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Monheit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joel</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cantor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Derek</forename><surname>Delia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dina</forename><surname>Belloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1475-6773.2010.01200.x</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">21054376</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC3037781</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-S389FZ5N-L</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">8ABE2F3AEA2E172262BD79D51B6F400CE865F3CD</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://europepmc.org/articles/pmc3037781?pdf=render" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Services Research</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0017-9124</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1p2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="267" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-11-05" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drawing Plausible Inferences about the Impact of State Dependent Coverage Expansions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alan</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Monheit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joel</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cantor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Derek</forename><surname>Delia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/1475-6773.12313</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">25994070</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC4450921</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-868032B9-W</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">28CD6FE3A7E439A8311CC4E3A6DC6A7C045C3AE7</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://europepmc.org/articles/pmc4450921?pdf=render" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Services Research</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Health Serv Res</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0017-9124</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="631" to="636" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-05-20" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contraception Use, Abortions, and Births: The Effect of Insurance Mandates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Karen</forename><surname>Mulligan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s13524-015-0412-3</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">26153735</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Demography</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Demography</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0070-3370</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1533-7790</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1195" to="1217" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-07-08" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Covering Young Adults through Their Parents&apos; or Guardians&apos; Health Policy</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.ncsl.org/issues-research/health/dependent-health-coverage-state-implementation.aspx#State_Action" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-12-05" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Conference of State Legislatures</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mandating Prescription Contraception Coverage: Effects on Contraception Consumption and Preventive Health Services</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kerri</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Raissian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Leonard</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lopoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11113-014-9353-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Population Research and Policy Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Popul Res Policy Rev</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0167-5923</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1573-7829</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="481" to="510" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-12-14" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Women Rush to Get Long-Acting Birth Control after Trump Wins</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NPR</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-11-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Accessed</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2016/11/11/501611813/women-rush-to-get-long-acting-birth-control-after-trump-wins" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-02-20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Significant Placebo Results in Difference-in-Differences Analysis: The Case of the ACA’s Parental Mandate</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Slusky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1057/eej.2015.49</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eastern Economic Journal</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Eastern Econ J</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0094-5056</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1939-4632</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="580" to="603" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-09" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Affordable Care Act Has Led To Significant Gains In Health Insurance And Access To Care For Young Adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Benjamin</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sommers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Buchmueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sandra</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Decker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Colleen</forename><surname>Carey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Kronick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1377/hlthaff.2012.0552</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">23255048</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/3881/9cf130f53b260c1a460d4be7cfe0d3b77f96.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Affairs</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Health Affairs</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0278-2715</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1544-5208</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="174" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-01" />
			<publisher>Health Affairs (Project Hope)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">U.S. Insurance Coverage of Contraceptives and the Impact Of Contraceptive Coverage Mandates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Adam</forename><surname>Sonfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rachel</forename><forename type="middle">Benson</forename><surname>Gold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Frost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jacqueline</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Darroch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1363/3607204</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">15136210</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">PSRH</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1538-6341</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">02</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-03" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Burden of unintended pregnancy in the United States: potential savings with increased use of long-acting reversible contraception</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Trussell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nathaniel</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Fareen</forename><surname>Hassan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alexander</forename><surname>Prezioso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amy</forename><surname>Law</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Anna</forename><surname>Filonenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.contraception.2012.07.016</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22959904</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC3659779</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://europepmc.org/articles/pmc3659779?pdf=render" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contraception</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Contraception</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0010-7824</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-02" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Average Earnings of Year-Round, Full-Time Workers by Educational Attainment: 2009</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bureau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Statistical Abstract of the United States</title>
		<editor>U.S. Census Bureau</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC: U.S. Census Bureau</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
