<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">REPUTATION TRANSMISSION WITHOUT BENEFIT TO THE REPORTER: A BEHAVIORAL UNDERPINNING OF MARKETS IN EXPERIMENTAL FOCUS</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Wiley</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-08-10">August 10, 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kenju</forename><surname>Kamei</surname></persName>
							<email>kenju.kamei@durham.ac.uk</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Louis</forename><surname>Putterman</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Economics and Finance</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Durham University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>DH1 3LB</postCode>
									<settlement>Durham</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Brown University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02912., 508</postCode>
									<settlement>Providence, Phone</settlement>
									<region>RI</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">REPUTATION TRANSMISSION WITHOUT BENEFIT TO THE REPORTER: A BEHAVIORAL UNDERPINNING OF MARKETS IN EXPERIMENTAL FOCUS</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Economic Inquiry</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Econ Inq</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0095-2583</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="158" to="172"/>
							<date type="published" when="2017-08-10">August 10, 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/ecin.12477</idno>
					<ptr type="open-access" target="http://dro.dur.ac.uk/21759/1/21759.pdf" />
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T22:11+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Reputation is a commonly cited check on opportunism, but it is often unclear what motivates an agent to report another&apos;s behavior when it is easy for the aggrieved individual to move on. In a sharply focused laboratory experiment, we find that many cooperators pay to report a defecting partner without the possibility of pecuniary benefit when this has the potential to deprive the latter of future gains and to help his next partner. We illustrate how a social preference can explain such costly reporting, and also discuss evidence for a role of emotions. (JEL C91, D03, D63) * Funding for this project came from the Murata Science Foundation, with additional support from Brown University. We wish to thank Cheewadhanaraks Matanaporn for programming of the experiment software, and Benjamin Chowdhury, Kathleen Hu, and especially Hui Wen Ng for assistance with the literature review, theoretical analysis, and data analysis. We also thank Yan Chen for her hospitality while the authors conducted the experiments at the University of Michigan, and we thank two anonymous reviewers, Pedro Dal Bó and other participants at the Brown University theory lunch, and participants at the 2015 Social Dilemmas Conference at Brown, and at the ESA World Meeting in Sydney, Australia in July 2015 for helpful comments.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. INTRODUCTION</head><p>People face many situations marked by potential benefits of cooperating with others and accompanying dangers of being exploited by them. The fact that it is sometimes possible to choose interaction partners based on their reputations for cooperativeness and that one might accordingly have an incentive to invest in such a reputation, is an oft-noted factor capable of incentivizing cooperation. But what motivates actors to transmit the required reputational information?</p><p>Both sentiment-focused moral philosophers like Adam <ref type="bibr">Smith (1761)</ref> and more recent evolutionary psychologists argue that human nature, which the latter view as having evolved during millennia of small band existence, includes innate dispositions towards cooperation. 1 Built-in inclinations that help us to overcome dilemmas of cooperation may include special interest in others' cheating, emotions of anger supporting willingness to expend resources to punish cheaters, and emotions of guilt and shame that function as self-punishments when indiscretions are not detected.</p><p>Closer to our topic of information transmission is gossip, said to account for much of human social interaction in every known culture <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Dunbar 2004)</ref>. A considerable fraction of gossip consists of reports of others' misdeeds. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Feinberg et al. (2012)</ref> report evidence that "individuals who observe an antisocial act experience negative affect and are compelled to share information</p><p>1. An accessible book-length treatment is provided by <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Pinker (2003)</ref>. Discussions by economists include <ref type="bibr">Bowles and Gintis (2011)</ref>. See also <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Gintis et al. (2005)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">Wilson (2012)</ref>. about the antisocial actor with a potentially vulnerable person," and that "individuals possessing more prosocial orientations are the most motivated to engage in such gossip, even at a personal cost" <ref type="bibr">(p. 1015)</ref>. Such information appears to have a distinct power to grab attention, and psychological normalcy includes a desire to avoid being the subject of negative gossip. <ref type="bibr">2</ref> Being the subject of negative reports may also have direct material consequences, if others hesitate to interact with individuals known for past reneging or defection. In modern economies, individuals can choose where to shop, which plumber to hire, and so forth. But the same mobility that puts potential cooperation partners in competition with each other threatens the reputational mechanism if a cost is entailed in spreading the word about an interaction partner's defection. If one has already decided to leave the untrustworthy partner behind and there is no incentive to encourage her to change, how will others learn whom to avoid? If all victims care only about own material payoffs, if they cannot profitably exchange the information, and if there is any cost associated with conveying it, then there will be no such reporting. <ref type="bibr">3</ref> However, there may be nonmaterial motivations for the costly reporting of cheating or opportunistic behavior. First, engaging in negative gossip may be a direct source of satisfaction, paralleling reports that pleasure centers in the brain are activated when experimental subjects punish selfish counterparts in a trust game <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(de Quervain et al. 2004)</ref>. Second, tipping others off not to naively cooperate with the miscreant may bring satisfaction not for the act itself but thanks to anticipation of the punishment that this may visit on that actor. The large literature showing cooperative subjects' willingness to spend money to reduce free riders' earnings in voluntary contribution experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Chaudhuri 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Falk et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Gächter and Herrmann 2009)</ref> suggests that such motives are widespread, and raises the possibility that punitive motives might also motivate reporting. Third, conceivably the victim feels empathy or obligation towards others 2. As Adam <ref type="bibr">Smith (1761)</ref> wrote: "Man naturally … dreads, not only blame, but blame-worthiness."</p><p>3. Note that in network theory (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Jackson and Zenou 2014)</ref>, the standard assumption is that while creation of links may itself be costly, information travels costlessly among those actors who are linked together, and that information is passed along by default whenever two agents are linked and the informed agent is indifferent to having transmission occur. We could locate no discussion of behavioral or social preference explanations of willingness to incur costs to transmit information, in this literature. who are in danger of being victimized, and may accordingly try to warn them.</p><p>Given the importance of reputational mechanisms to solving dilemmas of cooperation and the rapid growth of behavioral economics and social preference research using the techniques of experimental economics, one might expect the costly reporting of partners' behaviors to be the focus of numerous studies. Rather than focusing on the decision to engage in costly reporting, however, the most closely related papers have focused on the design of reputation mechanisms or the effects of information transmission. We address this gap by conducting an experiment that investigates both the willingness to pay to report an interaction partner's uncooperativeness, and subjects' beliefs about how common that willingness is. Our experimental design, which builds on familiar prisoners' dilemma stage games, allows us to isolate the willingness to engage in reporting when a personal monetary payoff is absent, so that only desires to punish the individual, to protect her future interaction partner, or to engage in information sharing for its own sake (gossip) are potential motives for reporting. We demonstrate that reporting is significantly less common when it is costly than when free, but that costly reporting does occur often. We show cooperator-defector reporting to be far more common than cooperator-cooperator, defector-cooperator, or defector-defector reporting. Indeed, a majority of cooperators meeting defectors report them despite its cost and lack of personal benefit, in our study. We identify conditions under which such reporting, and its relative frequency across behavior pairings, is consistent with an illustrative model of social preferences, the inequity aversion model of <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Fehr and Schmidt (1999)</ref>.</p><p>One condition which must be satisfied to make reporting attractive to an inequity averse agent, in our setting, is belief that a sufficient share of the population chooses cooperation. Although reporting at positive cost is never rational for strictly selfish agents in our experiment, there exist configurations of beliefs such that the same does not apply to cooperating. We conduct an incentivized elicitation of beliefs about others' cooperation and reporting, and with the resulting data we calculate which subjects could be rationally choosing or rejecting cooperation out of simple payoff maximization, and which choose cooperation (or defection) in error or due to a social preference or emotion. Almost all observed decisions to defect in the experiment are explicable by payoff maximization under own beliefs regarding others' cooperation and reporting probabilities. Rational maximization of own payoff also explains many choices to cooperate, but a substantial number of cooperation choices require alternative explanation. In addition to social preference analysis, we keep in mind that our data on reporting, especially, are compatible with more psychological explanations, and we bring to bear evidence on the role of emotions in a final portion of our discussion.</p><p>The rest of the article is organized as follows: Section II briefly summarizes related literature; Section III describes our experimental design; Section IV provides the theoretical predictions and hypotheses under both monetary payoff maximization and our illustrative social preference theory; Section V reports results; and Section VI concludes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. LITERATURE</head><p>Although many decisions to cooperate are explicable by rational and self-interested agents' believing that others' actions may be nonstandard <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Kreps et al. 1982)</ref>, decisions to engage in costly reporting are never compatible with material selfinterest in our set-up. Social preferences and emotions, as discussed for instance by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Camerer and Loewenstein (2003)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Sobel (2005)</ref>, may be required to explain such reporting, if present.</p><p>The literature on the experimental study of costly punishment, beginning with rejections in ultimatum game experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Camerer and Thaler 1995)</ref> and continuing into work on public goods games with punishment opportunities <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Fehr and Gächter 2000)</ref>, includes numerous attempts to explain actions without material benefit to the actor. Experiments find that many subjects incur a cost to punish when there can be no material benefit, and that the threat of punishment can reduce or eliminate incentives to free-ride. <ref type="bibr">4</ref> One way to understand costly punishment in such games is to see punishers as having an aversion to others free-riding or defecting while they themselves cooperate. For such individuals, imposing an earnings reduction on free riders at a monetary cost to themselves delivers 4. For example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Ertan et al. (2009)</ref>, find that ex post, individual subjects earn more the more they contribute to the public good when opportunities to engage in costly punishment are available. Reviews of the literature on punishment in voluntary contribution experiments include <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Gächter and Herrmann (2009)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Chaudhuri (2011)</ref>. a utility gain that offsets their lowered money earnings. While such punishing can be thought of as resulting from a psychological trait of negative reciprocity <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Bowles and Gintis 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Hoffman, McCabe, and Smith 1998)</ref> perhaps linked to an emotional state of anger, it might also be rationalized or rendered mathematically tractable by a simpler framework of inequity aversion <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Fehr and Schmidt 1999)</ref>.</p><p>From a structural standpoint, costly reporting and costly punishing represent different stages in a possible sequence of actions. To study punishment conditioned on contributions, <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Fehr and Gächter (2000)</ref> provided their subjects with accurate, cost free information on the contributions of individual team members, but this left unaddressed the question of how such information is obtained and shared in practice. Costly reporting or monitoring is a needed precursor to costly punishment except where effort-free mutual observability is an automatic by-product of working together. The motives underlying reporting need not be identical to those for punishment, so the decision deserves study in its own right.</p><p>Several scholars have researched costly reporting in the form of online product reviews <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Dellarocas 2003)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Resnick and Zeckhauser (2002)</ref> look at the relationship between eBay reviews and sales, as well as the prevalence of and motivation behind reviewing. They find reviewing to be frequent and suggest that the giving of feedback despite the absence of private material gain might be understood as the carrying out of a "quasi-civic duty" or as part of a "high courtesy equilibrium." <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Gregg and Scott (2006)</ref> find that eBay reviews are a major deterrent to fraud, helping to reduce asymmetry of information between buyers and sellers. <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Wang (2010)</ref> addresses the motivations behind leaving a review, specifically with respect to Yelp, a for-profit business review site. He finds strong evidence that social image and reviewer productivity are correlated. Bolton, Greiner, and Ockenfels (2013) study structural issues related to online reviews, conducting an experiment that provides evidence that negative reviews in environments like eBay can be deterred by the fear of retaliation.</p><p>But while the boom in e-commerce provides much of the impetus for recent studies of reputation formation, traditional economic interactions not amenable to the same fixes also justify attention to costly reporting. As <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Abraham et al. (2016)</ref> write, "there now exists a huge literature that aims at evaluating and designing reputation mechanisms for internet trading" but still "we know surprisingly little about the determinants which allow for the formation of reputation in economic systems." Like those authors, our main interest is in "traditional economic transactions, i.e., in environments where no mechanisms exist that make reputational information publicly available."</p><p>Abraham et al. is one of a few recent papers, including also <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Gërxhani, Brandts, and Schram (2013)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Fehr and Sutter (2016)</ref>, in which costly reporting without clear private benefit plays a part in an experiment. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Gërxhani, Brandts, and Schram (2013)</ref> study transmission of information about employee trustworthiness among employers, in one treatment making such transmissions anonymous so that direct reciprocity is ruled out as an incentive. However, their players interact in the same condition for 20 periods, which can give rise to incentives for "reputation building." 5 Also, their reporting cost is small, partly a by-product of their experiment's multiperiod structure, and they do not focus on motivations to report, including possibly asymmetric motivations to report "bad actors." <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Abraham et al. (2016)</ref> compare dyadic private information transmission at both zero and positive cost within small populations playing a series of 36 trust games. The repeated setting here too contributes to the cost of any single reporting action being quite small, and it creates incentives to build cooperation in reporting, although reporting is much less common in their experiment when costly than when free. Our paper is the first of which we are aware that studies costly reporting in a controlled setting where the reporting cost can be appreciable and private material gain is fully ruled out. 6 5. If players believe it to be widely believed that some people are "conditionally cooperative," then they may find it privately beneficial to invest in promoting such beliefs by behaving cooperatively, since this may support a "cooperative culture" within the group until "end game" behaviors set in. See, for example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Palfrey and Prisbrey (1997)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Healy (2007)</ref>, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Kamei and Putterman (2016)</ref>.</p><p>6. Another study of reporting that effectively rules out private material gain from reporting is <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Fehr and Sutter (2016)</ref>. Like us, they explicitly relate their findings to the anthropologically observed human propensity to gossip. Rather than fix the cost, they study willingness to pay to pass on a report, and find considerable willingness to spend amounts averaging about 0.3 Euro, or about 18% of what the third party earns in a period if not sending a message. But unlike in our experiment their costly reporters are third parties rather than parties to the exchanges. Whereas the third party feature is what accounts</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">FIGURE 1 Payoff Matrix Player 2 Player 1 X Y X $10, $10 $4, $11 Y $11, $4 $5, $5</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. EXPERIMENTAL DESIGN</head><p>Our experiment consists of four main treatments with opportunities to report a counterpart's decision, in three of which reporting is costly. (An additional costly reporting treatment conducted by strategy method is discussed later.) In each treatment, subjects play two one-shot prisoners' dilemma games, each with different, anonymous, randomly selected participants. The payoff structures of the first and second games are identical and of equal money value to end-of-session earnings. The payoff table of each round in U.S. dollars is summarized in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. <ref type="bibr">7</ref> A key feature of our design is that subjects decide whether to play the cooperate (denoted X) or the defect (denoted Y) option in both games at the outset. Thus, in the instructions read by the participants, we write XX (YY) to represent the cooperate (defect) option, duplicating the letter choice to indicate its play in two games. In what follows (but not in the subject instructions, which avoid such terms) we refer to a subject who chooses XX (YY) as a cooperator (defector), or occasionally XX-(YY-) chooser. Committing subjects at the outset to a single choice captures the notion that people have tendencies that they carry from interaction to interaction. Adoption of this feature simplifies both analysis and reporting decisions, since it means for absence of material benefit to the reporter, in Fehr and Sutter, it is limited repetition and perfect stranger matching that has this effect in our design.</p><p>7. Payoffs were quoted in dollars; no "lab currency" was used. While predictions for the PD game are the same over a wide range of payoff configurations, the degree of "temptation" to defect, "fear" of being defected on, and the potential to gain from mutual cooperation relative to mutual defection, are impacted by the specific payoff structure, so that conclusions from an experiment with one payoff configuration may not extend, behaviorally, to alternative payoffs. See, for instance, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Ahn et al. (2001)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Charness et al. (2016)</ref>. We made both the "temptation" and the "fear" small because we anticipated that predictions about the share of cooperators, and actual inclinations to cooperate, would thus be larger, in turn increasing reporting of defectors. that reporting, for example, a defector, can be a reliable warning about the kind of agent the next partner will encounter. Of course, we need to take into consideration that imposition of this rule affects players' strategic calculations. Accordingly, precommitment for two rounds of play should not be misconstrued as being a mechanism to force type revelation in the sense of the theoretical literature. Indeed, we will show shortly that under some beliefs, it becomes rational for a strictly self-interested agent to select XX (cooperate).</p><p>After being randomly matched with a counterpart, selecting between the two options, and being informed of the outcome of their first round interaction, each player in the reporting treatments decides whether to report the decision of her first counterpart. If a player is reported, then the second-period counterpart of the reported player is told what that player chose in the first round 8 and is given the option to change his initial choice of X or Y taking into account the report he received-this being the sole exception to the rule that an initial choice is binding for two rounds of play. Subjects know that they will certainly not play the game a second time with the same counterpart, so reporting in the hope that one might oneself be the beneficiary of the information is ruled out. The counterpart will also be told whether she was reported on by her initial partner, which determines whether the player whose initial choice was reported to her is in a position to select a new action. 9 For example, consider two players, A and B. Suppose that both A and B are paired with other randomly assigned partners (not each other) in the first game. Suppose also that A chooses XX (cooperate) and B chooses YY (defect). Now imagine that B's first round partner decides to report her (B's) decision to B's second interaction partner, namely A. Since B was reported, A has a chance to change his initial choice from X to Y so as to avoid being exploited by B. A is also free to stick to the choice of X. Suppose, finally, that A (the cooperator) is not reported by his initial partner. A is thus informed that B has no opportunity to 8. That is, the computer delivers a truthful report. The potential issues of deciding whether to report truthfully and whether to believe a report that has been received are thus eliminated as concerns. We discuss the impact of this simplifying element in the conclusion. 9. To preserve maximum anonymity among the subjects in the experiment, those who had no opportunity to change their own choice were asked to answer a trivia question bearing no relation to the experiment, to keep number of computer clicks consistent across all those in the lab. change her choice, so A knows with certainty that B is playing Y in his interaction with her. In this example, A knows that switching to Y will protect him with certainty and that the choice would carry no danger of foregoing a mutual cooperation payoff.</p><p>As another example, consider a cooperator (XX-chooser) C who learns that her second counterpart D had selected XX and has no opportunity to change his decision (C's initial counterpart did not report C's choice). C may wish to switch to Y to exploit D, but might decide to stick with X in order to avoid feeling guilty, experiencing disutility from advantageous inequality, and so on. In the otherwise similar situation in which D can change his choice, C would have that information and would need to factor in her belief about the likelihood of D changing to Y (which may in turn be influenced by D's belief about the likelihood of C switching). <ref type="bibr">10</ref> To check sensitivity of reporting to its cost, we vary it across treatments. A reporting cost of $1, $0.50, $0.05, and $0 is present in the high-cost (HC), mediumcost (MC), low-cost (LC), and no-cost (NC) treatments, respectively. <ref type="bibr">11</ref> Subjects are also asked, after their own choice of XX or YY, for their beliefs about the percentage of their peers choosing XX, and-after their reporting decisions-for their beliefs about the percentages of defectors and of cooperators who will be reported. The elicited beliefs extend our ability to explore possible motivations behind subjects' decisions. So as not to raise its salience too much, we do not tell subjects about the presence of the belief elicitation tasks before they make the corresponding 10. While our design is one of finite repetition, we view the question addressed-that of lack of monetary incentive to engage in costly reporting-as relevant also to a world of indefinitely repeated interactions, since agents in such environments may also periodically need to seek new interaction partners and may avoid dealing again with an individual found to be opportunistic, but have no selfish material motive for incurring a cost to convey the information to others, especially when interacting in a population so large that inducing reciprocal reporting from others is not a plausible motive. Having only two interactions makes practical relatively large stakes in the lab for each interaction, while the fact that the report affects only one future interaction makes the motivational problem more challenging by limiting the punishment that reporting can inflict.</p><p>11. We suspected that a cost of $1 would suffice to deter many from reporting in the context of an experiment with expected total earnings in the neighborhood of $15 to $25, thought we might see more reporting with that cost halved, and we included the much lower cost $0.05 in case substantial reporting were forthcoming only at a more trivial cost. We included zero cost to observe the inclination to report when cost is not a factor. choices. Subjects are asked for their expectations regarding behaviors of other participants only (themselves not included), to avoid hedging. Eliciting beliefs is incentivized by offering a $1 bonus payment for guesses that are within 5 percentage points of the actual percentage. At the end of their session, subjects are also asked about emotions potentially affecting their reporting decisions: (1) their level of anger toward their initial partners and (2) their feelings of obligation to help the third party in the second round via reporting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. THEORETICAL PREDICTIONS WITHOUT AND WITH SOCIAL PREFERENCES</head><p>Although our main focus is on costly reporting, we discuss here predictions of subject decisions with regard to both the cooperating and reporting decision, since each may be conditioned by beliefs about the other. We begin with the extreme assumption of strictly selfish preferences, rationality, and common knowledge (SRC), then relax the common knowledge assumption to allow for beliefs that some may be otherwise motivated, and finally relax the selfish preference assumption to allow that the decisionmaker herself may have a social preference capable of explaining actual costly reporting and some decisions to cooperate contrary to material self-interest. We leave consideration of emotional factors to be discussed when we view the experimental results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Common Knowledge of Rationality and Self-Interest</head><p>The standard theory predictions in the experiment (with SRC) are straightforward. In the HC, MC, and LC treatments, it is never payoffenhancing to report, since reporting is costly and players are never matched with the same partner twice. Even if there were to be reporting, which subjects could randomly choose to do in the NC treatment, YY would remain the predicted first choice and Y the free second choice of those receiving reports, thus having no impact on how the PD games themselves are played.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HYPOTHESES WITH SELF-INTEREST, RATIONALITY AND COMMON KNOWLEDGE (H-SRC)</head><p>In the HC, MC, and LC treatments, each subject chooses not to pay to report choices of her first interaction partner, while reporting occurs randomly in the NC treatment. Subjects in all treatments choose YY (defect). A subject having the opportunity to make a free second choice (which, by the above, occurs only in the NC treatment) always selects Y.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Dropping Common Knowledge</head><p>Even if a subject is strictly self-interested and rational, belief that others might behave prosocially and/or that others believe such types exist can lead to a different choice over XX versus YY. Let a i be the fraction of subjects that i believes will cooperate (select XX), b i the fraction she believes will report a cooperating counterpart, and c i the fraction she believes will report a defecting one (0 ≤ a i , b i , c i ≤ 1). We solve for the conditions under which i selects XX or YY under assumptions representing two ends of a continuum of beliefs i might have about free second game choices; we call the two beliefs "pessimistic" and "optimistic," respectively. If pessimistic, i assumes that an individual free to revise her second choice always selects Y, in line with self-interest, whereas if optimistic, i assumes that cooperatively-oriented participants (XX-choosers) will stick with X given an opportunity to make a fresh choice, provided that they are informed that they are meeting another subject who chose XX. <ref type="bibr">12</ref> As shown in Section A.1 in Appendix S1, Supporting Information, under the pessimistic second game belief, we obtain:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">selfish player i cooperates (defects) if (1) 5a i ( c i − b i ) + c i &gt; 2 (≤ 2) .</formula><p>By contrast, under the optimistic second game belief, as shown in Section A.2 in Appendix S1, we obtain:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">selfish player i cooperates (defects) if (1 ′ ) 5a i c i + a i b i + c i &gt; 2 (≤ 2) .</formula><p>A higher fraction of subjects chooses to cooperate based on criterion (1 ′ ) compared with criterion (1).</p><p>12. Clearly the "optimistic" assumption is strong in that it eschews distinctions based on whether the XXchooser being met with can also change her choice. Its optimism is nonetheless bounded in that YY-choosers free to revise their second choice are still assumed always to stick to Y. Our data show that some (but not all) cooperators stick to cooperation when having the report of meeting a cooperator, but no defector switches to cooperation in this situation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HYPOTHESES ALLOWING FOR BELIEF IN SOCIAL PREFERENCES AMONG OTHERS (H-SPO)</head><p>If i is a material payoff maximizer, but believes that others might cooperate and pay to report <ref type="bibr">(cooperators, defectors)</ref> with probabilities a i , b i , and c i ≥ 0, then i will never pay to report her first interaction partner, and will randomly report or not report if reporting is cost free. Subject i will choose cooperation (defection) if 5a i (c i − b i ) + c i &gt; 2 (≤2), assuming that i has "pessimistic" beliefs about cooperators' free second choices, and will choose cooperation (defection) if 5a i c i + a i b i + c i &gt; 2 (≤2), assuming that i has "optimistic" beliefs about those choices. 13</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Social Preferences and Decisions to Report</head><p>Unlike cooperating, costly reporting can never be optimal for an agent aiming to maximize own monetary payoff. Explaining its occurrence thus requires error, emotion, or nontraditional elements in the utility function. We illustrate how the latter can work if the potential reporter i has the inequity-averse preferences proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Fehr and Schmidt (1999)</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">u i ( π i |π j ) = π i − α i • max { π j − π i , 0 } (2) − β i • max { π i − π j , 0 } ,</formula><p>where α i ≥ β i ≥ 0, meaning that aversion to inequality that is unfavorable to the decisionmaker (reflected in weight α i ) is at least as strong as that to favorable inequality (reflected in weight β i ), and that the decision-maker never values the latter ("aheadness") for its own sake (β i takes no negative values). Also assume that β i &lt; 1. There are four possible situations under which reporting might occur:</p><p>Case 1: subject i cooperates and learns that her counterpart has also cooperated.</p><p>Case 2: subject i cooperates and learns that her counterpart has defected.</p><p>Case 3: subject i defects and learns that her counterpart has cooperated.</p><p>Case 4: subject i defects and learns that her counterpart has also defected.</p><p>13. Note that by writing conditions (1) and (1 ′ ) as shown, we assume that subjects whose beliefs render them rationally indifferent between XX and YY will select the latter, if strictly self-interested. This means that when analyzing our experiment results in Section V, we place the few cases in which (1) or (1 ′ ) hold with exact equality in the set of observations for which an observed choice of XX requires a social preference explanation.</p><p>For simplicity, we assume that the only other individual, j, whose payoff π j affects u i if α i (and perhaps β i ) &gt; 0, is the first interaction partner of decision-maker i, with respect to whom i's decision to engage in reporting is made. 14 Then it can be shown (details are in Section A.4 in Appendix S1) that costly reporting will occur: in Case 1 if 6a i &gt; ρ, (α + β) b i -β &gt; 0 and (3a)</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">( 6a i -ρ ) &gt; ρ∕ [ (α + β) b i -β ] (3b) in Case 2 if ( 6a i -ρ ) &gt; ρ∕α in Case 4 if 6a i &gt; ρ, (α + β) c i -β &gt; 0 and (3c) ( 6a i -ρ ) &gt; ρ∕ [ (α + β) c i -β ]</formula><p>where ρ is the reporting cost. <ref type="bibr">15</ref> The analysis in Supporting Information shows that the conditions for Cases 2 and 4 hold regardless of whether i applies the pessimistic or the optimistic assumption about free second choices, whereas the condition for Case 1 applies only when i makes the pessimistic assumption; if she makes the optimistic assumption instead, i will never pay to report. As for Case 3, the analysis indicates that a defector i will never report a cooperating counterpart if β i &lt; 1, as assumed above. Even if some individuals have unusually high β values, the individuals in question would be unlikely to be defectors (see Section IV.D), so costly reporting of cooperators by defectors will rarely if ever occur. Condition (3b) indicates that the more averse to disadvantageous inequality is the cooperator (the higher her α i ), the more others she believes to have chosen to cooperate (the higher her a i ), and the lower is the reporting cost ρ, the more likely she is to report a defector. Aversion to advantageous inequality, β, plays no role in this decision. In addition, the condition implies that all inequity-averse cooperators report defectors at zero cost (in the NC treatment), as long as a i &gt; 0.</p><p>14. i's potential concern for j's next partner, whom i may wish to warn or at least inform of j's type, is a plausible additional concern that we discuss later. The simple Fehr-Schmidt model also abstracts from explicit considerations of reciprocity <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Rabin 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Charness and Rabin 2002)</ref> and concern for others' intentions <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Cox et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Dufwenberg and Kirchsteiger 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Falk and Fischbacher 2006)</ref> as such. Finally, unlike Saito (2013), we assume that the decisionmaker cares only about ex ante expected differences (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Brock et al. 2013 and</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Kamei 2016)</ref>.</p><p>15. i is indifferent between reporting and not reporting if the right hand inequality in each line holds instead with the equals operator. i (subscripts on alpha and beta) omitted in (3) to conserve space. These conditions suggest that if distributions of types (that is, of α and β values) are not different in each case, then the threshold belief a i required for costly reporting is lowest for Case 2. <ref type="bibr">16</ref> In conditions (3a) and (3c), there is also the further implication that costly reporting is conditional on the belief that others do it (a cooperator [defector] is more likely to report another cooperator [defector] if she has a high belief b i [c i ]). As for relative frequency of reporting in Cases 1 and 4, the two conditions show reporting to be more likely in Case 4 than Case 1 if c i &gt; b i , an intuitively appealing idea that turns out to be strongly supported by our experimental data. Adding to this the finding that reporting is not predicted for any individual making the optimistic assumption about free second choices, we arrive at the implication that, assuming sufficient variation of belief a i not systematically linked to preference type, costly reporting should be most common in the case of cooperators meeting defectors (Case 2), with the cases of defectors meeting defectors (Case 4) and cooperators meeting cooperators (Case 1) following in that order.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HYPOTHESES ON REPORTING DECI-SIONS WITH INEQUITY-AVERSE SOCIAL PREFERENCES (H-R-SP) (i) Costly reporting due to inequity averse preferences is most likely in the case of a cooperator meeting a defector, followed by the case of a defector meeting a defector, with reporting of cooperators by cooperators still less common and that of cooperators by defectors rarely if ever occurring; (ii) defectors (cooperators)</head><p>are more likely to report their defector (cooperator) counterpart the greater the share of others they believe report (the greater is their belief c i [b i ]); (iii) the higher is belief a i , and the lower is reporting cost ρ, the larger the share of individuals who will engage in costly reporting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Social Preferences, Beliefs, and Decisions to Cooperate</head><p>Although decisions to cooperate can occur without a social preference, as shown above, having a social preference may cause an agent for whom neither (1) nor (1 ′ ) holds to nonetheless select X (XX). Using again inequity-averse utility function (2) for purposes of illustration, assuming beliefs a i , b i , and c i , and adopting in turn the pessimistic and optimistic beliefs about free second choices, we work out conditions for cooperation <ref type="bibr">16</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">Notice that α − [(α + β)b i − β] = (α + β)(1 − b i ) ≥ 0. α − [(α + β)c i − β] = (α + β)(1 − c i ) ≥ 0.</formula><p>in Section A.3 in Appendix S1, and simply summarize here the conclusion:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">HYPOTHESIS ON COOPERATING WITH INEQUITY-AVERSE SOCIAL PREFERENCES (H-C-SP)</formula><p>A subject i who has inequity-averse preferences will be more likely to choose XX the more others she expects to cooperate (the higher her belief a i ), the more averse to advantageous inequality she is (higher β i ), and the less averse to disadvantageous inequality she is (lower α i ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V. RESULTS AND ANALYSIS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Overview of the Experiment</head><p>A total of 172 students (152 in the four main reporting treatments and 20 in the strategy method treatment) participated in ten experiment sessions in 2013 and 2014 at the University of Michigan. 17 Among them, 58.7% of subjects (101) were female. No subject participated in more than one session, and the sessions lasted about an hour on average, about half of this time being spent on reading of instructions and answering comprehension questions. The experiment was programmed in z-tree <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Fischbacher 2007)</ref>. All instructions (for the example of the LC treatment, see Supporting Information) were neutrally framed, avoiding terms such as "cooperate," "trust," and so on. Subjects had to answer a number of control questions (see the instructions) to confirm their understanding of the experiment. Communication between subjects was not permitted. Average earnings were $20.84, including a $5 participation fee, with a standard deviation of $4.16. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> summarizes key subject behaviors and beliefs, with panels (A) (at left), (B) (upper right), and (C) lower right displaying cooperation decisions, decisions to report defectors, and decisions to report cooperators, respectively. We begin with our main focus, costly reporting. A glance at panel (B) makes clear that there was much costly reporting, but overwhelmingly reporting of defectors by cooperators, as predicted. Focusing on the left panel of 17. Sessions were conducted by Kamei while he was Assistant Professor at Bowling Green State University. All subjects were recruited from the University of Michigan experimental lab's subject pool using solicitation messages via ORSEE (Online Recruitment System for Economic Experiments). We aimed to recruit 20 participants to each session, but actual numbers varied somewhat due to differing show-up rates, averaging 17.2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FIGURE 2</head><p>Choices of XX or YY, Reporting Decisions, and Beliefs: (A) % of Choosing XX, (B) % of Reporting YY, and (C) % of Reporting XX  <ref type="figure">Figure 2B</ref>, we see that some 45%-65% of cooperators who encountered a defector chose to report when costly, and that reporting occurred considerably more often (almost 90% report) at cost zero (NC treatment) than at positive costs (an overall average of 58.6% report in LC, MC, and HC). The remainder of this panel and the panel below it, in <ref type="figure">Figure 2C</ref>, show that there is also some, but considerably less, costly reporting of cooperators by cooperators and of defectors by defectors, and no costly reporting of cooperators by defectors. Overall, an average of 8.0% of subjects in the cooperator-cooperator, defectorcooperator, and defector-defector situations choose to report.</p><p>RESULT 1. (a) Costly reporting of defectors by cooperators is common (almost 59% report); (b) costly reporting in other cases is significantly less common (overall, 8%); (c) there is significantly less reporting at a positive than at a zero cost. These results are consistent with H-R-SP.</p><p>Turning to cooperation decisions and expectations, <ref type="figure">Figure 2A</ref> shows that regardless of the presence of reporting costs and their size if present, around 50%-60% of the subjects choose XX in each of the main treatments. <ref type="bibr">18</ref> The diamonds and triangles in the same panel indicate that cooperators' average expectation regarding the fraction of others who would choose cooperation was significantly higher (around 70%) than that of defectors (around 40%). The difference is highly significant (p &lt; .001, see <ref type="table">Table B</ref>.4 in Appendix S2). With respect to reporting, the right side of panel (B) shows that the average cooperator believed more defectors would be reported than did the average defector, a difference significant for LC subjects and in all costly reporting treatments pooled (p &lt; .001, see <ref type="table">Table B</ref>.4 in Appendix S2).</p><p>The displayed frequencies of cooperation and reporting are clearly inconsistent with H-SRC, which, based on the assumption of rational selfish individuals with common knowledge, predicts neither costly reporting nor cooperation. 19</p><p>18. The fractions of cooperators are not significantly different between any two treatments, according to two-sided, two-sample tests of proportions. See panel (C) of <ref type="table">Table B.1 in  Appendix S2.</ref> 19. We performed binomial probability tests for the conservative null hypothesis that the probability of choosing XX equals 5%, assuming that errors occur with a probability of 5%. This hypothesis was rejected in each treatment. We also performed binomial probability tests for the conservative null hypothesis that the probability that cooperators report the initial choices of their defecting partners equals 5%, assuming</p><p>We now discuss in more detail the reporting decisions, considering in Section V.B their consistency with the illustrative social preference model discussed above, and discussing evidence for a role of emotions in Section V.C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Predicting Reporting Decisions with Inequity-Averse Preferences</head><p>In the three treatments in which reporting is costly, 58.6% of cooperators meeting defectors, 16.6% of defectors meeting defectors, 8.8% of cooperators meeting cooperators, and 0% of defectors meeting cooperators, pay the cost to report their counterpart, an ordering of frequencies exactly matching part (i) of H-R-SP. <ref type="bibr">20</ref> We use again the Fehr-Schmidt model to illustrate the ease or difficulty of predicting reporting choices with a model of social preference. Although we can't identify individual utility function parameters in order to predict which subjects will report their counterparts, as an exercise we estimate the proportion who would be expected to report based on conditions (3a), (3b), and (3c), and selfreported beliefs a i , b i , and c i if we assume that each subject has the same likelihood of belonging to each of the four preference types identified and assigned estimated population proportions by Fehr and Schmidt, in precisely those proportions. <ref type="bibr">21</ref> These calculations imply that about 68.9% of the cooperators who encountered defectors, 13.5% of the cooperators who encountered cooperators, and 14.2% of the defectors who encountered defectors would engage in reporting at the costs obtaining in their treatments given their beliefs and the prevalence of each type. These predicted shares are rather similar to the shares actually reporting, the similar differences between the high share for Case 2 reporting and the low shares for Cases 1 and 4, in estimate and reality, being especially remarkable.</p><p>We can also estimate multivariate regressions to check for patterns consistent with the reporting that errors occur with a probability of 5%. This hypothesis was also rejected in each treatment. See <ref type="table">Table B.2 in  Appendix S2.</ref> 20. The percentage of defectors being reported by cooperators is significantly larger than the percentage being reported in the other action pairings according to two-sample z-tests of proportions using pooled data of the three costly reporting treatments (see panel B.2 of <ref type="table">Table B</ref>.1 in Appendix S2).</p><p>21. Specifically, Fehr and Schmidt estimate that about 30% of individuals have α = β = 0, about 30% have α = .5, β = .25, 30% have α = 1, β = .6, and 10% have α = 4, β = .6. See also <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> in <ref type="bibr">Fehr and Schmidt (2010)</ref>. conditions of inequalities (3a)-(3c). In <ref type="table">Table B</ref>.8 in Appendix S2, we show estimates of simple linear regressions to predict reporting, where the independent variables are the values of the three beliefs and two treatment dummies to control for reporting cost. The regressions for Cases 1 and 4 show partial consistency with conditions (3a) and (3c) in that the belief variables b i and c i obtain positive and significant coefficients in their respective estimates. These coefficients suggest a sort of "conditional cooperativeness" with respect to reporting: the higher the fraction of others a subject believes report a player who behaves like her counterpart (one who cooperates, in Case 1, one who defects, in Case 4), the more likely that the subject herself pays to report. The estimate for Case 2 suggests a similar sort of conditionality: among cooperators who meet a defector, those believing that a higher share of defectors are reported are themselves more likely to report. <ref type="bibr">22</ref> The estimated coefficients on the expected share cooperating (a i ) and on treatment dummy variables are insignificant (in one case marginally significant), however, failing to support expectations (based on conditions (3a)-(3c)) that frequency of reporting would be increasing in a i and decreasing in ρ. 23 H-R-SP is supported, with respect to the relationship between cost and reporting frequency, insofar as there is far more reporting at a cost of zero than at a positive cost, in general, and more reporting at zero cost than at each specific positive cost taken individually (see panels (A) and (B) of <ref type="table">Table  B</ref>.1 in Appendix S2). 24 A finer-scale correlation between reporting cost and reporting incidence is also found insofar as subjects' self-reported 22. There have been numerous behavioral findings of tendency to perform a pro-social or cooperative act conditional on beliefs that others do so, for example, <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Fischbacher and Gächter (2010)</ref> for conditional contributing in public goods games and <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Kamei (2014)</ref> for conditional costly punishing in public goods games with punishment opportunities.</p><p>23. Failure of belief a i to obtain a significant positive coefficient, whereas c i obtains one, in the regression for the Case 2 data, is inconsistent with condition (3b), which implies that a i rather than c i should be significant. The estimated coefficient on a i is insignificant even in specifications that exclude b i and c i terms.</p><p>24. The fact that reporting is far greater at zero cost than at a money cost as low as $0.05 might reflect a "mental accounting" distinction between money and time costs, or a peculiarity of the zero cost as discussed, for example, by <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Shampanier et al. (2007)</ref>. This suggests that there could be a substantial number of individuals willing to provide online reviews with what they treat psychologically as spare time, but who would be deterred if even a small monetary cost were involved.</p><p>expectations are ones of greater reporting in treatments with lower reporting cost <ref type="table">(Table B</ref>.4 in Appendix S2), but between the different positive costs there is no correlation with actual reporting frequency. <ref type="bibr">25</ref> RESULT 2. (i) The percentages of subjects engaging in costly reporting are well predicted using Fehr and Schmidt's estimates of the prevalence and strength of aversion to disadvantageous inequality and our subjects' self-reported beliefs about frequency of cooperation. Specifically, costly reporting of defectors by cooperators is by far the most frequent case, with costly reporting of cooperators by defectors (predicted to occur rarely if ever) not observed and reporting in the remaining two cases relatively infrequent. (ii) Sensitivity of reporting to its cost is supported by significantly more reporting at cost 0 than at costs $0.05, $0.50, and $1.00, and by close correlation between expectations of others' reporting and specific reporting cost.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Reporting and Emotions</head><p>Whereas social preference models like that of Fehr and Schmidt assume rational calculation of utility maximizing choices subject to socially interdependent preferences, observed reporting may sometimes have more emotional underpinnings. We turn to evidence that emotions played a part in our subjects' decisions.</p><p>Our first source of evidence that emotions helped to trigger some of the observed costly reporting is an additional treatment that resembles the MC treatment in all respects except that rather than having subjects decide whether to report their initial counterpart's choice after learning what that choice was, they are asked to decide in advance whether to send a costly report if the participant with whom they are matched turns out to have selected XX, and likewise whether to send a report if their counterpart 25. We note that insensitivity to reporting cost within the range studied by us is consistent with Fehr and Schmidt's assumptions. Specifically, calculations show that with the frequencies of types (α i , β i settings, see footnote 21) assumed by those authors, little sensitivity to reporting cost is predicted within the range of our treatments. For example, calculations predict that 70% of cooperators will report a defector in both treatments LC and MC, with a drop only to 66.7% predicted to report defectors in HC. Of course, the insensitivity of reporting frequency to cost in our data may be more a quirk of small numbers than a fundamental finding. turns out to have selected YY. <ref type="bibr">26</ref> Of the 20 subjects that participated in this strategy method session, 11 selected XX, similar to the 50% share in the MC treatment. Thanks to the set-up, we got decisions from all 11 about whether they would report if meeting a YY-chooser. Only 2 of the 11 (i.e., 18%) chose to pay the required $0.50 to report their first counterpart if that person chose YY. In the MC treatment, with the same payoffs and cost but a sequential design in which subjects first learned the actual decision of their assigned counterpart, there were nine who chose XX and learned the counterpart had chosen YY, and six of them chose to engage in costly reporting upon learning of their counterpart's action, that is, 66.7%. A two-sided twosample z test of proportions says that the 18% and 66.7% proportions are statistically significantly different from each other (p = .028). The substantial difference suggests that "hot" emotion <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Loewenstein 2000)</ref> may have played a role in reporting in our main treatments.</p><p>Other evidence for a role of emotions comes from the survey that all subjects in the main treatments completed following their decisions. Subjects were asked-following all decisions, so as not to contaminate them-to state how pleased or angry they felt about their first counterpart's decision, and how much (if any) sense of obligation they felt to help their first counterpart's next partner. The answers to the anger question indicate that the greatest amount of anger was felt by cooperators who encountered defectors in their first interaction. Self-reported anger is always significantly less for subjects in other pairings-XX meets XX, YY meets XX, and YY meets YY. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3A</ref> shows that among the cooperators who encountered defectors, average self-reported anger towards the counterpart is significantly higher (p = .04) for those who chose to report than for those who did not choose to report. Thus, the strength of anger could have been a factor prompting decisions to report, although the ex post nature of the answers gives reason for caution. 27 26. These reporting decisions were taken after each subject had made her own choice between XX and YY and had indicated what percentage of others she expected would choose XX. Following the reporting decisions, subjects stated their beliefs about others' reporting decisions under each contingency. To minimize the impact of the expectation elicitation processes, subjects were not informed in advance of the fact that expectations were to be elicited, as in our other treatments.</p><p>27. The anger variable is a subject's response to the question: "How did you feel about your first counterpart's RESULT 3. Indications that emotions played a part in costly reporting consist of (i) a significantly smaller share of cooperators choosing to report defectors in a strategy method treatment than in the corresponding sequential treatment, and (ii) a significantly higher self-report of anger towards a defector by reporting than by nonreporting cooperators.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Obligation, Altruism, and Normative Motives for Reporting</head><p>The postdecision exit survey is consistent with presence of another potential motive for a cooperator to report a defecting counterpart: a desire or sense of obligation to help that individual's next partner (say k) avoid being exploited. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3B</ref> shows that more than 50% of those actually reporting indicate having felt an obligation to help k, versus less than 25% of those not reporting. <ref type="bibr">28</ref> Self-reported feelings of obligation to help are much smaller in the XX-meets-XX, YYmeets-YY, and YY-meets-XX cases (see <ref type="figure">Figure  B</ref>.1 in Appendix S2).</p><p>Although a social preference model might also attach value to helping k, we did not include this motive in our simple illustration using the Fehr-Schmidt model because, with its focus on inequalities and inattention to intentions and other sources of deservingness, that model predicts reporting to help this third party (the counterpart's next partner) only under a narrow range of cases. An alternative explanation, in which reporting to help k is motivated by belief that cooperators not only cooperate but report conditional on others doing the same, is discussed in Supporting Information and is consistent with Table B.8's finding that for every 1% increase in the proportion of subjects whom i believed would report a YY-chooser, there is an 0.84% increase in i's likelihood of reporting a YY-chooser oneself, consistent with conditional cooperation. decision? Please rate on a scale from 1 = very pleased to 7 = very angry." That many people view defecting against a cooperating partner as grossly unfair is suggested by the fact that more than half of unaffected third parties chose to incur a cost to punish a unilateral defector in a laboratory experiment by <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Fehr and Fischbacher (2004)</ref>.</p><p>28. The obligation to help variable is a subject's response to the question: "Did you feel a sense of obligation to help your first counterpart's next counterpart by sending a report? Please rate on a scale from 1 = did not feel obligated at all, to 7 = felt strongly obligated." Notes: p values indicate Mann-Whitney test results (two-sided). The Anger variable is a subject's response to the following question: "How did you feel about your first counterpart's decision? Please rate on a scale from 1 = very pleased to 7 = very angry." The Obligation variable is a subject's response to the following question: "Did you feel a sense of obligation to help your first counterpart's next counterpart by sending a report? Please rate on a scale from 1 = did not feel obligated at all, to 7 = felt strongly obligated." ***Significant at 1% level; **significant at 5% level; *significant at 10% level.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. What Accounts for Cooperation and Defection?</head><p>Although decisions to engage in costly reporting are our focus, we briefly report here to what degree decisions to cooperate or defect are explicable by self-interest given beliefs about others' choices (see <ref type="table">Table B</ref>.3 in Appendix S2 for the details). We also discuss briefly whether the Fehr-Schmidt model can account for instances of cooperation that are inconsistent with self-interest, given beliefs.</p><p>A substantial majority of choices between cooperation and defection-63.8% with the pessimistic second game belief, 79.6% with the optimistic belief-are consistent with self-interested rationality. Specifically, assuming each subject's self-reported beliefs to be those on which she in fact conditioned her decision, criterion (1) correctly predicts about 64% of choices between XX and YY, and criterion (1 ′ ) about 80%, meaning that a selfish rational subject would have chosen as the subject in question did in almost two thirds (80%) of cases, if she were pessimistically (optimistically) assuming that all free second choices by XX-choosers are Y (X). However, while 90% or more of decisions to defect are consistent with self-interest under the pessimistic assumption in each treatment, the proportion of XX choices that are consistent with self-interest is considerably smaller: 26.1% (43.5%), 31.6% (63.2%), 61.9% (90.5%), and 43.5% (78.3%) of cooperators had beliefs making cooperating payoff-maximizing under the pessimistic (optimistic) belief in the HC, MC, LC, and NC treatments, respectively. In all, H-SPO is capable of accounting for many decisions to cooperate, but still leaves either the majority or a substantial minority of those decisions unexplained, depending on what the subject was assuming about others' second game choices.</p><p>Can the latter decisions to cooperate be explained by a simple social preference, for example, the one used illustratively by us? Leaving details to Supporting Information, we find that only a small fraction of the cooperators whose stated beliefs failed to selfishly dictate cooperation under even the optimistic assumption-specifically, about 12%-would have chosen to cooperate out of inequity averse utility maximization given the frequencies of α and β values assumed by <ref type="bibr">Fehr and Schmidt (2010)</ref>. Many of the remaining cooperation choices can be explained by aversion to advantageous inequality, but the majority of these cases are consistent with the Fehr-Schmidt model only at degrees of aversion to advantageous relative to disadvantageous inequality that exceed the levels assumed in Fehr and Schmidt's typology. Put differently, the decision-makers in question must strongly wish to avoid defecting against a cooperator and be willing to take a substantial risk of being defected against, equivalent to having β &gt; α in the Fehr-Schmidt model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI. CONCLUSION</head><p>Numerous studies have focused on the roles social preferences and emotions may play in accounting for decisions favorable to social welfare but lacking benefit to the actor. Surprisingly, the potentially costly act of transmitting information has received little attention. A preferenceor emotion-triggered tendency to report at some cost to oneself could be indispensable to social efficiency in situations in which individuals have the option of simply leaving behind undesirable interaction partners without incurring the time, effort or cost to warn others about them. Inclinations to engage in reporting-perhaps closely related to the anthropological and psychological identification of gossip as a human universal-may be crucial to the viability of many reputation-based incentive systems.</p><p>Our experiment underscores the fact that reputation formation may involve costs to those sharing or transmitting the information on which reputational knowledge is based, and it illustrates how laboratory experiments can enhance our understanding of the motivations relevant to decisions to bear such costs. We simplified the problem by assuming that whatever information is transmitted is accurate, and that the recipient knows this to be so with certainty. Although the complications introduced when the message transmitted is a free choice of the reporter and when the recipient must accordingly decide whether to place trust in it require further research, a body of emerging results provides some assurance that most of our findings are likely to hold in such an environment as well. 29 <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Fonseca and Peters (2015)</ref>, who find that the preponderance of reports about the trustworthiness of trust game players are truthful, and that the availability of such reports raises efficiency. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Abraham et al. (2016)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Fehr and Sutter (2016)</ref> permit false reports but find few, with Abraham et al. stating "ratings typically provide a true account" and Fehr and Sutter stating "it turned out that only a small fraction of gossip contains wrong information." In both experiments, subjects appear to act upon reports presuming their truthfulness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="29.">A recent example is</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Hypothesis on Cooperating with Inequity-Averse Social Preferences H-R-SP: Hypotheses on Reporting Decisions with Inequity-Averse Social Preferences H-SPO: Hypotheses Allowing for Belief in Social Preferences among Others H-SRC: Hypotheses with Self-Interest, Rationality and Common Knowledge LC: Low Cost MC: Medium Cost NC: No Cost SRC: Strictly Selfish Preferences, Rationality, and Common Knowledge</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIGURE 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Average Anger Level and Average Feeling of Obligation to Help Third Party k who report YY-choosers XX-choosers who do not report YY-choosers p = .0009***</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUPPORTING INFORMATION</head><p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the online version of this article:</p><p>Appendix S1. Theoretical analysis Appendix S2. Additional tables and figures Appendix S3. Instructions for the LC treatment</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reputation formation in economic transactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Abraham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Veronika</forename><surname>Grimm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Christina</forename><surname>Neeß</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Seebauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jebo.2015.10.010</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Behavior &amp; Organization</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Economic Behavior &amp; Organization</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0167-2681</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-01" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cooperation in PD Games: Fear, Greed, and History of Play</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ostrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Shupp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Public Choice</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Engineering Trust: Reciprocity in the Production of Reputation Information</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gary</forename><surname>Bolton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ben</forename><surname>Greiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Axel</forename><surname>Ockenfels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1287/mnsc.1120.1609</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://research.economics.unsw.edu.au/RePEc/papers/2009-02.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Management Science</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Management Science</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0025-1909</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1526-5501</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-02" />
			<publisher>Institute for Operations Research and the Management Sciences (INFORMS)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The evolution of strong reciprocity: cooperation in heterogeneous populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Samuel</forename><surname>Bowles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Herbert</forename><surname>Gintis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tpb.2003.07.001</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">14642341</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theoretical Population Biology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Theoretical Population Biology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0040-5809</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-02" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A Cooperative Species: Human Reciprocity and its Evolution</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Princeton, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dictating the Risk: Experimental Evidence on Giving in Risky Environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Michelle</forename><surname>Brock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Lange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Erkut</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Ozbay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/aer.103.1.415</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/95d2/1b9cb51b06e1294336f4b40c51f30bf70c9a.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">American Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-8282</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="415" to="437" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-02" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Behavioral Game Theory Experiments and Modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Colin</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Camerer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Teck-Hua</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/b978-0-444-53766-9.00010-0</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://faculty.haas.berkeley.edu/hoteck/PAPERS/Camerer-Ho-Book.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Game Theory with Economic Applications</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="517" to="573" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Behavioral Economics: Past, Present, and Future</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Camerer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Loewenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Behavioral Economics</title>
		<editor>C. Camerer, G. Lowenstein, and M. Rabin</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Princeton, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anomalies: Ultimatums, Dictators and Manners</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Colin</forename><surname>Camerer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Richard</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Thaler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/jep.9.2.209</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://authors.library.caltech.edu/22127/1/2138174%5B1%5D.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Perspectives</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Economic Perspectives</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0895-3309</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-05" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding Social Preferences with Simple Tests</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Charness</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rabin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1162/003355302760193904</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-R9M396XK-T</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">1D9991D2FCC8CAC47ACCF27444A3252777B7C05D</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://escholarship.org/content/qt0dc3k4m5/qt0dc3k4m5.pdf?t=lnqjgj" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0033-5533</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1531-4650</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="817" to="869" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-08-01" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social surplus determines cooperation rates in the one-shot Prisoner&apos;s Dilemma</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gary</forename><surname>Charness</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Luca</forename><surname>Rigotti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Aldo</forename><surname>Rustichini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.geb.2016.08.010</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Games and Economic Behavior</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Games and Economic Behavior</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0899-8256</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-11" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sustaining cooperation in laboratory public goods experiments: a selective survey of the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ananish</forename><surname>Chaudhuri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10683-010-9257-1</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/VQC-3D7CK7X2-K</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">D8C705D7D062F01F0D6FB79532D7B124FA175FA7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Experimental Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Exp Econ</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1386-4157</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1573-6938</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-09-29" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A tractable model of reciprocity and fairness</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Friedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Steven</forename><surname>Gjerstad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.geb.2006.05.001</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://excen.gsu.edu/workingpapers/GSU_EXCEN_WP_2006-05.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Games and Economic Behavior</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Games and Economic Behavior</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0899-8256</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-04" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Digitization of Word-of-Mouth: Promise and Challenges of Online Feedback Mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chrysanthos</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Dellarocas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2139/ssrn.393042</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://dspace.mit.edu/bitstream/1721.1/1851/1/4296-03.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SSRN Electronic Journal</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">SSRN Journal</title>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1556-5068</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1407" to="1431" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A theory of sequential reciprocity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Dufwenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Georg</forename><surname>Kirchsteiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.geb.2003.06.003</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www.dklevine.com/archive/a_theory.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Games and Economic Behavior</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Games and Economic Behavior</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0899-8256</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="268" to="298" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-05" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gossip in evolutionary perspective.</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I M</forename><surname>Dunbar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/1089-2680.8.2.100</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://attach.matita.net/ziorufus/Dunbar gossip.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Review of General Psychology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Review of General Psychology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1089-2680</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1939-1552</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<publisher>American Psychological Association (APA)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Who to punish? Individual decisions and majority rule in mitigating the free rider problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Arhan</forename><surname>Ertan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Talbot</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Louis</forename><surname>Putterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.euroecorev.2008.09.007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Economic Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">European Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0014-2921</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="495" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-07" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A theory of reciprocity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Armin</forename><surname>Falk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Urs</forename><surname>Fischbacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.geb.2005.03.001</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Games and Economic Behavior</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Games and Economic Behavior</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0899-8256</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="315" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-02" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Driving Forces Behind Informal Sanctions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Armin</forename><surname>Falk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ernst</forename><surname>Fehr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Urs</forename><surname>Fischbacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1468-0262.2005.00644.x</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-97WNNCK8-1</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">B9EAFE513F2AA8E786BEAD34C18F28635C726925</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.econstor.eu/bitstream/10419/33524/1/495900176.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Econometrica</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Econometrica</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0012-9682</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1468-0262</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2017" to="2030" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-11" />
			<publisher>The Econometric Society</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Third-party punishment and social norms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ernst</forename><surname>Fehr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Urs</forename><surname>Fischbacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s1090-5138(04)00005-4</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.zora.uzh.ch/id/eprint/110635/1/iewwp106.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution and Human Behavior</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Evolution and Human Behavior</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1090-5138</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-03" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cooperation and Punishment in Public Goods Experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ernst</forename><surname>Fehr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Simon</forename><surname>Gächter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/aer.90.4.980</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www.econ.uzh.ch/static/wp_iew/iewwp010.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">American Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-8282</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="980" to="994" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-09" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Theory of Fairness, Competition, and Cooperation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fehr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1162/003355399556151</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-PGGGZK64-B</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">71AFA470499C4D43F0238FCB109C8DD2984FFFD4</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.zora.uzh.ch/id/eprint/155543/1/ZORA_NL_155543.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Quarterly Journal of Economics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0033-5533</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1531-4650</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="817" to="868" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-08-01" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On Inequity Aversion: A Reply to Binmore and Shaked</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Behavior and Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gossip and the Efficiency of Interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fehr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Working Papers in Economics and Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The virtues of gossip: Reputational information sharing as prosocial behavior.</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><surname>Feinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robb</forename><surname>Willer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><surname>Stellar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dacher</forename><surname>Keltner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1037/a0026650</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22229458</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/15f0/3c4129f0514c905030c5ef307857c91e42d5.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-3514</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1939-1315</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1015" to="1030" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<publisher>American Psychological Association (APA)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">z-Tree: Zurich toolbox for ready-made economic experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Urs</forename><surname>Fischbacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10683-006-9159-4</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/VQC-T6T7D0KQ-W</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">5C881698C72D71C96979B9FCF72C3C31996882EC</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2Fs10683-006-9159-4.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Experimental Economics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Exp Econ</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1386-4157</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1573-6938</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-02-07" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social Preferences, Beliefs, and the Dynamics of Free Riding in Public Goods Experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Urs</forename><surname>Fischbacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Simon</forename><surname>Gächter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/aer.100.1.541</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://kops.uni-konstanz.de/bitstream/123456789/11946/1/12813.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">American Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-8282</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="541" to="556" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-03" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gossip among Trustors Increases Trust and Trustworthiness in the Trust Game</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fonseca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science Association World Meetings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paper presented at Economic</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reciprocity, culture and human cooperation: previous insights and a new cross-cultural experiment</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gachter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1098/rstb.2008.0275</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">19073476</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC2689715</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://europepmc.org/articles/pmc2689715?pdf=render" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0962-8436</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1471-2970</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">364</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1518</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="791" to="806" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-03-27" />
			<publisher>The Royal Society</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The emergence of employer information networks in an experimental labor market</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Klarita</forename><surname>Gërxhani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jordi</forename><surname>Brandts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Arthur</forename><surname>Schram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.socnet.2013.08.001</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Networks</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Social Networks</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0378-8733</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="541" to="560" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-10" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Moral Sentiments and Material Interests: The Foundations of Cooperation in Economic Life</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gintis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bowles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Boyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fehr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Role of Reputation Systems in Reducing On-Line Auction Fraud</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dawn</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Gregg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Judy</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2753/jec1086-4415100304</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Electronic Commerce</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">International Journal of Electronic Commerce</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1086-4415</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1557-9301</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-04" />
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Group Reputations, Stereotypes, and Cooperation in a Repeated Labor Market</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paul</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Healy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/aer.97.5.1751</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/25bd/fdb68aa392570ea7391f13c938af3f2fa213.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">American Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-8282</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1751" to="1773" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-11" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BEHAVIORAL FOUNDATIONS OF RECIPROCITY: EXPERIMENTAL ECONOMICS AND EVOLUTIONARY PSYCHOLOGY</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mccabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Vernon</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1465-7295.1998.tb01719.x</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-PZZGHMBC-Z</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">C5A98E96B2EBF604A6683211CA93939FFD458BB3</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://dlc.dlib.indiana.edu/dlc/bitstream/handle/10535/5736/behavioral%20foundations%20of%20reciprocity.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economic Inquiry</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0095-2583</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1465-7295</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="352" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-07" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Games on Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yves</forename><surname>Zenou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/b978-0-444-53766-9.00003-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Handbook of Game Theory with Economic Applications</title>
		<editor>P. Young and S. Zamir</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Amsterdam, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="163" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Promoting Competition or Helping the Less Endowed? Distributional Preferences and Collective Institutional Choices under Intragroup Inequality</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kenju</forename><surname>Kamei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/0022002716656446</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/pdf/10.1177/0022002716656446" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Conflict Resolution</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Conflict Resolution</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-0027</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1552-8766</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="626" to="655" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-07-04" />
			<publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Economics Letters. Epub ahead of print</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/00220027166</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1177/00220027166" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Play It Again: Partner Choice, Reputation Building and Learning From Finitely repeated Dilemma Games</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kenju</forename><surname>Kamei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Louis</forename><surname>Putterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/ecoj.12320</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://dro.dur.ac.uk/15891/1/15891.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Economic Journal</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Econ J</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0013-0133</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">602</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1069" to="1095" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-07-25" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Epub ahead of print</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Play It Again: Partner Choice, Reputation Building and Learning From Finitely repeated Dilemma Games</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kenju</forename><surname>Kamei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Louis</forename><surname>Putterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/ecoj.12320</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://dro.dur.ac.uk/15891/1/15891.pdf" />
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/ecoj.12320" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Economic Journal</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Econ J</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0013-0133</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">602</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1069" to="1095" />
			<date type="published" when="2016-07-25" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rational cooperation in the finitely repeated prisoners&apos; dilemma</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kreps</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Milgrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0022-0531(82)90029-1</idno>
		<idno type="PII">0022-0531(82)90029-1</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-NBF8GBT9-C</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">752F4D2D3CF240D273E5E131CC57743C81529346</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www.dklevine.com/archive/refs4239.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Theory</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Economic Theory</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-0531</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="252" />
			<date type="published" when="1982-08" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emotions in Economic Theory and Economic Behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">George</forename><surname>Loewenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/aer.90.2.426</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/ddd3/8fff9f6e1c12e1944e4cf35e9b7aaeb5aaf1.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">American Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-8282</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="426" to="432" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-05" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anomalous Behavior in Public Goods Experiments: How Much and Why?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Palfrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Prisbrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="829" to="875" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Blank Slate: The Modern Denial of Human Nature</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pinker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>De Quervain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Fischbacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Treyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schellhammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Schnyder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Buck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fehr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5688</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1254" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The Neural Basis of Altruistic Punishment</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incorporating Fairness into Game Theory and Economics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rabin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1281" to="302" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trust among strangers in internet transactions: Empirical analysis of eBay&apos; s reputation system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Resnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Zeckhauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0278-0984(02)11030-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Economics of the Internet and E-commerce</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Emerald (MCB UP )</publisher>
			<date>2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="157" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social Preferences under Risk: Equality of Opportunity versus Equality of Outcome</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kota</forename><surname>Saito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/aer.103.7.3084</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://authors.library.caltech.edu/43282/1/aer.103.7.3084.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">American Economic Review</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-8282</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3084" to="3101" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-12" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Zero as a Special Price: The True Value of Free Products</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kristina</forename><surname>Shampanier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nina</forename><surname>Mazar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dan</forename><surname>Ariely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1287/mksc.1060.0254</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/9178/3e7de55a3a0f2523b7c4f4f85c12faf5a5bf.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marketing Science</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Marketing Science</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0732-2399</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1526-548X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="742" to="757" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-11" />
			<publisher>Institute for Operations Research and the Management Sciences (INFORMS)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Theory of Moral Sentiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Adam</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1017/cbo9780511800153.005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Adam Smith: The Theory of Moral Sentiments</title>
		<editor>A. Millar</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London, UK and Edinburgh, Scotland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date>null</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interdependent Preferences and Reciprocity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joel</forename><surname>Sobel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1257/0022051054661530</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://econ.ucsd.edu/%7Ejandreon/Econ264/papers/Sobel%20JEL%202005.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Economic Literature</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Economic Literature</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-0515</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="392" to="436" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-05" />
			<publisher>American Economic Association</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of Economic Literature</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anonymity, Social Image, and the Competition for Volunteers: A Case Study of the Online Market for Reviews</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Zhongmin</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2202/1935-1682.2523</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/QT4-4Q3QXN9S-7</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">43640A9889A38997DAC2EAB1A20859EB3E6D8BE9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The B.E. Journal of Economic Analysis &amp; Policy</title>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1935-1682</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-01-21" />
			<publisher>Walter de Gruyter GmbH</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Social Conquest of Earth</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<publisher>Liveright</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
