<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A systematic account of the genus Plagiostoma (Gnomoniaceae, Diaporthales) based on morphology, host-associations, and a four-gene phylogeny</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Elsevier BV</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011-03">2011-03</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Luis</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mejía</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Castlebury</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Rossman</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Sogonov</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 85167</postBox>
									<postCode>3508 AD</postCode>
									<settlement>Utrecht</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Systematic Mycology &amp; Microbiology Laboratory, USDA-ARS</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Rm. 304, B010A, 10300 Baltimore Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>20705</postCode>
									<settlement>Beltsville</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Plant Biology and Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Rutgers University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>New Brunswick</addrLine>
									<postCode>08901</postCode>
									<region>NJ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute Apartado</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>0843-03092</postCode>
									<settlement>Balboa, Ancon</settlement>
									<country>Republic of Panama</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">EMSL Analytical, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>10768 Baltimore Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>20705</postCode>
									<settlement>Beltsville</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="laboratory">CBS-H 11343 CBS 911.79 Switzerland Acer pseudoplatanus M. Monod GU366973 DQ313549 EU219260 GU353957 Apiognomonia veneta NA CBS 897.79 Switzerland Platanus orientalis M. Monod GU377974 DQ313532 EU219259 GU353958 Plagiostoma aesculi BPI 748430 CBS 109765 Austria Aesculus hippocastaneum W. Jaklitsch GU367021 DQ323530 EU199138 GU354004 BPI 878950 CBS 126127</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="laboratory">GU367019 GU367076 GU367110 GU354002 BPI 878950 LCM 447b.01 Germany Aesculus hippocastaneum L.C. Mejía GU367020 GU367077 GU367111 GU354003 BPI 840942 CBS 121905 Austria Aesculus hippocastaneum W. Jaklitsch GU367022 EU254994 EU219269 GU354005 Plagiostoma amygdalinae NA CBS 791.79 Switzerland Euphorbia amygdaloides M. Monod GU367030 EU254995 GU367113 GU354012 Plagiostoma apiculatum BPI 747938 CBS 109775 (= AR 3455) Austria Salix sp. W. Jaklitsch GU367008 DQ323529 EU199141 GU353990 BPI 878951 LCM 393.01 France Salix dasyclados L.C. Mejía GU367010 GU367067 GU367101 GU353992 BPI 878952 CBS 126126 (= LCM 436.01) USA: WA Salix sitchensis L.C. Mejía GU367009 GU367066 GU367100 GU353991 Plagiostoma barriae BPI 878954</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>LCM 601.01</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Salix irrorata L.C. Mejía GU367013 GU367070 GU367104 GU353996 BPI 878958 LCM 403.02 France Salix caprea L.C. Mejía GU367012 GU367069 GU367103 GU353995 Plagiostoma euphorbiaceum NA CBS 816.79 Switzerland Euphorbia palustris M. Monod GU367031 EU255003 -GU354013 Plagiostoma euphorbiae NA CBS 340.78 The Netherlands Euphorbia palustris W. Gams GU367034 DQ323532 EU219292 GU354016 Plagiostoma exstocollum BPI</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>878961, 127662</postCode>
									<settlement>CBS</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">CA Salix sp</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Corylus californica L.C. Mejía GU366988 GU367046 GU367086 GU353972 BPI 878959 LCM 422.01 USA: OR Corylus californica L.C. Mejía GU366985 GU367043 GU367085 GU353969 Plagiostoma fraxini BPI 746412 CBS 109498 USA: MD Fraxinus pennsylvanica S. Redlin GU367033 AY455810 EU219263 GU354015 Plagiostoma geranii NA CBS 824.79 Switzerland Geranium sylvaticum M. Monod GU367032 EU255009 EU219273 GU354014 Plagiostoma imperceptibile BPI 878967</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>LCM 456.01</addrLine>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="laboratory">GU367023 GU367078 GU367112 GU354006 BPI 863769 AR 3821 USA: NY Acer sp. L. Vasilyeva GU367025 EU255039 EU219257 GU354008 Plagiostoma populinum NA CBS 144.57 The Netherlands Populus trichocarpa B. Gerrits van den Ende GU367018 GU367075 GU367109 GU354001 NA CBS 174.58 The Netherlands Populus canadensis B. Gerrits van den Ende GU367017 GU367074 GU367108 GU354000 Plagiostoma pulchellum BPI 878971 CBS 126653 (= LCM 365.04) USA: MD Salix babylonica L.C. Mejía GU367006 GU367063 GU367098 GU353987 BPI 878972 LCM 371.02 USA: MD Salix babylonica L.C. Mejía GU367007 GU367064 GU367099 GU353988 BPI 878973 LCM 438.04 USA: WA Salix lucida L.C. Mejía GU366004 GU367061 GU367096 GU353985 BPI 878974 LCM 623.01 Argentina Salix humboldtiana L.C. Mejía GU367005 GU367062 GU367097 GU353986 NA CBS 170.69 The Netherlands Populus balsamifera Unknown -EU255043 -GU353989 Plagiostoma rhododendri NA CBS 847.79 Switzerland Rhododendron hirsutum M. Monod GU367026 EU255044 EU2192578 GU354009 Plagiostoma robergeanum</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff10">
								<orgName type="laboratory">GU366993 GU367051 GU367089 GU353977 BPI 878979 LCM 596.01 USA: WA Alnus sp. L.C. Mejía GU366994 GU367052 GU367090 GU353978 Plagiostoma versatile BPI 878980 CBS 124978 (= LCM 594.01) USA: WA Salix scouleriana L.C. Mejía GU366979 GU367038 GU367082 GU393963 BPI 878981 LCM 595.01 USA: WA Salix scouleriana L.C. Mejía GU366980 GU367039 GU367083 GU393964 BPI 878982 LCM 598.01 USA: OR Salix sp. L.C. Mejía GU366981 GU367040 GU367084 GU393965 BPI 877702 CBS 121251 Canada Salix sp. M.V. Sogonov GU366982 EU255059 EU219268 GU393966</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A systematic account of the genus Plagiostoma (Gnomoniaceae, Diaporthales) based on morphology, host-associations, and a four-gene phylogeny</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Studies in Mycology</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Studies in Mycology</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0166-0616</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="235"/>
							<date type="published" when="2011-03" />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.3114/sim.2011.68.10</idno>
					<idno type="PMID">21523196</idno>
					<idno type="PMCID">PMC3065992</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T21:32+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Ascomycota</term>
					<term>Betulaceae</term>
					<term>epitypification</term>
					<term>Fraxinus</term>
					<term>new species</term>
					<term>phylogeny</term>
					<term>Salicaceae</term>
					<term>Sordariomycetidae</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Members of the genus Plagiostoma inhabit leaves, stems, twigs, and branches of woody and herbaceous plants predominantly in the temperate Northern Hemisphere. An account of all known species of Plagiostoma including Cryptodiaporthe is presented based on analyses of morphological, cultural, and DNA sequence data. Multigene phylogenetic analyses of DNA sequences from four genes (β-tubulin, ITS, rpb2, and tef1-α) revealed eight previously undescribed phylogenetic species and an association between a clade composed of 11 species of Plagiostoma and the host family Salicaceae. In this paper these eight new species of Plagiostoma are described, four species are redescribed, and four new combinations are proposed. A key to the 25 accepted species of Plagiostoma based on host, shape, and size of perithecia, perithecial arrangement in the host, and microscopic characteristics of the asci and ascospores is provided. Disposition of additional names in Cryptodiaporthe and Plagiostoma is also discussed.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>The genus Plagiostoma (Gnomoniaceae, Diaporthales) includes microscopic fungi that inhabit the leaves, stems, twigs, and branches of woody and herbaceous plants from a range of families including the Betulaceae, Euphorbiaceae, Geraniaceae, Hippocastanaceae, Oleaceae, Polygonaceae, Salicaceae, Sapindaceae, and Staphylaceae in temperate regions of the Northern Hemisphere . Although some species of Plagiostoma cause diseases, most do not show symptoms prior to production of perithecia on dead tissues. Described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fuckel (1870)</ref>, the morphological concept of Plagiostoma remained relatively unchanged <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Barr 1978</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">, Monod 1983</ref>) until recently. Multigene phylogenetic studies suggest that the genus Plagiostoma forms a highly supported monophyletic clade that includes the type species of Plagiostoma, P. euphorbiae, and the type species of Cryptodiaporthe, C. aesculi, among others <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Mejía et al. 2008</ref>.  included 13 species in the genus Plagiostoma, several of which were previously placed in Cryptodiaporthe.</p><p>A brief historical account of the major taxonomic treatments of Plagiostoma and Cryptodiaporthe illustrates the views of these genera through time. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fuckel (1870)</ref> proposed the genus Plagiostoma for sphaericeaous species characterised by flattened perithecia oriented horizontally having short, lateral, erumpent necks. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fuckel (1870)</ref> included the genera Ceratostoma, Gnomonia, Linospora, Melanospora, and Rhaphidospora together with Plagiostoma in the tribe Ceratostomeae of the Sphaeriacei. In his original description of Plagiostoma, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fuckel (1870)</ref> included four species, P. euphorbiae, P. petiolicola, P devexum, and P. suspecta. Fuckel's concept of Plagiostoma was followed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Höhnel (1917)</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">and von Arx (1951)</ref> who, like Fuckel, considered Plagiostoma to be relatively closely related to Gnomonia, the name on which the Gnomoniaceae is based. These authors differentiated Gnomonia from Plagiostoma mainly by orientation of the perithecial neck. Gnomonia was characterised by having central, upright, perithecial necks in contrast to species of Plagiostoma with eccentric, laterally oriented, perithecial necks. In her treatment of the order Diaporthales, <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Barr (1978)</ref> followed Fuckel's concept of Plagiostoma and placed Gnomonia and Plagiostoma in the same suborder Gnomoniineae but in different families, i.e. Gnomonia in the Gnomoniaceae and Plagiostoma in the Valsaceae. The Valsaceae was defined based on having "beaks oblique or lateral, erumpent separately or converging through stromatic disc" <ref type="bibr">(Barr, 1978 p. 15)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Barr (1978)</ref> made nine new combinations in Plagiostoma expanding the number of species in the genus to <ref type="bibr">13.</ref> In his monograph of the Gnomoniaceae, <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Monod (1983)</ref> accepted most species treated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Barr (1978)</ref>. However, Monod considered that the typification of Plagiostoma as P. euphorbiae by Höhnel <ref type="bibr">(1917)</ref> was not representative of Plagiostoma because the perithecial necks of this species are eccentric rather than lateral as stipulated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fuckel (1870)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Monod (1983)</ref> transferred P. euphorbiae to the genus Gnomonia and re-typified Plagiostoma with P. devexum. In agreement with <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Barr (1991)</ref> and  the typification of the genus Plagiostoma with P. euphorbiae by <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Höhnel (1917)</ref> is accepted here because this typification predates <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Monod (1983)</ref> and is in accordance with Article 10 of the International Code of Botanical Nomenclature <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(McNeill et al. 2006)</ref>.</p><p>A systematic account of the genus Plagiostoma (Gnomoniaceae, Diaporthales) based on morphology, host-associations, and a four-gene phylogeny L.C. Mejía 1, 2, 3* , L.A. Castlebury 1 , A.Y. Rossman 1 , M.V. Sogonov 4 and J.F. White, Jr. 2 a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma In addition, the character of perithecial neck orientation has been found not to be phylogenetically informative .</p><p>Cryptodiaporthe was described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Petrak (1921)</ref> for species with euvalsoid arrangement of perithecia and, in contrast to Diaporthe, lacks a blackened margin in the substratum surrounding the perithecia. In describing Cryptodiaporthe, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Petrak (1921)</ref> designated C. aesculi as type and included C. hystrix and C. populina. Later, <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wehmeyer (1933)</ref> recircumscribed Cryptodiaporthe emphasising the lack of a blackened margin within the substratum and made 17 new combinations in this genus for species previously included in Diaporthe expanding the genus to 19 species.</p><p>In this study, specimens of Plagiostoma were collected primarily from North America but also from South America, Europe, and China. Among these recent collections eight new species were discovered and a number of described species were recollected, cultured, and sequenced. A multigene phylogenetic analysis is provided of 24 of the 25 species of Plagiostoma accepted here. Eight new species are described and illustrated, four species are redescribed, and four new combinations are proposed. A key to the 25 accepted species of Plagiostoma is provided along with the disposition of additional species names in Cryptodiaporthe and Plagiostoma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MATERIAL AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Collection of specimens, culture preparation, and morphological observations</head><p>Collections were made as listed in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> from the following countries mainly during the spring and summers of 2007 and 2008: Argentina (Tucumán), China (Yunnan), France (Deux-Sèvres Département), Germany (Frankfurt), and the United States of America <ref type="bibr">(California, Maryland, New York, Oregon, Washington)</ref>. Specimens consisting of overwintered, dead, attached, or fallen twigs and branches with perithecia were placed in paper bags, airdried, and stored at 8-10 °C in sealed plastic bags for a period of 1 wk to 6 mo before processing. All specimens are deposited in the U.S. National Fungus Collections (BPI).</p><p>Observations, measurements, and digital imaging of morphological characters and isolation of cultures were performed using the same equipment and procedures as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Mejía et al. (2008)</ref>. AxioVision v. 4.7.2.0 (Carl Zeiss Image Solutions, Carl Zeiss, New York, NY, USA) was used in conjunction with those methods to measure structures. Fresh specimens were mounted in water for microscopic observations; dried specimens were mounted in 3 % potassium hydroxide. Cultural characteristics were observed on Potato Dextrose Agar (PDA, Difco™, Becton, Dickinson &amp; Co., Sparks, MD, USA) 7 d after plating as described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Mejía et al. (2008)</ref>. Colony diameters were measured twice perpendicularly and averaged and thus are listed as average colony diameter <ref type="bibr">(a.c.d.)</ref>. Representative cultures of species considered in this study were deposited at the Centraalbureau voor Schimmelcultures (CBS, The Netherlands) as listed in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DNA extraction and PCR amplification</head><p>DNA extractions were done as described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Mejía et al. (2008)</ref> using a Fast Prep FP 120 with Lysing Matrix "A" (MP Biomedicals, Solon, OH, USA) for mechanical lysis. Four gene fragments were amplified and sequenced for the phylogenetic analyses: the complete nuclear ribosomal internal transcribed spacer regions 1 and 2 including 5.8 S rDNA (ITS), regions of the RNA polymerase second largest subunit (rpb2), beta-tubulin (β-tubulin), and translation elongation factor 1-alpha (tef1-α) genes. The ITS and rpb2 genes were amplified and sequenced as described in  in 25 μL reactions with two internal sequencing primers designed specifically for species of Plagiostoma: rpb2 Plag-F (5' CGT CGC TGC ATY ATC TCR CA 3') and rpb2 Plag-R (5' TGY GAG ATR ATG CAG CGA CG 3'). β-tubulin was amplified using primers T1 and T22 and sequenced with the PCR primers and the internal primers T2 and T12 from O' <ref type="bibr">Donnell &amp; Cigelnik (1997)</ref>. For some isolates it was necessary to amplify the tef1-α region in two fragments using the following primer combinations: EF1-728F /EF1-1199R and EF1-983F/ EF1-1567R <ref type="bibr">(Carbone &amp; Kohn 1999, Castlebury, unpubl.</ref> data, for primer 1199R 5' GGG AAG TAC CMG TGA TCA TGT 3', <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Rehner 2001)</ref>. The rpb2 gene could not be amplified for P. convexum, P. euphorbiaceum, and P. pulchellum CBS 170.69. In addition, β-tubulin could not be amplified for P. pulchellum CBS 170.69. For the purpose of determining taxonomic affinities of species previously described as Cryptodiaporthe or Plagiostoma but not congeneric with P. euphorbiae (type species), a region of the nuclear ribosomal large subunit (LSU) was amplified as described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Castlebury et al. (2002)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phylogenetic analyses</head><p>Editing and alignment of DNA sequences were performed as described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Mejía et al. (2008)</ref>. Individual genes were aligned separately and subsequently concatenated into a single alignment. <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> includes detailed information about the gene sequences including GenBank numbers. The concatenated sequence alignment includes β-tubulin (1584 bp), ITS (625 bp), rpb2 (1212 bp), and tef1-α (1149 bp) for a total of 4570 bp and 45 isolates. The taxa included in this alignment represent 24 of the 25 accepted species of Plagiostoma with Apiognomonia hystrix and A. veneta as outgroup taxa. Outgroup selection was based on the sister relationship of the genus Apiognomonia with Plagiostoma as inferred by a three-gene phylogeny of the family Gnomoniaceae . Positions with ambiguous alignment were excluded from the analyses.</p><p>The concatenated alignment was partitioned by gene and codon position for β-tubulin, rpb2, and tef1-α using PAUP <ref type="bibr">(Swofford 2002)</ref>. The gene partitions were analysed for conflict with the partition homogeneity test (PHT) as implemented in PAUP (Swofford 2002) using the following settings: 100 homogeneity replicates, 10 random sequence addition replicates, and MULTREES off. Conflict among gene partitions was assessed by reciprocal bootstrap analyses <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Reeb et al. 2004)</ref>  determined by Modeltest v. 3.7 <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Posada &amp; Crandall 1998)</ref> following the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC). Genes were first analysed individually and then as a combined alignment using maximum parsimony, Bayesian, and maximum likelihood analyses. Trees and bootstrap support of branches were estimated by MP analysis as in  with all characters considered unordered with equal weight and an additional analysis with unordered characters weighted as follows: weight = 3 for first and second codon positions and weight = 1 for third codon position. Additionally, trees were estimated using Bayesian analysis with the program MrBayes v. 3.1.2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Huelsenbeck &amp; Ronquist 2001)</ref> as described in  with sampling every 500 generations. Model settings for each gene were determined using the program MrModeltest v. 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Nylander 2004)</ref> and selected based on the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC). The first 50 000 generations were discarded (burn-in period) based on comparison of tree likelihood scores. A 50 % majority rule consensus tree and a consensus phylogram were constructed from the trees saved after the burn-in period. The Bayesian posterior probabilities (PP) of nodes of the consensus trees are presented in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. Trees were also estimated by Maximum Likelihood (ML) analysis using the program PAUP (Swofford 2002) as described in  with Modeltest v. 3.7 <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Posada &amp; Crandall 1998)</ref> used to estimate the best model for the concatenated alignment. Maximum likelihood bootstrap analysis was not conducted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Collection of specimens</head><p>The following plant species are reported as new hosts for species of Plagiostoma: Alnus tenuifolia, <ref type="bibr">Salix dasyclados, S. humboldtiana, S. irrorata, S. lucida, and S. sitchensis</ref>  <ref type="table">(Table 1)</ref>. Plagiostoma pulchellum from Argentina and P. yunnanense from southwestern China were collected in regions where no species of Plagiostoma had been previously reported.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phylogenetic analyses</head><p>The partition homogeneity test suggested conflict among the four genes (ITS, rpb2, β-tubulin, and tef1-α) sequenced for this study (P = 0.01) with rpb2 as the source of this conflict. For combinations of the remaining three genes <ref type="bibr">(ITS,</ref>, no incongruence among gene trees was detected when all three were analysed (P = 0.09), with P = 0.07 for ITS and β-tubulin and P = 0.24 for ITS and tef1-α. The following are the likelihood settings estimated for each gene for the reciprocal NJ bootstrap analyses: ITS: Base = equal Nst = 2 TRatio = 2.5434 Rates = equal Pinvar = 0.8337; rpb2: Base = equal Nst = 6 Rmat = (1.0000 4.6961 1.0000 1.0000 13.3827) Rates = gamma Shape = 0.2029 Pinvar = 0; β-tubulin: Base = (0.2006 0.3249 0.2505) Nst = 2 TRatio = 2.1757 Rates = gamma Shape = 0.5017 Pinvar = 0; and tef1-α: Base = (0.1918 0.3110 0.2229) Nst = 2 TRatio = 1.8586 Rates = gamma Shape = 0.6109 Pinvar = 0.</p><p>The ITS, β-tubulin, and tef1-α trees individually resolved terminal clades for most of the species analysed. Trees for each gene are provided -see online Supplementary Information. No single gene analysis resolved all the species of Plagiostoma with bootstrap support higher than 70 %. The following numbers of species were resolved by genes with bootstrap &gt; 70 %: ITS = 11, rpb2 = 9, β-tubulin = 12, and tef1-α = 11. In general, rpb2 was not as useful for resolving clades of closely related species as the other three genes. The ITS gene resolved and supported all terminal clades except P. amygdalinae and P. euphorbiaceae for which the sequences were nearly identical. However, it did not support backbone nodes at levels greater than 70 %. In contrast, bootstrap support greater than 90 % for all backbone nodes containing two or more species was obtained in the β-tubulin, rpb2, and tef1-α gene trees. The topology of the individual gene trees differed only slightly. One topological conflict supported by bootstrap values greater than 70 % was observed between the β-tubulin analysis resulting in a clade (97 %) that included all species of Plagiostoma on Salicaceae and the rpb2 analysis resulting in a clade (72 %) that included some but not all the species on Salicaceae with some species on other hosts.</p><p>Phylogenetic trees resulting from the combined four-gene dataset <ref type="bibr">(ITS,</ref><ref type="bibr">rpb2,</ref> were compared with those resulting from the ITS, β-tubulin, tef1-α dataset found to be conflict-free by the PHT. Maximum parsimony analyses of the four-gene combination resulted in 114 equally parsimonious trees (length = 1713, CI = 0.689, RI = 0.809) for the unweighted analysis and 42 equally parsimonious trees (length = 2062, CI = 0.689, RI = 0.807) for the weighted analysis. Fifty percent majority rule consensus trees computed for each analysis did not differ in the terminal species clades but higher bootstrap support was obtained for several clades in the weighted analysis. Maximum parsimony analysis of the three-gene combination composed of ITS, β-tubulin, and tef-α resulted in eight equally parsimonious trees (length = 1275, CI = 0.707, RI = 0.817). The tree topologies obtained by MP analyses of the two alignments did not contradict each other; however, bootstrap support for several nodes increased in analyses of the four-gene combination. Therefore, subsequent analyses were performed on the four-gene combination.</p><p>The following models were the best estimates for each gene and were applied during the Bayesian analyses: HKY + I + G for ITS and tef1-α, SYM + G for rpb2, and HKY + G for β-tubulin. The model TrN+G was estimated to be the best for the entire alignment by both hLRT and BIC and those settings were applied to the maximum likelihood analysis: Base = (0.2245 0.2859 0.2454) Nst = 6 Rmat = (1.0000 3.5234 1.0000 1.0000 5.8336) Rates = gamma Shape = 0.2849 Pinvar = 0. Bayesian, ML, MP, and weighted parsimony (WP) analyses of the four-gene alignment all resulted in the same topology. Maximum likelihood analysis of the concatenated alignment of four genes resulted in one tree -lnL score of 13921.12887 and is presented as the inferred phylogeny of Plagiostoma <ref type="figure">(Fig. 1)</ref>. Bayesian PP and MP bootstraps are shown above and below the branches. This phylogeny of Plagiostoma supports the recognition of eight new species, which are described in the taxonomic section of this work. Bayesian PP and MP bootstrap supports greater than 90 % were obtained for all the species of Plagiostoma in this multigene phylogeny. Plagiostoma euphorbiae-verrucosae is not included in the multigene phylogeny as only the ITS was available for this species. This species was confirmed as belonging in Plagiostoma by analysis of ITS sequences (tree not shown).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Evaluation of clades and species</head><p>Both Bayesian analysis and MP bootstrapping support a clade containing 11 species that occurs exclusively on hosts of the family Salicaceae. All of these species occur on the bark of twigs and branches with one species, Plagiostoma versatile, also occurring in the leaf midvein and petioles. Within the species on Salicaceae, a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma one clade consists of four closely related species characterised by having an expanded perithecial neck: P. apiculatum, P. dilatatum, P. imperceptibile, and P. pulchellum. These species are distinguished by morphological features such as perithecium size, ascospore size and length-to-width (l : w) ratio, and hyphal colour in culture. Plagiostoma imperceptibile is characterised by having ascospores longer than 18 μm but with a length-width ratio (l : w) less than five. Plagiostoma pulchellum is characterised by having ascospores with a l : w greater than five and by producing rosy-coloured hyphae that become dark green on PDA. Plagiostoma apiculatum and P. dilatatum are similar to one another but the perithecia and ascospores of P. dilatatum are larger than those of P. apiculatum. Plagiostoma convexum with a moderately expanded perithecial neck is highly supported (&gt; 95 % MP, PP) as basal to these four species.  <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree (ML score = -lnL 13921.12887) estimated from sequences of the β-tubulin, ITS, rpb2, and tef1-α genes for 24 species of Plagiostoma and two species of Apiognomonia. Bayesian posterior probabilities greater than 80 % are shown above each branch and maximum parsimony bootstrap values greater than 70 % are shown below branches. Trees for each gene were also generated; see online Supplementary Information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Species with cylindrical necks</head><p>Plagiostoma ovalisporum and the pathogenic species P. populinum are closely related and contained within a larger clade including the five species previously mentioned (100 % MP, PP). The remaining species of Plagiostoma on Salicaceae form a weakly supported clade sister to the species on Salicaceae with expanded necks mentioned above. This clade contains three species having cylindrical, usually elongated, perithecial necks, and elongated ascospores: P. salicellum, P. versatile, and P. yunnanense. The remaining member of this clade, P. oregonense, is characterised by short, expanded perithecial necks and short ascospores.</p><p>Bayesian PP and MP bootstrapping also support a clade (83 % MP, 100 % PP) of eight species with hosts representing a range of woody and herbaceous plant families. One of the subclades in this group is composed of three species that grow on Euphorbiaceae: P. amygdalinae, P. euphorbiaceum, and P. euphorbiae, type species of the genus. Basal to these species is P. fraxinum on Fraxinus pennsylvanica. A second subclade contains P. exstocollum and P. samuelsii both on betulaceous hosts and P. rhododendri on Rhododendron. The rest of the species included in the tree, namely P. aesculi, P. barriae, P. geranii, P. petiolophilum, and P. robergeanum, are relatively distant from one another and the species previously mentioned. Plagiostoma robergeanum, a species that grows on Staphylea (Staphyleaceae) in Europe, was basal to the other species of Plagiostoma.</p><p>Specimens of P. pulchellum were collected in Europe, North America (USA), and South America (Argentina). This species is recognised as the most widely distributed species of Plagiostoma included in this study and is presented here as the first report of Gnomoniaceae for South America. Plagiostoma yunnanense is the first report of Plagiostoma for China.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p>Due to the morphological diversity in species of Plagiostoma, as illustrated in Figs 2-6, no single morphological character is unique or diagnostic for this genus. The following morphological characters differentiate Plagiostoma from other genera of the Gnomoniaceae as defined by <ref type="bibr">Sogonov et al. (2008, table 2)</ref>. Unlike Gnomonia, species of Plagiostoma have perithecia that often collapse from the base when dry as illustrated in <ref type="bibr">Sogonov et al. (2008, fig. 43 B-C)</ref>. In Plagiostoma the neck length is short to long about equal or less than the diameter of perithecia, while in Ophiognomonia the perithecial neck length is usually very long, often pointed, and 2.5-5 times the perithecial diameter. Species of Ophiognomonia occur only on leaves while those of Plagiostoma are found on leaves as well as woody tissues. Except for P. rhododendri, the ascospores of Plagiostoma are not broader at the upper part as in Gnomoniopsis. Ascospores of Plagiostoma are never cylindrical or femuroid as in Cryptosporella. Species of Plagiostoma with ellipsoid, aseptate ascospores similar to those of C. hypodermia do not have a valsoid arrangement of perithecia as do species of Cryptosporella.</p><p>Species of Plagiostoma, except for P. rhododendri, are not apiosporous, differentiating them from species of Apiognomonia except A. hystrix, which possesses flattened perithecial necks. Species of Pleuroceras have elongated ascospores that are quite distinct from those of Plagiostoma. The type and only species of Ditopella, D. ditopa, is characterised by having polysporic asci. Phragmoporthe conformis, a species closely related to Ditopella ditopa, is characterised by phragmosporic ascospores, a character not present in Plagiostoma. The perithecia of Amphiporthe hranicensis, the type species of Amphiporthe, are grouped near the base of the entostroma and, thus, are different from those found in Plagiostoma. In addition, Amphiporthe hranicensis produces perithecia in clusters of up to 20, with perithecial necks protruding as a group from the host periderm and surrounded by gray stromatic tissue.</p><p>Perithecial neck characters and ascospore morphology are the most important characters for differentiating Plagiostoma from other genera in the Gnomoniaceae. Host identity, geographic locality, and presence or absence of stroma are secondary characters for the identification of species. For example, the presence of white stromatic tissues surrounding the emerging perithecial necks is diagnostic in species such as P. aesculi, P. salicellum, and P. samuelsii. Within Plagiostoma perithecial neck shape ranges from very short, cylindrical to expanded and thick or thin, cylindrical and elongated with various shapes in the opening area, e.g. conic, flared, or rounded. In one species, P. versatile, the perithecial neck can be both very short when on twigs or elongated when on a leaf midvein suggesting that this structure varies with substrate. Four species, P. apiculatum, P. convexum, P. dilatatum, and P. imperceptibile, are characterised by having an apically expanded perithecial neck. The expanded neck was noticed by Wallroth (1833, as coronatum dilatatis) and Butin (1958, as cushion-or padlike structure) but neither of these authors used this character to differentiate species. This structure may be involved in rupture of host periderm and release of the ascospores.</p><p>The asci of Plagiostoma are clavate, obclavate, ovoidal, cylindrical, or cylindric-fusoid, generally with a short stalk but with a long stalk in P. imperceptibile. Ascospores of Plagiostoma are ellipsoid, ellipsoid-fusoid, oblong-ellipsoid, or ovoid usually with one median septum, although three species, P. euphorbiae-verrucosae, P. fraxini, and P. ovalisporum, have non-septate ascospores and one species, P. rhododendri, is apiosporous. Ascospores vary in size from short, 7.7-13.8 × 2.2-6.6 μm in P. fraxini, to relatively long, 18-27 × 3-4 μm in P. versatile and P. yunnanense. Most species lack appendages although P. salicellum has short, thick, evanescent appendages and P. devexum and P. samuelsii may have long, thin appendages. Morphological characters that are phylogenetically informative for subclades of Plagiostoma include the expanded neck characteristic of species with broadly ellipsoid ascospores versus the cylindrical neck characteristic of species with narrowly ellipsoidal ascospores.</p><p>In traditional classification schemes of the Diaporthales, Cryptodiaporthe and Plagiostoma were considered distinct and not closely related genera, each with a specific morphology and arrangement of perithecia <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Barr 1978</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">, Kobayashi 1970</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">, Monod 1983</ref>). Species of Plagiostoma were characterised by the lack of a stroma and production of a single perithecium, primarily on leaves. Species of Cryptodiaporthe were characterised by production of a rudimentary stroma and grouped perithecia, primarily in the bark of their host branches. The differences between Cryptodiaporthe and Plagiostoma have been emphasised such that some authors placed them in different families or subfamilies <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Barr 1978</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">, Wehmeyer 1975</ref>). <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Monod's (1983)</ref> concept of Plagiostoma differed significantly from the concept presented here. Of the 13 species treated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Monod (1983)</ref> as Plagiostoma, only Plagiostoma devexum is accepted here in that genus. Of the 13 species of Plagiostoma accepted by , only P. euphorbiae and P. devexum were originally described as Plagiostoma with Plagiostoma barriae newly described in that work. Plagiostoma aesculi and P. salicellum were previously regarded by <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wehmeyer (1933)</ref> as Cryptodiaporthe. Four a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma additional species of Cryptodiaporthe are here formally combined in Plagiostoma, namely P. apiculatum, P. convexum, P. populinum, and P. pulchellum. The recognition of these four species formerly classified as Cryptodiaporthe salicina broadens the range of morphological and ecological traits of the genus Plagiostoma. The pathogenic species, P. apiculatum, P. fraxini, and P. populinum, contrasts with the concept of Plagiostoma as primarily saprobic.</p><p>The economically important species of Plagiostoma are pathogens that cause cankers on willows and poplars. Plagiostoma apiculatum (synonym Cryptodiaporthe salicella) is here determined to be the correct name for the fungus causing a canker disease of willow <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Sinclair &amp; Lyon 2005)</ref>. This species, referred to by the anamorph Diplodina microsperma, has been reported as the most abundant endophyte in healthy twigs of Salix fragilis in England <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Petrini &amp; Fisher 1990)</ref> and is thus an important component of the host microbiota. Similarly, the closely related species P. dilatatum, P. imperceptibile, and P. pulchellum form a black halo or spot on the host surface, a feature that may be associated with the early stages of canker development. Whether or not these species are primarily pathogenic or establish an asymptomatic infection that later develops into cankers needs to be determined. These species form a highly supported monophyletic group <ref type="figure">(Fig. 1</ref>) characterised by having an expanded perithecial neck and broad ellipsoid to renoid ascospores. This group of species is part of a larger, highly supported clade that also includes P. convexum, P. ovalisporum, and P. populinum (synonym Cryptodiaporthe populea), the pathogen causing a canker of poplars. Plagiostoma fraxini causes anthracnose on ash (Fraxinus pennsylvanica) and fringetree (Chionanthus retusis) <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Gregory et al. 2004</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">, Sinclair &amp; Lyon 2005</ref>, and is sister to the clade containing three species on Euphorbiaceae.</p><p>Species of Plagiostoma occur on a broad range of host plant families within the Eudicots, although most species are associated with Rosids. This study shows an association between a clade composed of 11 species of Plagiostoma and the host family Salicaceae <ref type="figure">(Fig. 1</ref>) especially on the genus Salix. Most of the species of Plagiostoma on Salix have expanded necks. These findings agree with those for other genera within the Gnomoniaceae that are associated primarily with specific host genera in the Betulaceae such as Cryptosporella on Alnus and Betula  and Gnomonia on the Coryloideae . . Ascospores (7.7-)8.6-12.7(-13.8) × (2.2)2.8-5.9(-6.6) μm fide <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Redlin &amp; Stack (1988</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Sutton (1980)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TAXONOMY KEY TO SPECIES OF PlaGiostoma</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">1. Ascospores non-septate ............................................................................................................................................................................ 2 1'. Ascospores 1-septate ................................................................................................................................................................................</formula><p>Perithecia produced in dead, fallen or still attached host organs, immersed in bark of stems, branches, and twigs, in midvein or petiole of leaves (P. fraxini on leaf lamina), on stalks of herbaceous plants, and on peduncles (P. rhododendri). Most species initially appearing as conic-shaped or rounded elevations, usually 0.2-0.5 mm high × 1-2 mm diam, produced where a single perithecium or group of perithecia push up host surface from below. Perithecial necks protrude through epidermis or periderm making a small hole or slit, with perithecia partially or completely exposed by peeling host periderm. In bark, perithecia arranged in groups or solitary, scattered, numerous; in leaves, perithecia discrete, but growing close together. Stroma scanty, flocculose, gray, brownish, cream, yellowish white, or whitish. Perithecia black, globose, slightly flattened or suboblate, usually collapsed from base when dry, with or without stromatic tissue surrounding neck. Neck central to marginal, mostly cylindrical, also flattened, short and stout, upright, straight or contorted, or slanted and straight; 30-150 μm diam not including expanded area, with or without a disk-like expansion, up to 450 μm diam; apex rounded, acute, flared, cupulate, papillate, or conic, black, brown, yellow or hyaline, with or without furrows. Asci clavate, obclavate, ovoidal to cylindrical and cylindric-fusoid, usually with a short stalk, with a long stalk in P. imperceptibile, with a conspicuous apical ring that may appear single and thick or as two refractive bodies, eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel, biseriate, multiseriate, or twisted. Ascospores ellipsoid, ellipsoid-fusoid, oblong-ellipsoid, ovoid, hyaline, non-or 1-septate, constricted or not at median to submedian septum, apiosporous in P. rhododendri, often with four or more rounded guttules, or appearing granulated, with or without an appendage at each end. Cultures of Plagiostoma generally grow moderately (4 cm) to fast (5-6 cm) diam after 7 d on PDA, velvety, granular, with concentric halo, with scant aerial mycelium, translucent, white, pale to very dark gray, hazel, dark green, olive or with various dark yellow to orange pigmentation, margins fringed, stringed, or root-like.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Monod (1983)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Species of Plagiostoma</head><p>Note: <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Monod (1983)</ref> provided a detailed description of this species as Gnomonia amygdalinae. Although ITS sequences of P. amygdalinae (Monod 207 = CBS 791.79) and P. euphorbiaceum (MS196 = CBS 121241, Monod 465 = CBS 816.79) suggest that these taxa are the same, the multigene phylogeny obtained here reveals that P. amygdalinae and P. euphorbiaceum are distinct species. Plagiostoma amygdalinae occurs on leaves and has a longer and thinner perithecial neck, shorter asci, thinner apical ring, and ascospores not constricted at septum and thinner than P. euphorbiaceum that occurs on twigs, stems, and branches (also see <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Monod 1983)</ref>. Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary, scattered, appearing initially as slight punctiform elevations of periderm surrounded by a black halo with tip of neck protruding through slit, usually with three short radiating slits, halo paler in some collections, later becoming completely black, globose, (223-)252-364(-440) μm high × (349-)370-476(-477) μm diam (mean = 314 × 429 μm, SD 59, 77, n = 8), each with one neck. Neck central to eccentric, straight to oblique, with a pale brown papilla, with an expanded area that appears disk-like, sometimes evident only as a thick neck, initially below epidermis, becoming exposed, producing a black halo at surface, (115-)159-256(-351) μm long (mean = 208, SD 78, n = 8), expanded area (187-)224-340(-389) μm diam (mean = 284, SD 74, n = 8), (62.5-)81-128(-134) μm diam at apex (mean = 104, SD 29, n = 7). Asci cylindrical, (45-)51-80(-86) × 10-16(-18) μm (mean = 68 × 13, SD 15, 4, n = 19), apical ring 2.5-5.0 μm diam, variable in shape e.g. elongated as two bodies or hexagonal, with eight ascospores arranged biseriate to multiseriate. Ascospores oblong-ellipsoid, slightly tapering to rounded ends, straight to slightly curved, one median to submedian septum, not constricted, (12-)16-18.5(-21) × (3-)5-6(-7) μm (mean = 16.5 × 5.5, SD 2.5, 1.0, n = 106), l : w (2.4-)2.9-3.2(-4) (mean = 3.0, SD 0.3, n = 106), with granular cytoplasm. Cultures: Moderate to fast growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 5 cm (SD 0.4, n = 4), thin aerial mycelium of velvety granular texture, central area vinaceous buff 45, with scattered black mycelial clumps of 0.5 mm diam in central area, margin white, stringy; reverse similar but slightly darker.</p><p>Habitat and host: On dead twigs and branches of Salix spp., <ref type="bibr">Salix alba, S. alba subsp. vitellina, S. dasyclados</ref> Notes: The specimen designated here as lectotype is part of the collection of Sphaeria apiculata referred to in the protologue. It agrees with Wallroth's description of S. apiculata. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fuckel (1870)</ref> recircumscribed Sphaeria apiculata Wallr. based on Fungi Rhenani 918. The original Latin description of Sphaeria apiculata includes morphological characters of the perithecia such as an apiculate papilla, i.e. "coronatum dilatatis", here interpreted as the diskshaped expansion of the perithecial neck, and "nucleo atro" at the apex. These morphological characters are present in the type specimen BPI 799092 of S. apiculata designated here as the lectotype. The protologue of S. apiculata by Wallroth (1833) does not include a description of the ascospores, however, the fungus on this specimen contains broadly ellipsoid ascospores. This specimen and thus Plagiostoma apiculatum is distinctive and differs from Plagiostoma salicellum as discussed under that species.</p><p>The concept of the name Sphaeria apiculata has been confused. The following is an account of this species and its various synonyms based on the results of our study of the original description, type specimens, and relevant later specimens. Höhnel (1917), <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Petrak (1921)</ref>, and later authors considered Sphaeria apiculata to have narrowly elongated ascospores while <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wehmeyer (1933)</ref> recognised this species as having broadly ellipsoid ascospores and considered Cryptodiaporthe salicina to be a synonym. Höhnel (1917) examined specimens made by Rehm, Krieger, and his own of Diaporthe spina and considered this name to be a synonym of Sphaeria apiculata. He acknowledged differences in perithecial neck length among collections of these two species. To determine the synonymy of these two species we compared the original description of D. spina with the original description of S. apiculata by Wallroth (1833) as well as the recircumscription by Fuckel (1870). In his original description of D. spina <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Fuckel (1870)</ref> provided a drawing that is quite unlike the original description of S. apiculata. Based on the comparison of descriptions and the specimens observed, we do not consider S. apiculata and D. spina to be synonyms. The synonymy of these two species proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Höhnel (1917)</ref> and accepted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Petrak's (1921)</ref> who provided a description of Cryptodiaporthe apiculata (≡ Sphaeria apiculata ) may be the reason that later authors considered S. apiculata to be characterised by narrow, elongated ascospores as described and observed for D. spina. <ref type="bibr">Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 62: 69. 2008</ref><ref type="bibr">. Note: Sogonov et al. (2008</ref> provided a description and illustrations of this species. Cultures of isolates used in this study are illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Fig. 7G-H</ref> Ascospores ellipsoid-fusoid, tapering toward rounded ends, curved or straight, one median to submedian septum, constricted, <ref type="bibr">(16-)</ref>18-20(-22) × 4-5 μm (mean = 18.5 × 4.5, SD 1.0, 0.4, n = 51), l : w (3.2-)3.9-4.5(-4.9) (mean = 4.2, SD 0.4, n = 51), with four refractive bodies of various shapes, often globose. Notes: Plagiostoma convexum as Sphaeria convexa was considered a synonym of Cryptodiaporthe salicina by <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wehmeyer (1933)</ref>. Plagiostoma convexum has ascospores that agree with those drawn by <ref type="bibr">Wehmeyer (1933 as C. salicina, plate XIII, figs 3-5)</ref>. In his description of S. salicina, <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Currey (1858)</ref> mentions that the septum in the sporidia (ascospores) is "often very difficult to make out", but the ascospores in his drawing have a septum.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wehmeyer (1933)</ref> listed 28 synonyms of Cryptodiaporthe salicina. Among specimens that <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wehmeyer (1933)</ref> recognised under that name, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Butin (1958)</ref> elaborated differences in ascospore morphology, conidial state, host, and ecological characteristics and distinguished three species: C. apiculata (Wallr.) Petr., C. populea (Sacc.) Butin, and C. pulchella (Sacc.) Butin, here accepted as Plagiostoma apiculatum, P. populinum, and P. pulchellum. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Butin (1958)</ref> did not consider any of these species to be conspecific with Sphaeria salicina Curr. On the contrary he listed Cryptodiaporthe salicina based on Sphaeria salicina Curr. as a synonym of Cryptodiaporthe salicella, here recognised as Plagiostoma salicellum. Although <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wehmeyer (1933)</ref> listed Sphaeria sphingiophora Oudem. 1873 [≡ Diaporthe sphingiophora (Oudem.) Sacc.] as a synonym of C. salicella, S. sphingiophora occurs on Cornus. It is unlikely to be the same species as P. convexum. Diaporthe cupulata Berl. &amp; Destrée was considered a synonym of Sphaeria convexa by <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wehmeyer (1933)</ref>, however, the ascospore sizes of these species are different. We do not consider them to be synonymous. The specimen at BPI of Sphaeria salicina Pers., Scleromyceti Sueciae 10, was examined and determined to be a species of Valsa.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Monod (1983)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Plagiostoma barriae</head><p>Note: <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Barr (1978)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Monod (1983)</ref> provided detailed descriptions of this species. Plagiostoma dilatatum L.C. Mejía, sp. nov. MycoBank MB515700. <ref type="figure">Figs 3A-D</ref>, 7I-L.</p><p>Etymology: dilatatum -dilate; referring to the dilated or expanded area of the perithecial neck that appears disk-like when seen from above, and like a thick collar in section.</p><p>Perithecia globosa, (277-)320-442(-502) μm elata, (382-)475-572(-642) μm diametro; rostrum breve, apice punctatum, (152-)257-308(-327) μm longum, cum expansa area disciformi vertice visu, simili collo in sectione, (217-)352-401(-452) μm diametro ubi latissima, (92-)95-108(-122) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae reniformes vel oblongo-ellipticae, uni-septatae, constrictae ubi medianae vel submedianae septatae, <ref type="bibr">(12-)</ref>13-15(-22) × (4-)4-5(-7) μm, L:l (2.6-)3.0-3.3(-3.8).</p><p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary or aggregated, appearing initially as slight elevation of periderm surrounded by a black halo, later developing into a black circular spot, apex protruding through a tiny slit, globose, (277-)320-442(-502) μm high × (382-)475-572(-642) μm diam <ref type="bibr">(mean = 383 × 515,</ref><ref type="bibr">SD 78,</ref><ref type="bibr">79,</ref><ref type="bibr">n1 = 11,</ref><ref type="bibr">n2 = 10)</ref>, each with one neck. Neck central to eccentric, relatively short, with punctate ostiolar opening, expanded, initially below epidermis, appearing disk-like when seen from above, like a thick collar in section, becoming exposed, with black halo or circular area below epidermis, when epidermis removed, exposing expanded neck and apex, sometimes two necks joined at expanded area; sometimes black mycelium of developing conidioma above perithecia; neck (152-)257-308(-327) μm long (mean = 263, SD 61, n = 10), (217-) 352-401(-452) μm diam at base (mean = 367, SD 67, n = 10), (92-)95-108(-122) μm diam at apex (mean = 103, SD 10, n = 9). Asci cylindric, (48-)54-62(-77) × (8-)12-14(-18) μm (mean = 58 × 13, SD 7.2, 2.5, n = 15), long stalked, apical ring 2.1-4.3 μm diam, appearing rectangular, with eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel to multiseriate. Ascospores renoid to oblong-ellipsoid, slightly tapering to rounded ends, slightly curved, one, median to submedian septum, slightly constricted, (12-)13-15(-22) × 4-5(-7) μm (mean = 15 × 5, SD 2.5, 1.0, n = 48), l : w (2.6-)3.0-3.3(-3.8) (mean = 3.2, SD 0.3, n = 48), with granular cytoplasm.</p><p>Cultures: Moderate to fast growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 5.2 cm (SD 0.2, n = 8), thin aerial mycelium of velvety to granular texture, whitish to vinaceous buff 86, becoming olivaceous 48 toward margin; fasiculate mycelium buff 45 developing from concave central area; reverse same; 7 d a.c.d. denser mycelium hazel 88 in centre, with vinaceous 86, black droplets on surface, with immersed mycelium dark, reverse dark, with a lighter halo and whitish to translucent margin.  Perithecia immersed in bark, aggregated in groups up to 12, joined by a scanty, brownish to cream stroma, occasionally solitary, appearing as elevations in bark where perithecial necks emerge through slit or crack in periderm, usually ellipsoid in shape when seen from top, black, suboblate, (186-)194-227(-278) μm high × (219-)269-336(-341) μm diam (mean = 216 × 293, SD 31, 49, n = 9), each with one neck. Neck marginal, slightly sulcate, long, (197-)247-281(-382) μm long (mean = 270, SD 54, n = 9), (50-) 53-63(-67) μm diam at base (mean = 59, SD 6.1, n = 9), (39-)44-49(-50) μm diam at apex (mean = 46, SD 3.7, n = 9). Asci cylindric to clavate, (15-)39-57(-76) × (3.5-)6.5-11(-13) μm (mean = 49.5 × 8.5, SD 15.1, 2.6, n = 26), apical ring 1.5-3.5 μm diam, with eight ascospores arranged biseriate. Ascospores ellipsoid, tapering to rounded ends, 1-septate, constricted at submedian septum, (9-) 10-15(-16) × 2-3(-4) μm (mean = 12.5 × 3.0, SD 2.4, 0.7, n = 49), l : w (3-)4-4.5(-6) (mean = 4.3, SD 0.4, n = 49), usually with at least four refractive circular bodies in each ascospore, two large ones on each side of septum, one smaller one at end of each cell.</p><p>Cultures: Moderate to fast growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 4.3 cm (SD 1, n = 16), thin aerial mycelium appearing velvety, margin fringed, stringy, whitish to buff 45 or vinaceous buff 86 from top, with a slightly to pronounced halo of thick, white mycelium extending about 2 cm from centre, reverse whitish to buff 45.</p><p>Habitat and host: On dead, still attached, overwintered twigs of Corylus californica (Betulaceae).  <ref type="bibr">Redlin &amp; Stack, Mycotaxon 32:185. 1988</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Distribution: USA (Oregon</head><p>Note: This species, often as its anamorph referred to as Discula fraxinea (Peck) Redlin &amp; Stack, causes an anthracnose disease of ash and fringetree (Oleaceae) known most commonly in the eastern and midwestern United States, rarely from Oregon <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Gregory et al. 2004</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Redlin &amp; Stack (1988)</ref>  Note: <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Müller &amp; Arx (1962)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Monod (1983)</ref>  Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary, appearing as slight elevations of periderm, central area pale, delimited by black halo from which apex of neck protrudes, black, globose, (289-)309-356(-414) μm high × (385-)412-462(-504) μm diam (mean = 338 × 437, SD 44, 41, n = 7), each with one neck. Neck central to eccentric, short, with apex scarcely protruding through a tiny slit, with neck expanded below epidermis, disk-like when seen from above, like a thick collar in section, with black halo or circular black spot through epidermis or black when exposed, (136-)175-211(-225) μm long (mean = 189, SD 38, n = 4), (251-)301-318(-351) μm diam at widest point (mean = 307, SD 36.3, n = 5), (87-)89-100(-113) μm diam at apex (mean = 97.5, SD 10.5, n = 5). Asci ovoid elongate, often with long, slender, persistent stalk, (67-)76-80(-87) × <ref type="bibr">(13-)</ref>18-21(-24) μm (mean = 77.5 × 19.5, SD 4.9, 3.1, n = 11), apical ring 3.0-4.5 μm diam, with eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel to multiseriate. Ascospores renoid to oblong-ellipsoid, slightly tapering to broadly rounded ends, slightly curved, one median septum, slightly constricted, (18-)19-20(-21) × (5-)6-7(-8) μm (mean = 19.5 × 6.5, SD 0.9, 0.6, n = 45), l : w (2.5-)3(-4) (mean = 3, SD 0.3, n = 45), with granular cytoplasm.</p><p>Cultures: Moderate growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 4 cm (SD 0.4, n = 4), thin aerial mycelium of velvety, powdery texture, margin stringy, colour grey becoming vinaceous buff 86 from the top, reverse isabelline 65. Note: Plagiostoma imperceptibile has an expanded neck similar to other species in the clade, specifically P. apiculatum, P. convexum, P. dilatatum, and P. pulchellum <ref type="figure">(Fig. 1)</ref>.</p><p>Plagiostoma oregonense L.C. Mejía, sp. nov. MycoBank MB515703. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figs 4A-C</ref>, 7S-T.</p><p>Etymology: oregonense -from Oregon, referring to the only state in the USA where it was collected.</p><p>Perithecia subglobosa, (261-)270-326(-373) μm elata, (369-)381-400(-407) μm diametro; rostrum breve, (156-)168-182(-185) μm longum, cum expansa area, disciformi vertice visu, simili collo in sectione, (176-)182-204(-221) μm diametro ubi latissima, 119-120(-121) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae latoellipticae vel ellipticae, uni-septatae, constrictae medianae vel submedianae septatae, <ref type="bibr">(16-)</ref>17-19(-22)×(4-)6(-7) μm, L:l (2.6-)2.9-3.2(-4.0).</p><p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary, evident as conic-shaped elevation of periderm with neck protruding, black, globose to subglobose, (261-)270-326(-373) μm high × (369-)381-400(-407) μm diam (mean = 304 × 389, SD 60, 19, n = 3), each with one neck. Neck eccentric or lateral, expanded, usually attached to periderm, (156-)168-182(-185) μm long (mean = 173, SD 16, n = 3), (176-)182-204(-221) μm diam at base (mean = 195, SD 23, n = 3), (119-)119-120(-121) μm diam at apex (mean = 120, SD 1.0, n = 3). Asci cylindric, (74-)78-92(-95) × <ref type="bibr">(12-)</ref>15-17(-19) μm (mean = 86 × 16, SD 8, 2, n = 10), apical ring 2.8-4.0 μm diam, looks like a stretched hexagon, with eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel or biseriate. Ascospores broadly ellipsoid to ellipsoid, with rounded ends, 1-septate, constricted at median to submedian septum, <ref type="bibr">(16-)</ref>17-19(-22) × (4.5-)5.5-6(-7) μm (mean = 18.0 × 6.0, SD 1.5, 0.5, n = 36), l : w (2.6-)2.9-3.2(-4.0) (mean = 3.1, SD 0.3, n = 36), with granular cytoplasm.</p><p>Cultures: Moderate growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 4.6 cm (SD 0.1, n = 2), thin aerial mycelium of felty texture, margin fringed, stringy, central area white, with a halo of aerial mycelium 1.5 cm from centre, marginal area buff 45m, reverse with a central circular area of 2 cm diam fawn 87. Etymology: ovalis -ovoid; sporum -spore, referring to the ovoid shape of the ascospores.</p><p>Perithecia globosa, (246-)277-363(-385) μm elata, (394-)403-414(-427) μm diametro; rostrum breve, (131-)146-159(-162) μm longum, apice cupulatum, (125-)136-153 <ref type="bibr">(-194)</ref> μm basi, (113-)117-160(-168) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae ovoideae, non-septatae, (12-)14-16(-17) × (7-)7-8(-9) μm, L:l (1.6-) 1.8-2.0(-2.2).</p><p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary, or in groups up to five, usually in a row, scattered, erumpent, appearing as raised, conical area of bark periderm, with neck protruding through slit or hole, black, globose, (246-)277-363(-385) μm high × (394-)403-414(-427) μm diam (mean = 322 × 409, SD 57, 11, n = 6), each with one neck. Neck lateral, short and thick, apex cupulate, (131-)146-159(-162) μm long (mean = 151, SD 12, n = 6), (125-)136-153 <ref type="bibr">(-194)</ref> μm diam at base (mean = 150, SD 24, n = 6), (113-)117-160(-168) μm diam at apex (mean = 139, SD 24, n = 6). Asci cylindric to obclavate, (63.5-) 68.5-75.5(-87.5) × (12.5-)14.5-17(-18) μm (mean = 72 × 15.5, SD 6.5, 1.5, n = 19), apical ring 3.5-4.5 μm diam, with eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel to biseriate. Ascospores ovoid, non-septate, appearing double-walled, more evident when stained with cotton blue lactophenol or Melzer's reagent, <ref type="bibr">(12-)</ref>14-16(-17) × 7-8(-9) μm (mean = 15 × 7.5, SD 1.2, 0.5, n = 35), l : w (1.6-)1.8-2(-2.2) (mean = 1.9, SD 0.1, n = 35).</p><p>Cultures: Moderate growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 4.2 cm (SD 0.1, n = 2), thin aerial mycelium of felty texture, margin fringed, like roots, whitish, with denser mycelium in centre within a radius of 1 cm, reverse buff 45 becoming dark grey, whitish in the margin. Notes: This species differs from other species of Plagiostoma by having ovoid, non-septate ascospores. The other two known species of Plagiostoma with non-septate ascospores, P. euphorbiae-verrucosae and P. fraxini, occur on hosts other than Salix and their ascospores are ellipsoid-fusoid. Unlike P. dilatatum, P. ovalisporum does not have a circular black halo or spot at the point where the perithecial necks emerge through the periderm.  <ref type="bibr">Barr, Mycol. Mem. 7: 136. 1978.</ref> Notes: <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Barr (1978)</ref> provided a detailed description of this species as Cryptodiaporthe petiolophila.</p><p>Plagiostoma populinum <ref type="bibr">(Fuckel)</ref>   <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Butin (1958)</ref>.</p><p>≡ Cryptodiaporthe populea (Sacc.) <ref type="bibr">Butin, Sydowia 11: 31. 1958</ref><ref type="bibr">[1957</ref>.</p><p>Moderate to fast growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 3.3 cm (SD 1.2, n = 8), thin aerial mycelium of velvety or felty texture, whitish to buff 45 or rosy buff 6 in central area and isabeline 65 in the margin, with some droplets (honey 64) in the centre, with fringed margin appearing like roots, reverse whitish to fawn 87 or honey 64, in some cultures becoming dark and with a concentric halo light.</p><p>Cultures are illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">Fig. 8A</ref>-D.</p><p>Notes: <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Butin (1958)</ref> presented a full description with illustrations of this species as Cryptodiaporthe populea. Because the name Cryptodiaporthe populina <ref type="bibr">(Fuckel)</ref>Petr. based on Valsa populina Fuckel was already occupied in Cryptodiaporthe, <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Butin (1958)</ref> based his new combination on Diaporthe populea Sacc. When placed in Plagiostoma the basionym Cryptospora populina Fuckel provides the oldest epithet for this species.   <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Butin (1958)</ref>.</p><p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary, often growing close together, appearing initially as slight elevation of periderm, with black halo or black spot where apex protrudes through a small hole, black, globose, (311-)371-473(-613) μm high × (467-)483-642(-660) μm diam (mean = 435 × 563, SD 128, 99, n = 4), each with one neck. Neck central to eccentric, straight to oblique, with an expanded disklike area, initially below epidermis, becoming exposed with time, producing black halo or spot at surface, (169-)173-319(-388) μm long (mean = 257, SD 105, n = 4), (153-)209-256(-306) μm diam at widest point (mean = 231, SD 62.5, n = 4), (93-)99-160(-212) μm diam at apex (mean = 137, SD 54, n = 4). Asci ovoid elongated, (75-)85-107(-117) × (15-)17-21 <ref type="bibr">(-24)</ref> μm <ref type="bibr">(mean = 95 × 19,</ref><ref type="bibr">SD 13.5,</ref><ref type="bibr">3</ref>.0, n = 15), apical ring 4-4.8 μm diam, very thick, with eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel to multiseriate. Ascospores oblong ellipsoid-elongated, slightly tapering, with rounded ends, straight to slightly curved, one median to submedian septum, not constricted, (17-)18-22(-27) × (5-)6-7(-7.5) μm (mean = 20.3 × 6.3, SD 2.9, 0.6, n = 39), l : w (2.5-)2.9-3.4(-4.4) (mean = 3.2, SD 0.4, n = 39), with granular cytoplasm.</p><p>Cultures: Moderate growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 3.9 cm (0.8 n = 6), thin aerial mycelium whitish to rosy vinaceous 58 colour, of velvety, granular texture due to mycelial clumps ca. 500 um diam, isabeline 65, produced in central area of 2.4 cm diam, central area appearing often moist, margin translucent to buff 45, with hyphae extending radially, stringy, becoming fringed toward margin; reverse whitish to rosy vinaceous 58 or olivaceous. At 14 d small black and dark green slimy droplet surrounded by a second halo rosy vinaceous 58 with white greyish margin, reverse same colour pattern.</p><p>Habitat and host: On dead, still attached branches of Populus balsamifera, Populus sp., <ref type="bibr">Salix babylonica, S. humboldtiana and S. lucida (Salicaceae)</ref>.</p><p>Distribution: North America, South America (Argentina), and Europe.</p><p>Type specimen: France, Troyes, on branch of Populus alba cv. pyramidalis, Briard n. 5, PAD-not available. Notes: <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Butin (1958)</ref> refers to this species as saprobic on Populus spp. The evidence presented in this study shows that this species also infects Salix spp. and has a more extensive geographic distribution than previously reported.</p><p>Plagiostoma rhododendri (Auersw.) <ref type="bibr">Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 62: 72. 2008</ref><ref type="bibr">. Basionym: Gnomonia rhododendri Auersw. in Gonn. &amp; Rabenh., Mycol. Europ. 5/6: 26. 1869</ref> ≡ Apiognomonia rhododendri (Auersw.) <ref type="bibr">Remler, Bibliotheca Mycologica 68: 74. 1979.</ref> Note: <ref type="bibr">Remler (1979 as A. rhododendri)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Monod (1983 as G. rhododendri)</ref>  Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary or in groups up to five, scattered, evident as slight elevation of periderm, black, subglobose, (157-)208-308(-331) μm high × (339-)372-410(-507) μm diam (mean = 257 × 397, SD 60, 43, n = 11), each with one neck. Neck cylindrical, eccentric to lateral, surrounded by a whitish stroma, (96-)147-202(-308) μm long (mean = 177, SD 67, n = 11), (61-)80-84(-95) μm diam at base (mean = 81, SD 8.8, n = 11), (54-)74-85(-91) μm diam at apex (mean = 79, <ref type="bibr">SD 10,</ref><ref type="bibr">n = 11)</ref>. Asci cylindric to clavate, (40-)51.5-59(-63) × <ref type="bibr">(11-)</ref> <ref type="bibr">13-14(-15)</ref> μm (mean = 55 × 13, SD 5.8, 1.4, n = 15), with apical ring 2.0-3.5 μm diam, with eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel or irregularly seriate. Ascospores ellipsoid-elongated, slightly tapering toward rounded ends, 1-septate, often with short appendages 1.5-2 μm, slightly constricted at median to submedian septum, (14-)17-20(-27) × 3-4(-5) μm (mean = 18.5 × 3.5, SD 2.3, 0.5, n = 57), l : w (3.2-)5.2-6.6(-8.7) (mean = 5.9, SD 1.1, n = 57), with granular cytoplasm.  a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma Notes: The application of the name Sphaeria salicella Fr. has been the source of confusion and the subject of taxonomic studies since the 1800's. It was clearly specified by <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Fries (1823)</ref> that this name is typified by Fries : Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 issued in 1821. According to <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wehmeyer (1933)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Butin (1958)</ref> confusion about this name was in part due to the fact that different parts of exsiccati Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 contain different species. One of the two species has the narrowly ellipsoid, elongated ascospores of P. salicellum while the other has the broadly ellipsoid ascospores of P. apiculatum. Not recognising the confusion regarding Scleromyceti Sueciae 188, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Petrak (1921)</ref> wrongly suggested that S. salicella was characterised by having broadly ellipsoid ascospores and made a new combination Cryptodiaporthe salicella (Fr.) Petr. in addition to the new combination C. apiculata (Wallr.) Petr. based on S. apiculata Wallr. The latter species was wrongly considered to have narrowly ellipsoid, elongated ascospores. It is not clear if <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Petrak (1921)</ref> looked at the type specimen of S. apiculata or if he based his conclusions solely on the description of S. apiculata by Wallroth (1833). <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wehmeyer (1933)</ref> arrived at a conclusion different from that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Petrak (1921)</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wehmeyer (1933)</ref> studied the exsiccati Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 at the Farlow Herbarium and determined that this number and hence S. salicella Fr. were characterised by having narrowly ellipsoid, elongated ascospores. To use his words, S. salicella represents "the narrow-spored species". He synonymised S. salicella Fr. with C. apiculata (Wallr.) Petr. and published the combination C. salicella (Fr.) Wehm. (1933) non <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Petrak (1921)</ref>. In addition, <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wehmeyer (1933)</ref> made the new combination C. salicina (Curr.) Wehm. based on S. salicina Curr. for species having broadly ellipsoid ascospores (see notes under P. convexum). Later <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Butin (1958)</ref> studied species of Cryptodiaporthe on Populus and Salix, examined Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 at Uppsala Herbarium, and suggested that S. salicella should be understood as the species with broadly ellipsoid ascospores and followed Petrak's concept of S. salicella.</p><p>We studied the Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 (Sbarbaro collection) available at the BPI Herbarium as well as other exsiccati of taxa that have been synonymised with S. salicella and C. salicina including S. apiculata. In doing so we paid close attention to the original descriptions of S. apiculata Wallr. and S. salicella Fr. In referring to Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 Fries (1823) described S. salicella as having a powdery "albicant" (whitish) stroma and that the multiple ostioles are "erumpent simultaneously". The specimen of Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 at BPI includes all of these morphological characters and has ascospores that are ellipsoid elongated (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">Fig. 5A, B, D, and G)</ref>.</p><p>In their treatment of Plagiostoma,  made the combination Plagiostoma salicellum (Fr.) Sogonov. In our study of P. salicellum we noticed that ascospore length and width can be quite variable, even within an ascus, but with a prevalence of elongated ascospores <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">(Fig. 5A-H)</ref>. A second specimen, BPI 878975 from Germany on Salix repens, was sequenced and determined to be conspecific with the epitype of P. salicellum within a major clade containing two other species having cylindrical ostioles and ellipsoid elongated ascospores. Unlike the lectotype and epitype of P. salicellium, the ascospores of BPI 878975 are ellipsoid but not elongated. In spite of this difference in ascospore morphology, BPI 878975 is P. salicellum based on the cylindrical perithecial neck surrounded by a whitish stroma as well as DNA sequence data.</p><p>In summary Plagiostoma salicellum is characterised by having cylindrical perithecial necks surrounded by a whitish stroma and ascospores predominantly ellipsoid-elongated, less commonly ellipsoid, tapering to slightly acute, rounded ends <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">(Fig. 5D-G)</ref>, unlike P. apiculatum that has oblong ellipsoid to renoid, broadly rounded ascospores <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Fig. 2H-J)</ref>.</p><p>Plagiostoma samuelsii L.C. Mejía, sp. nov. MycoBank MB515707. Figs 5I-O, 8M-P.</p><p>Etymology: Named in honour of distinguished mycologist Gary J. Samuels for his outstanding contributions to the systematics of Pyrenomycetes.</p><p>Perithecia subglobosa, (192-)204-258(-305) μm elata, (295-)302-327(-334) μm diametro, rostrum conicum, (114-)128-161(-170) μm longum, (69-)72-74(-81) μm diametro basi, (58-)62-73(-78) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae ellipticae, uniseptatae, constrictae ubi medianae vel submedianae septatae, <ref type="bibr">(10-)11-12(-19</ref>) × 3-4 μm, appendiculatae duabus extremitatibus, anguste filiformes, ascosporis vulgo 2-plo longiores, appendices deliquescentes.</p><p>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary or in groups up to five, scattered on substrate, evident as conical shaped elevations of host periderm with necks protruding through small holes in periderm, black, subglobose, (192-)204-258(-305) μm high × (295-)302-327(-334) μm diam (mean = 239 × 313, SD 43, 16, n = 6), each with one neck. Neck eccentric to lateral, surrounded by a whitish stroma, cone-shaped with rounded apex, (114-)128-161(-170) μm long (mean = 145, SD 23, n = 6), (69-)72-74(-81) μm at base (mean = 73.8, SD 3.9, n = 6), (58-)62-73(-78) μm at apex (mean = 67.5, SD 8.0, n = 6). Asci cylindric to clavate, (32-)42-62(-79) × (6-)7-11 <ref type="bibr">(-12)</ref> μm (mean = 53 × 9, SD 13, 2.1, n = 24), apical ring 1.8-3.6 μm diam, with eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel or biseriate. Ascospores ellipsoid, 1-septate, constricted at median to submedian septum, with two deliquescent appendages, one at end of each cell, narrowly filiform, usually twice the length of ascospores, <ref type="bibr">(10-)11-12(-19</ref>) × 3-4 μm (mean = 12 × 3.5, SD 1.4, 0.2, n = 48), l : w (2.8-)3.2-3.5(-4.8) (mean = 3.4, SD 0.4, n = 48), with four refractive bodies in each cell, two big ones near septum, one smaller one at end of each cell.</p><p>Cultures: Fast growth on PDA after 7 d reaching edge of petri plates of 6 cm diam (n = 8), thin aerial mycelium of felty to granular texture, fringed, stringy margin, with concentric halo of dense mycelium 1.4 cm from centre, buff 45 inside halo or central region, white toward margin, some cultures with depression at concentric halo, reverse honey 64 developing a halo fawn 87 near margin. Notes: Plagiostoma samuelsii is the only species of Plagiostoma on leaves of Alnus except for P. jensenii M.E. Barr. Unlike P. samuelsii, P. jensenii lacks a stroma and perithecial neck and has longer and wider ascospores (20-30 × 4-6 μm) with very short pulvinate appendages <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Barr 1991</ref> Etymology: versatile -versatile, referring to the occurrence of this species on different plant organs, twigs, branches, and leaves; and to the variable nature of the perithecia that grow with short necks on twigs and branches and with medium to long necks on leaves.</p><p>Perithecia subglobosa, (178-)194-317(-345) μm elata, (232-)264-378(-444) μm diametro; rostrum cylindricum, (60-)77-137(-226) μm longum, (51-)56-80(-87) μm diamtro basi, (37-)49-60(-76) μm apice. Ascosporae elliptico-elongatae, uniseptatae, constrictae ubi medianae vel submedianae septatae, (18-)20-23(-25) × 3-4 μm, L:l (4.9-)5.6-6.8 <ref type="bibr">(-8.6</ref>).</p><p>Perithecia immersed in bark of twigs or in midvein and petioles of adaxial and abaxial side of leaves, solitary or in pairs, scattered, on twigs evident as slight elevations of periderm that appear black, upper part of perithecia showing a few cell layers below epidermis, on leaves producing swollen, raised areas on midvein, becoming highly erumpent, cracking periderm and leaving an ellipsoidal cavity, with longer neck on leaves than on twigs, black, subglobose, (178-)194-317(-345) μm high × (232-)264-378(-444) μm diam (mean = 248 × 323, SD 68.5, 78, n = 8), each with one neck. Neck eccentric to lateral, short, ostiolar opening sulcate with four grooves, (60-)77-137(-226) μm long (mean = 115, SD 59.7, n = 8), (51-)56-80(-87) μm diam at base (mean = 68.5, SD 13.4, n = 8), (37-)49-60(-76) μm diam at apex (mean = 55, <ref type="bibr">SD 11.8,</ref><ref type="bibr">n = 8)</ref>. Asci cylindric to clavate, (49-)54-66(-71) × <ref type="bibr">(11-)</ref> <ref type="bibr">13-16(-20)</ref> μm (mean = 60 × 15, SD 7.5, 2.5, n = 15), apical ring 2.0-3.5 μm diam, with eight ascospores arranged biseriate. Ascospores ellipsoid elongated, slightly tapering toward rounded ends, 1-septate, constricted at median to submedian septum, (18-)20-23(-25) × 3-4 μm (mean = 21.5 × 3.5, SD 2.0, 0.4, n = 36), l : w (4.9-)5.6-6.8(-8.6) (mean = 6.2, SD 1.0, n = 36), usually with four large refractive bodies, two near septum, one in each end of cells.</p><p>Cultures: Fast growth on PDA after 7 d reaching the edge of petri plates of 6 cm diam (n = 12), thin aerial mycelium of felty to granular texture, margin fringed, like roots, buff 45 with clumps of white mycelium, with a halo of elevated mycelium at 1.5 cm from centre, reverse buff 45 becoming dark, with halo visible from reverse. Notes: The ascospores of this species are similar to those of Plagiostoma salicellum, however, the perithecial necks of P. versatile lack the whitish stroma characteristic of P. salicellum. Etymology: referring to the place where this species was collected: Yunnan, China.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Plagiostoma yunnanense</head><p>Perithecia globosa, (231-)267-311(-318) μm elata, (282-)312-352(-362) μm diametro, rostrum cylindricum, contortum, (315-)318-321(-322) μm longum, (77-) 78-81(-82) μm diametro basi, (57-)59-63(-66) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae elliptico-elongatae, uni-septatae, leviter vel non constrictum ubi septatae, (19-)23-26(-27) × 3-4, L:l (6. 6-)6.8-7.9(-8.2).</p><p>Perithecia immersed, solitary or in groups, numerous, appearing as conical elevations of periderm where necks protrude, black, globose, (231-)267-311(-318) μm high × (282-)312-352(-362) μm diam (mean = 284 × 328, SD 48, 42, n = 3), each with one neck. Neck eccentric, contorted, (315-)318-321(-322) μm long (mean = 319, SD 3.8, n = 3), (77-)78-81(-82) μm diam at base (mean = 79,   </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>4 2. Ascospores ovoid, (12-)14-16(-17) × 7-8(-9) μm. On twigs of Salix sp., in North America (USA: ID) .............................. P. ovalisporum 2'. Ascospores ellipsoid-fusoid. Not on Salix, in Europe and North America ................................................................................................. 3 3. Ascospores 20-25.5 × 5.3-6 μm fide Monod (1983), with pointed ends. On Euphorbia, in Europe .................. P. euphorbiae-verrucosae 3'</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Plagiostoma apiculatum (Wallr.) L.C. Mejía, comb. nov. MycoBank MB515689. Figs 2A-J, 7C-F Basionym: Sphaeria apiculata Wallr., Fl. Crypt. Germ. 2: 778. 1833. ≡ Metasphaeria apiculata (Wallr.) Sacc., Syll. Fung. 2: 166. 1883. ≡ Gnomonia apiculata (Wallr.) G. Winter, Rabenh., Kryptog.-Fl., ed. 2, vol. 1(2): 589. 1887. ≡ Diaporthe spina Fuckel var. apiculata (Wallr.) Rehm, Ann. Mycol. 7: 404. 1909. ≡ Cryptodiaporthe apiculata (Wallr.) Petr., Ann. Mycol. 19: 177. 1921.Anamorph: Diplodina microsperma (Johnst.) B.Sutton, Mycol. Pap.  141: 69. 1977.    </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Morphology on natural substrate. A-J: Plagiostoma apiculatum: A,B,I,J = BPI 799002 (lectotype), C-G = BPI 747938 (epitype), H = BPI 878952. K-R. P. convexum: K-M = BPI 799418 (lectotype), L-R = BPI 843490 (epitype). Bars = (A, K) 1 mm; (B-F, L, O-Q) 100 μm; (G-J, M-N, R) 10 μm. a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Habitat and host: On dead, still attached twigs of Salix caprea and S. irrorata (Salicaceae).Distribution: France (Melle). Holotype: France, Deux-Sèvres Département, Melle, Melle Arboretum, on Salix irrorata, 15 Apr 2008, L.C. Mejía 402, BPI 878959, derived cultures CBS 124976 = LCM 402.02, = LCM402.01. Additional specimens examined: France, Deux-Sèvres Département, Foret del' Hermitain, on Salix caprea, 17 Apr. 2008, L.C. Mejía 403, BPI 878958, derived cultures LCM403.01, LCM403.02.Notes: The intricate mycelium that develops above the body of the perithecia in some pustules resembles the conidioma of Diplodina, the anamorph of Plagiostoma.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Plagiostoma euphorbiae-verrucosae (M. Monod) Sogonov,Stud. Mycol. 62: 72. 2008    Basionym: Gnomoniella euphorbiae-verrucosae M.Monod, Beih.  Sydowia 9: 42. 1983.   Note: Monod (1983 provided a detailed description of this species. Plagiostoma exstocollum L.C. Mejía, sp. nov. MycoBank MB515701. Figs 3E-H, 7M-P. Etymology: exsto -standing out; collus -neck, referring to the perithecial neck that emerges from the host periderm. Perithecia suboblata, (186-)194-227(-278) μm etata, (219-)269-336(-341) μm diámetro, rostrum (197-)247-281(-382) μm longum, (50-)53-63(-67) μm diamwtro basi, (39-)44-49(-50) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae ellipsoideae, uni-septatae, constrictae ubi submedianae septatae, (9-)10-15(-16) × (2-)2-3(-4) μm, L:l (3-)4-4.5(-6).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>provided detailed descriptions of this species as Gnomonia geranii. Plagiostoma imperceptibile L.C. Mejía, sp. nov. MycoBank MB515702. Figs 3I-M, 7Q-R.Etymology: imperceptibile referring to the very short, non-protruding neck, thus the species is difficult to see in nature.Perithecia globosa, (289-)309-356(-414) μm elata, (385-)412-462(-504) μm diametro, rostrum breve, (136-)175-211(-225) μm longum, cum expansa area, disciformi vertice visu, simili collo in sectione, (251-)301-318(-351) μm diametro ubi latissima, (87-)89-100(-113) μm diametro apice. Ascosporae reniformes vel oblongo-ellipticae, uniseptatae, constrictae ubi septatae, (18-)19-20(-21) × (5-)6-7(-8) μm, L:l (2.5-)2.9-3.1(-3.8).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Habitat and host: On twigs of Salix sp. (Salicaeae).Distribution: USA (California).a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma Holotype: USA, California, Shasta Co., Cow Creek, close to Old Station, onSalix sp., 18 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 456, BPI 878967,  derived cultures LCM456.01 and LCM456.02 = CBS 127495.    </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Habitat and host: On overwintered branches of Salix sp. (Salicaceae). Distribution: USA (Oregon). Holotype: USA, Oregon, Lincoln Co., Fogarty Creek, on Salix sp., 24 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 597, BPI 878968, derived culture LCM597.01 = CBS 126124. Plagiostoma ovalisporum L.C. Mejía, sp. nov. Figs 4D-H, 7U-V.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Habitat and host: On dead twigs of Salix sp. (Salicaceae). Holotype: USA, Idaho, Idaho Co., near Burgdorf, Burgdorf Rd. FR246, parking area at camping site at Three Mile Creek, approx. GPS: N45º 18.139 W 115º 55.782, elevation 6309 ft, on dead twigs of Salix sp., 5 Sep. 2008 (NAMA Annual Foray, Orson K. Miller Jr. Memorial Foray), A.M. Minnis s.n., BPI 878969, derived culture CBS 124977 = LCM458.01.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Morphology on natural substrate. A-C: Plagiostoma oregonense BPI 878968 (holotype). D-H. P. ovalisporum: BPI 878969 (holotype). I-M. P. pulchellum: I, M = BPI 878971, J = BPI 878974, K-L = BPI 878972. Bars = (A, D, I) 1 mm; (K) 300 μm; (B, E, J) 100 μm; (H, L-M) 20 μm; (C, F-G) 10 μm.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Habitat and host: On dead, still attached branches of Salix alba, S. repens, and Salix sp. (Salicaceae). Distribution: Europe. Lectotype of Sphaeria salicella designated here: Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 issued 1821, Sbarbaro Collection, BPI exsiccati). Epitype of Sphaeria salicella designated here: Austria, St. Margareten im Rosental, Kaernten, Drau-Auen. 9452/1, as Cryptodiaporthe apiculata on Salix alba, 2 May 2002, W. Jaklitsch 1889, BPI 843527, derived culture CBS 121466. Additional specimen examined: Germany, Langen, on Salix repens, L.C. Mejía , BPI 878975, derived culture CBS 126121 = LCM 449.01.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Morphology on natural substrate. A-H: Plagiostoma salicellum: A, B, D, G = Scleromyceti Sueciae 188 (lectotype), C, E, F, H = BPI 843527 (epitype); note whitish stromatic tissue surrounding perithecial neck in Figs 5.5 B and C. I-O: P. samuelsii: I, M, P = BPI 878977 (holotype), N-O = BPI 878979. Bars = (A) 1 mm; (I) 500 μm; (C, J) 200 μm; (B, K) 100 μm; (D-G) 20 μm; (H, L-P) 10 μm.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Habitat and host: On dead, still attached twigs and branches of Alnus incana var. tenuifolia, A. rubra, and Alnus spp. (Betulaceae).Distribution: USA (California, Oregon, Washington). Holotype: USA, California, Plumas Co., Little Last Chance Creek, Chilcook Campground, on Alnus incana var. tenuifolia, 17 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 454, BPI 878977, derived CBS 125668 = LCM454.04. Specimens examined: USA, Oregon, Jackson Co., Upper Rogue River, on Alnus (tenuifolia?), 21 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 419, BPI 878976, derived culture LCM419.01 and LCM419.02; Upper Rogue River trail on Alnus sp. 21 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 474, BPI 878978, derived culture LCM474.01; Washington, Clallam Co., Crescent Lake, on Alnus rubra (branch on soil), 27 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 596, BPI 878979, derived culture LCM596.01.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Habitat and hosts: On dead twigs of Salix scouleriana and Salix sp., on overwintered leaves of Salix sp. (Salicaceae). Distribution: USA (Oregon, Washington); Canada (British Columbia). Holotype: USA, Washington, Jefferson Co., intersection of Upper Hoh River Road &amp; Route 101, on Salix scouleriana, 27 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 594, BPI 878980, derived culture CBS 124978 = LCM594.01. Additional specimens examined: Canada, British Columbia, Vancouver, on overwintered dead leaves of Salix sp., 12 May 2006, M. V. Sogonov 379, BPI 877702, derived culture CBS 121251 = AR4294. USA, Oregon, Lane Co., Willamette Pass, on Salix sp., 22 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 598, BPI 878982, derived culture LCM598.01; Washington, Jefferson Co., Hoh River Campground, on Salix scouleriana, 27 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 595, BPI 878981, derived culture LCM595.01.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>L.C. Mejía &amp; Zhu L. Yang, sp. nov. MycoBank MB515709. Figs 6D-F, 8W-X.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Morphology on natural substrate. A-C. Plagiostoma versatile: A-B = BPI 878980 (holotype), C = BPI 877702. D-F. P. yunnanense BPI 878983 (holotype). Bars = (A, C-D, F) 200 μm; (B, E) 10 μm.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Culture morphology. A-B. Plagiostoma aesculi. CBS 126127 = LCM447.01. C-F. P. apiculatum. C-D. LCM 393.01. E-F. CBS 126126 = LCM436.01. G-H. P. barriae. LCM 601.02. I-L. P. dilatatum. I-J. LCM 402.01. K-L. LCM 403.01. M-P. P. exstocollum. M-N. LCM 422.02. O-P. LCM 468.02. Q-R. P. imperceptibile. LCM 456.01. S-T. P. oregonense. Ex-type CBS 126124 = LCM 597.01. U-V. P. ovalisporum.LCM 458.05. W-X. P. petiolophilum. CBS 126123 = LCM 181.01. A-D, I-L, W-X. Colony habit, 10 d, 23 °C. E-H, M-R, U-V. Colony habit, 9 d, 23 °C. S-T. Colony habit, 7 d, 23 °C. A, C, E, G, I, K, M, O, Q, S, U, W. Reverse. B, D, F, H, J, L, N, P, R, T, V, X. Surface.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Culture morphology. A-D. Plagiostoma populinum. A-B. CBS 144.57. C-D. CBS 174.58. E-J. P. pulchellum. E-F. LCM 438.04. G-H. LCM 371.02. I-J. LCM 623.01. K-L. P. salicellum. CBS 126121 = LCM449.01. M-P. P. samuelsii. M-N. Ex-type CBS 125668 = LCM 454.04. O-P. LCM 596.01. Q-V. P. versatile. Q-R. Ex-type CBS 124978 = LCM 594.01. S-T. LCM 595.01. U-V. LCM 598.01. W-X. P. yunnanense. Ex-type CBS 124979 = LCM 513.03. A-D, G-H, W-X. Colony habit, 10 d, 23 °C. E-F, K-N. Colony habit, 9 d, 23 °C. I-J, O-V. Colony habit, 7 d, 23 °C. A, C, E, G, I, K, M, O, Q, S, U, W. Reverse. B, D, F, H, J, L, N, P, R, T, V, X. Surface.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>using distance settings for each partition as</figDesc><table><row><cell>Taxon</cell><cell>Specimen Culture</cell><cell>Country</cell><cell>Host</cell><cell cols="2">Collector β-tubulin ITS</cell><cell>rpb2</cell><cell>tef1-α</cell></row><row><cell>Plagiostoma yunnanense</cell><cell>BPI 878983 CBS 124979</cell><cell>China</cell><cell>Salix sp.</cell><cell>L.C. Mejía</cell><cell cols="3">GU366975 GU367035 GU367079 GU353959</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(= LCM 513.03)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Plagiostoma yunnanense</cell><cell>BPI 878983 LCM 513.02</cell><cell>China</cell><cell>Salix sp.</cell><cell>L.C. Mejía</cell><cell cols="3">GU366976 GU367036 GU367080 GU353960</cell></row></table><note>Table 1. (Continued).</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). On Chionanthus and Fraxinus (Oleaceae), in Canada and USA ....................................................................................................................................................................... P. fraxini 4. On Salicaceae ........................................................................................................................................................................................... 5 4'. On hosts other than the Salicaceae ........................................................................................................................................................14 5. Perithecia neck cylindric. On woody substrates except P. versatile, which occurs on both leafy and woody substrates .......................... 6 5'. Perithecial neck dilated i.e. with an expanded or thickened area that appears disk-like when seen from above, like a thick collar in section, usually appearing with a black halo or black spot in host surface where perithecial necks protrude. On woody substrates ..... 10 6. Perithecial neck surrounded by a whitish stroma. On Salix, in Europe ................................................................................... P. salicellum 6'. Perithecial neck without a whitish stroma. On Salix or Populus, in Europe and elsewhere ...................................................................... 7 7. On twigs and branches of Populus, in Europe and North America (USA). Ascospores 14-16 × 6-9 μm fide Butin (1958) ................................................................................................................................................................................................. P. populinum 7'. On twigs and branches of Salix, in China, Europe, and North America. Ascospores greater than 16 μm long ........................................ 8 8. Ascospores ellipsoid-fusoid, constricted, curved, tapering to acute ends, (16-)18-20 (-22) × 4-5 μm. In Europe and North America (USA: NY) ................................................................................................................................................................................ P. convexum 8'. Ascospores ellipsoid-elongated, slightly constricted, straight to slightly curved, rounded ends, generally longer than 20 μm. In China or North America ......................................................................................................................................................................... 9 9. Perithecial neck slightly twisted in upper half, of constant length. Ascospores (19-)23-26(-27) × 3-4 μm. On Salix sp., in China (Yunnan) ................................................................................................................................................................ P. yunnanense 9'. Perithecial neck straight, of variable length, very short in twigs, longer in leaves. Ascospores (18-)20-23(-25) × 3-4 μm. On Salix spp., in North America (Pacific Northwest region). ...................................................................................................... P. versatile a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma DESCRIPTIONS Plagiostoma Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen Vereins Naturk. 23-24: 118. 1870. Lectotype designated by Höhnel (1917): Plagiostoma euphorbiae(Fuckel) Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen Vereins Naturk. 23-24: 118.  1870.   Cryptodiaporthe Petr., Ann. Mycol. 19: 118. 1921. Lectotype designated by<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Clements and Shear (1931)</ref>: Cryptodiaporthe aesculi(Fuckel)  Petr., now Plagiostoma aesculi(Fuckel)  Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 62: 69. 2008. = Rostrocoronophora Munk, Dansk Bot. Arkiv 15: 98. 1953. Type: R. geranii (Hollós) Munk, now Plagiostoma geranii (Hollós) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 62: 72. 2008.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Anamorph: Diplodina Westend., Bull. Acad. Roy. Sci. Belgique, sér.</cell></row><row><cell>2, 2: 562. 1857.</cell></row><row><cell>Anamorph type species: Diplodina salicis Westend., Bull. Acad.</cell></row><row><cell>R. Sci. Belg., Cl. Sci., sér. 2 12(7) (1857), now recognised as</cell></row><row><cell>Diplodina microsperma (Johnst.) B. Sutton, Mycol. Pap. 141: 69.</cell></row><row><cell>1977 fide</cell></row></table><note>=</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc> provided a description and illustrations of this species. Cultures are illustrated here inFig. 7A-B. Langen, on branches of Aesculus hippocastaneum, L.C. Mejía, BPI 878950, culture LCM 447.01 = CBS 126127. Gnomoniella amygdalinae f. euphorbiae-stepposae Sandu, Stud. Cercet. Biol., Bot. 18: 18. 1966 fide</figDesc><table><row><cell>Plagiostoma amygdalinae (Fuckel) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol.</cell></row><row><cell>62: 70. 2008.</cell></row></table><note>Plagiostoma aesculi (Fuckel) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 62: 69. 2008.Basionym: Cryptospora aesculi Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen Vereins Naturk. 23-24: 193. 1870.≡ Cryptosporella aesculi (Fuckel) Sacc., Michelia 1: 30. 1877.[≡ Diaporthe aesculi (Fuckel) Höhn., Ann. Mycol. 16: 116. 1918, nom. illeg. non Cooke &amp; Harkn. 1881] ≡ Cryptodiaporthe aesculi (Fuckel) Petr., Ann. Mycol. 19:119. 1921.Note:Specimen examined: Germany,Basionym: Gnomonia amygdalinae Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen Vereins Naturk. 23-24: 121. 1870.≡ Gnomoniella amygdalinae (Fuckel) Sacc., Syll. Fung. 1: 418. 1882. =</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, and S. sitchensis (Salicaceae). Europe and North America. Lectotype of Sphaeria apiculata designated here: BPI 799092, labelled Sphaeria apiculata Wallr., ex. Herb. Strasbourg. Fungi Rhenani 918, as Sphaeria apiculata, from Salix vitellina, BPI bound. Vienna, St. Margareten im Rosental, Kaernten, Drau-Auen, 9452/1, on Salix alba, 2 May 2002, W. Jaklitsch 1890, BPI 843511, derived culture AR 3826; St. Margareten im Rosental, Drau-Auen, Kaernten. 9452/2, on Salix alba, 14 Apr. 2001, W. Jaklitsch 1741, BPI 872037. France, Deux-Sèvres Département, Melle, Melle Arboretum, 15 Apr. 2008, on twigs of Salix dasyclados, L.C. Mejía 393, BPI 878951, derived cultures L.C. Mejía 393.01 and CBS 124974 = LCM393.03. USA, Washington, Kitsap County, Kitsap Memorial State Park, on twigs of Salix sitchensis, 28 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 436, BPI 878952, derived culture CBS 126126 = LCM436.01.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Distribution: Epitype of Sphaeria apiculata designated here: Austria, Vienna,</cell></row><row><cell>21 st district, Marchfeldkanalweg, MTB 7764/1, on Salix sp., 20 May</cell></row><row><cell>2000, W. Jaklitsch 1463, BPI 747938, derived culture CBS 109775</cell></row><row><cell>= AR3455.</cell></row><row><cell>Exsiccatus examined:</cell></row></table><note>Additional specimens examined: Austria,</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. Originally described from the state of Washington (USA), this species is here reported from Oregon. Oregon, on Acer sp., coll. L.C. Mejía LCM 484.01, BPI 878953, derived culture CBS 126125 = LCM 484.01; Washington, on Acer macrophyllum, L.C. Mejía 601, BPI 87895, derived culture LCM 601.01. Sacc., Syll. Fung. 1: 630. 1882. = Cryptodiaporthe salicina Wehm. as (Curr.) Wehm., The Genus Diaporthe Nitschke and its Segregates p. 194. 1933.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Specimens examined: USA, Plagiostoma convexum (Preuss) L.C. Mejía, comb. nov.</cell></row><row><cell>MycoBank MB515690. Fig. 2K-R.</cell></row><row><cell>Perithecia immersed in bark, solitary or in groups of up to four,</cell></row><row><cell>appearing initially as slight conic elevation of periderm with apex</cell></row><row><cell>protruding through a small hole, black, globose, (180-)213-258(-</cell></row><row><cell>326) μm high × (282-)303-352(-415) μm diam (mean = 238 × 329,</cell></row><row><cell>SD 38, 44, n = 13), each with one neck. Neck central to eccentric,</cell></row><row><cell>cylindrical, thick, usually thicker toward apex, some thicker elsewhere</cell></row><row><cell>on neck, upright, diagonally straight, or curved, closely appressed</cell></row><row><cell>when in groups, (82-)161-204(-222) μm long (mean = 176, SD 36,</cell></row><row><cell>n = 13), (71-)82-104(-121) μm diam at base (mean = 95, SD 16, n =</cell></row><row><cell>13), (64-)78-108(-128) μm diam at apex (mean = 93, SD 21, n = 13),</cell></row><row><cell>apex usually paler. Asci clavate, (54-)60-63(-69) × (14-)15-18(-20)</cell></row><row><cell>μm (mean = 61 × 17, SD 4.5, 2.2, n = 8) apical ring 3.0-4.0 μm diam,</cell></row><row><cell>with eight ascospores arranged obliquely parallel to multiseriate.</cell></row></table><note>Basionym: Sphaeria convexa Preuss, Linnea 26: 714. 1853.≡ Diaporthe convexa (Preuss)[≡ Sphaeria salicina Curr., Trans. Linn. Soc. Lond., 22: 279, 1858 non Sphaeria salicina Pers., 1796] ≡ Diaporthe punctata (Cooke) Berl. &amp; Voglino, Syll. Fung., Add. 108. 1886.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Habitat and host: On twigs of Salix spp.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Distribution: Germany, USA (New York).</cell></row></table><note>Lectotype specimen of Sphaeria convexa designated here: Sphaeria convexa Preuss, without other data, ex. Herb. Brussels in Shear study collection types and rarities, BPI 799418. Epitype specimen of Sphaeria convexa designated here: USA, New York, Tompkins Co., near Ithaca, Arnot Forest, on Salix sp., 12 Jul 2002, L. Vasilyeva, BPI 843490, derived culture CBS 123206.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The rest of his description agrees with the description of S. convexa. It also agrees with the lectotype specimen of S. convexa, BPI 799418 ex. Herb. Brussels with a note on the label saying apparently from Preuss). This evidence suggests that S. salicina Curr. 1858 and S. convexa Preuss 1852 represent the same species. Because S. salicina Curr. is a later homonym of Sphaeria salicina Pers. 1796, this basionym cannot be used and the next available epithet is S. convexa; hence the correct name for this taxon is Plagiostoma convexum. The specimen BPI 799418 is here designated the lectotype and the specimen BPI 843490 with the ex-epitype culture CBS 123206 is designated the epitype of Sphaeria convexa.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Sphaeria devexa Desm., Pl. Cryptog. Nord. de France, Edit. II, Ser. II, No. 367. 1856. Diaporthe sechalinensis Sacc., Atti Del Congr. Bot. Di Palermo 1902: 52. 1902 fide Monod (1983). = Ceriosporella polygoni A. L. Sm. &amp; Ramsb., Trans. Brit. Mycol. Soc. 4: 325. 1914 fide</figDesc><table><row><cell>Plagiostoma devexum (Desm.) Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen</cell></row><row><cell>Vereins Naturk. 23-24: 119. 1870.</cell></row><row><cell>≡ Gnomonia devexa (Desm.) Auersw. in Gonn. &amp; Rabenh., Mycol. Europ.</cell></row><row><cell>5/6: 23. 1869.</cell></row><row><cell>≡ Gnomoniella devexa (Desm.) Sacc., Syll. Fung. 1: 417. 1881.</cell></row><row><cell>≡ Gnomoniopsis devexa (Desm.) Moesz &amp; Smarods, Bot. Közlem. 38:</cell></row><row><cell>68. 1941.</cell></row><row><cell>= Sphaeria excentrica Cooke &amp; Peck, Annual Rep. New York State Mus. 25:</cell></row><row><cell>105. 1873 fide Monod (1983).</cell></row><row><cell>≡ Gnomoniella excentrica (Cooke &amp; Peck) Sacc., Syll. Fung. 1: 418. 1882.</cell></row><row><cell>=</cell></row></table><note>Basionym:</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). Oregon, Jackson Co., Upper Rogue River, River Bridge Campground, on Corylus californica, 20 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 468, BPI 878961, derived culture CBS 127663 = LCM468.01. Oregon, Jackson Co., River Bridge Campground, Upper Rogue River, on Corylus californica, 20 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 469, BPI 878962; on Corylus californica, 21 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 422, BPI 878959, derived culture LCM422.02; on Corylus californica, 21 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 472, BPI 878963, derived culture LCM472.01; Upper Rogue River trail, on Corylus californica, 21 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 473, BPI 878964, derived culture LCM473.01; Oregon, Lane Co., Willamette National Forest, Salmon Creek, 22 May 2008. L.C. Mejía 483, BPI 878965, derived culture LCM483.01; on Corylus californica, 23 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 464, BPI 878960, derived culture LCM464.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Holotype: USA, Specimens examined: USA, Plagiostoma fraxini (Redlin &amp; Stack) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol.</cell></row><row><cell>62: 72. 2008.</cell></row></table><note>Basionym: Gnomoniella fraxini</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>provided a detailed description of this species as Gnomoniella fraxini.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Plagiostoma geranii (Hollós) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 62: 72.</cell></row><row><cell>2008.</cell></row><row><cell>Basionym: Gnomonia geranii Hollós, Annls. Mus. Nat. Hung. 7: 52.</cell></row><row><cell>1909.</cell></row><row><cell>≡ Rostrocoronophora geranii (Hollós) Munk, Dansk Bot. Arkiv 15: 98.</cell></row><row><cell>1953.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>L.C. Mejía, comb. nov. Diaporthe populea Sacc. in Mouton, Bull. Soc. Roy. Bot. Belgique 26: 174. 1887 fide</figDesc><table><row><cell>MycoBank MB515705.</cell></row><row><cell>Basionym: Cryptospora populina Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen</cell></row><row><cell>Vereins Naturk. 23/24: 193. 1870.</cell></row></table><note>=</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>: Diaporthe pulchella Sacc. &amp; Briard in Sacc., Atti Ist. Veneto Sci. 2, Ser. 6, 437. 1884. Cryptodiaporthe pulchella (Sacc. &amp; Briard) Butin, Phytopathol. Z. 32: 407. 1958. = Diaporthe recedens Sacc., Ann. Mycol. 12: 290 1914 fide</figDesc><table><row><cell>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma</cell></row><row><cell>Plagiostoma pulchellum (Sacc. &amp; Briard) L.C. Mejía, comb.</cell></row><row><cell>nov. MycoBank MB515706. Figs 4I-M, 8E-J.</cell></row></table><note>Basionym≡</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Specimens examined: Argentina, Tucumán, vicinity of Villa Nougués, on twigs ofSalix humboldtiana, 16 Nov 2008, L.C. Mejía 623, BPI 878974, derived cultures LCM623.01 and LCM623.03. Netherlands, ex leaf of Populus balsamifera, (CBS 170.69 as Cryptodiaporthe pulchella. USA, Maryland, Prince George's Co., Beltsville, USDA-BARC, outside of B011A, on twigs of Salix babylonica, 3 Mar 2008, Amy Y. Rossman &amp; L.C. Mejía 365, BPI 878971, derived culture LCM365.04 = CBS 126653; Maryland, Prince George's Co., Greenbelt, Lake Artemisia, on twigs of Salix babylonica, 15 Mar 2008, L.C. Mejía 371, BPI 878972, derived culture LCM371.02; Washington, Kitsap Co., Kitsap Memorial State Park, on twigs of Salix lucida, 28 May 2008, L.C. Mejía 438, BPI 878973, derived cultures LCM438.03 (= CBS 126122) and LCM438.04.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>presented descriptions of this species. Diaporthe salicella (Fr.) Sacc., Mycotheca Venet. 135. 1873. ≡ Gnomonia salicella (Fr.) J. Schröt., Pilze Schles. 3, 2: 392.1897. ≡ Chorostate salicella (Fr.) Traverso, Fl. Ital. Crypt. 2: 203. 1906. ≡ Cryptodiaporthe salicella (Fr.) Wehm., The Genus Diaporthe Nitschke and its Segregates p. 193. 1933.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Plagiostoma robergeanum (Desm.) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol.</cell></row><row><cell>62: 73. 2008.</cell></row><row><cell>Basionym: Sphaeria robergeana Desm., Ann. Sci. Nat. Bot. ser. 3,</cell></row><row><cell>16: 306. 1851.</cell></row><row><cell>≡ Diaporthe robergeana (Desm.) Niessl. in Rabenh., Fungi Europ. 2222.</cell></row><row><cell>1882.</cell></row><row><cell>≡ Cryptodiaporthe robergeana (Desm.) Wehm., The Genus Diaporthe</cell></row><row><cell>Nitschke and its Segregates p. 200. 1933.</cell></row><row><cell>Note: Wehmeyer (1933) provided a description of this species as</cell></row><row><cell>Cryptodiaporthe robergeana.</cell></row><row><cell>Plagiostoma salicellum (Fr.) Sogonov, Stud. Mycol. 62: 73.</cell></row><row><cell>2008. Fig. 5A-H.</cell></row><row><cell>Basionym: Sphaeria salicella Fr., Syst. Mycol. 2: 377. 1823.</cell></row></table><note>≡</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). Most likely P. jensenii does not belong in Plagiostoma. versatile L.C. Mejía &amp; Sogonov, sp. nov. MycoBank MB515708. Figs 6A-C, 8Q-V.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Plagiostoma</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">www.studiesinmycology.org</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Fig. 3. Morphology on natural substrate. A-D: Plagiostoma dilatatum: A-C = BPI 878959 (holotype), D = BPI 878958. E-H: P. exstocollum: E-G = BPI 878961 (holotype), H = BPI 878964. I-M: P. imperceptibile BPI 878967 (holotype). Bars = (A, E, I) 1mm; (M) 200 μm; (B, F, H, J) 100 μm; (C-D) 20 μm; (G, K-L) 10 μm.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>This work was funded by the National Science Foundation Partnerships for Enhancing Expertise in Taxonomy (NSF 03-28364). Additional funding for field work by LCM was received through Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ, from the Neyra Fund, the Spencer Davis Research Award from the Department of Plant Biology and Pathology, a Special Study Support Award, and a Graduate School Travel Award and through the Backus Award from the Mycological Society of America. Much appreciation is extended to Lena Struwe for her valuable comments and insights during the course of this work. We acknowledge and appreciate</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma Plagiostoma euphorbiae <ref type="bibr">(Fuckel) Fuckel, Jahrb. Nassauischen Vereins Naturk. 23-24: 118. 1870</ref>.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Monod (1983)</ref>.</p><p>Note: This species was fully described and illustrated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Fröhlich &amp; Hyde (1995)</ref> and . Note: <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Monod (1983)</ref> provided a detailed description of this species. Plagiostoma euphorbiaceum is phylogenetically related to P. amygdalinae as discussed under that species.</p><p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma SD 2.4, n = 3), (57-)59-63(-66) μm diam at apex (mean = 61, SD 4.8, n = 3). Asci not observed. Ascospores ellipsoid-elongate, with rounded ends, 1-septate, slightly or not constricted at median to submedian septum, (19-)23-26(-27) × 3-4 μm (mean = 24 × 3.3, SD 2.7, 0.4, n = 6), l : w (6.6-)6.8-7.9(-8.2) (mean = 7.3, SD 0.7, n = 6), with granular cytoplasm.</p><p>Cultures: Moderate growth on PDA after 7 d a.c.d. 3.4 cm (SD 0.2, n = 4). Mycelium of granular texture, margin stringy, whitish with granules, becoming grey or vinaceous buff, reverse with dark inclusions near centre, most of colony whitish.</p><p>Habitat and host: On dead, still attached branches of Salix sp. (Salicaceae).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Distribution: China (Yunnan).</head><p>Holotype: China, Yunnan, Ailoshan, on <ref type="bibr">Salix sp., 14 Jul. 2008, L.C. Mejía 513, BPI 878983, derived</ref>  Cryptodiaporthe liquidambaris Petr., Sydowia 5: 236. 1951.</p><p>Notes: A fresh specimen determined to be this species was cultured and sequenced. Analyses of LSU sequences place this species within the Diaporthales but not within any described family. Notes: A fresh specimen determined to be this species was cultured and sequenced. Analyses of LSU sequences place this species within the Diaporthales but not in any described family. Notes: A fresh specimen determined to be this species was cultured and sequenced. This species falls within the Gnomoniaceae according to analyses of ITS sequences but not within any known genus. The perithecial neck of this species is lateral, upright, and slightly curved at the apex. Notes: This species is now regarded as Gnomonia alnea (Fr.) Sogonov and was described and illustrated in .</p><p>Plagiostoma arnstadtiense (Auersw.) M. Monod, Beihefte Sydowia 9: 143. 1983.</p><p>Basionym: Gnomonia arnstadtiensis Auersw. in <ref type="bibr">Gonnerm. &amp; Robenh., Mycol. Europ. 5/6: 22. 1869.</ref> Notes: This species is now accepted in Gnomonia according to .</p><p>Plagiostoma bavaricum (Rehm) M.E. <ref type="bibr">Barr, Mycol. Mem. 7: 112. 1978</ref><ref type="bibr">. Basionym: Hypospila bavarica Rehm, Ann. Mycol. 6:322. 1908</ref> Note: Based on an LSU sequence, this species belongs in the Gnomoniaceae but it cannot be placed in a genus. Plagiostoma conradii (Ellis) M.E. <ref type="bibr">Barr, Mycol. Mem. 7: 107. 1978</ref>.</p><p>Basionym: Diaporthe conradii Ellis, Am. Nat. 17: 316. 1883.</p><p>Notes: A fresh specimen determined to be this species was cultured and sequenced. Analysis of the LSU sequence suggests this species is closely related to Cryptodiaporthe aubertii and Cryptosporella but not within any known genus in the Gnomoniaceae. The perithecial neck of this species is lateral and upright. Notes: Two isolates of this species were sequenced. This species apparently belongs in the Gnomoniaceae but it cannot be placed in a genus. Plagiostoma jensenii M.E. <ref type="bibr">Barr, Mycotaxon 41: 298. 1991.</ref> Note: Based on the lack of a perithecial neck and the pulvinate appendages on the ascospores, P. jensenii most likely does not belong in Plagiostoma.</p><p>Plagiostoma lugubre (P. Karst.) Bolay, Ber. Schweiz. Bot. <ref type="bibr">Ges. 81: 436. 1972.</ref> Basionym: Gnomonia lugubris P. Karst., Bidr. Känn. Finl. Nat. Folk 23: 121. 1873.</p><p>Note: The disposition of this species was not investigated in this study.</p><p>Plagiostoma magnoliae (Ellis) M.E. <ref type="bibr">Barr, Mycol. Mem. 7: 117. 1978</ref><ref type="bibr">. Basionym: Gnomonia magnoliae Ellis, Amer. Nat. 17: 318. 1883</ref>.</p><p>Notes: This species has been reported in leaves of Magnolia virginiana in North America. The perithecial neck of this species is lateral and obliquely upright as drawn by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Barr (1978)</ref>. The disposition of this species was not investigated in this study.</p><p>Plagiostoma micromegalum (Ellis &amp; Everh.) M.E. <ref type="bibr">Barr, Mycol. Mem. 7: 112. 1978</ref>. Plagiostoma robertiani (Petr.) M.E. <ref type="bibr">Barr, Mycol. Mem. 7: 113. 1978</ref><ref type="bibr">. Basionym: Gnomonia robertiani Petr., Ann. Mycol. 23: 122. 1925</ref>: No material of this species was located.</p><p>a SySteMatic account of the genuS Plagiostoma Andrew Minnis for providing a specimen from which the new species Plagiostoma ovalisporum was described and for nomenclatural advice. Christian Feuillet kindly provided translations of the diagnoses into Latin. Tunesha Phipps and Sasha Allen are sincerely acknowledged for their technical expertise in the molecular laboratory. LCM appreciates the following people for graciously hosting visits for collecting and facilitating the shipment of specimens: Michael Giraurd, Adriana Hladki, Tina Hoffman, Christian Lechat, Christophe Lecuru, and Ralph Mangelsdorff. Special thanks to Zhu LiangYang for hosting LCM and providing superb logistical support during his collecting trip in China.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ascospores ellipsoid to broadly ellipsoid, constricted, tapering to narrowly rounded ends</title>
		<idno>16-)17-19(-22) × (4-)6</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ascospores oblong-ellipsoid to renoid, not or slightly constricted, rounded ends, size different than above. On Populus and Salix, in North America and elsewhere</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">On</forename><surname>Salix</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">............................................................................................................................. P. oregonense 10 ; ............................................................................................................................................................. 11</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<editor>North America (USA: OR) ....</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ascospores slightly curved, l : w &lt; 5. On Salix spp</title>
		<idno>17-)18-22(-27) × (5-)6-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Ascospores usually straight, sometimes slightly curved, l : w &gt; 5</title>
		<editor>Europe and North America . ...</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>On Populus and Salix</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asci ovoid elongated, with long, usually persistent stalk</title>
		<idno>18-)19-20(-21) × (5-)6-7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ascospores</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>8) μm, l : w (2.5-)2.9-3.1(-3.8)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Asci cylindric, often with long but not persistent stalk. Ascospores averaging &lt; 18 μm long</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">On</forename><surname>Salix Sp</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">..................................................................................................................... P. imperceptibile 12 ; Europe and North America .................. 13</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">(</forename><surname>In North America</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">..................................................................................................................... P. imperceptibile 12 ; Europe and North America .................. 13</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">. .</forename><surname>Usa: Ca)</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">..................................................................................................................... P. imperceptibile 12 ; Europe and North America .................. 13</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On leaves of Euphorbiaceae, specifically Euphorbia amygdaloides and E. stepposa. Ascospores 13-15.5 × 2.3-3 μm fide Monod (1983 as Gnomonia amygdalinae), with a thin appendage at each end</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">) . .</forename><surname>Ascospores ; France</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">..................................................................................................................................................................... P. apiculatum 14. On hosts in the Euphorbiaceae ............................................................................................................................................................... 15 14&apos;. On hosts other than Euphorbiaceae ........................................................................................................................................................ 17 15 ; ............................................................................. P. amygdalinae 15 ; ..................................................................... 16</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">North</forename><surname>Europe</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">..................................................................................................................................................................... P. apiculatum 14. On hosts in the Euphorbiaceae ............................................................................................................................................................... 15 14&apos;. On hosts other than Euphorbiaceae ........................................................................................................................................................ 17 15 ; ............................................................................. P. amygdalinae 15 ; ..................................................................... 16</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">. .</forename><surname>America</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">..................................................................................................................................................................... P. apiculatum 14. On hosts in the Euphorbiaceae ............................................................................................................................................................... 15 14&apos;. On hosts other than Euphorbiaceae ........................................................................................................................................................ 17 15 ; ............................................................................. P. amygdalinae 15 ; ..................................................................... 16</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<idno>P. dilatatum 13&apos;. Ascospores (12-)16-18.5(-21) × (3-)5-6(-7) μm, mean = 17 × 6 μm, l : w (2.4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Europe</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>On Salix. On twigs, branches, or stems of the Euphorbiaceae. Ascospores without appendages ....</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sogonov</forename><surname>Μm Fide</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">) ............ P. euphorbiae 16</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<idno>Perithecial neck less than 100 μm. Ascospores (12-)13-13.5(-15.5) × (3-)3.5</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Perithecial neck 100-150 μm. Ascospores 14-17.5 × 3.5-4.5 μm fide Monod (1983 as Gnomonia euphorbiacea) ....</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ascospore upper cell rounded, basal cell short-conic, 13-16 × 4-5 μm/12-16 × 5-7 μm fide Monod 1983 &amp; Remler 1979 as Apiognomonia rhododendri. In pedicels and branches of Rhododendron spp</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">................................................................................................................................................................................................</forename><surname>Acer</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">........................................................................................................................................................................ 19 18 ; ) .............................................................. P. barriae 18 ; .................................................................................................................................................................. P. petiolophilum 19 ; .................................................................................................................................... 20 19&apos;. Ascospores without appendages ............................................................................................................................................................ ; ............................................................................................................ P. samuelsii 20 ; NY) ............................................................................................................... P. devexum 21 ; Europe .................................................. P. rhododendri 21&apos;. Ascospores not as above ........................................................................................................................................................................ 22 22 ; ........................................................................................................................................................................ P. ; .................................................................................................. ; Europe ...................................................................................................................................... P. aesculi 23 ; ...................................................................................... 24</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">the Pacific Northwest region of USA. Ascospores (11.5-)14-15.5(-17.5) × (2.5-)3.5-4(-4.5) μm fide Sogonov et</title>
		<editor>Europe or North America ....</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Europe and USA. Perithecia in groups or solitary, with necks emerging together or not, surrounded or not by a brownish stroma. On hosts other than Aesculus hippocastanum, in Europe or North America ....</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">exstocollum 24&apos;. Stroma absent. Perithecia solitary or in groups with convergent</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Stroma brownish, covering perithecia but not surrounding necks. Perithecia arranged in groups, with necks emerging together but oriented in different directions where they protrude through host epidermis</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>On Corylus californica, in the Pacific Northwest region of USA. protruding necks. On Staphylea, in Europe ....</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ueber die Gattung Laestadia und die Gnomoniaceen</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Antonie van Leeuwenhoek</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="272" />
			<date type="published" when="1951" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Diaporthales in North America with emphasis on Gnomonia and its segregates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Barr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mycological Memoir</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Revisions and additions to the Diaporthales</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Barr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mycotaxon</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="305" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Über die auf Salix und Populus vorkommenden Arten der Gattung Cryptodiaporthe Petr.</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Butin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1439-0434.1958.tb01783.x</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-NWN0N7WH-9</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">FB2AC88A4C1ACFFE897B85C6872704C8F8535E9E</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Phytopathology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">J Phytopathol</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0931-1785</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1439-0434</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="399" to="415" />
			<date type="published" when="1958-08" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Method for Designing Primer Sets for Speciation Studies in Filamentous Ascomycetes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ignazio</forename><surname>Carbone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Linda</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/3761358</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mycologia</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Mycologia</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0027-5514</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">553</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999-05" />
			<publisher>JSTOR</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Preliminary Overview of the Diaporthales Based on Large Subunit Nuclear Ribosomal DNA Sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lisa</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Castlebury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amy</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Rossman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Walter</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Jaklitsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Larissa</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Vasilyeva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/3761867</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mycologia</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Mycologia</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0027-5514</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1017</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002-11" />
			<publisher>JSTOR</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MycoBank: an online initiative to launch MycoBank to the 21 st century</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Clements</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Cl ; H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Shear</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">New</forename><surname>Wilson Co</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>York</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Crous</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stalpers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Robert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Stegehuis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Studies in Mycology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="1931" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The Genera of Fungi</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">XX.-Synopsis of the Fructification of the Compound Sphaeriae of the Hookerian Herbarium.</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Frederick</forename><surname>Currey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1096-3642.1856.tb00098.x</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-XH45QDZ7-R</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">85A8189D2BCF26E8643FF59E6D4794FF7101C8BC</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://zenodo.org/record/1637918/files/article.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transactions of the Linnean Society of London</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1945-9432</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="287" />
			<date type="published" when="1858-12" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maculatipalma fronsicola gen. et sp. nov. causing leaf spots on palm species in north Queensland with descriptions of the related genera: Apioplagiostoma and Plagiostoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fries</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ex</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lund</forename><surname>Berlingiana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fröhlich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hyde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mycological Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="727" to="734" />
			<date type="published" when="1823" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Systema Mycologicum 2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Symbolae mycologicae. Beiträge zur Kenntniss der Rheinischen Pilze.</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fuckel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5962/bhl.title.47117</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/itempdf/101771" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Symbolae Mycologicae. Julius Niedner</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Wiesbaden</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>J. Niedner,</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1869" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anthracnose caused by Discula fraxinea on the new host Chinese fringetree and white ash in Delaware</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gregory</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mulrooney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Rossman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Castlebury</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Disease</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">427</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Höhnel F Von</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">System der Diaportheen. Sonderabruck aus den Berichten der Deutschen Botanischen Gesellschaft</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1917" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="631" to="638" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MRBAYES: Bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ronquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/17.8.754</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">11524383</idno>
		<idno type="PII">1460-2059</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-B26KH8GB-7</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">3CBFF51EAEB5A4F4D8ECCA476E463AE7A1AA1BFD</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article-pdf/17/8/754/8201380/170754.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Bioinformatics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1367-4803</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1460-2059</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="754" to="755" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-08-01" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Taxonomic studies of Japanese Diaporthaceae with special reference to their life histories</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kobayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bulletin of the Government Forest Experiment Station (Japan)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">226</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="1970" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">International Code of Botanical Nomenclature (Vienna Code). Regnum Vegetabile 146</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcneill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Barrie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Burdet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Demoulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hawksworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<publisher>Gantner Verlag KG</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phylogenetic placement and taxonomic review of the genus Cryptosporella and its synonyms Ophiovalsa and Winterella (Gnomoniaceae, Diaporthales)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Luis</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mejía</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lisa</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Castlebury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amy</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Rossman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mikhail</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Sogonov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.mycres.2007.03.021</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">18222674</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mycological Research</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Mycological Research</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0953-7562</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-01" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monographie taxonomique des Gnomoniaceae</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Monod</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Beihefte zur Sydowia. Annales Mycologici, Ser. 2</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="315" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Die Gattungen der didymosporen Pyrenomyceten</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Arx</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Von</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Beitr. Kryptogamenfl. Schweiz</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="922" />
			<date type="published" when="1962" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MrModeltest v. 2. Program distributed by the author</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jaa</forename><surname>Nylander</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolutionary Biology Centre</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two Divergent Intragenomic rDNA ITS2 Types within a Monophyletic Lineage of the FungusFusariumAre Nonorthologous</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kerry</forename><surname>O'donnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename><surname>Cigelnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1006/mpev.1996.0376</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">9007025</idno>
		<idno type="PII">S1055-7903(96)90376-0</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-HZZR33LR-0</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">806E5E728FE03F1CB3A1EBE7CA23BD19633C0E52</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1055-7903</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="116" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-02" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mycologische Notizen. II</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Petrak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annales Mycologici</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="1921" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Occurrence of fungal endophytes in twigs of Salix fragilis and Quercus robur</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Petrini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0953-7562(09)81336-1</idno>
		<idno type="PII">S0953-7562(09)81336-1</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-FX3MK4HW-3</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">BC1FA6164697CD04FA58D0FA0480B7C26EFC1191</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mycological Research</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Mycological Research</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0953-7562</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1077" to="1080" />
			<date type="published" when="1990-12" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MODELTEST: testing the model of DNA substitution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Posada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Crandall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/14.9.817</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">9918953</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article-pdf/14/9/817/9731960/140817.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Bioinformatics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1367-4803</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1460-2059</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="817" to="818" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-10-01" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gnomoniella fraxini sp. nov., teleomorph of the ash anthracnose fungus and its connection to Discula fraxinea comb</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Redlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Stack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mycotaxon</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="198" />
			<date type="published" when="1988-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contribution of RPB2 to multilocus phylogenetic studies of the euascomycetes (Pezizomycotina, Fungi) with special emphasis on the lichen-forming Acarosporaceae and evolution of polyspory</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Valérie</forename><surname>Reeb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">François</forename><surname>Lutzoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Claude</forename><surname>Roux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ympev.2004.04.012</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">15288074</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1055-7903</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1036" to="1060" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-09" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">EF1 alpha primers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rehner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ocid.nacse.org/research/deephyphae/EF1primer.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ascomyceten aur Ericaceen in den Ostalpen</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Remler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bibliotheca Mycologica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="321" />
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">First Report of Ash Anthracnose Caused by Discula fraxinea in Oregon</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Rossman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Castlebury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Putnam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1094/pdis.2004.88.2.222c</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Disease</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Plant Disease</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0191-2917</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="222" to="222" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-02" />
			<publisher>Scientific Societies</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leafinhabiting genera of the Gnomoniaceae</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sinclair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Sogonov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Castlebury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Rossman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mejía</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jr</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diaporthales. Studies in Mycology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>Cornell University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Diseases of trees and shrubs</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Coelomycetes. Fungi Imperfecti with Pycnidia, Acervuli and Stromata</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">PAUP*. Phylogenetic Analysis Using Parsimony (*and Other Methods)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Kew, Surrey, England. Swofford DL; Sunderland</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Version 4.0b10 Sinauer Associates</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The British species of the genus Diaporthe Nits. and its segregates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wehmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0007-1536(33)80010-6</idno>
		<idno type="PII">S0007-1536(33)80010-6</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-075H7MXW-H</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">B29102B6262FD1A98CFDC1B6861A28C98F422689</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transactions of the British Mycological Society</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Transactions of the British Mycological Society</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0007-1536</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="295" />
			<date type="published" when="1933-03" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Pyrenomycetous Fungi</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wehmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RT. Mycological Memoir</title>
		<editor>Hanlin</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="250" />
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
