<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Parasitic Infection of an Endemic Fish (Blicca bjoerkna) and an Exotic Fish (Hemiculter beucisculus) In Anzali Lagoon, Caspian Sea, Iran</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pazooki</surname></persName>
							<email>pazooki2001@yahoo.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Marine Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Shahid Beheshti University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Te-hran</settlement>
									<region>G. C</region>
									<country key="IR">Iran</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">Tajbakhsh</forename><surname>Goorabzarmakhi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Marine Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Biological Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Shahid Beheshti University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Te-hran</settlement>
									<region>G. C</region>
									<country key="IR">Iran</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Masoumian</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Fish Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Iranian Fisheries Research and Training Organization</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tehran</settlement>
									<country key="IR">Iran</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Parasitic Infection of an Endemic Fish (Blicca bjoerkna) and an Exotic Fish (Hemiculter beucisculus) In Anzali Lagoon, Caspian Sea, Iran</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received 11 Dec 2010; accepted 09 Aug 2011</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T22:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Parasites</term>
					<term>Blicca bjeorkna</term>
					<term>Hemiculter leucisculus</term>
					<term>Lagoon</term>
					<term>Iran</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Background: In Anzali Lagoon, there are some endemic and exotic fishes. The present study was conducted to compare the parasitic fauna of Blicca bjeorkna, as an endemic fish and Hemiculter leucisculus, as an introduced fish to the lagoon. Methods: A parasitological investigation was done on 78 specimens of B. bjoerkna and 114 of H. leucisculus. The fishes were collected from August 2009 to April 2010 by the electro fishing from Anzali Lagoon. Results: Eleven parasites species were found in 192 fish samples. The prevalence and mean intensity of parasites in each host were as follows:</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>nzali Lagoon is a very important reservoir in the Caspian Sea Fauna Region (North of Iran), there are some fish parasites recorded from this area such as: Diplostomum spathaceum from Esox lucius, Perca fluviatilis, Carassius carassius, Ctenopharyngodon idella, Cyprinus carpio, Hypophthalmichthys molitrix, Tinca tinca, and Abramis brama; Raphidascaris acus from Esox lucius, Abramis brama, Tinca tinca, Carassius carassius and Perca fluviatilis. There some more parasites from different fishes such as: Tetraonchus menonteron and Gyrodactylus elegans, Eustrongilides excisus, Rhabdochona hellichi from Esox lucius, Chalcalburnus chalcoides and Cucullanus mulleri from Carassius carassius, Anisakis schupakovi from Silurus glanis, Argulus foliaceus from Hypophthalmichthys molitrix, Piscicola geometra and Asymphylodora tincae from Tinca tinca <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. A number of exotic fish species were introduced in Iranian freshwaters. These species encompass 18.7% from the 81% of the fish inhabiting in south part of the Caspian Sea. Hemiculter leucisculus (Saw belly) is one of these species with low economic value. This species might be accidentally transferred to this region with fertilized egg and or larvae of Chinese carp for aquaculture, the place and origin of this fish is Yunnan, south-west of China <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>. None-indigenous fish may have undesirable effects on endemic fish species, including destruction of habitat and water quality, predation, aggressive behavior such as fin nipping, retardation of reproductive activity, food competition, and introduction of parasites and disease to the new environment. Levels of parasitism and parasite diversity were significantly greater in native fishes than in exotic species, and this may contribute to an enhanced demographic perform-ance and competitive ability in invading exotics. Levels of parasitism and parasite diversity in native fishes were negatively related to habitat disturbance, in particular to a suite of factors that indicate increased human use of the river and surrounding environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>. Native parasites infecting exotic fish will increase their bio-potential through a vast host range. The exotic fish may play as a reservoir role for maintenance of parasite <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>. The aims of this study were to survey the parasite fauna on Blicca bjeorkna, as a native fish, and Hemiculter leucisculus, as an exotic fish, and to compare the prevalence of parasitic infection in these two species.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and Methods</head><p>A parasitological investigation was done on Blicca bjeorkna; the local name is Sim Parak (n= 78, <ref type="figure">Fig.1</ref>) and Hemiculter leucisculus; the local name is Tiz Kooli (n=114, <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>). The fishes were collected from August 2009 to April 2010 by the electro fishing from same locality of Anzali Lagoon. The live specimens were transferred to Iranian Aquaculture Research Center (Guilan, Anzali) and were kept in aquariums. Parasitological studies implemented for protozoa and Monogenea on fresh smears of gills, eyes, skin, and fins by stereo and light microscope. Examined fish were fixed in formalin (10%) and transferred to Aquatic Research Laboratory (Shahid Beheshti University) for further study of other metazoan parasites. The parasites were identified according to key of Moravec 1994, 1998, Bykhovskaya 1964, Shulman 1984 and Lom &amp; Dykova 1992 <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analysis</head><p>Statistical analysis was performed by the software package of SPSS. Data were subjected to the analysis of variance (ANOVA). Significant differences in prevalence and mean intensity of parasitism between exotic and endemic fish was detected by Chi square test when α= 0.05.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Eleven parasite species were found in both of fishes ( <ref type="figure">Fig. 3 and 4</ref>, <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>). One hundred percent of Blicca bjeorkna and 49.12% of Hemiculter leucisculus were contaminated by various parasites. Presented findings showed a significant difference in prevalence of parasitic infection between exotic and endemic fishes (P&lt;0.05). The endemic fish was infected more than exotic fish and more parasites diversity was observed in endemic fish than exotic species. Some of parasitic species were seen in both fishes, but some others were only in B. bjoerkna or H. leucisculus. More specific parasites were found in B. bjoerkna whereas they were not identified in H. leucisculus. B. bjoerkna was presented as a new host for M. musajevi and C. osculatum; and H. leucisculus was introduced as a new host for T. perforata, Ps. tomentosa and R. acus.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>One of the factors affecting on specification of parasitic infection is origin of the fish species, whether native or exotic. Several investigations revealed that parasitic infection is more common in native fish species than exotic one <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>. In a previous, parasitic species richness and parasitic diversity were significantly ( P&lt;0.05) more in native fish than in exotic one <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 :Fig. 2 :Fig. 3 :Fig. 4 :</head><label>1234</label><figDesc>Hemiculter leucisculus (Tiz kooli) Blicca bjoerkna (Sim Parak) A. T. perforata from skin, gills and fins. B. Myxobolus musajevi from gills. C. Dactylogyrus difformis from gills. D. Dactylogyrus sphyrna from gills. E. Metacercaria of Posthodiplostomum cuticula from skin and fins. F. Rhaphidocotyle sp. from gills. G. Metacercaria of Diplostomum spataceum from the eyes A. posterior part of Contracaecum osculatum. B. anterior part of C. osculatum. C. posterior part of Raphidascaris acus. D. anterior part of Rh. acus. E. posterior part of Pseudocapillaria tomentosa. F. anterior part of Ps. tomentosa. G. posterior part of Philometra rischta. H. anterior part of Ph. rischta with released larvae</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Intensity and prevalence of parasite species of the host fishes in Anzali Lagoon</figDesc><table><row><cell>Parasite species</cell><cell>Hf</cell><cell>Efn</cell><cell>Ifn</cell><cell>Int±S.D.</cell><cell>Prv (%)</cell></row><row><cell>T. perforata</cell><cell>B. bjoerkna</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>42</cell><cell>*</cell><cell>53.85</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>H. leucisculus</cell><cell>114</cell><cell>31</cell><cell>*</cell><cell>27.19</cell></row><row><cell>M. musajevi</cell><cell>B. bjoerkna</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1±0.79</cell><cell>27.19</cell></row><row><cell>D. difformis &amp;</cell><cell>B. bjoerkna</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>69</cell><cell>8.058±7.24</cell><cell>88.46</cell></row><row><cell>D. sphyrna</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Diplostumum</cell><cell>B. bjoerkna</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>77</cell><cell>9.51±9.09</cell><cell>98.72</cell></row><row><cell>spataceaum</cell><cell>H. leucisculus</cell><cell>114</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>1.33±0.54</cell><cell>7.89</cell></row><row><cell>P. cuticula</cell><cell>B. bjoerkna</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>4.25±2.5</cell><cell>15.38</cell></row><row><cell>Ripidocotyle sp</cell><cell>B. bjoerkna</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2±0.74</cell><cell>1.28</cell></row><row><cell>C. osculatum</cell><cell>B. bjoerkna</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>1.64±0.79</cell><cell>17.95</cell></row><row><cell>Ph. rischta</cell><cell>B. bjoerkna</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>1.4±0.54</cell><cell>12.8</cell></row><row><cell>Ps. tomentosa</cell><cell>H. leucisculus</cell><cell>114</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1.62±0.49</cell><cell>7.02</cell></row><row><cell>R. acus</cell><cell>B. bjoerkna</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0.03±0.26</cell><cell>1.04</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>H. leucisculus</cell><cell>114</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3±0.28</cell><cell>0.88</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">Hf: host fishes, Efn: examined fish number, Ifn: infected fish number, S.D: standard deviation, Prv: preva-</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">lence (%), *: The number of parasites was not clear for calculated their intensity</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The origin of fish is one of the most important and affecting factors on the prevalence of parasite infection. Other factors are included food diet, immune competence, and fish dispersion in its habitat. The exotic fish may have a role in maintenance of a parasite and transfer the infection to other host fish in the environment according to their immune system resistance. There are many parasites recorded from different fish species in Anzali Lagoon but there is not any comparative study between endemic and exotic fishes. During this study, the examined fishes are introduced as new hosts: H. leucisculus for Trichodina perforata, Dactylogyrus sphyrna, Pseudocapillaria tomentosa, Raphidascaris acus and B. bjoerkna for Myxobolus mosajevi, Contracaecum osculatum.</figDesc><table><row><cell>low host specifications and the hosts have</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>close relationship (2). In a case, at which a</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>parasite is introduced to a new host, this</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>could damage the host even more because</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>there is no identified relationship between</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>the host and parasite. Furthermore, the host</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>may not have enough defensive strength</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>against the parasite (5, 7). In the present</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>study, both the prevalence of parasitic infec-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>tion and diversity were more in B. bjoerkna</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>than in H. leucisculus. Parasites with low</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>host specifications such as T. perforata, Ps.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>tomentosa and D. spataceaum were found in</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>H. leucisculus can easily contaminate differ-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ent host.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>exotic fish may not be able to continue their</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>life cycle in the new environment. This re-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>duced parasitic charge increased the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>competitive ability and the size of exotic</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>species in comparison with native species</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(17, 18).</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>The second one is the absence of other re-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>quired host (intermediate or reservoir host)</cell></row><row><cell>). Some studies</cell><cell>in the new environment. Thirdly, the highly</cell></row><row><cell>about roles of parasites in animal invasions</cell><cell>host specifications caused limitations in</cell></row><row><cell>and missing parasites in introduced species,</cell><cell>transfer of parasite from native fish species</cell></row><row><cell>demonstrated several reasons for reduced</cell><cell>to the exotic ones. Conversely, parasites may</cell></row><row><cell>parasitic load of exotic species. Firstly, those</cell><cell>transfer from exotic fish to the native ones.</cell></row><row><cell>parasites that contaminated the introduced</cell><cell>The parasite transfer is greater when it has</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>This research was supported by Shahid Beheshti University, G. C. The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Check-list of Iranian fish parasites. Iranian Fisheries Research Organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pazooki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Masoumian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Jafari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spread of parasites and diseases of aquatic organisms by acclimatization: a short review</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1095-8649.1991.tb04398.x</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-JJCKCX9R-3</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">11C1EBD0B99B612E91C7B062258A3CBD37E229D7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Fish Biology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">J Fish Biology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-1112</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1095-8649</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="679" to="686" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-11" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exotic fish species in the Tigris-Euphrates basin</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Coad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Abdoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09397140.1996.10637707</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Zoology in the Middle East</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Zoology in the Middle East</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0939-7140</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">2326-2680</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-01" />
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Status of the fish fauna in the South Caspian Basin of Iran</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Bahram</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kiabi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Asghar</forename><surname>Abdoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mehdi</forename><surname>Naderi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/09397140.1999.10637782</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Zoology in the Middle East</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Zoology in the Middle East</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0939-7140</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">2326-2680</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-01" />
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Roles of parasites in animal invasions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Prenter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Calum</forename><surname>Macneil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jaimie</forename><forename type="middle">T A</forename><surname>Dick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alison</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tree.2004.05.002</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">16701290</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://planet.uwc.ac.za/nisl/Gwen%27s Files/Biodiversity/Chapters/Info to use/Chapter 5/parasites.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0169-5347</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="390" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-07" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Review of impacts of displaced/ introduces fauna associated with inland waters, national state of the environment technical report, state of the environment unit, Australian government publishing services. Canberra</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Arthington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mckenzie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Concurrent invaders—four exotic species of Monogenea now established on exotic freshwater fishes in Australia</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alistair</forename><forename type="middle">D M</forename><surname>Dove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ingo</forename><surname>Ernst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0020-7519(98)00134-9</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">9846613</idno>
		<idno type="PII">S0020-7519(98)00134-9</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-92QDPWDB-9</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">8D30D5E6010160D89709C0C79D4935B2ED1D1E7C</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal for Parasitology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">International Journal for Parasitology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0020-7519</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1755" to="1764" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-11" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Asian fish tapeworm, Bothriocephalus acheilognathi, in Australian freshwater fishes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Adm</forename><forename type="middle">D M</forename><surname>Dove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cribb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mockler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lintermans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1071/mf96069</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Marine and Freshwater Research</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Mar. Freshwater Res.</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1323-1650</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">181</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>CSIRO Publishing</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Parasites of native and exotic freshwater fishes in the southwest of Western Australia. PhD. thesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hassan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Murdoch University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parasites of native and exotic freshwater fishes in south-western Australia</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lymbery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hassan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Morgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Beatty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Doupé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1095-8649.2010.02615.x</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">20557630</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-N54TXGLW-Q</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">7334E68A975B8E634B3C3367D398DE94AD7AE42B</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Fish Biology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-1112</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1095-8649</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1770" to="1785" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-04-13" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biological characteristics of the introduced sawbelly,Hemiculter leucisculus(Basilewski, 1855), in three wetlands of northern Iran: Alma-Gol, Adji-Gol and Ala-Gol</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Patimar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Abdoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kiabi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1439-0426.2008.01080.x</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-9Q74L9MQ-Z</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">2400C1FD94684268094E819DCF041BFD3B6CB4CD</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Ichthyology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0175-8659</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1439-0426</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="617" to="620" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-10" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Key to the parasites of freshwater fishes of USSR translation from Russian by Palestine program for scientific translation. Jerusalem</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bykhovskaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1964" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Studies on Protozoan Parasites of Australian Fishes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jiří</forename><surname>Lom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Iva</forename><surname>Dyková</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s0932-4739(11)80218-x</idno>
		<idno type="PII">S0932-4739(11)80218-X</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-FG4NG3B5-6</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">FC0503FCECB1C321574AD809A2651DCAB858D40B</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Protistology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">European Journal of Protistology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0932-4739</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="439" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-11" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Parasitic nematodes of freshwater fishes of Europe. Academia, Praha. -Publishing House of Academy of Sciences of Czech Republic</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Moravec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nematodes of freshwater fishes of the Neotropical Region. Institute of parasitology, Academy of Science of the Czech Republic</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Moravec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distribution and impacts of introduced freshwater fishes in Western Australia</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Morgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Howard</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mark</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Maddern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Beatty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/00288330.2004.9517257</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/00288330.2004.9517257?needAccess=true" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New Zealand Journal of Marine and Freshwater Research</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">New Zealand Journal of Marine and Freshwater Research</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0028-8330</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1175-8805</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="523" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-08" />
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ss</forename><forename type="middle">Parasitic</forename><surname>Shulman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Protozoa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Key to parasitic of freshwater fishes of the USSR</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Nauka, Leningrad, USSR</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">426</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>the Russian)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduced species and their missing parasites</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mark</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Torchin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lafferty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dobson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Valerie</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mckenzie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Armand</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kuris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nature01346</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">12571595</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/GT4-JZ2VFZC1-7</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">175843030021D119BB407CDA93345855226CEE99</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Nature</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0028-0836</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1476-4687</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">421</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6923</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="628" to="630" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-02" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
