<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Test-retest reliability of Motricity Index strength assessments for lower extremity in post stroke hemiparesis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Maryam</forename><surname>Fayazi</surname></persName>
							<email>mfayyaze@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physical Therapy, Rehabilitation Faculty</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">MSc student of Physical Therapy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tehran University of Medi-cal sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tehran</settlement>
									<country key="IR">Iran</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Shohreh</forename><forename type="middle">Noorizadeh</forename><surname>Dehkordi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mehdi</forename><surname>Dadgoo</surname></persName>
							<email>mdadgoo@tums.ac.ir</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Masoud</forename><surname>Salehi</surname></persName>
							<email>salehi74@yahoo.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physical Therapy, Rehabilitation Faculty, Tehran Univer-sity of Medical Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tehran</settlement>
									<country key="IR">Iran</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physical Therapy, Rehabilitation Faculty, Tehran University of Medical Sciences</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of biostatistics, Faculty of management and Medical informatics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tehran University of Medical Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tehran</settlement>
									<country key="IR">Iran</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physical Therapy, Rehabilitation faculty</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tehran University of Medical Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tehran</settlement>
									<country key="IR">Iran</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Test-retest reliability of Motricity Index strength assessments for lower extremity in post stroke hemiparesis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received: 12 November 2011 Revised: 7 January 2012 Accepted: 10 January 2012 __________________________________________________________________________________________</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-14T00:15+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Reliability</term>
					<term>Motricity Index</term>
					<term>Hemiparesis</term>
					<term>Chronic stroke. ________________________________________________________________________________________</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Background: The Motricity Index was used to measure strength in upper and lower extremities after stroke. The weighted score based on the ordinal 6 point scale of Medical Research Council was used to measure maximal isometric muscle strength. There is dearth of articles dealing with the reliability of this method. Therefore, the aim of this study was to determine the test retest reliability of Motricity Index strength assessments for paretic lower limb in 20 chronic stroke patients with one week interval. Methods: In a cross sectional study, intrarater reliability of lower extremity Motricity Index strength assessments with one week interval were measured. Result: The SPSS 18 was used for analysis of data. Two-way random-consistency model of ICC was used for assessment of test-retest reliability. The ICC values showed high reliability of strength measurement of Motricity Index (ICC=0.93). Conclusion: The Motricity Index can be a reliable instrument for measuring the strength of involved lower extremity when assessment is done by one rater following chronic stroke.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>The most important motor deficit after stroke is the paresis of the affected side, contralateral to vascular lesion in the brain <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. Muscle weakness, as one of the negative features of upper motor neuron syndrome is characterized by the loss of ability to generate normal levels of muscle force. It is also associated with physiological changes as abnormal force coupling with agonists and antagonists and abnormal muscle activation patterns. Due to such deficits the capacity of the paretic lower limb to maintain normal functions such as balance, initiation and control of movement would decrease <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>. However, weakness happens on the ipsilateral side as early as one week following stroke. Post stroke weakness and its accompanying motor impairments result in diminished performance of daily living and loss of independence <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref>. Therefore, it is important for clinicians to identify hemiparetic weakness. In other words, there is a need to have a reliable tool to assess muscle strength in the clinical basis. Among many experimental and clinical tools such as isokinetic dynamometer and handheld dynamometer which are expensive and time consuming for measuring  <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref>. In order to grade muscle force, they used the ordinal six points scale of Medical Research Council <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>. The MRC grades were converted into modified weighted scores according to patients' difficulty in progressing from one grade to the next (Table1). The three scores were summed and added by one, and total score was ranged from 0 (complete paresis) to 100 (normal strength). <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Collen et al (1990)</ref> assessed the inter rater reliability of Motricity Index. Their results implicated reliability and sensitivity of motricity index <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>. In another study, they investigated the reliability of six impairment measures and disability of Motricity Index (leg score) in 25 patients suffered from a chronic stroke. Quantification was done by 3 therapists on 3 sessions over 5 weeks. All six measures were relia-ble in statistical terms <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>. It seemed that there is dearth of articles dealing with the reliability of strength measurement with Motricity Index. Therefore, the purpose of this study was to estimate the test-retest reliability of Motricity Index strength measurement in the affected lower limb muscles in two sessions over one week in chronic stroke patients.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p>In a cross sectional-analytical study, 20 subjects (10 female and10 male) with age range of 37 to 76 years and post stroke duration of 3 months to 4 years who could follow instructions, were participated in this study. All of them had referred to neurological Physical therapy Clinic in Rehabilitation Faculty of Tehran University of Medical Sciences from May to July of 2011. Those who had the experience of articular pain as a result of arthrosis, surgery or trauma on their lower extremity were excluded. Initially, a written consent was obtained from each participant. Then they became familiar with the procedure. One physical therapist assessed the strength of hip flexor, knee extensor and ankle dorsiflexor muscles in two sessions over one week. All the assessments were performed at the same time of day on two sessions. The rater was blind to total Motricity Index score and to data analysis on two sessions conducted with someone else. It took less than five minutes to perform Motricity Index. The participants were placed in a chair that had back support. Hip flexion was tested with the hip joint with a 90 ̊ bent. The   rater instructed the patients to bring the knee towards the chin, while she monitored the contraction of hip flexors by placing her hand on the anterior of the distal of thigh. Then the therapist resisted the movement. According to the quality of muscle contraction the score was recorded. Rater was also aware of any trick motion such as leaning the back during the movement by placing one hand on their back. The knee extension was examined while it was bent at 90 ̊ flexion with the unsupported foot, followed by the examiner asked the subjects to extend the knee and touch her hand which was held at the level of the knee. Meanwhile, she monitored the contraction of quadriceps with the other hand which gave resistance to movement. Then the score was recorded. Furthermore, the movement of dorsiflexion was assessed as the ankle relaxed in a plantar flexed position, then the examiner placed her hand on the forefoot, while the patient was asked to dorsiflex the foot, the examiner palpated and also resisted the contraction of tibialis anterior with the other hand on the forefoot <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>. Finally, all three scores were summed and the Motricity Index for lower extremity was calculated. Retest was done with one week interval, and hand placement was identical on two sessions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis</head><p>Data analysis was done using the SPSS v. 18. Two way random-consistency model of ICC (2,1) was used for assessment of testretest reliability. <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref> demonstrated the suggested interpretation of statistical value for reliability testing <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>. <ref type="table">Table 3</ref> is shown the characteristics of all 20 participants and descriptive statistics shown in <ref type="table">Table 4</ref>. Two-way randomconsistency model of ICC was used for as-sessment of test-retest reliability. As <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table  5</ref> is indicated, all scores of Motricity Index in lower limbs of 20 patients on two sessions assessments were strongly reliable(8).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>Although reliability of strength assessments in neurologic conditions have been suspected by many researchers, our results showed that Motricity Index has high reliability on two session assessment by one rater. Despite the fact that manual muscle testing is the most common approach in clinical assessment, traditional manual muscle testing (MMT) could not be a valid indicator of muscle strength in neurologic patients in acute phase due to presence of strong spasticity and synergistic movement pattern and loss of selective contractions. In chronic stage of neurologic conditions when some improvement had occurred in motor control, MMT could provide precise information about muscle strength <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>. Many factors affect on strength evaluations by manual muscle testing in neurologic patients such as position changes, altered muscle tone, variations in producing force in rater's hand over two sessions. Despite all these confounding factors, Motricity Index based on manual testing of strength, could provide the overall estimation of lower extremity strength. In addition, it seemed that this index was a better representative of gross changes of motor recovery than MMT overtime, because it used the weighted scores. The result of this study was further supported by the Collen et al (r=0.87)(6), but with the difference that we investigated the reproducibility of strength measures by one rater because using another rater introduced another source of variation while Collen et al measured interrater reliability that could be expected to reduce correlations between tests. These studies mainly focused on "break test" in which the examiner pushes against the subject maximal effort to hold the position. Accordingly the results of these studies could not be generalized to ones which incorporated "make test" like handheld dynamometry that was held stationary while the patients exerted the maximal force required. Bohannon <ref type="bibr">(2000)</ref> found that Motricity Index in the comparison with the dynamometer, have high criterion validity. Hence, he suggested that in the absence of such tools, clinicians could implement this index for strength testing of lower extremity (10). Therefore it seemed that the Motricity Index is a simple and reliable measure of muscle strength post stroke that can be applied readily and does not need any especial equipment and training. Further reliability testing in upper extremity is recommended.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>Motricity Index strength assessments for involved lower extremity in chronic stroke can be highly reliable when assessment is done by one rater following chronic stroke.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The lower extremity scores for muscle strength using the Motricity index.</figDesc><table><row><cell>muscle force, Motricity Index is a more fea-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>sible measure that can demonstrate the</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>overall patients' impairment. It is a simple,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>brief measure of general motor function that</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>can predict the mobility outcomes post-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>stroke (4). In 1980, Demeurisse et al devel-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>oped a new method to assess isometric</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>muscle strength on post stroke hemiparesis.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>They studied thirty one movements at prox-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>imal, middle and distal joints of upper and</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>lower extremities. They decided to reduce</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>many movements to just one essential</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>movement at each joint that was the repre-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>sentative of general strength at that joint. In</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>upper extremity the movements were</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>shoulder abduction, elbow flexion and</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>pinch grip. In lower limb the three move-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ments were hip flexion, knee extension and</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ankle dorsiflexion</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Quality of muscle contraction</cell><cell>Motricity scores</cell><cell>MRC Grade</cell></row><row><cell>No Movement</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Palpable contraction in muscle, but No</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Movement</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Visible Movement, but not full range</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>against Gravity</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Full range of Movement against Gravity,</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>but not against resistance</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Full Movement against gravity, but</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>weaker than the other side</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Normal Power</cell><cell>33</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>Demeurisse (1990)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Interpretation of statistical value for reliability testing.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Strength of</cell><cell>Statistical value</cell></row><row><cell>agreement</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Poor</cell><cell>0/2 &lt;</cell></row><row><cell>Fair</cell><cell>0/21-0/40</cell></row><row><cell>Moderate</cell><cell>0/41-0/60</cell></row><row><cell>Good</cell><cell>0/61-0/80</cell></row><row><cell>Very good</cell><cell>0/81-1</cell></row><row><cell>Paul Brennan(1992)</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 .Table 4 .</head><label>34</label><figDesc>Subject baseline characteristics of 20 chronic stroke patients Descriptive values for Motricity Index value .</figDesc><table><row><cell>Characteristics</cell><cell cols="3">Subject (n= 20) Freq. (%)</cell></row><row><cell>Age (Years)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean ± SD</cell><cell></cell><cell>55.58±13.45</cell></row><row><cell>Range</cell><cell></cell><cell>37-76</cell></row><row><cell>Gender</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell></cell><cell>10</cell><cell>50</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell></cell><cell>10</cell><cell>50</cell></row><row><cell>Type of Stroke</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ischemic</cell><cell></cell><cell>17</cell><cell>85</cell></row><row><cell>Hemorrhagic</cell><cell></cell><cell>3</cell><cell>15</cell></row><row><cell>Side of involvement</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Right</cell><cell></cell><cell>8</cell><cell>40</cell></row><row><cell>Left</cell><cell></cell><cell>12</cell><cell>60</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Duration of illness (months)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean ± SD</cell><cell></cell><cell>19.41±17.37</cell></row><row><cell>Range</cell><cell></cell><cell>3 -48</cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>Mean</cell><cell cols="2">Std. Deviation</cell></row><row><cell>Motricity Index</cell><cell>58.20</cell><cell>17.683</cell></row><row><cell>(first session)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Motricity Index</cell><cell>56.60</cell><cell>19.632</cell></row><row><cell>(second session)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>ICC Value</cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell>SEM</cell><cell>Significance level</cell></row><row><cell>Motricity Index</cell><cell>0.93</cell><cell>0.84 -0.97</cell><cell>4.66</cell><cell>0.000</cell></row></table><note>Test-retest reliability of Motricity Index on the involved side of 20 chronic stroke patients.</note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This study was a part of MS thesis supported by Tehran University of Medical Sciences, grant no. p/26/54/317. We thank all the volunteers that participated in this study.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Strengthening to Promote Functional Recovery Poststroke: An Evidence-Based Review</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sang</forename><surname>Pak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Carolynn</forename><surname>Patten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1310/tsr1503-177</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">18647724</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/4ece/425cf7182713340f8b5d1923047c1057e806.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Topics in Stroke Rehabilitation</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Topics in Stroke Rehabilitation</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1074-9357</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1945-5119</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="199" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-05" />
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding Motor Impairment in the Paretic Lower Limb After a Stroke: A Review of the Literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Arene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hidler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1310/tsr1605-346</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">19903653</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Topics in Stroke Rehabilitation</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Topics in Stroke Rehabilitation</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1074-9357</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1945-5119</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="346" to="356" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-09" />
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Weakness and strength training in persons with poststroke hemiplegia: Rationale, method, and efficacy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Carolynn</forename><surname>Patten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Lexell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Heather</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1682/jrrd.2004.03.0293</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/db11/ac06bc9d23d79469e8d2e60ee3df2ba1ee2d.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Rehabilitation Research and Development</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">JRRD</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0748-7711</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3A</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">293</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<publisher>Journal of Rehabilitation Research &amp; Development</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motor Evaluation in Vascular Hemiplegia</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Demeurisse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Demol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Robaye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1159/000115178</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">7439211</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Neurology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Eur Neurol</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0014-3022</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1421-9913</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="382" to="389" />
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
			<publisher>S. Karger AG</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Aids to the investigation of peripheral nerve injuries</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Medical Research</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Council</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1942" />
			<pubPlace>London: HMSO</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing motor impairment after stroke: a pilot reliability study.</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Collin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/jnnp.53.7.576</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">2391521</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC488133</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/NVC-TGFWTCGX-C</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">F7DAF881BC5CBF9AB626E4FCCB8E04DAA13FA861</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://jnnp.bmj.com/content/53/7/576.full.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery &amp; Psychiatry</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery &amp; Psychiatry</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-3050</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="576" to="579" />
			<date type="published" when="1990-07-01" />
			<publisher>BMJ</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal of Neurology</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mobility after stroke: Reliability of measures of impairment and disability</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Fiona</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Collen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Derick</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Carole</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bradshaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3109/03790799009166594</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">2211468</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Disability Studies</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">International Disability Studies</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0259-9147</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="1990-01" />
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical methods for assessing observer variability in clinical measures.</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Brennan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Silman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmj.304.6840.1491</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">1611375</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC1882212</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/NVC-8QJJ3L79-Q</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">D51B4BA627E1BCCA0D74F070FEA940F5A60752EF</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.bmj.com/content/304/6840/1491.full.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">BMJ</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0959-8138</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1468-5833</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">304</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6840</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1491" to="1494" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-06-06" />
			<publisher>BMJ</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Criterion validity of lower extremity Motricity Index scores</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>O' Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T ;</forename><surname>Schmitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Bohannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>733. 10</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical Rehabilitation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="208" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Physical Rehabilitation</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
