<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Aristolochic acids — Induced transcriptomic responses in rat renal proximal tubule cells in vitro</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Elsevier BV</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-06-02">2 June 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Katarzyna</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bloch</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Liverpool John Moores University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Liverpool</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Liverpool John Moores University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Liverpool</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Edward</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lock</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Liverpool John Moores University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Liverpool</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Aristolochic acids — Induced transcriptomic responses in rat renal proximal tubule cells in vitro</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Genomics Data</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Genomics Data</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">2213-5960</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="254" to="256"/>
							<date type="published" when="2015-06-02">2 June 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.gdata.2015.05.028</idno>
					<idno type="PMID">26484264</idno>
					<idno type="PMCID">PMC4584013</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 13 May 2015 Accepted 23 May 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T22:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Aristolochic acid Genotoxic Carcinogen Rat renal proximal tubule cells Microarray</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Aristolochic acids (AAs) are the active components of herbal drugs derived from Aristolochia species that have been used for medicinal purposes since antiquity. However, AAs have recently been discovered to be highly nephrotoxic and induced urothelial cancer in humans and malignant tumors in the kidney and urinary tract of rodents. In this study, we exposed rat renal proximal tubule cells in vitro to a sub-cytotoxic level of AAs at three different time points (6 h, 24 h and 72 h). We then analyzed the gene expression profile after the compound exposure. Functional analysis with Ingenuity Pathways Analysis and DAVID tools revealed that at the late time point (72 h) there are many significantly altered genes involved in cancer-related pathways such as p53 signaling. MIAMI-compliant microarray data are deposited in the NCBI GEO database under accession number GSE68687 and can be found at: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE68687.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Direct link to deposited data</head><p>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE68687.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Introduction</head><p>Aristolochic acids (AAs) are a mixture of structurally related nitrophenanthrene carboxylic acids, mainly 8-methoxy-6-nitrophenanthro [3,4-d] 1,3-dioxolo-5-carboxylic acid (aristolochic acid I) and its 8-demethoxylated form (aristolochic acid II) ( <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>) that are secondary metabolites of Aristolochia and Asarum plant species.</p><p>Herbal drugs containing aristolochic acids have been used since antiquity, however in 1982, AAs were reported to be highly carcinogenic in rats causing renal and forestomach cancers <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>. Later similar findings were reported in mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. In 1991, a unique and rapidly progressive renal fibrosis referred as Aristolochic Acid Nephropathy (AAN), was observed in around 5% of patients that took weight-reducing pills containing AAs <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Over 100 cases of AAN have been identified with around half needing renal transplantation <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. AA consumption (as harvest contamination) is also hypothesized to be a causative agent in the development of a similar type of kidney fibrosis with malignant transformation of the urothelium -Balkan Endemic Nephropathy <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. To date AAs have been shown to be among the 2% of the most potent known carcinogens <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. IARC has classified herbal remedies containing species of the genus Aristolochia as carcinogenic to humans (Group 1) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, whereas naturally occurring mixtures of AAs are classified into Group 2A (probably carcinogenic to humans). AA is a direct-acting mutagen in TA100 and TA1537 Salmonella typhimurium strains, but is not mutagenic in the nitroreductase-deficient strains (TA98NR and TA100NR) <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. AAs were found to be positive in the L5178Y mouse lymphoma assay and MN assay <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Renal tubular epithelial cells are very sensitive to AAs and undergo apoptosis or necrosis in response to this compound, with AAI being the more cytotoxic congener <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The carcinogenic effect of AAs is not fully elucidated but is associated with the formation of covalent  AA-DNA adducts. Rats treated with AAs develop mutations in p53 gene and the presence of AA-DNA adducts in renal cortex and p53 mutations in tumor tissue were reported in patients with endemic nephropathy <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Materials and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Materials</head><p>A mixture of AAI and AAII was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich, UK. TRIzol reagent and GlutaMAX were obtained from (Invitrogen, UK) and RNeasy Total RNA Mini Kit and RNA later from (Qiagen, UK).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Cell culture</head><p>NRK-52E cells (ATCC, CRL-1571) were cultured in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM) with 10% fetal calf serum, penicillin 100 IU ml −1 , and streptomycin solution 100 μg ml −1 in a humidified 5% CO 2 incubator at 37°C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Cytotoxicity-determination of IC 10</head><p>A dose-response curve for AAs was determined using the MTT assay <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. Cells were exposed for 72 h in 96-well plates to a wide range of concentrations of AAs dissolved in DMSO and diluted to give a final concentration of 0.1% v/v DMSO. Control cells were exposed to DMSO alone (0.1% v/v). At least three separate experiments were conducted. The dose that caused approximately 10% cytotoxicity (IC 10 ) at 72 h was selected for the transcriptomics studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Cell treatment</head><p>NRK-52E cells were cultured to confluence on 6-well plates. For transcriptomics studies, cells were exposed to AAs dissolved in DMSO (0.1% v/v) at the IC 10 concentration at 72 h (1.65 μM) or DMSO (0.1% v/v) alone. After 6 h, 24 h and 72 h the medium was removed and RNA was extracted from cells. For replication, three studies were conducted at each time point.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">RNA isolation and microarray</head><p>From in vitro studies total RNA was isolated from DMSO (control) and AA-treated cells. TRIzol reagent was used for RNA isolation. Total RNA was purified using the RNeasy Total RNA Mini Kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer's instructions. RNA was checked for purity and integrity using Agilent 2001 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies GmbH, Germany) before processing. Transcriptomics data was generated using GeneChip Rat Genome 230 2.0 The rat array provides comprehensive coverage of the transcribed rat genome and comprised of more than 31,000 probe sets, analyzing over 30,000 transcripts and variants from over 28,000 well-substantiated rat genes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.">Microarray hybridization</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.1.">Target preparation</head><p>cDNA was prepared using the Affymetrix IVT express kit (Affymetrix, Santa Clara). cDNA synthesis and labeling were performed according to the manufacturer's procedures. Subsequent labeling of the samples was conducted by synthesis of Biotin-labeled complementary RNA (cRNA) using the GeneChip IVT labeling kit (Affymetrix). Purified cRNA was quantified using a spectrophotometer, and unfragmented samples were checked on the Bioanalyzer. Subsequently, cRNA samples were fragmented for target preparation according to the Affymetrix manual and checked on the Bioanalyzer. Samples were stored at −20°C until ready to perform hybridization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.2.">Hybridization</head><p>cRNA targets were hybridized on high-density oligonucleotide gene chips (Affymetrix Human Genome U133 Plus 2.0 and GeneChip Rat Genome 230 2.0 Arrays) according to the Affymetrix Eukaryotic Target Hybridization manual. The gene chips were washed and stained using the Affymetrix Fluidics Station 450 and Genechip Operating Software and scanned by means of an Affymetrix GeneArray scanner.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.3.">Microarray analysis</head><p>The intensity values of different genes (probe sets) generated by Affymetrix GeneChip Operating Software were imported into GeneSpring <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. Chemical structure of aristolochic acid I and II.  version 11 software (Agilent) for data analysis. The raw data files (CEL files) containing signal values for individual probes were pre-processed to generate one value per probeset. Pre-processing of arrays was done using GC-RMA (Robust Multiarray Analysis algorithm). To identify the differentially expressed (DE) probe sets, two sampled t-test (unpaired t-test) with a P-value b 0.05 and Benjamini-Hochberg correction for multiple testing correction and a fold cut off of 2 was used. Comparisons were made between control DMSO-exposed and AA-exposed cells. Three studies were conducted at each time point.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.4.">Functional annotation</head><p>To understand the biological meaning behind the list of DE genes, Kyoto Encyclopaedia of Genes and Genomes database (KEGG) pathways analysis and Gene Ontology (GO) from DAVID website (The Database for Annotation, Visualization and Integrated Discovery) v 6.7 (http:// david.abcc.ncifcrf.gov/) were used. Only GO and pathways with Pvalue b 0.05 (Benjamin-Hochberg corrected) and with 5 or more genes were analyzed and discussed. In addition, Ingenuity Pathway Analysis (IPA) was used. Only pathways and functions with P b 0.05 (Fisher's exact test right-tailed) were analyzed and discussed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.5.">Data deposition</head><p>MIAMI-compliant microarray data were deposited in the NCBI GEO database under accession number GSE68687; http://www.ncbi.nlm. nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE68687.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Gene expression profile induced after aristolochic acids exposure</head><p>No genes were differentially expressed after 6 h and 24 h exposure to AAs, however at 72 h, 1204 genes were found to be differentially expressed. Both IPA and KEGG pathways identify p53 signaling as a top statistically significantly enriched pathway <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">(Tables 1 and 2)</ref>. Additionally after 72 h exposure genes involved in apoptosis, stress response, DNA damage and glutathione biosynthesis were identify <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">(Tables 2 and 3</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p>Our results suggest that microarray analysis is a useful tool for detecting AA exposure in vitro and the gene expression analysis can identify the responses to toxicity and carcinogenicity of AAs in rat renal proximal tubule cells. In addition, the significantly altered genes were identify to be associated with cancer pathways and specifically p53 signaling, DNA damage responses and apoptosis. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>r n a l h o m e p a g e : h t t p : / / w w w . j o u r n a l s . e l s e v i e r . c o m / g e n o m i c s -d a t a /</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>KEGG pathways enriched after 72 h exposure to AAs.</figDesc><table><row><cell>KEGG pathway</cell><cell>No. of genes</cell><cell>Total no. of genes</cell><cell>P-value</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>involved in</cell><cell>involved in the</cell><cell>(Benjamini)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>pathway</cell><cell>pathway (%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>p53 signaling pathway</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>1.9</cell><cell>8.5E−8 (1.3E−5)</cell></row><row><cell>Pathways in cancer</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>3.6</cell><cell>8.6E−5 (6.4E−3)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Ingenuity pathways enriched after 72 h exposure to AAs.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Ingenuity canonical pathway</cell><cell>No. of genes involved</cell><cell>P-value</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>in the pathway</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>p53 signaling</cell><cell>17/98</cell><cell>9.65E−08</cell></row><row><cell>Glutathione biosynthesis</cell><cell>3/3</cell><cell>4.96E−05</cell></row><row><cell>ATM signaling</cell><cell>10/59</cell><cell>5.20E−05</cell></row><row><cell>Cell cycle: G2/M DNA damage</cell><cell>9/49</cell><cell>6.44E−05</cell></row><row><cell>checkpoint regulation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Molecular mechanisms of cancer</cell><cell>8/99</cell><cell>6.74E−05</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>GO enriched after 72 h exposure to AAs.</figDesc><table><row><cell>GO</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>This study was funded primarily by the 6th EU Framework project (LSHB-CT-2006-037712) carcinoGENOMICS.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The carcinogenic action of aristolochic acid in rats</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Mengs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J-A</forename><surname>Poch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/bf00302751</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/1BB-6HSHFS9D-8</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">6C8A7399BABE8D5A36FD70B0059ED63F335CA577</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Archives of Toxicology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Arch Toxicol</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0340-5761</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1432-0738</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="1982-11" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature America, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tumour induction in rats following exposure to short-term high dose aristolochic acid I</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Qiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/mutage/gei007</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">15644423</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-46XTGG33-5</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">456779191269A712D69AF22D802440084C2578E1</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://academic.oup.com/mutage/article-pdf/20/1/45/6138865/gei007.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mutagenesis</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Mutagenesis</title>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1464-3804</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-01-25" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tumour induction in mice following exposure to aristolochic acid</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Mengs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/bf00293699</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">3190449</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/1BB-42PB215J-V</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">05CB616AF2070102398C03DABBB51B4CAFCB8DB6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Archives of Toxicology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Arch Toxicol</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0340-5761</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1432-0738</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="504" to="505" />
			<date type="published" when="1988-06" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature America, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vanherweghem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Altern. Complement. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aristolochic acid as a probable human cancer hazard in herbal remedies: a review</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Arlt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stiborova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schmeiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/mutage/17.4.265</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">12110620</idno>
		<idno type="PII">1464-3804</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-14HXGVPR-9</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">B73945F623843D62BD92CB2E6EBBC5CB60ABF9DD</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://academic.oup.com/mutage/article-pdf/17/4/265/9895006/170265.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mutagenesis</title>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1464-3804</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-07-01" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aristolochic acid and the etiology of endemic (Balkan) nephropathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Grollman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shibutani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moriya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Moll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fernandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Rosenquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Medverec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Jakovina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Brdar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Slade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Turesky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Goodenough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rieger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vukelic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jelakovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.0701248104</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">17620607</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC1913550</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www.pnas.org/content/104/29/12129.full.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0027-8424</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1091-6490</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12129" to="12134" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-07-09" />
			<publisher>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ls</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boca Raton, FL</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">IARC Monographs on the Evaluation of Carcinogenic Risks to Humans, 82, World Health Organization, International Agency for Research on Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="556" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutagenicity of the two main components of commercially available carcinogenic aristolochic acid in Salmonella typhimurium</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schmeiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pool</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wiessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0304-3835(84)90067-3</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">6378360</idno>
		<idno type="PII">0304-3835(84)90067-3</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-BFH31T42-7</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">483BA67C091A81BC1FE0FF9AA7DC236143035DBB</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Letters</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Cancer Letters</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-3835</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="1984-05" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of simplified in vitro screening tests to detect genotoxicity of aristolochic acid</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cifone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Murli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Erexson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mecchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lawlor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.fct.2004.07.016</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">15500939</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Food and Chemical Toxicology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Food and Chemical Toxicology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0278-6915</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2021" to="2028" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-12" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular evidence for an involvement of organic anion transporters (OATs) in aristolochic acid nephropathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nadiya</forename><surname>Bakhiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Volker</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Arlt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Bahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gerhard</forename><surname>Burckhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hansruedi</forename><surname>Glatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tox.2009.07.014</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">19643159</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Toxicology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Toxicology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0300-483X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">264</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-10" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">p53 mutations as fingerprints for aristolochic acid – an environmental carcinogen in endemic (Balkan) nephropathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Neda</forename><surname>Slade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ute</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Moll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Branko</forename><surname>Brdar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Arijana</forename><surname>Zorić</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Bojan</forename><surname>Jelaković</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.mrfmmm.2009.01.005</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">19428366</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC2729401</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://europepmc.org/articles/pmc2729401?pdf=render" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mutation Research/Fundamental and Molecular Mechanisms of Mutagenesis</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Mutation Research/Fundamental and Molecular Mechanisms of Mutagenesis</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0027-5107</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">663</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-04" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid colorimetric assay for cellular growth and survival: Application to proliferation and cytotoxicity assays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tim</forename><surname>Mosmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0022-1759(83)90303-4</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">6606682</idno>
		<idno type="PII">0022-1759(83)90303-4</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-CK25PFRF-B</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">A2DC7251D68A1B10A149BBEC6A8B52E738A2F0A5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Immunological Methods</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Immunological Methods</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-1759</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="1983-12" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
