<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Development and Characterization of 10 Microsatellite Loci in the Giant Cardon Cactus,Pachycereus pringlei(Cactaceae)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Wiley</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014-02">2014-02</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Carina</forename><forename type="middle">Gutiérrez</forename><surname>Flores</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">Adrian Lozano</forename><surname>Garza</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">José</forename><forename type="middle">L León De La</forename><surname>Luz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Francisco</forename><forename type="middle">J García De</forename><surname>León</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Development and Characterization of 10 Microsatellite Loci in the Giant Cardon Cactus,Pachycereus pringlei(Cactaceae)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Applications in Plant Sciences</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Applications in Plant Sciences</title>
						<idno type="eISSN">2168-0450</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page">1300066</biblScope>
							<date type="published" when="2014-02" />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.3732/apps.1300066</idno>
					<idno type="PMID">25202601</idno>
					<idno type="PMCID">PMC4103605</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T22:59+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Cactaceae</term>
					<term>microsatellites</term>
					<term>Pachycereus pringlei</term>
					<term>pyrosequencing</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The giant cardon cactus, Pachycereus pringlei (S. Watson) Britton &amp; Rose (Cactaceae), is a columnar cactus that is widely distributed in the Sonoran Desert in Mexico, including the Baja California peninsula, all islands in the Gulf of California, and the coastal region of Sonora State (Turner et al., 1995). This species offers an attractive model for evolutionary studies. Its wide distribution is characterized by a heterogeneous array of environmental conditions (Garcillán et al., 2010), as well as a geographic variation in the distribution of its major pollinator, the lesser long-nosed bat Leptonycteris curasoae (Fleming et al., 1998). Heterogeneity in biotic and abiotic factors can result in differential selective pressures across populations, promoting genetic differentiation and local adaptation. For P. pringlei , a latitudinal pattern of abundance, height, and basal diameter in the Baja California peninsula is associated with annual and summer rainfall, as well as winter temperature (Medel-Narváez et al., 2006). This species also exhibits an unusual geographical variation</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>of breeding systems among Cactaceae, including hermaphroditism <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">( Medel-Narváez, 2008 )</ref>, gynodioecy (female and hermaphrodites), and trioecy (males, females, and hermaphrodites). This spatial segregation of sexes is partly associated with variations in abundance of its major pollinator <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">( Fleming et al., 1998 )</ref>.</p><p>The Baja California peninsula had a dynamic geologic history, including the formation of the Gulf of California approximately 5.5 mya <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">( Lonsdale, 1989 )</ref> and major climatic changes during the Pleistocene <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">( Van Devender, 1990</ref> ) that have had a profound effect on the distribution and genetic structure of other columnar cacti with similar ranges of distribution, such as Lophocereus schottii (Engelm .) Britton &amp; Rose <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">( Nason et al., 2002 )</ref> and Stenocereus gummosus (Engelm.) A. C. <ref type="bibr">Gibson &amp; K. E. Horak ( Clark-Tapia and Molina-Freaner, 2003 )</ref>. Currently, there is one molecular study based on low polymorphic markers (allozymes) that suggests no genetic differentiation within the range of P. pringlei <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">( Fleming et al., 1998 )</ref>. In this study, we used the latest 454 GS-FLX titanium sequencing platform to locate polymorphic microsatellite loci in P. pringlei and propose that these molecular markers be used in genetic studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS AND RESULTS</head><p>Genomic DNA was extracted from fresh cortex tissue of one P. pringlei cactus growing near La Paz, Baja California Sur, Mexico (23.985 ° N, 110.187 ° W), using a procedure with cetyltrimethylammonium bromide (CTAB) modifi ed for mucilaginous cactus tissues <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">( de la Cruz et al., 1997 )</ref>. A voucher specimen (JLLL11726 [HCIB28440]) was deposited in the Herbarium HCIB at Centro de Investigaciones Biológicas del Noroeste (CIBNOR). Approximately 5 μ g of genomic DNA was treated with RNAse and submitted to the Genome Sequencing Center at the University of California, Santa Cruz, where the sample was 1 Manuscript received 21 August 2013; revision accepted 30 September 2013.</p><p>The authors thank Raymundo Domínguez-Cadena and Alfonso Medel-Narváez for their fi eld assistance, Carlos Garza of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) for providing sequencing service, and Ira Fogel of Centro de Investigaciones Biológicas del Noroeste (CIBNOR) for providing editorial assistance. The Secretaría del Medio Ambiente y Recursos Naturales (SEMARNAT ) issued collection permits (SGPA/DGVS/07004/11). Funding was provided by the Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología (CONACYT; grant CB-2008-01-106925). C.G.F. is a recipient of a CONACYT student fellowship (165852 • Premise of the study: Microsatellite primers were developed for the cardon, a giant columnar cactus ( Pachycereus pringlei ) of the Sonoran Desert, to investigate intraspecifi c genetic patterns of diversity and population structure. • Methods and Results: Using 454 GS-FLX technology and bioinformatics tools, microsatellite primers were successfully identifi ed on 282 reads, including di-, tri-, tetra-, penta-, and hexanucleotides. A set of 10 primers were characterized on 80 individuals collected in two areas of the Baja California peninsula, Mexico. All 10 loci were polymorphic, with a mean of 6.3 alleles per locus and overall levels of observed and expected heterozygosities ranging from 0.41 to 0.59 and from 0.40 to 0.57, respectively. Alleles per individual plant ranged from one to four, suggesting a polyploidal genome.</p><p>• Conclusions: These loci should be useful for future investigations of population structure, genetic diversity, and gene fl ow in the cardon cactus.</p><p>Favoring larger motif (repetition numbers) and lower melting temperature differences between pairs of primers, we selected 38 loci for PCR amplifi cation and a banding pattern of 10 cacti samples collected at El Comitán near La Paz (23.985 ° N, 110.187 ° W). Total DNA was extracted from cortex tissue, using the modifi ed CTAB procedure mentioned earlier. PCR reactions were performed in 10-μ L volumes using a thermocycler (ICycler, Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, California, USA). Each reaction contained 50 ng of DNA, 0.2 mM of each dNTP (no. 18427-088, Invitrogen, Carlsbad, California, USA), 0.4 μ M of each primer (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, California, USA), 1 × PCR buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl, 50 mM KCl [pH 8.4]), 1-2.5 mM MgCl 2 , 0.4 U Taq DNA polymerase (no. 11615-010, Invitrogen), and 0.1 mg mL −1 of bovine serum albumin (BSA; no. B90015, New England Biolabs, Ipswich, Massachusetts, USA). Cycling conditions included initial denaturation at 94 ° C for 5 min, 30 cycles at 94 ° C for 1 min each, 45 s at the locus-specifi c annealing temperature (see <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> and Appendix S1), extension at 72 ° C for 1 min, and a fi nal extension at 72 ° C for 25 min. PCR products were visualized by silver staining in 6% polyacrylamide (Bio-Rad Laboratories), 7.5 M urea, and a 10-bp ladder (Invitrogen). Results of PCR amplifi cation of the 38 pairs of primers are given in Appendix S1.</p><p>Ten of the 38 primer pairs yielded distinct bands in the expected size range; consistent amplifi cation patterns and fewer stutter bands were selected for characterization in 40 individuals that were sampled at El Comitán and 40 that were sequenced using 454 pyrosequencing with the GS-FLX titanium platform (Roche Diagnostics, Basel, Switzerland), along with seven other species. The alignments were run according to the barcode plate strategy, as outlined in the GS-FLX Shotgun DNA Library Preparation Method Manual (supplied by Roche Diagnostics, Roche Applied Science, Mannheim, Germany).</p><p>All 454 reads were fi rst converted from fl owgrams to FASTA and FASTAqual fi les without 454 adapters, using the sff_extract software (http://bioinf. comav.upv.es/sff_extract/index.html). We found 398,286 sequence reads with an average read length of 274 bp from two independent runs. MSATCOM-MANDER software <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">( Faircloth, 2008 )</ref> was used to identify perfect microsatellites containing at least fi ve repeat units for dinucleotides and four for tri-, tetra-, penta-, and hexanuclotides. Perfect microsatellite motifs were found in 10,685 (2.6%) reads, of which dinucleotide repeats were most abundant (62%), followed by trinucleotide repeats (31%), and tetranucleotide repeats (6%). Using Primer3 software <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">( Rozen and Skaletsky, 2000 )</ref> embedded in the QDD software <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">( Meglécz et al., 2010 )</ref>, primer design was possible in 282 reads, with the following parameters: (1) melting temperatures 50-70 ° C, (2) PCR product between 90 and 320 bp, (3) GC content &gt;40%, (4) primer length between 17 and 27 nucleotides, (5) primer self-complementarities and complement between them fulfi ll the quality criteria used as default parameters in the Primer3 software.  <ref type="bibr">Ensenada,</ref><ref type="bibr">Baja California (29.063 ° N,</ref><ref type="bibr">114.155 ° W)</ref>. Duplicate samples of each individual were stored in 96% ethanol at the Laboratorio de Genética para la Conservación at CIBNOR . PCR reactions were performed, as described above, using optimized primer-specifi c annealing temperatures <ref type="table">( Table 1 )</ref>, magnesium chloride, and forward-labeled primers (5 ′ end-labeled with FAM, NED, PET, and VIC; Applied Biosystems). Individuals were genotyped by assessing allele size on a genetic analyzer (model 310, Applied Biosystems), using the GeneScan 600 LIZ Size Standard (Applied Biosystems) and GeneMapper 4.1 software (Applied Biosystems).</p><p>Locus designation, primer sequences, repeat motifs, annealing temperatures, PCR product sizes, and GenBank accession numbers are listed in <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> . All 10 loci were polymorphic, exhibiting two to 10 alleles per locus (mean A = 5.5) among cacti from El Comitán, and two to seven alleles per locus (mean A = 3.7) among cacti from Punta Prieta. Alleles per individual plant ranged from one to four in both populations, suggesting a polyploidal genome <ref type="table">( Table 2 )</ref> .</p><p>Observed heterozygosity was estimated in Microsoft Excel (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, Washington, USA). Expected heterozygosity was estimated in ATETRA software for tetraploid species that account for all possible combinations of allele copy numbers in populations with partial heterozygotes <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">( Van Puyvelde et al., 2010 )</ref>. Genetic diversity in terms of heterozygosity varied from low to high across loci in both populations. Observed heterozygosity ranged from 0.13 to 0.78 (mean H o = 0.59) and expected heterozygosity ranged from 0.37 to 0.77 (mean H e = 0.57) at El Comitán. At Punta Prieta, observed heterozygosity ranged from 0.03 to 0.85 (mean H o = 0.41) and expected heterozygosity ranged from 0.03 to 0.72 (mean H e = 0.40) ( <ref type="table">Table 2 )</ref>. For this study, we assumed tetraploidy in both populations because we observed as many as four alleles per locus in individual plants. Our results are also consistent with a tetrasomic pattern of inheritance previously suggested in P. pringlei , based on an allozymatic study <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">( Murawski et al., 1994</ref> ) and a chromosome counting study <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">( Pinkava et al., 1973 )</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p>The 10 microsatellites are the fi rst to be developed for the cardon cactus, P. pringlei , and the genus Pachycereus . These polymorphic loci will be useful in studies of genetic diversity and genetic population differentiation and provide valuable information to understand the importance of biotic and abiotic factors involved in geographic variation in the genetic pool of this widespread cactus of the Sonoran Desert.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LITERATURE CITED</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>DEVELOPMENT AND CHARACTERIZATION OF 10 MICROSATELLITE LOCI IN THE GIANT CARDON CACTUS,</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>PRIMER NOTE</cell></row><row><cell>PACHYCEREUS PRINGLEI (CACTACEAE) 1</cell></row><row><cell>CARINA GUTIÉRREZ FLORES 2 , O. ADRIAN LOZANO GARZA 2 , JOSÉ L. LEÓN DE LA LUZ 2 ,</cell></row><row><cell>AND FRANCISCO J. GARCÍA DE LEÓN 2,3</cell></row><row><cell>).</cell></row><row><cell>3 Author for correspondence: fgarciadl@cibnor.mx</cell></row><row><cell>doi:10.3732/apps.1300066</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 1 .TABLE 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Characteristics of 10 microsatellite loci developed for the cardon cactus, Pachycereus pringlei . Genetic diversity of the 10 microsatellite loci developed from the cardon cactus, Pachycereus pringlei .Note : A = number of alleles per locus; A I = number of alleles per locus in an individual plant; H e = expected heterozygosity; H o = observed heterozygosity; n = number of individuals sampled.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Locus</cell><cell>Primer sequences (5 ′ -3 ′ )</cell><cell>Repeat motif</cell><cell>T a ( ° C)</cell><cell>Size range (bp)</cell><cell>GenBank accession no.</cell></row><row><cell>Ppri01</cell><cell>F: GCGAGGGTGTCTCAAATGAT</cell><cell>(CT) 12</cell><cell>58</cell><cell>202-223</cell><cell>KC349892</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>R: TAATCCCCTCCCACCTAACC</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ppri02</cell><cell>F: TTCCATCGTCCCCTCACTTA</cell><cell>(AG) 11</cell><cell>66</cell><cell>115-119</cell><cell>KC349893</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>R: CATTCACCACCGTGAACACT</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ppri03</cell><cell>F: GGTGTTCCTCGCTCTCATTC</cell><cell>(CT) 11</cell><cell>65</cell><cell>133-155</cell><cell>KC349894</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>R: CTCGCAAATCCAAGCAAAAT</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ppri04</cell><cell>F: TTCAAATCATTCAATAAAACAAGAGC</cell><cell>(TC) 13</cell><cell>63</cell><cell>96-112</cell><cell>KC349895</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>R: ATGGAGGTCGAGGATCAAGA</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ppri05</cell><cell>F: AAACTGCAGGTGTTTCAGGG</cell><cell>(GTTT) 8</cell><cell>61</cell><cell>166-186</cell><cell>KC349896</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>R: AATGAAGCGAAAGGAAGCAA</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ppri06</cell><cell>F: GCTCACGTTGGCAGATTTGT</cell><cell>(AAAT) 6</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>138-146</cell><cell>KC349897</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>R: GGTGATGACAAAAGGTTTTGC</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ppri07</cell><cell>F: TGGACTTCCAAGGGATAATGA</cell><cell>(AAAT) 8</cell><cell>59</cell><cell>127-143</cell><cell>KC349898</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>R: TCAACTCAAAGTGTCAGTGCTG</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ppri08</cell><cell>F: AATAGCGCATGCCTCAAAGG</cell><cell>(CT) 8 (CTTT) 2</cell><cell>66</cell><cell>109-126</cell><cell>KC349899</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>R: CAATAGTCCAGAAATAGGTCAGGTCA</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ppri09</cell><cell>F: AAGAGACAGGCCCTGAGACA</cell><cell>(TC) 10</cell><cell>68</cell><cell>119-140</cell><cell>KC349900</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>R: TCGTAGGTTCCATCACCACA</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ppri10</cell><cell>F: TTCTCGAAGCCCCGCTTAC</cell><cell>(GATA) 6 (GACA) 3</cell><cell>64</cell><cell>79-107</cell><cell>KC349901</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>R: GCACGTCAAAGATGCAAGCA</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Note : T a = annealing temperature.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>aa Locality information for populations: El Comitán, Baja California Sur, Mexico (23.985 ° N, 110.187 ° W); Punta Prieta, Ensenada, Baja California, Mexico (29.063 ° N, 114.155 ° W).sampled at Punta Prieta,</note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2">Laboratorio de Genética para la Conservación, Centro de Investigaciones Biológicas del Noroeste (CIBNOR), Instituto Politécnico Nacional 195, Col. Playa Palo de Santa Rita Sur, La Paz, Baja California Sur 23096, Mexico</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The genetic structure of a columnar cactus with a disjunct distribution: Stenocereus gummosus in the Sonoran desert</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Clark-Tapia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Molina-Freaner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/sj.hdy.6800252</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">12764419</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.nature.com/articles/6800252.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Heredity</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Heredity</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0018-067X</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1365-2540</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="450" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-05-23" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA isolation and amplifi cation from cacti</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Cruz</forename><surname>De La</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ramírez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hernández</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Molecular Biology Reporter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="325" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">msatcommander: detection of microsatellite repeat arrays and automated, locus-specific primer design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Brant</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Faircloth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1471-8286.2007.01884.x</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">21585724</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-QQ9087WW-D</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">A55839A29BC5A3F323BE16F334961CE5A1E95C49</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecular Ecology Resources</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Molecular Ecology Resources</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1755-098X</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1755-0998</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-01" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geographic variation in the breeding system and the evolutionary stability of trioecy in Pachycereus pringlei (Cactaceae)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Theodore</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Fleming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sandrine</forename><surname>Maurice</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hamrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1023/a:1006548132606</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/VQC-70R64F4C-L</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">16C182C47C10ADF1BCB2B6BF249195ED6AC27302</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolutionary Ecology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Evolutionary Ecology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0269-7653</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1573-8477</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="289" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-03" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Cartographers of Life: Two Centuries of Mapping the Natural History of Baja California</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pedro</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Garcillán</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Charlotte</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>González Abraham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Exequiel</forename><surname>Ezcurra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1353/jsw.2010.0001</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Southwest</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of the Southwest</title>
		<idno type="ISSNe">2158-1371</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geology and tectonic history of the Gulf of California</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Lonsdale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1130/dnag-gna-n.499</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Eastern Pacific Ocean and Hawaii</title>
		<editor>E. L. Winterer, D. M. Hussong, and R. W. Decker</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boulder, Colorado, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Geological Society of America</publisher>
			<date>1989</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="521" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estudio ecológico y genético del Cardón ( Pachycereus pringlei ) en el Desierto Sonorense</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Medel-Narváez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Centro de Investigaciones Biológicas del Noroeste</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>La Paz, Baja California, Mexico</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Doctoral Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patterns of abundance and population structure of Pachycereus pringlei (Cactaceae), a columnar cactus of the Sonoran Desert</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alfonso</forename><surname>Medel-Narvaez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">José</forename><surname>Luis Leon De La Luz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Francisco</forename><surname>Freaner-Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Francisco</forename><surname>Molina-Freaner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11258-006-9128-1</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/VQC-BCF63JHS-W</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">7DACADB8955A4E46A1243938C0A71BD7D047B0F2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Ecology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Plant Ecol</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1385-0237</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1573-5052</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">187</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-03-25" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">QDD: a user-friendly program to select microsatellite markers and design primers from large sequencing projects</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Emese</forename><surname>Meglécz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Caroline</forename><surname>Costedoat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Vincent</forename><surname>Dubut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">André</forename><surname>Gilles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thibaut</forename><surname>Malausa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nicolas</forename><surname>Pech</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jean-François</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp670</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">20007741</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/HXZ-6L9MZMZH-M</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">693CFED461C2F21AB2C61FE0D6016F75E8190CF5</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article-pdf/26/3/403/16897513/btp670.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1367-4803</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1460-2059</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="404" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-12-10" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press (OUP)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mating system of Pachycereus pringlei: an autotetraploid cactus</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Darlyne</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Murawski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Theodore</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Fleming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kermit</forename><surname>Ritland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hamrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/hdy.1994.11</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.nature.com/articles/hdy199411.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Heredity</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Heredity</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0018-067X</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1365-2540</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-01" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HISTORICAL VICARIANCE AND POSTGLACIAL COLONIZATION EFFECTS ON THE EVOLUTION OF GENETIC STRUCTURE IN LOPHOCEREUS, A SONORAN DESERT COLUMNAR CACTUS</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Nason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hamrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Theodore</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Fleming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.0014-3820.2002.tb00146.x</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">12487352</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-XLFGZSTC-F</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">FC43D025226553685B70F28CB105D52B7432B7F4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Evolution</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Evolution</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0014-3820</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1558-5646</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2214" to="2226" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-11" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chromosome Numbers in Some Cacti of Western North America-II</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pinkava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mcleod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mcgill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2307/2805484</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/1BB-QLVP5VG0-R</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">2F9ACEF29FFE42665131C40029D83EA148506ABF</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brittonia</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Brittonia</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0007-196X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1973-01" />
			<publisher>Springer Nature</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Primer3 on the WWW for General Users and for Biologist Programmers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Steve</forename><surname>Rozen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Helen</forename><surname>Skaletsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1385/1-59259-192-2:365</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www.flyrnai.org/supplement/MMB-RosenSkaletsky.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bioinformatics Methods and Protocols</title>
		<editor>S. Misener and S. A. Krawetz</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Totowa, New Jersey, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Humana Press</publisher>
			<date>2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="386" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Late Quaternary vegetation and climate of the Sonoran Desert, United States and Mexico</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bowers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L ;</forename><surname>Burguess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Van Devender</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Packrat middens: The last 40,000 years of biotic change</title>
		<editor>J. L. Betancourt, T. R. Van Devender, and P. S. Martin</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Tucson, Arizona, USA; Tucson, Arizona, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Arizona Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="165" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sonoran Desert plants</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">atetra, a new software program to analyse tetraploid microsatellite data: comparison with tetra and tetrasat</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Van Puyvelde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Geert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Triest</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1755-0998.2009.02748.x</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">21565028</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-DPM8W9ZT-1</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">112E4DB72715184C1B4D874A1637969EB70537FE</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecular Ecology Resources</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1755-098X</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1755-0998</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="334" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-03" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
