<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Comparative Evaluation of Dimensional Accuracy of Elastomeric Impression Materials when Treated with Autoclave, Microwave, and Chemical Disinfection</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Suresh</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kamble</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Prosthodontics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">MIDS Dental College</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Latur</settlement>
									<region>Maharashtra</region>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rakshit</forename><forename type="middle">Vijay</forename><surname>Khandeparker</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Oral &amp; Maxillofacial Surgeon</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Apollo Victor Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Goa</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Somasundaram</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Faculty member</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Prosthodontics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Mahsa Dental College</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Mahsa University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Kulalumpur</settlement>
									<country key="MY">Malaysia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Shweta</forename><surname>Raghav</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Orthodontics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Senior Lecturer</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">College of Dental Sciences &amp; Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Rau, Indore</settlement>
									<region>MP</region>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rashmi</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Babaji</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">BDS</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Private Practitioner</addrLine>
									<settlement>Shimoga</settlement>
									<region>Karnataka</region>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joju</forename><surname>Varghese</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department Orthodontics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Malabar Dental College</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manoor, Malappuram</settlement>
									<region>Kerala</region>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>Consultant, Oral</roleName><forename type="first">Khandeparker</forename><surname>Rv</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Maxillofacial</forename><surname>Surgeon</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution">Victor Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Goa</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Comparative Evaluation of Dimensional Accuracy of Elastomeric Impression Materials when Treated with Autoclave, Microwave, and Chemical Disinfection</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Received: 27 th March 2015 Accepted: 25 th July 2015 Conflicts of Interest: None</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T21:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Autoclave</term>
					<term>chemical</term>
					<term>dimensional changes</term>
					<term>elastomeric</term>
					<term>impression material</term>
					<term>microwave</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Dimensional accuracy of elastomeric impression materials after autoclave microwave, and chemical disinfection … Kamble SS et al</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Impression procedures are required for various dental procedures to make accurate casts of oral structures. During impression procedure, impression materials often come in contact with saliva and blood, which may get infected with infectious diseases such as AIDS, herpes, hepatitis, or tuberculosis. Hence, disinfection of impression materials is important as dentist, oral hygienist, and dental laboratory person often expose to infectious diseases. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> In 1998, FDI guidelines suggested that all impression materials should be disinfected before sending to laboratory. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> Even American Dental Association (ADA) and center for disease control suggested disinfection of impression materials to prevent cross infection. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> Disinfection can be done by either immersion or spraying impression materials with disinfectants. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Disinfectants used should be as effective as antimicrobial agents, and not adversely affect the dimensional accuracy of impression material. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Various disinfectants are advised for disinfecting impression materials such as, sodium hypochlorite, glutaraldehyde, iodophor, and phenol. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> According to the organization for safety and asepsis procedures, 10-15 min exposure of disinfectants is recommended. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> These chemicals can kill bacteria but not spores, hence sterilization by means of autoclaving and microwave methods are suggested. Autoclaving is one of the most effective methods of sterilization. Studies related to the accuracy of elastomeric impression materials after autoclaving is very scares. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Addition silicone elastomeric impression materials (polyvinylsiloxane) are widely used because of their excellent dimensional accuracy with minimal distortion. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> It has been thought that disinfectants can alter the dimensional accurate of impression materials. Hence, the purpose of this study was to evaluate and compare the dimensional accuracy of elastomeric impression materials when treated with autoclave, microwave, and chemical disinfection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and Methods</head><p>This study uses three different types of impression materials; dentsply aquasil (addition type), zetaplus (condensation type), and impregum penta soft (polyether type) ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1)</ref>. 30 impressions with 10 for each group impression materials were made according to manufacturer's instructions. The stainless steel die was used according to ADA specification no.19 and ISO International standard 4823 to fabricate specimens. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> The syringe material was dispensed directly from cartridge The mold consisted of a base was scored with 3 horizontal lines perpendicular to 2 vertical lines with each 0.050 mm wide. 3.8 mm internal diameter steel ring was positioned accurately on the base and perforated steel plate was used to apply pressure after loading elastomers. Initially, the metal ring was placed on the base of the mold fallowed by direct injection of light body material onto platform. Then tray material was mixed and loaded according to manufacturer instruction. Excess materials were removed through perforation. The specimens were allowed to set in thermostatically controlled water bath at 37°C to simulate oral condition. Total of 30 specimens with 10 for each group (materials) were fabricated. After fabricating the samples, the distance between the inner profiles of horizontal line was measured (0.005 mm) using microscope before and after subjecting to disinfection with autoclave (Group-1), chemical -1% sodium hypochlorite (Group-2), and microwave (Group-3) methods by same examiner. Mean values were tabulated and analyzed using t-test and SPSS software IBM version 21. The percentage of dimensional change was assessed using formula; dimensional change % = (A-B)/A × 100, where "A" is distance between the inner profile of horizontal line before disinfection and "B" is after disinfection procedure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>The Tables 2 indicates % of linear dimensional change of different elastomeric materials after different disinfection procedures dentsply aquasil showed smallest dimensional change (−0.0046%) and impregum penta soft highest linear dimensional changes (−0.026%). With chemical disinfection linear expansion occurred. Highest contraction occurred with microwave method compared to autoclave and chemical type. The Tables 3 indicates dimensional change of different elastomeric materials after different disinfection procedures. All the tested elastomeric impression materials showed some degree of dimensional changes <ref type="table">(Table 3)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>Accurate reproduction of surface details of the oral structure is must after impression making. Disinfection of impression materials is advised to avoid cross infection. Impression materials may show dimensional changes after disinfection. Chemical disinfection alone is insufficient hence autoclave at high temperature is necessary to kill microbes and their spores. Microwave sterilization is used as an alternative approach, where electromagnetic energy from the microwave is considered to be alternative to the conventional method. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> This study measures the dimensional changes of impression materials after chemical, autoclave, and microwave sterilization.</p><p>In the present study, microwaving method showed highest dimensional changes followed by autoclave method and chemical sterilization <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">(Tables 2 and 3</ref>). This could be because of elastomer fluid intake in microwave method and dry nature of microwave. Results of our studies are similar to studies by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Ramakrishnaiah et al. 2012 and</ref><ref type="bibr">Cynthia et al. 2003. 4,7</ref> Warden et al. from their study concluded that steam autoclaving of impression is a safe method of microbial reduction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> Thota et al. from their study suggested that autoclave disinfection is effective for addition and condensation silicon, compare to polyether since polyether is hydrophilic which has to be disinfected by chemical means. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> Chemical disinfection produced minimal dimensional changes compared to other two methods. Tullner et al. observed no clinical significant dimensional changes with disinfection using 2% gluteraldehyde. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Ivanis et al. (2000)</ref> concluded that polyether expanded with chlorhexidine 0.5% disinfection compared to addition and condensation type. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> Ahila and Subramanian. (2012) observed no significant dimensional changes after disinfecting impression materials with glutaraldehyde, povidone, and sodium hypochlorite. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> Katyayan et al. (2011) and <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Walker et al. (2007)</ref> concluded that dimensional changes of elastomer was within ADA specification after disinfection with phenol and 0.5% sodium hypochlorite. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> Similar results were observed by Guiraldo et al.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> It has been observed that elastomer expand with chemical sterilization and contract with autoclave and microwave method. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> All of the tested impression materials were quite accurate before disinfection, but showed some degree of dimensional changes after disinfection. These dimensional changes is well below the ADA specification slandered &lt;0.5%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>The present study showed that all the disinfection procedures produce minor dimensional changes of impression material. However, it is within ADA specification. Hence, steam autoclaving and microwave method can be used as an alternative method to chemical sterilization as an effective method.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Journal of International Oral Health 2015; 7(9):22-24 Dimensional accuracy of elastomeric impression materials after autoclave microwave, and chemical disinfection … Kamble SS et al on surface, and the tray material was placed over light body material.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(2012); Dorner et al. (2014); Garrofé et al. (2011).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 : Elastomeric impression materials used in present study. Product Type Manufacturer</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Dentsply Aquasil</cell><cell>Addition silicone</cell><cell>Dentsply/caulk, milford,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>polyvinylsiloxane syringe</cell><cell>DE</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and putty</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zetaplus</cell><cell>Condensation silicone</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>putty and light body</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Impregum penta soft</cell><cell>Polyether</cell><cell>3M ESPE, St. Paul, MN</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 : Linear dimensional changes (%) of impression materials after disinfection procedure.</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Materials</cell><cell cols="3">Group-1 (%) Group-2 (%) Group-3 (%)</cell></row><row><cell>Dentsply aquasil</cell><cell>−0.0046</cell><cell>+0.0026</cell><cell>−0.024</cell></row><row><cell>Zetaplus</cell><cell>−0.0082</cell><cell>+0.0039</cell><cell>−0.022</cell></row><row><cell>Impregum penta soft</cell><cell>−0.0048</cell><cell>+0.0034</cell><cell>−0.026</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Journal of International Oral Health 2015; 7 <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>:22-24 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dimensional accuracy of elastomeric impression materials after autoclave microwave, and chemical disinfection … Kamble SS et al</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface detail reproduction and dimensional accuracy of stone models: influence of disinfectant solutions and alginate impression materials</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ricardo</forename><forename type="middle">Danil</forename><surname>Guiraldo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thaís</forename><forename type="middle">Teixeira</forename><surname>Borsato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sandrine</forename><forename type="middle">Bittencourt</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Murilo</forename><forename type="middle">Baena</forename><surname>Lopes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alcides</forename><surname>Gonini-Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mário</forename><forename type="middle">Alexandre Coelho</forename><surname>Sinhoreti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1590/s0103-64402012000400018</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">23207859</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://www.scielo.br/pdf/bdj/v23n4/a18v23n4.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brazilian Dental Journal</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Braz. Dent. J.</title>
		<idno type="ISSNe">0103-6440</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="421" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<publisher>FapUNIFESP (SciELO)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Comparative Evaluation of the Dimensional Stability of Three Different Elastomeric Impression Materials after Autoclaving – An Invitro Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kiran</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Thota</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jasthi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ravuri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7860/jcdr/2014/9768.5036</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">25478447</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC4253265</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JOURNAL OF CLINICAL AND DIAGNOSTIC RESEARCH</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">JCDR</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">2249-782X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<publisher>JCDR Research and Publications</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative evaluation of dimensional stability and surface quality of gypsum casts retrieved from disinfected addition silicone impressions at various time intervals: An in vitro study</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ahila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Subramanian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Dent Oral Hyg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of chemical disinfection, autoclave, microwave sterilization on the dimensional accuracy of polyvinylsiloxane elastomeric impression materials</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ramakrishnaiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kheraif</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Qasim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Appl Sci J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface Quality and Long-term Dimensional Stability of Current Elastomeric Impression Materials after Disinfection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mary</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Meagan</forename><surname>Rondeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Cynthia</forename><surname>Petrie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amy</forename><surname>Tasca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Karen</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1532-849x.2007.00206.x</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">17559536</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-Q5L4TR0V-F</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">638BC1C51866400E9F69A1CB1F549FF2070254A7</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Prosthodontics</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">J Prosthodontics</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1059-941X</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1532-849X</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="343" to="351" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-09" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">American Dental Association Specification No. 19 for Aqueous, Elastomeric Dental Impression Materials</title>
		<ptr target="http//www.132.248.225.10/posgrado/materials/normas/norma_19.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1878-10-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Last accessed on</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dimensional accuracy and surface detail reproduction of two hydrophilic vinyl polysiloxane impression materials tested under dry, moist, and wet conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Cynthia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>O'mahony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Spencer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Prosthet Dent</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Method of microbial reduction and/or sterilization of impression materials</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Warden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Chorbaji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Monzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Patent abstract of Japan. 1995; 07112910 A</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linear dimensional changes in dental impressions after immersion in disinfectant solutions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Tullner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Commette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Peter</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Moon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0022-3913(88)90407-6</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">3060605</idno>
		<idno type="PII">0022-3913(88)90407-6</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/6H6-KRRBCQKS-K</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">99AF544D6B8C906B731BA1C034E12953C3834CE5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Prosthetic Dentistry</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Journal of Prosthetic Dentistry</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0022-3913</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="725" to="728" />
			<date type="published" when="1988-12" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dimensional stability of elastomeric impression materials disinfected in a solution of 0.5% chlorhexidine gluconate and alcohol</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ivanis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zivko-Babie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lazie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pandurie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Stomatol Croat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dimensional accuracy and detail reproduction of two hydrophilic vinyl polysiloxane impression materials tested under different conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Preetiagarwal</forename><surname>Katyayan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Manish</forename><surname>Katyayan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Natarajan</forename><surname>Kalavathy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4103/0970-9290.94697</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22484900</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Indian Journal of Dental Research</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Indian J Dent Res</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0970-9290</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">881</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<publisher>Medknow</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of disinfection of irreversible hydrocolloid impression materials with 1% sodium hypochlorite on surface roughness and dimesnsional accuracy of dental stone casts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dorner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Da Siva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Uemura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Borges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Fernandes</forename><surname>Junior</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Yamamto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Gene Dent</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="122" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linear dimensional stability of elastomeric impression materials over time</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Garrofé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ferrari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Picca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kaplan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Odontol Latinoam</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
