<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Comparison therapeutic efficacy of underwater and overground walking training on the healthy subjects balancing ability</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Society of Physical Therapy Science</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Society of Physical Therapy Science</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Null-</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>PT</roleName><forename type="first">Myoung-Kwon</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Physical Therapy</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Rehabilitation Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Daegu University: Jillyang</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>712-714</postCode>
									<settlement>Gyeongsan</settlement>
									<region>Gyeongbuk</region>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Comparison therapeutic efficacy of underwater and overground walking training on the healthy subjects balancing ability</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Journal of Physical Therapy Science</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">J Phys Ther Sci</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0915-5287</idno>
						<idno type="eISSN">2187-5626</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Society of Physical Therapy Science</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="924" to="926"/>
							<date type="published" when="2017" />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1589/jpts.29.924</idno>
					<idno type="PMID">28603373</idno>
					<idno type="PMCID">PMC5462700</idno>
					<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.jstage.jst.go.jp/article/jpts/29/5/29_jpts-2017-044/_pdf" />
					<note type="submission">This article was submitted Jan. 26, 2017, and was accepted Feb. 20, 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2020-08-13T21:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Balance</term>
					<term>Gait</term>
					<term>Underwater treadmill</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>This study&apos;s working hypothesis is that underwater walking training is beneficial for healthy subjects balance. [Subjects and Methods] Forty eight subjects (Underwater walking group=25, Overground walking group=23) completed the experiment. Healthy subjects with no orthopedic history of lower extremity injuries were recruited. Gait training is performed using the underwater treadmill consisted of 30-minute walking sessions, five times per week for four weeks. [Results] After the intervention, the medial-lateral and anterior-posterior balance indices increased significantly. [Conclusion] This study conducted underwater walking training on the healthy subjects, with positive effects on balancing ability.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Balancing ability is defined as the ability to maintain the body's center of gravity while minimizing sway in the base of support. Postural balance, on the other hand, indicates the ability to continuously retain balance in accordance with the center of mass (COM) and movement, and to maintain the proper postural control against actions and external rocking within the base of support <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2)</ref> . Gait training is a common method of improving the balancing ability. It is recommended for aerobic capacity improvement, body fat reduction, lowering the blood pressure, improving insulin sensitivity, and improving gait and balancing abilities <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3)</ref> . Research testing the effects of gait training examines types and speed of walking. Underwater walking training is special in that it provides a work-out environment of reduced gravity with the use of the buoyancy of water <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3)</ref> . Water workouts relieve stress from weight on the joints, enhances muscular function without imposing excessive impact to the muscle, and improves flexibility and balance <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4)</ref> .</p><p>Most research has focused on gait training in the ground, and there are very few investigations of underwater walking training and its effects on balancing ability <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4)</ref> . Given this background, this study examines the effects of underwater walking training on the healthy subjects balancing ability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUBJECTS AND METHODS</head><p>Forty eight subjects (Underwater walking group=25, Overground walking group=23) completed the experiment. The characteristics of the two groups (n=48) before and after intervention are shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>. The selection criteria were as follows: no history of orthopedic surgery on a lower limb, never taken any drug due to a neurologic problem, and no musculoskeletal system disease. In underwater and overground walking training groups average ages, heights, and weights were 20.14 ± 1.27, 21.37 ± 1.41 years, 174.16 ± 10.17, 172.54 ± 8.67 cm, and 72.35 ± 6.58, 68.94 ± 7.84 kg, respectively. Sufficient explanation of this study's intent and the overall purpose was given, and voluntary consent to participate in this study was obtained from all of the subjects. Information on the study and written informed consent according to the ethical standards of the Declaration of Helsinki were provided to all subjects prior to their participation.</p><p>The trials consisted of underwater and overground walking training. The subjects either walked on an underwater treadmill (HydroTrack ® Underwater Treadmill System, Conray, Inc., Phoenix, AZ, USA) or walked on an overground treadmill (HL-1100, Healthlife, Korea). The water temperature was set at about 33 °C and the depth was fixed to reach up between the subjects' xiphoid process and the navel. The speed of the treadmill was limited to a maximum velocity of 2-4 m/s in both groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4)</ref> . The both group consisted of 30-minute walking sessions, five times per week for four weeks.</p><p>After the intervention, balance measuring equipment (Good Balance, Metitur, Finland) was used to quantitatively measure each subject's balance ability <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5)</ref> . The balance test was performed by a physical therapist who had completed the course for the balance test method and was experienced in clinical practice for over three years. To measure balance function, the subject was instructed to stand on a triangle platform and maintain a symmetrical posture with the feet shoulder width apart. A visual fixed point was located in front of the subject to minimize head movements. The subject's arms were placed comfortably at the hip joints and the center of pressure (COP) was measured for 30 seconds in the standing posture with the eyes open. COP was measured three times and average values were calculated. The software also calculates several variables describing the quantitative aspects of individual's test behaviour, e.g. amount and speed of anterior-posterior and medial-lateral sway, amplitude of sway, the first moment of sway velocity (combined amplitude and velocity of the movement of the center of pressure), power spectrum analysis (FFT analysis) etc. Low score of anterior-posterior and medial-lateral sway implies excellent balance ability. The index of balance function score ranges between 0 and 100, and a higher score implies greater balance ability to perform the task. A reliable and valid measurement of the functioning of posture control mechanisms is a prerequisite for discovering the reasons for balance problems or evaluating the effects of treatment and rehabilitation.</p><p>The mean and SD were calculated for each variable. Before the intervention, differences in the general characteristics of the experimental group were analyzed by descriptive statistics. Variables were compared before and after training within experimental group using paired sample t-tests. The statistical analysis was conducted using SPSS 20.0 (SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA), and statistical significance was accepted for p values &lt;0.05</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p>The underwater walking training showed significant increases in all variance after intervention (p&lt;0.05). Significant intergroup differences in post-training gains were observed for all varience (p&lt;0.05). The effect sizes of gains in the underwater and overground walking training were high for medial-lateral and anterior-posterior locus length, balance function indices (effect sizes 0.84, 1.11, and 0.96, respectively) ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p>This study assessed underwater walking training on healthy subjects, and the results showed a positive effect on balancing ability. An earlier study found that a stretching exercise increased balancing ability in healthy subjects <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5)</ref> .When a person moves in the water, buoyancy and resistance of the water induce rocking of posture. This body movement activates proprioception to maintain upright posture <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6)</ref> . Movement in the water allows easier application of open and closed kinetic chain exercise than on the ground.</p><p>In the present study, a variable-speed underwater treadmill training with adjustable water depth and frontal resistance provided by pump-driven directional water jets has been used as a novel mode of aquatic exercise. This system theoretically provides a more favorable mode of exercise for the overweight and obese, in that walking or jogging intensity (velocity and resistance) can be controlled, whereas the buoyancy of water reduces the impact force of ambulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7)</ref> .</p><p>Other researchers have previously investigated, physical function and walking ability were improved in adults with incomplete spinal cord injury following a structured program of underwater treadmill training featuring individualized levels of body weight support and carefully staged increases in speed and duration <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4)</ref> . From a clinical perspective, these findings highlight the potential of underwater treadmill training in persons with physical disabilities and diseases that would benefit from weight-supported exercise.</p><p>Underwater walking training provides a treatment environment that is psychologically stable. The physical nature of water presents advantages in improving muscular strength and endurance, motion range of joints, increase in cardiopulmonary abilities, and improving the quality of life, as gait and balancing ability improve <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8)</ref> . When adults with arthritis were treated with underwater walking training, their balancing ability and motion range of joints improved <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9)</ref> . It appears that buoyancy, temperature, and other qualities of water stimulated proprioception and decreased postural rocking.</p><p>The underwater treadmill training has been used most frequently as a treatment modality in sports injury or orthopedic rehabilitation settings and has only recently been used with obese individuals. Therefore, further clinical controlled studies with larger sample sizes and longer interventions should be carried out to validate the clinical benefits of the underwater walking.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Characteristics of the experimental and control groups pre-and post-intervention (values are presented as means (standard deviations)</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">EG (n=25)</cell><cell cols="2">CG (n=23)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Pre-test</cell><cell>Post-test</cell><cell>Pre-test</cell><cell>Post-test</cell></row><row><cell>Medial-lateral locus length (mm/s) a, b</cell><cell cols="2">128.7 (21.3) 120.1 (19.6)*</cell><cell>131.6 (19.7)</cell><cell>127.5 (18.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Anterior-posterior locus length (mm/s) a, b</cell><cell cols="2">188.3 (20.6) 175.2 (22.3)*</cell><cell>190.2 (19.7)</cell><cell>188.3 (20.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Index of balance function (score) a, b</cell><cell>70.3 (10.6)</cell><cell>82.2 (9.6)*</cell><cell>73.2 (12.8)</cell><cell>75.3 (14.8)</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">EG: underwater walking group; CG: overground walking group; *p&lt;0.05</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">a Significant difference between gains in the two groups</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>b Effect size &gt;0.70</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J. Phys. Ther. Sci. 29: 924-926, 2017</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between the Berg Balance Scale and Static Balance Test in Hemiplegic Patients with Stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Makoto</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hiroyuki</forename><surname>Fujisawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yooichiro</forename><surname>Machida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Shin</forename><surname>Minakata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1589/jpts.25.1043</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">24259912</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC3820219</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.jstage.jst.go.jp/article/jpts/25/8/25_jpts-2013-098/_pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Physical Therapy Science</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">J Phys Ther Sci</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0915-5287</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1043" to="1049" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<publisher>Society of Physical Therapy Science</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>CrossRef</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of Lower Limb Muscle Fatigue on Balance Function</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kazuhisa</forename><surname>Inoue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mitsutoshi</forename><surname>Uematsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hiroshi</forename><surname>Maruoka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kazuhiko</forename><surname>Hara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Naohiko</forename><surname>Kanemura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tadashi</forename><surname>Masuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sadao</forename><surname>Morita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1589/jpts.25.331</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="https://www.jstage.jst.go.jp/article/jpts/25/3/25_JPTS-2012-349/_pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Physical Therapy Science</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">J Phys Ther Sci</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0915-5287</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<publisher>Society of Physical Therapy Science</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of training at a walk on conventional and underwater treadmills on fiber properties and metabolic responses of superficial digital flexor and gluteal muscles to high-speed exercise in horses</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Anna</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Firshman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lisa</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Borgia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stephanie</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Valberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2460/ajvr.76.12.1058</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">26618730</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Veterinary Research</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">American Journal of Veterinary Research</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0002-9645</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1058" to="1065" />
			<date type="published" when="2015-12" />
			<publisher>American Veterinary Medical Association (AVMA)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>CrossRef</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of underwater treadmill training on leg strength, balance, and walking performance in adults with incomplete spinal cord injury</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sandra</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Caputo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dana</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Fuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Don</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Morgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1179/2045772314y.0000000217</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">24969269</idno>
		<idno type="PMCID">PMC4293539</idno>
		<ptr type="open-access" target="http://europepmc.org/articles/pmc4293539?pdf=render" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Spinal Cord Medicine</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">The Journal of Spinal Cord Medicine</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1079-0268</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">2045-7723</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-06-26" />
			<publisher>Informa UK Limited</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>CrossRef</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fall Incidence in Frail Older Women after Individualized Visual Feedback-Based Balance Training</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sanna</forename><surname>Sihvonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sarianna</forename><surname>Sipilä</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sara</forename><surname>Taskinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pertti</forename><surname>Era</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1159/000080180</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">15477703</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gerontology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Gerontology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0304-324X</idno>
		<idno type="ISSNe">1423-0003</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="416" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<publisher>S. Karger AG</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>CrossRef</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of Acute Static Stretching on Force, Balance, Reaction Time, and Movement Time</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Behm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Bambury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Farrell</forename><surname>Cahill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><surname>Power</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1249/01.mss.0000135788.23012.5f</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">15292749</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medicine &amp; Science in Sports &amp; Exercise</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Medicine &amp; Science in Sports &amp; Exercise</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0195-9131</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1397" to="1402" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-08" />
			<publisher>Ovid Technologies (Wolters Kluwer Health)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>CrossRef</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative Efficacy of Water and Land Treadmill Training for Overweight or Obese Adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Greene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Brad</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lambert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Greene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Aaron</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Carbuhn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Crouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1249/mss.0b013e3181a23f7f</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">19657288</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medicine &amp; Science in Sports &amp; Exercise</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Medicine &amp; Science in Sports &amp; Exercise</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">0195-9131</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1808" to="1815" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-09" />
			<publisher>Ovid Technologies (Wolters Kluwer Health)</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>CrossRef</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydrotherapy-a new approach to improve function in the older patient with chronic heart failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Åsa</forename><surname>Cider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Schaufelberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Katharina</forename><forename type="middle">Stibrant</forename><surname>Sunnerhagen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Bert</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/s1388-9842(03)00048-5</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">12921815</idno>
		<idno type="ark">ark:/67375/WNG-4RT1WJNL-Q</idno>
		<idno type="istexId">A371286B9DE0CB54ED094DD428708ABEC5C2F6AD</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Heart Failure</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">European Journal of Heart Failure</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1388-9842</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="535" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-08" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>CrossRef</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biomechanical characteristics of adults walking in shallow water and on land</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ana</forename><forename type="middle">M F</forename><surname>Barela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sandro</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marcos</forename><surname>Duarte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jelekin.2005.06.013</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">16111894</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Electromyography and Kinesiology</title>
		<title level="j" type="abbrev">Journal of Electromyography and Kinesiology</title>
		<idno type="ISSN">1050-6411</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="250" to="256" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-06" />
			<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>CrossRef</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
