<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mem. Inst. Oswaldo Cruz</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Mem&#x000f3;rias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0074-0276</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1678-8060</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Instituto Oswaldo Cruz, Minist&#x000e9;rio da Sa&#x000fa;de</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25410986</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4296487</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0074-0276140334</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Institutional journals as an alternative model for open
access</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' --><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>109</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>848</lpage><permissions><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License, which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><counts><page-count count="2"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Open access together with advances in information and communication technology (ICT) have
transformed the economics of academic publishing. They have also highlighted a revitalized
role for institutional journals. These journals often published through institutional
mandates can offer open access without the perceived conflicts of interest created by
charging publishing fees. The <italic>Mem&#x000f3;rias</italic>
<italic>do</italic>
<italic>Instituto Oswaldo</italic>
<italic>Cruz</italic> provides an interesting case study for other institutional
journals.</p><p>Traditionally journals were published in printed format and financed through subscriptions
to libraries and individuals. Capital was required, to finance the editorial office and the
production and publishing costs, until a level of subscription income was reached that made
the journal self-financing or profitable. Some journals never obtained sufficient income
and required continued subsidies to operate. This need for capital or subsidies meant that
journal publishing was generally the preserve of commercial publishers, scientific
societies or academic institutions. Very occasionally a brave entrepreneur would enter the
field and if successful start their own publishing house.</p><p>Advances in ICT revolutionised the journal publishing workflow. Increasingly sophisticated
software platforms vastly increased the efficiency of editorial offices allowing multiple
journals to be published from a single office or individual journals to be published by an
editor and a virtual office. Improved electronic publishing rapidly made the digital format
the preferred medium for readers resulting in markedly reduced printing and distribution
costs. It was against this background that the open access movement arose with the primary
goal of making the results of scientific research free to access, for all and forever.</p><p>Although advances in ICT had increased the efficiency of editorial offices and reduced
publishing and dissemination costs, some funding was still needed. Therefore if access to
scientific information was to be free an alternative to subscription income was required.
Article processing or publishing charges (APCs) were thus introduced with the revolutionary
idea of switching the cost of access to journal articles from the reader (or often
libraries acting as surrogate purchasers) to the author (or often their research funder or
author institution). This change in financing was justified by the arguments that the
financing of research should include the cost of publication of the research and that the
results of publically funded research should be publically and freely available.</p><p>A corollary to the advances in ICT and the introduction of APCs was that the financial
barrier for new entrants to journal publishing was removed. The advent of cloud computing
and specialised open source software programs allowed any entrepreneur with some basic
knowledge to start publishing journals with very little capital. At the same time the APCs
provided a scalable funding model where costs and expenses were directly related to income
received making a journal profitable whether it published a few dozen or a few thousand
articles. The result has been an explosion in the number of new journals coming on-line and
thousands of new titles appearing with very similar names often confusing both experienced
and new researchers.</p><p>A consequence of this easy profitability has been that the field of journal publishing has
attracted a breed of unscrupulous entrepreneurs more interested in quick profits and less
concerned about publication ethics. As journal income is directly related to the number of
articles published, there is a clear financial incentive to accept as many articles as
possible regardless of quality and to incentivize a kind of vanity publishing. These
predatory publishers have tarnished the name of open access publishing and have been used
by some critics to cast the whole field of open access publishing into disrepute.</p><p>In traditional publishing, institutional journals were often considered as inferior to
those journals published by academic societies and commercial publishers. It was often
thought that these journals favoured in-house authors, their reviewers were biased against
external researchers and in general the journals were too inbred and anachronistic in the
modern world of international science. However the same trends that have revolutionised
academic publishing have also transformed the best of these journals. ICT has facilitated
the opening of these journals with international editorial boards and an international
reach attracting authors and readers from many countries. For example, the <italic>Mem&#x000f3;rias
do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz</italic> has an international editorial board. During the past
two years it has received submissions from authors in 70 countries and published articles
with authors in 40 countries. The journal since its founding more than a hundred years ago
(its first issue was in 1909) has always enjoyed strong institutional support. This has
allowed the journal to be freely accessible online from the earliest days of internet
journal publishing (since 1994). It has never charged APCs as the Oswaldo Cruz Institute of
Oswaldo Cruz Foundation has always believed that the publication of high quality scientific
research is an important part of its mandate. This strong institutional support has allowed
the journal to concentrate on quality rather than be concerned with income. As a result the
<italic>Mem&#x000f3;rias</italic> has achieved one of the highest impact factors of any journal
in Latin America and is the most cited journal on the continent. More recently the
<italic>Mem&#x000f3;rias</italic> has adopted the Creative Commons licence and is fully open
access compliant.</p><p>The principles of open access are supported by most scholars. They have a professional
interest in the widest access to their published work. The moral case for free access to
publicly funded research has been eloquently made. However APCs represent a barrier for
some researchers who do not have access to funds for publishing, besides the perceived
conflict of interest of APCs for journals.</p><p>Journals published by academic institutions often do not charge for access and with modern
technology those that do, could and should make access free as part of their institutional
mandates. These journals, free of the conflict of interest in charging their authors
publishing fees, can strive for the highest publishing standards in an open access
environment. Of course there are other institutional journals who both provide open access
and are leaders in their fields, for example the Bulletin of the World Health Organization,
published by World Health Organization in the field of public health, and Emerging
Infectious Diseases, published by the Centres for Disease Control. The
<italic>Mem&#x000f3;rias</italic> is therefore not an anomaly but a pioneer in the re-emergence
of institutional journals as an alternative model for open access publishing.</p><sig-block><sig><bold>Hooman Momen</bold><break/><italic>Editorial Board,</italic><break/> Mem&#x000f3;rias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz <break/></sig></sig-block></body></article>