<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ViewNLM-v2.3.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JKMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15716600</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2808573</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2005.20.1.42</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of Particulate Matter (PM<sub>10</sub>) on The Pulmonary Function of Middle-School Children</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Jeong Hee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Dea Hyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Ja Kyoung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>Su Jin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>Byong Kwan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1">Department of Pediatrics, College of Medicine, Inha University, Incheon, Korea.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>*</label>Department of Pediatrics, College of Medicine, Kangwon University, Chunchon, Korea.</aff><aff id="A3"><label>&#x02020;</label>Department of Pediatrics, College of Medicine, Pochon CHA University, Pochon, Korea.</aff><author-notes><corresp>
Address for correspondence: Byong Kwan Son, M.D. Department of Pediatrics, Inha University College of Medicine, 7-206 Shinheung-dong 3-ga, Jung-gu, Incheon 400-711, Korea. Tel: +82.32-890-3519, Fax: +82.32-890-2844, <email>sonbk@inha.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>5</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>It has been reported that the particulate matter under 10 &#x000b5;m (PM<sub>10</sub>) has deleterious effects on respiratory health. The purpose of this study was to assess the influence of PM<sub>10</sub> upon normal children's lung function. The subjects were 368 middle school students in two areas of Incheon Metropolitan City. One (Incheon) is in the central city and the other (Ganghwa) is in the suburbs. Air pollution data in the vicinities of two participating schools were obtained from monthly report of air quality from Korean Ministry of Environment in 2000. Pulmonary function testing (PFT) was done two times, the first one in March and the second one in December with the same students. We analyzed the relationship between the PM<sub>10</sub> levels and pulmonary functions (FEV<sub>1</sub>, FVC) of the children. The monthly average of the PM<sub>10</sub> level between the two areas showed no significant difference (55.3 vs. 52.3 &#x000b5;g/m<sup>3</sup>). In both regions, the difference of the PM<sub>10</sub> level between March and December was statistically significant (64 vs. 56 &#x000b5;g/m<sup>3</sup> in Incheon, 64 vs. 54 &#x000b5;g/m<sup>3</sup> in Ganghwa). The findings of the PFT values in March were significantly lower than those values found in December for both regions. In conclusion, we suggest that PM<sub>10</sub> has some adverse effect on the pulmonary function of normal children.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Pneumoconiosis</kwd><kwd>Filtration</kwd><kwd>Particulate Matter (PM<sub>10</sub>)</kwd><kwd>Respiratory Function Tests</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Air pollution has been of great concern since the major industrial events associated with air pollution happened in Europe and the United States between the thirties and the fifties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). Many studies have shown that air pollution is strongly associated with the human health, and the results of air pollution include an increased mortality rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>), an increased number of patients with respiratory or cardiovascular diseases at outpatient departments or emergency rooms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>), the aggravation of asthma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>), the increase of respiratory symptoms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>) or the decrease of pulmonary function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>).</p><p>Particulate matter of a diameter under 10 &#x000b5;m (PM<sub>10</sub>) is a mixture of solid and liquid particles in the air, and major sources of these fine particles are diesel engine exhaust, food cooking operations, and dust from wood burning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Particles derived from mobiles and stationary combustion sources are more likely to be in the respirable range. The decrease of peak expiratory flow (PEF) in children with asthma has been noted in those places where the density of traffic is heavy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). Prior studies have found significant associations between concentrations of PM<sub>10</sub> and decrements in pulmonary function test (PFT) values for in children with and without asthma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>).</p><p>Recently, the number of traffic cars has been continuously increasing in Korea, and not surprisingly, the prevalence of asthma has also been increasing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). We hypothesized that PM<sub>10</sub>, which is mainly generated from automobiles, would have deleterious effects on the respiratory tract for even normal children. We also wanted to evaluate the effects of PM<sub>10</sub> from the yellow dust storms on the lung function of children. This study was conducted to evaluate the effect of PM<sub>10</sub> on the pulmonary function of normal Korean middle school children.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Subjects</title><p>We assumed that middle-school students are more apt to undergo the pulmonary function test and present accurate results, therefore we randomly selected middle school students from two areas of Incheon Metropolitan City; one area is in the central city (Incheon) where the traffic is heavy and the other area is in a suburb (Ganghwa). We randomly selected a few classes in each grade in a school, and the number of students was 124 (male; 75, female; 49) from Incheon and 244 (male; 125, female; 119) from Ganghwa (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The student subjects were excluded if they had respiratory symptoms within one week before the test and if they had a history of chronic respiratory disease including bronchial asthma and if their growth measurements (height and weight) were over the 97th percentile or below the 3th percentile of Korean standard for their ages.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Pulmonary function testing was done using a portable electric mini-spirometer, in which forced expiratory volume per second (FEV<sub>1</sub>) and forced vital capacity (FVC) were measured. Prior to pulmonary function testing, a detailed explanation was given to the subjects by the trained examiners. After the test was performed five times, the minimum and maximum values were discarded and the three remaining values were averaged. In March and December of 2000, pulmonary function testing was done repeatedly with the same students. We selected March as the month when the yellow dust storms mainly occurred to evaluate the effects of PM<sub>10</sub> on the lung function of healthy children. In addition, we also wanted to evaluate the effects of PM<sub>10</sub> generated mainly from automobiles, so we chose December, when the effects of both the yellow dust storms and ozone were minimal.</p><p>PM<sub>10</sub> data in the vicinity of two participating schools were obtained from the monthly reports of air quality from Korean Ministry of Environment in 2000 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis were done using SAS&#x000ae; version 6.12 for Windows, in which t-tests and the general linear model were used for univariate and multivariate analysis, respectively. A probability value of less than 0.05 was considered to be statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Baseline level of PM<sub>10</sub> and other air pollutants</title><p>According to the data from the Korean Ministry of Environment in 2000 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>), the mean values of monthly levels of PM<sub>10</sub> were 52.3 &#x000b5;g/m<sup>3</sup> in Incheon and 55.8 &#x000b5;g/m<sup>3</sup> in Ganghwa, and there was no significant difference between the two areas. In March, the mean values of PM<sub>10</sub> were the same as 64 &#x000b5;g/m<sup>3</sup> in both areas. In December, the mean concentrations of PM<sub>10</sub> were 56 &#x000b5;g/m<sup>3</sup> and 53 &#x000b5;g/m<sup>3</sup> in Incheon and in Ganghwa, respectively, and no statistical significance was noted between the two areas. In both regions, however, the levels of PM<sub>10</sub> were higher in March than in December (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). The mean levels of NO<sub>2</sub> and SO<sub>2</sub> were higher in Incheon than in Ganghwa, but the mean levels of O<sub>3</sub> were higher in Ganghwa than in Incheon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>The results of pulmonary function test</title><p>In both regions, the higher academic year was, the greater the FEV<sub>1</sub> and FVC values were. Moreover, the FEV<sub>1</sub> and FVC values were greater in male students than in female students during the same academic year. The FEV<sub>1</sub> and FVC value were greater in December than in March for the same academic year in both areas (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The prevalence of asthma has increased worldwide and this has been most strikingly observed in the industrialized countries during the last decade. Epidemiologic studies suggest that environmental factors including air pollution play an important role for the increasing prevalence of asthma. The major air pollutants are CO, NO<sub>X</sub>, O<sub>3</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub> and particulate matters. Among these pollutants, PM<sub>10</sub> can have easily access to the lung via the respiratory tract, and this matter can deposit within the lung (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). According to the study in Utah, U.S.A., during the winter when the level of PM<sub>10</sub> was high, the number of patients with respiratory diseases was three times higher than that measured during the winter, when the level of PM<sub>10</sub> was low since the steel factory workers went on a strike (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). Moreover, several investigators reported that not only have the number of patients at outpatient department or an emergency room increased, but also the hospitalized or expired patients increased on the days when atmospheric dust was prevalent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). In Korea, the highest daily level of total suspended particles (TSP) was reported to be correlated with the number of hospitalization for asthma among the patients who were over 40 yr of age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>).</p><p>We thought that the levels of PM<sub>10</sub> were higher in Incheon than in Ganghwa because the density of traffic is more serious in Incheon. Contrary to our expectations, the levels of PM<sub>10</sub> were not statistically different between the two areas, although the levels of NO<sub>2</sub> and SO<sub>2</sub> were higher in Incheon than in Ganghwa. The pulmonary functions of the students in two areas were not different either. Yet in both areas, the levels of PM<sub>10</sub> were higher in March than in December.</p><p>The levels of PM<sub>10</sub> often exceeded a 24-hr mean level of 150 &#x000b5;m/m<sup>3</sup> for Korean environment air quality standards in March. These findings would be due to the yellow dust storms which refers to the wind-blown dust generated from northern China and Mongolia during the spring season. In Korea, yellow dust storms are usually observed in March and May every year, when the level of PM<sub>10</sub> exceeds the level of environmental standard by two or three times (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>). The size of particulate matter from the yellow dust is mainly 3 &#x000b5;m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). This range of particulate matter is easily respirable. So it is expected that this kind of particulate matter would have deleterious effects on respiratory system of normal children. Yellow dust storms occurred 4 times during March 2000 in Incheon and Ganghwa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>).</p><p>The present study showed that the values of FEV<sub>1</sub> and FVC were greater in December than in March for both male and female students at all academic years. Even when taking into consideration the increase of the children's height and weight during the nine months period, the results of pulmonary function test in December were higher than those for the grades one year older, who were checked in March, for almost all grades. Because only the level of PM<sub>10</sub> was significantly higher for March than for December in both areas, we suggest that the decrements of pulmonary function in March for both areas are associated with the increased level of PM<sub>10</sub> and yellow dust. This particulate matter may have some important role for decrement of pulmonary function.</p><p>There are several limitations in this study including the lack of personal exposure data, the possibility of other air pollutant's effects, and lack of exact data of air pollutants on the day when the pulmonary function testing was performed. The levels of NO<sub>2</sub> and SO<sub>2</sub> were two times higher in Incheon than in Ganghwa and the levels O<sub>3</sub> were higher in Ganghwa than in Incheon both for March and for December (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). However, the levels of SO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub> were similar in both May and December in each areas. The levels of NO<sub>2</sub> were higher for December than for March in both areas. Therefore, we believe that the decrements of the value of pulmonary function in March were caused by particulate matter.</p><p>In conclusion, we can suggest that PM<sub>10</sub>, especially the particulate matter generated from yellow dust storms may have significant negative effects on the FVC and FEV<sub>1</sub> values in normal children.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p>This study was conducted with the fund of <funding-source>Seoul National University Pediatrics Alumni</funding-source>.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mortality in the London fog incident, 1952</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1953</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>336</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13012086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Air pollution and daily mortality: a reviews and meta analysis</article-title><source>Environ Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8287841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dockery</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Air pollution and daily mortality in residential areas of Beijing, China</article-title><source>Arch Environ Health</source><year>1994</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8031176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Touloumi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsouyanni</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Trichopoulos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short-term effects of air pollution on daliy mortality in Athens: a time-series analysis</article-title><source>Int J Epidemiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>957</fpage><lpage>967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7860176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Leem</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Air pollution and daily mortality in Incheon, Korea</article-title><source>J Korean Med Sci</source><year>1999</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10402164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ostro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauchez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aranda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckeland</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Air pollution and mortality: result from a study of Santiago, Chile</article-title><source>J Expo Anal Environ Epidemiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8777376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Air particulate matters and daily mortality in Ulsan, Korea</article-title><source>Korean J Prev Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>90</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study on the interrelationship of air pollution and respiratory disease in Incheon City via children who visited the emergency room of Inha University Hospital</article-title><source>J Korean Pediatr Soc</source><year>2000</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1372</fpage><lpage>1379</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leem</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Roh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short-term effects of air pollution on hospital visits for respiratory diseases in Seoul</article-title><source>Korean J Occup Environ Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>342</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whittemore</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Korn</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asthma and air pollution in the Los Angeles area</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><year>1980</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7386702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vedal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Petkau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute effects of ambient inhalable particles in asthmatic and nonasthmatic children</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>1034</fpage><lpage>1043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9563716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Timonen</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pekkanen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Air pollution and respiratory health among children with asthmatic or cough symptoms</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>1997</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>546</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9279238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pekkanen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Timonen</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Runskanen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reponen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirme</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of ultrafine and fine particles in urban air on peak expiratory flow among children with asthmatic symptoms</article-title><source>Environ Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9339211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lipsett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Air pollution and emergency room visits for asthma in Santa Clara County, California</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><year>1997</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9105797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><source>The association of asthma patients with air pollution [dissertation]</source><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>Seoul</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Seoul National University</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>CA</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name><surname>Dockery</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute health effects of PM<sub>10</sub> pollution on symptomatic and asymptomatic children</article-title><source>Am Rev Respir Dis</source><year>1992</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>1123</fpage><lpage>1128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1586057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vigotti</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisanti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanobetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short term effects of urban air pollution on respiratory health in Milan Italy, 1980-89</article-title><source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source><year>1996</year><volume>50</volume><issue>Supp 1</issue><fpage>S71</fpage><lpage>S75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8758228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bedi</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Folinsbee</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pulmonary function effects of 1.0 and 2.0 ppm sulfur dioxide exposure in active young male non-smokers</article-title><source>J Air Pollut Control Assoc</source><year>1984</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1117</fpage><lpage>1121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6512104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cass</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Edgerton</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Source apportionment of PM2.5 in the Southeastern United States using solvent-extractable organic compounds as tracers</article-title><source>Environ Sci Technol</source><year>2002</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>2361</fpage><lpage>2371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12075791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Henley</surname><given-names>QS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebolledo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Checkoway</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierson</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pulmonary function changes in children associated with fine particulate matter</article-title><source>Environ Res</source><year>1993</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8404772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Zee</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoek</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Boezen</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schouten</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wijnen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunekreef</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute effects of urban air pollution on respiratory health with and without chronic respiratory symptoms</article-title><source>Occup Environ Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>802</fpage><lpage>813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10658536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Choung</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The trend for diagnosis and treatment of childhood asthma in Korean pediatricians</article-title><source>Pediatr Allergy Respir Dis</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>221</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>Monthly report of air quality</source><year>2000</year><month>3</month><date-in-citation>cited 6 Feb 2004</date-in-citation><comment>availabe from URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lib.me.go.kr/imgview_detail.asp">http://lib.me.go.kr/imgview_detail.asp</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>Monthly report of air quality</source><year>2000</year><month>12</month><date-in-citation>cited 6 Feb 2004</date-in-citation><comment>availabe from URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lib.me.go.kr/imgview_detail.asp">http://lib.me.go.kr/imgview_detail.asp</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Subramaniam</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Asgharian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Freijer</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Anjilvel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of lobar differences in particle deposition in the human lung</article-title><source>Inhal Toxicol</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12476357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zangwill</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monitoring of hospital emergency room visits as a method for detecting health effects of environmental exposures</article-title><source>Sci Total Environ</source><year>1984</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6710128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sunyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anto</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Murillo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Saez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of urban air pollution on emergency room admission for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>1991</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1877586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>A Report on Yellow Sand</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>Ministry of Environment</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kweon</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytotoxicity of yellow sand in lung epithelial cells</article-title><source>J Biosci</source><year>2003</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12682428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>Annual report of ambient air quality in Korea</source><year>2000</year><date-in-citation>cited 6 Feb 2004</date-in-citation><comment>available from URL : <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lib.me.go.kr/imgview.asp">http://lib.me.go.kr/imgview.asp</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Annual mean concentration of major pollutants for Incheon and Ganghwa during the study period. <sup>*</sup>Reference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-42-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Number of study subjects</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-42-i001"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Monthly mean concentration of PM<sub>10</sub> (&#x000b5;g/m<sup>3</sup>) for Incheon and Ganghwa in 2000</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-42-i002"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>*</sup>Reference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Mean concentration of major pollutants in March and in December for the two areas</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-42-i003"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>*</sup>Statistical difference was noted for the levels of air pollutants between March and December (<italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.05). <sup>&#x02020;</sup>Statistical difference was noted for the levels of air pollutants between Incheon and Kangwha (<italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.05). <sup>&#x02021;</sup>Reference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of FEV<sub>1</sub> values between March and December for each grade and gender of the study population</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-42-i004"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Comparison of FVC values between March and December for each grade and gender of the study population</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-42-i005"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>