<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ViewNLM-v2.3.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJO</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Korean Journal of Ophthalmology : KJO</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8942</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2092-9382</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Korean Ophthalmological Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21165236</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2992565</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3341/kjo.2010.24.6.364</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Orbital Metastatic Angiosarcoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hassane</surname><given-names>Souhail</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Fouad</surname><given-names>Elasri</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Said</surname><given-names>Iferkhass</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Karim</surname><given-names>Reda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Asmae</surname><given-names>Naoumi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Houcine</surname><given-names>Chana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abdelbar</surname><given-names>Oubaaz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1">Department of Ophthalmology, Mohammed V Military Teaching Hospital, University of King Mohammed V-Souissi, Rabat, Morocco.</aff><author-notes><corresp>
Reprint requests to Elasri Fouad. Department of Ophthalmology, Mohammed V Military Teaching Hospital, University of King Mohammed V-Souissi, Rabat, Morocco. Tel: 212-661881679, <email>elasri_76@hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>1</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2010 The Korean Ophthalmological Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We report a case of a 48-year-old man who developed metastatic angiosarcoma in her left orbit. A 48-year-old man was first sent to us for a check up of proptosis of the left eye. A left orbital tumor was recognized on orbital computed tomography scans. The open biopsy showed angiosarcoma. Chest X-ray films and thoracic computed tomography showed an abnormal mass in the left inferior lung field. Angiosarcoma was confirmed by transbronchial lung biopsy. In summary, we believed that the orbital tumour was an initial symptom of the metastasis ensuing from the lung angiosarcoma.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Hemangiosarcoma</kwd><kwd>Orbital metastasis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>The first descriptions of orbital and ocular metastases were made by Horner in 1864 and Perle in 1872 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. These metastases constitute 0, 5-5, 0% of all orbital tumours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. For the majority sites responsible for these metastases, they are carcinoma, the breast and the lung are the first primary sites responsible for these metastases (breast carcinoma in woman and lung or digestive cancer in man), however, metastatic orbital tumors presenting as the first sign of disseminate cancer are a rare event [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Angiosarcomas comprise 1% of all soft tissue sarcomas, with an orbital incidence of 3% of those cases. The majority is primary angiosarcoma; only two previous case of metastatic angiosarcoma to the orbit has been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Treatment options and efficacy is not well understood.</p><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case Report</title><p>A 48-year-old man smoking for 30 years was due to a pack a day presented a one-month history of exophthalmia, chemosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) and diplopia. An ophthalmic examination shows a visual acuity as 20/20 in OD, and in 15/20 OS check pupils is normal and exophthalmometry shows 6 mm proptosis in OS. Motility examination on admission demonstrated a left oculomotor limitation in all direction, accompanied with pain and a ledger left ptosis. The fundus examination was normal. A neurological examination on admission demonstrated a left oculomotor palsy, accompanied with pain.</p><p>Computed tomography (CT) showed a left superior orbital mass causing bone destruction, was extended to brain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>), the radiologist suspected a metastasis with unknown primary site. Therefore, a more thorough systemic evaluation was started to detect primary malignancy. The immunohistologic staining of the incisional biopsy specimen showed angiosarcoma, the tumor cells were positive for factor VIII and CD31 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). The biopsy was complicated by inflammatory edema of the orbit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). A chest X-ray film completed by thoracic CT has shown an abnormal mass in the left posterior and inferior lung field (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). Angiosarcoma has been diagnosed by transbronchial lung biopsy in immunohistological study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). The left orbital tumor was thought to be a metastasis caused by the lung cancer.</p><p>The patient received radiation therapy for the metastatic orbital tumor with a total dose 2,000 cGy in 10 fractions of 200 cGy per fraction and chemotherapy (cisp1atin 100 mg/m2 IV; day 1 + etoposide 100 mg/m2; days 1-3 repeated every 4 weeks for 2 months) for the lung cancer. However, he died 3 months after initial treatment because of the progression of the primary lesion as Weil as the progressive systemic metastasis in the brain.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Angiosarcomas are malignant neoplasms derived from endothelial cells of arteries, or veins. The origin of these tumors is unknown. The metastatic orbital angiosarcomas is exceptional, we believe this is the third reported case of metastatic angiosarcoma to the orbit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p>The confirmation is done by histopathologic evaluation, when cytokeratin is negative or focally positive with vimentin reactivity, a vascular tumor should be suspected and confirmed with vascular markers, CD31, CD34, and factor VIII [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. These are the endothelial-specific immunologic markers with variable specificity and sensitivity. Factor VIII-related antigen, in spite of its high specificity, is believed to be relatively insensitive, particularly in malignant vascular tumors. CD34 was reported to be a specific and sensitive endothelial marker, but it also reacts with nonvascular soft tissue neoplasm, including epitheloid sarcoma, malignant peripheral nerve sheath tumor, leiomyosarcoma, and clear cell sarcoma. CD31 has been shown to be a highly specific and sensitive endothelial marker that reacts rarely and only weakly with nonvascular tumours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p><p>The optimal therapy for angiosarcoma is not established. Resection, radiation, or combined resection and radiation were used in treating the angiosarcoma of the cranium, complete surgical resection in other sites followed by radiation therapy results better in long-term control of disease thane surgery alone. There may be reduction in recurrence with adjuvant chemotherapy, although the most active agents are not known [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Paclitaxel appears to be highly specific in dermal angiosarcoma, but is palliative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Chemotherapy may be a useful adjunct to surgery and/or radiation therapy in the management of angiosarcoma; however, chemotherapy alone is unlikely to be curative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Nevertheless, we believe that angiosarcoma of the orbit may have a worse prognosis than angisarcoma of bones other than the cranium, because the tumour may secondarily involve the brain and the patient dies with increased intracranial pressure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], as did our case.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brush</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuetze</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sires</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Angiosarcoma metastatic to the orbit</article-title><source>Ophthal Plast Reconstr Surg</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>64</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burnstine</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Frueh</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Elner</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Angiosarcoma metastatic to the orbit</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><year>1996</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8540860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohsawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Naka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of immunohistochemical procedures in diagnosing angiosarcoma. Evaluation of 98 cases</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>1995</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>2867</fpage><lpage>2874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7773935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fata</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Reilly</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Paclitaxel in the treatment of patients with angiosarcoma of the scalp or face</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>1999</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>2034</fpage><lpage>2037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10570428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Duffau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleuridas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary spheno-orbital angiosarcoma: case report and review of the literature</article-title><source>Neurosurgery</source><year>1999</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9932897</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Left orbital proptosis with chemosis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjo-24-364-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Coronal computed tomography shows a superior orbital mass with bony destruction and brain extended.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjo-24-364-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Chest computed tomography showing a left lung tumor.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjo-24-364-g003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Orbital metastasis of bronchial angiosarcoma (H&#x00026;E, &#x000d7;200).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjo-24-364-g004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Tumoral cells are staining by factor VIII.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjo-24-364-g005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Tumoral cells are marking with CD31 factor.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjo-24-364-g006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Important leap of inflammatory oedema of the orbit after biopsy.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjo-24-364-g007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Bronchial mucosa showed lumina lined by sarcomatous cells (H&#x00026;E, &#x000d7;200).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjo-24-364-g008"/></fig></floats-group></article>