<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes Care</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">diacare</journal-id><journal-title>Diabetes Care</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0149-5992</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1935-5548</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18809628</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2584180</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">31122279</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc08-1068</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Care/Education/Nutrition/Psychosocial Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Zinc Intake and Biochemical Markers of Bone Turnover in Type 1 Diabetes </article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maser</surname><given-names>Raelene E.</given-names></name><degrees>PHD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stabley</surname><given-names>John N.</given-names></name><degrees>MS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lenhard</surname><given-names>M. James</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Owusu-Griffin</surname><given-names>Phyllis</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Provost-Craig</surname><given-names>Michelle A.</given-names></name><degrees>PHD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Farquhar</surname><given-names>William B.</given-names></name><degrees>PHD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Medical Technology, University of Delaware, Newark, Delaware</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Diabetes and Metabolic Research Center, Christiana Care Health Services, Newark, Delaware</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Health, Nutrition, and Exercise Sciences, University of Delaware, Newark, Delaware</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Corresponding author: Raelene E. Maser, <email>rmaser&#x00040;udel.edu</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>31</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2279</fpage><lpage>2280</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008, American Diabetes Association</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><p>Readers may use this article as long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, and the work is not altered. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link> for details.</p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="zdc01208002279.pdf"/><abstract><p><bold>OBJECTIVE</bold>&#x02014;To examine the relationship between Zn nutritive status and biochemical markers of bone turnover in type 1 diabetes.</p><p><bold>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</bold>&#x02014;Serum osteocalcin, urine N-telopeptides, and dietary intake data, obtained by 3-day food records, were assessed for 66 individuals with type 1 diabetes.</p><p><bold>RESULTS</bold>&#x02014;Zn intake correlated with osteocalcin in the group overall (<italic>r</italic> &#x0003d; 0.48; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) but not with N-telopeptides. Examined by sex, both Zn and osteocalcin correlated for men (<italic>r</italic> &#x0003d; 0.57; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), but the correlation did not reach statistical significance for women (<italic>r</italic> &#x0003d; 0.34; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003d; 0.09). A direct-entry linear regression model with osteocalcin as the dependent variable was performed. Duration, sex, A1C, insulin use per kilogram, total calorie intake, and Zn intake were entered as potential independent variables. The model was statistically significant (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> &#x0003d; 0.32; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01). Zn intake (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), however, was the only independent correlate of osteocalcin.</p><p><bold>CONCLUSIONS</bold>&#x02014;This study provides evidence of a positive relationship between Zn intake and osteocalcin in type 1 diabetes.</p></abstract></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn><p>Published ahead of print at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://care.diabetesjournals.org">http://care.diabetesjournals.org</ext-link> on 22 September 2008.</p><p>The costs of publication of this article were defrayed in part by the payment of page charges. This article must therefore be hereby marked &#x0201c;advertisement&#x0201d; in accordance with 18 U.S.C. Section 1734 solely to indicate this fact.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><p>Zinc is important in bone metabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r1">1</xref>). Work in cell cultures and animal models have shown stimulation of osteoblasts by Zn (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r2">2</xref>), while osteoclastic cell formation was inhibited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r3">3</xref>). Reduced Zn levels associated with decreased bone mineral content have been observed for type 1 diabetic individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r4">4</xref>). To our knowledge, there have been no studies in type 1 diabetes that examine Zn nutritive status and biochemical markers of bone turnover.</p><sec><title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title><p>Type 1 diabetic participants (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 66; mean &#x000b1; SD age 42 &#x000b1; 10 years) were evaluated in the Human Performance Laboratory, University of Delaware, Newark, Delaware. This study had the approval of the institutional review board of the University of Delaware. Individuals with possible secondary causes of osteoporosis (e.g., hyperparathyroidism) were excluded, although seven did have borderline decreased vitamin D levels but normal parathyroid hormone levels. Analysis of the data omitting these subjects produced similar results; thus, they were included in the study cohort.</p><p>Women who were in menopause were excluded from participation. Menopausal status was based on self-reported frequency of menstrual cycles.</p><p>Participants recorded their dietary intake for 3 days. Nutrient content was determined with the Food Processor Nutrition Analysis and Fitness software package (version 8.0; ESHA Research, Salem, OR).</p><p>Blood and urine samples were collected in the morning following an overnight fast. Serum osteocalcin was measured via an immunoradiometric assay. Urine N-telopeptides were determined via a Vitros ECi competitive assay on a morning spot sample.</p><p>Univariate analyses included Student's <italic>t</italic> test, the &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>test, and Pearson correlations. Linear regression was used to assess potential independent associations for markers of bone turnover (i.e., dependent variable).</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>Biomarkers of bone turnover stratified by sex are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>. Participants consumed, on average, slightly more Zn than the daily recommended dietary allowance (RDA) (11 mg/day for men and 8 mg/day for women). It should be noted, however, that approximately one-third of the individuals demonstrated values less than the RDA. Osteocalcin levels were lower for individuals with Zn intake levels below the RDA (15.9 &#x000b1; 5 &#x0005b;<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 21&#x0005d; vs. 19.6 &#x000b1; 6 ng/ml &#x0005b;<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 45&#x0005d;; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05).</p><p>Zn intake correlated with osteocalcin in the group overall (<italic>r</italic> &#x0003d; 0.48; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). When examined by sex, both Zn intake and osteocalcin levels were highly correlated for men (<italic>r</italic> &#x0003d; 0.57; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), but the correlation did not reach statistical significance for women (<italic>r</italic> &#x0003d; 0.34; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003d; 0.09). No significant correlations were observed for N-telopeptides and Zn.</p><p>A direct-entry linear regression model, with osteocalcin as the dependent variable, was performed. With duration of diabetes, sex, A1C, insulin use per kilogram, total calorie intake, and Zn entered as potential independent variables, the overall model was significant (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> &#x0003d; 0.32; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01). Zn intake (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), however, was the only independent correlate of osteocalcin, whereas sex was borderline statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003d; 0.061). A potential interaction between sex and Zn intake was investigated and found not to be significant. In sex-specific models, controlling for the other variables, Zn intake (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) was independently associated with osteocalcin for men (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> &#x0003d; 0.34 and <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 for the model) but not for women. We also examined the <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> for the model when Mg, phosphorus (P), or Ca was entered as a potential independent variable replacing Zn. No other micronutrient produced as strong an <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> for the regression model as that for Zn, and only P was independently associated with osteocalcin (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). No independent association with Zn was found when N-telopeptides were used as the dependent variable.</p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>This study indicates that Zn intake is associated with a marker of bone turnover. Although it has been shown that Zn stimulates osteoblasts and the Zinc Effects on Nutrient/nutrient Interactions and Trends in Health and ageing (ZENITH) study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r5">5</xref>) showed some, albeit inconsistent, evidence of a relationship between Zn nutritive status and bone turnover, to our knowledge this is the first study in type 1 diabetes that shows an independent association for Zn intake and osteocalcin. Our results, however, suggest that this relationship may be stronger for men than for women.</p><p>Zn plays several roles in bone metabolism. Zn stimulates bone protein synthesis and bone formation in tissue cultures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r2">2</xref>). The anabolic effect of IGF-I in osteoblasts is enhanced by Zn (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r6">6</xref>). Zn deficiency, however, impairs DNA synthesis and protein metabolism, negatively impacting bone formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r1">1</xref>). In type 1 diabetic individuals with poor glycemic control, Arreola et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r4">4</xref>) showed a significant decrease in both bone mineral content and Zn, suggesting that Zn deficiency may be a contributory factor to bone loss. Some have suggested that Zn deficiency leads to an increase in free radical production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r7">7</xref>). Oxidative stress has been shown to be an independent risk factor for osteoporosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r8">8</xref>).</p><p>Why Zn intake appears to be more strongly associated with osteocalcin for men than for women is not clear. It may be because the women in our study were not in menopause. Herzberg et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r9">9</xref>) showed that urinary discharge of Zn is increased in postmenopausal women with osteoporosis. Thus, perhaps the role of Zn in bone metabolism plays a larger role for women once they have reached menopause. It should be noted that there was no significant association of age with markers of bone turnover for either sex. No association between Zn intake and N-telopeptides was noted. Only one morning urine sample was collected for N-telopeptides, which may explain the lack of association because of a large intra-individual variability for N-telopeptides.</p><p>This study provides evidence of a relationship between Zn and a marker of bone turnover in type 1 diabetes. As for its limitations, the cross-sectional nature of the study indicates associations, and causality remains to be clarified. In addition, for 9 of 25 subjects who were taking a multivitamin, the exact Zn content of their supplement could not be determined. A common multivitamin with an average Zn, Ca, Mg, and P content was assigned to these subjects. This assignment could have attenuated the associations, potentially obscuring that between N-telopeptides and Zn intake. Multivariate analysis omitting these subjects, however, produced similar results.</p><p>Although the importance of higher levels of osteocalcin with regard to bone health is not clear, dietary factors are modifiable. Given that an inadequate intake of Zn has been reported as a risk factor for fractures in men (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">10</xref>), Zn may be important in reducing this risk in people with type 1 diabetes.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal">Ilich JZ, Kerstetter JE: Nutrition in bone health revisited: a story beyond calcium. <source>J Am Coll Nutr</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>715</fpage>&#x02013;737, <year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11194525</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal">Yamaguchi M, Hashizume M: Effect of beta-alanyl-L-histidinato zinc on protein components in osteoblastic MC3T3-El cells: increase in osteocalcin, insulin-like growth factor-I and transforming growth factor-beta. <source>Mol Cell Biochem</source> <volume>136</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>&#x02013;169, <year>1994</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7845370</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal">Kishi S, Yamaguchi M: Inhibitory effect of zinc compounds on osteoclast-like cell formation in mouse marrow cultures. <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source> <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1225</fpage>&#x02013;1230, <year>1994</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7945416</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal">Arreola F, Paniagua R, Diaz-Bensussen S, Urquieta B, L&#x000f3;pez-Monta&#x000f1;o E, Partida-Hern&#x000e1;ndez G, Villalpando S: Bone mineral content, 25-hydroxycalciferol and zinc serum levels in insulin-dependent (type I) diabetic patients. <source>Arch Invest Med (Mex)</source> <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;199, <year>1990</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2103709</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal">Hill T, Meunier N, Andriollo-Sanchez M, Ciarapica D, Hininger-Favier I, Polito A, O'Connor JM, Coudray C, Cashman KD: The relationship between the zinc nutritive status and biochemical markers of bone turnover in older European adults: The ZENITH study. <source>Eur J Clin Nutr</source> <volume>59</volume> (Suppl 2):<fpage>S73</fpage>&#x02013;S78, <year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16254587</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal">Matsui T, Yamaguchi M: Zinc modulation of insulin-like growth factor's effect in osteoblastic MC3T3-E1 cells. <source>Peptides</source> <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1063</fpage>&#x02013;1068, <year>1995</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8532589</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal">Ozturk A, Baltaci AK, Mogulkoc R, Oztekin E, Sivrikaya A, Kurtoglu E, Kul A: Effects of zinc deficiency and supplementation on malondialdehyde and glutathione levels in blood and tissues of rats performing swimming exercise. <source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source> <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;166, <year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12958407</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal">S&#x000e1;nchez-Rodr&#x000ed;guez MA, Ruiz-Ramos M, Correa-Mu&#x000f1;oz E, Mendoza-N&#x000fa;&#x000f1;ez VM: Oxidative stress as a risk factor for osteoporosis in elderly Mexicans as characterized by antioxidant enzymes. <source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>124</fpage>&#x02013;130, <year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18088440</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal">Herzberg M, Foldes J, Steinberg R, Menczel J: Zinc excretion in osteoporotic women. <source>J Bone Miner Res</source> <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;257, <year>1990</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2333784</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal">Elmst&#x000e5;hl S, Gullberg B, Janzon L, Johnell O, Elmst&#x000e5;hl B: Increased incidence of fractures in middle-aged and elderly men with low intakes of phosphorus and zinc. <source>Osteoporos Int</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;340, <year>1998</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10024903</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Bone biomarkers and Zn intake levels for the study cohort (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold> &#x0003d; 66)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom"/><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Men</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Women</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top"><italic>n</italic></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">39</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Osteocalcin (ng/ml)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">19.9 &#x000b1; 5.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">16.2 &#x000b1; 5.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">N-telopeptides (nmol/mmol)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t1fn1">&#x0002a;</xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">31.2 &#x000b1; 12.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">25.1 &#x000b1; 10.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Zn (mg)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">15.8 &#x000b1; 9.0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">14.2 &#x000b1; 7.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">NS</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Subjects below the RDA for Zn intake per day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">15 (38)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">6 (22)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">NS</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are means &#x000b1; SD or <italic>n</italic> (&#x00025;) unless otherwise indicated.</p></fn><fn id="t1fn1"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p>Units of measurement for urine N-telopeptides are nmol bone collagen equivalents/mmol creatinine. NS, nonsignificant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-wrap></article>


