<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">diabetes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">diabetes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Diabetes</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Diabetes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0012-1797</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1939-327X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19675136</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2768165</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1096</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/db08-1096</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject><subj-group><subject>Metabolism</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Paradoxical Coupling of Triglyceride Synthesis and Fatty Acid Oxidation in Skeletal Muscle Overexpressing DGAT1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Xiaojing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Cheol Soo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>Gerald I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Klaus</surname><given-names>Katherine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>K. Sreekumaran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>Gary J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yiying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>Ira J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Yi-Hao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Medicine, Preventive Medicine and Nutrition, Columbia University, New York, New York; </aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup>Departments of Internal Medicine and Cellular and Molecular Physiology, Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, Connecticut; </aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup>Endocrine Research Unit and Department of Laboratory Medicine, Mayo Clinic College of Medicine, Rochester, Minnesota; </aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup>Department of Medicine &#x00026; Neuroscience, Diabetes Research and Training Center, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, New York, New York; </aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup>Department of Pediatrics, Naomi Berrie Diabetes Center, Columbia University, New York, New York.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Yi-Hao Yu, <email>yy102@columbia.edu</email>.</corresp><fn fn-type="current-aff"><p>C.S.C. is currently affiliated with the Laboratory of Cellular &#x00026; Molecular Physiology and Metabolism, Lee Gil Ya Cancer and Diabetes Institute, Gachon University of Medicine and Science, Incheon, Korea.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>8</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>58</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2516</fpage><lpage>2524</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2009 American Diabetes Association</copyright-statement><license license-type="creative-commons"><license-p>Readers may use this article as long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, and the work is not altered. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link> for details.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="zdb01109002516.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>OBJECTIVE</title><p>Transgenic expression of diacylglycerol acyltransferase-1 (DGAT1) in skeletal muscle leads to protection against fat-induced insulin resistance despite accumulation of intramuscular triglyceride, a phenomenon similar to what is known as the &#x0201c;athlete paradox.&#x0201d; The primary objective of this study is to determine how DGAT1 affects muscle fatty acid oxidation in relation to whole-body energy metabolism and insulin sensitivity.</p></sec><sec><title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title><p>We first quantified insulin sensitivity and the relative tissue contributions to the improved whole-body insulin sensitivity in muscle creatine kisase (MCK)-DGAT1 transgenic mice by hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamps. Metabolic consequences of DGAT1 overexpression in skeletal muscles were determined by quantifying triglyceride synthesis/storage (anabolic) and fatty acid oxidation (catabolic), in conjunction with gene expression levels of representative marker genes in fatty acid metabolism. Whole-body energy metabolism including food consumption, body weights, oxygen consumption, locomotor activity, and respiration exchange ratios were determined at steady states.</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>MCK-DGAT1 mice were protected against muscle lipoptoxicity, although they remain susceptible to hepatic lipotoxicity. While augmenting triglyceride synthesis, DGAT1 overexpression also led to increased muscle mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation efficiency, as compared with wild-type muscles. On a high-fat diet, MCK-DGAT1 mice displayed higher basal metabolic rates and 5&#x02013;10% lower body weights compared with wild-type littermates, whereas food consumption was not different.</p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>DGAT1 overexpression in skeletal muscle led to parallel increases in triglyceride synthesis and fatty acid oxidation. Seemingly paradoxical, this phenomenon is characteristic of insulin-sensitive myofibers and suggests that DGAT1 plays an active role in metabolic &#x0201c;remodeling&#x0201d; of skeletal muscle coupled with insulin sensitization.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="CS100">National Institutes of Health</funding-source><award-id rid="CS100">DK-60530</award-id><award-id rid="CS100">DK-071866</award-id><award-id rid="CS100">DK-063034</award-id><award-id rid="CS100">HL-73029</award-id><award-id rid="CS100">HL45095</award-id><award-id rid="CS100">DK-020541</award-id></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Despite the observation that higher fat content in skeletal muscle is associated with insulin resistance as commonly seen in obesity and type 2 diabetes, increased muscle fat content is also associated with exercise training, in which it is &#x0201c;paradoxically&#x0201d; coupled with enhanced insulin sensitivity (the &#x0201c;athlete paradox&#x0201d;) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2"/>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). In fact, higher fat content is also seen in &#x0201c;oxidative&#x0201d; (with greater fatty acid oxidation capacity), slow-twitch type I myofibers compared with &#x0201c;glycolytic,&#x0201d; fast-twitch type II myofibers. Interestingly, type I myofibers appear to be inherently more insulin sensitive than type II myofibers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). In human skeletal muscle, insulin-stimulated glucose transport directly correlates with the percentage of oxidative type I myofibers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6"/>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). Furthermore, exercise enhances muscle insulin sensitivity and is associated with increased muscle fat content and/or mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation capacity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). In contrast, a decrease in oxidative, and conversely an increase in glycolytic, capacity is characteristic of skeletal muscle seen in sedentary obese individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>).</p><p>Exercise increases myocytic diacylglycerol acyltransferase (DGAT) activity, and transgenic overexpression of DGAT1 in skeletal muscle in mice is sufficient to replicate the exercise paradox characterized by increased muscle fat content coupled with increased muscle insulin sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Exercise also increases skeletal muscle DGAT1 expression and improves insulin sensitivity in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). DGAT1 catalyzes the last step of triglyceride synthesis from diacylglyerol (DAG) and fatty acyl-CoA. By channeling fatty acid substrates into the triglyceride synthesis pathway, DGAT1 effectively decreases levels of muscle DAG and ceramide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>), two fatty acid derivatives that are believed to be causative in the development of obesity-related insulin resistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16"/>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). In sedentary humans or rodents with fat-induced insulin resistance, higher muscle triglyceride content is also associated with elevated myocytic DAG and/or ceramide levels as a result of fatty acid overload (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>); lipid metabolites and storage products are both increased in this substrate-driven process. Increased fatty acid load and consequent increases in intramyocellular fatty acid metabolites are lipotoxic and cause muscle insulin resistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Increased myocytic DAG, for example, causes insulin resistance via activation of protein kinase C&#x003b8; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>) leading to serine phosphorylation of insulin receptor substrate (IRS)-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). Thus, while increased DAG is causal, high myocytic triglyceride-content is not always a marker for muscle insulin resistance, as long as lipotoxic fatty acid metabolites are kept at low levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>).</p><p>Given the parallel increases in both muscle triglyceride stores and fatty acid oxidation activity as exemplified by oxidative type I myofibers or the exercise-trained muscle model, we hypothesized that triglyceride synthesis and fatty acid oxidation capacities are intrinsically interconnected and both are upregulated in insulin-sensitive muscles. The present study demonstrates upregulation of both triglyceride synthesis and fatty acid oxidation capacities in the insulin-sensitive, DGAT1 overexpressing muscle model. This study also suggests that DGAT1 overexpression is a cause of such a &#x0201c;paradoxical&#x0201d; change in fat metabolism. We postulate that this coordinated change enables the myocytes to keep the intracellular levels of fatty acid metabolites below a potentially lipotoxic level. By channeling lipotoxic fatty acid metabolites into storage (as triglyceride) and into a pathway for terminal oxidation, such a change may lessen fatty acid&#x02013;induced insulin resistance that is often associated with acquired obesity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>).</p><sec><title>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Mice, diets, and exercise.</title><p>MCK-DGAT1 transgenic mice and wild-type littermates were fed standard rodent diet or high-fat diet (HFD) as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). The swimming exercise regimen was the same as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Male mice were used in this study. Animal protocols were approved by the Columbia University Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee.</p></sec><sec><title>Hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamps.</title><p>Three-month-old mice were fed HFD or standard rodent diet for 8 weeks before the clamp study. The clamp was conducted in awake mice as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). All procedures were approved by the Yale University Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee. Briefly, after an overnight fast, [3-<sup>3</sup>H]-glucose (high-performance liquid chromatography purified; Perkinelmer) was infused at 0.05 &#x003bc;Ci/min for 2 h to assess the basal glucose turnover. Hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp was conducted for 120 min with primed/continuous infusion of human insulin (Novo Nordisk; 105 pmol/kg prime, 15 pmol &#x000b7; kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> &#x000b7; min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> infusion), keeping plasma glucose at &#x0223c;6.7 mmol/l (basal level). [3-<sup>3</sup>H]-glucose was infused at 0.1 &#x003bc;Ci/min throughout the clamp to estimate insulin-stimulated whole-body glucose fluxes. Calculations of hepatic glucose output (HGO), whole-body glycolysis, and whole-body glycogen synthesis were also as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). To assess muscle glucose uptake, separate groups of mice were clamped and 2-deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-[1-<sup>14</sup>C]glucose (2-[<sup>14</sup>C]DG; Perkinelmer) was injected as a bolus at the 75th min of the clamp as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation.</title><p>Four-month-old mice pretreated with HFD for 8 weeks were used for these experiments. Mitochondria were isolated from muscle tissues using Mitochondria Isolation Kits (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation was performed by measuring the rate of <sup>3</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O production from the substrate [<sup>3</sup>H]palmitate present in excess (final concentrations: 0.2 mmol/l palmitate with 10 &#x003bc;Ci/ml of 9,10(n)-[<sup>3</sup>H]palmitate and 1.25% BSA) in a mitochondria incubation medium (containing 20 &#x003bc;g mitochondria protein) as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Mitochondrial DNA copy number, ATP production rate, citrate synthase, &#x003b2;-hydroxyacyl-CoA dehydrogenase, and carnitine palmitoyl transferase I activities.</title><p>Four-month-old mice pretreated with HFD for 8 weeks were used for these experiments. Mitochondrial DNA copy number was measured using quantitative real-time PCR as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). Mitochondrial DNA for NADH dehydrogenases 1 and 4 (ND1 and ND4) and nuclear DNA for &#x003b2;-actin were coamplified within the same reaction wells (for primer sequences, see supplemental Table 1, available in an online appendix at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/cgi/content/full/db08-1096/DC1">http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/cgi/content/full/db08-1096/DC1</ext-link>). Mitochondrial ATP production rates were measured in isolated mitochondria through time-course monitoring of bioluminescence in response to a luciferin-luciferase ATP-monitoring reagent (Biotherma, Haninge, Sweden) as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Maximal activity of citrate synthase was measured in muscle homogenates by photospectrometry as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). &#x003b2;-hydroxyacyl CoA dehydrogenase (HAD) activity was also measured in muscle homogenates by following spectrophotometrically the conversion of acetoacetyl-CoA to &#x003b2;-hydroxybutyryl-CoA by &#x003b2;-HAD as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). Total carnitine palmitoyl transferase (CPT) activity was assayed radiochemically in isolated mitochondria by following the conversion of palmitoyl-<sc>l</sc>-carnitine from palmitoyl-CoA and radiolabeled <sc>l</sc>-carnitine as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). CPT-I activity was calculated from the total CPT activity after subtraction of CPT-II activity, which was measured in the presence of 0.2 mmol/l malonyl-CoA that inhibits CPT-I.</p></sec><sec><title>Transmission electron microscopy.</title><p>Four-month-old mice pretreated with HFD for 8 weeks were used. Muscles were isolated, fixed with 2.5% glutaraldehyde in 0.1M Sorenson's buffer (PH 7.2), and treated with 1% OsO4 also in Sorenson's buffer for 1 h. After dehydration and embedment in Lx-112 (Ladd Research Industries), thin sections (60 nm) were cut using a MT-7000 ultramicrotome, stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate, and examined under a JEOL JEM-1200 EXII electron microscope. Pictures were captured by an ORCA-HR digital camera (Hamamatsu) and recorded with an AMT Image Capture Engine.</p></sec><sec><title>Indirect calorimetry.</title><p>Twenty-week-old weight-matched male MCK-DGAT1 mice and wild-type littermates that had been on a HFD for 8 weeks were singly housed in metabolic chambers. After 2&#x02013;4 days of adaptation, oxygen consumption, locomotor activity, and respiration exchange ratio were measured continuously over at least 5 days during 12:12 light-dark cycles, using a CLAMS (Columbus Instruments, Columbus, OH) open-circuit indirect calorimetry system as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>RT-PCR, Western blot, DGAT activity, and triglyceride contents.</title><p>Four-month-old mice with 8-week HFD pretreatment were used for these experiments. RT-PCR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>) and Western blot (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>) were as described. Gene-specific primer sets are listed in supplemental Table 1. Primary antibodies to pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase (PDK)4, uncoupling protein (UCP)-3, CD36, and GAPDH (glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase) were obtained from Abcam (Cambridge, MA). DGAT activity was measured in vitro using [<sup>14</sup>C]-labeled palmitoyl-CoA as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>). The method to quantify muscle triglyceride content was as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis.</title><p>Statistical differences were first analyzed by ANOVA to determine overall treatment effects (genotype or exercise), followed by post hoc comparisons between concerned study groups (Statistica V6.0, StatSoft, OK). A two-tailed <italic>P</italic> value of &#x0003c;0.05 was used to indicate statistical significance. For indirect calorimetry measurements, ANOVA repeated measures (Prism, GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA) were used. Post hoc analyses were conducted using Tukey post hoc or Bonferroni comparisons. Data are expressed as means &#x000b1; SE.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>MCK-DGAT1 transgenic mice demonstrate improved resistance to diet-induced lipotoxicity, but they remain susceptible to hepatic insulin resistance on HFD.</title><p>Using glucose tolerance and insulin tolerance tests, we showed previously that MCK-DGAT1 mice were protected against HFD-induced insulin resistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Ex vivo 2-deoxyglucose uptake in skeletal muscles isolated from HFD-fed animals demonstrated that insulin sensitivity was greater in DGAT1-overexpressing muscles than in the wild-type muscles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). In this study, whole-body and tissue insulin sensitivities were assessed in vivo by hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamps in combination with radioisotope-labeled glucose infusions. Three-month-old male MCK-DGAT1 and wild-type mice were fed HFD for 8 weeks (WT-HF and DGAT1-HF, respectively) before the clamp study. Age- and sex-matched wild-type mice on standard rodent diet (WT-NC) were used as baseline control. The major findings are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, and other energetic and clamp parameters are summarized in supplemental Table 2. As expected, WT-HF mice showed marked insulin resistance with the mean whole-body glucose infusion rate at only &#x0223c;16 mg &#x000b7; kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> &#x000b7; min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>). DGAT1-HF mice were more insulin sensitive than WT-HF mice, achieving a mean whole-body glucose infusion rate of &#x0223c;29 mg &#x000b7; kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> &#x000b7; min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>). However, the baseline whole-body glucose infusion rate in the control WT-NC mice was &#x0223c;45 mg &#x000b7; kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> &#x000b7; min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>A</italic>), indicating that DGAT1 overexpression provided &#x0223c;45% protection against HFD-induced insulin resistance. Transgenic mice were not protected from HFD-induced hepatic insulin resistance. Compared with a &#x0003e;50% suppression of HGO in WT-NC mice during the clamping, insulin-mediated suppression of HGO was completely absent in both WT-HF and DGAT1-HF mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>B</italic>). To directly assess muscle insulin sensitivity under the same clamping conditions, a bolus infusion of 2-deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-[1-<sup>14</sup>C]glucose was given. Uptake of 2-deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-[1-<sup>14</sup>C]glucose in skeletal muscle was &#x0223c;30% greater in DGAT1-HF mice than in WT-HF mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>C</italic>), confirming that increased lipotoxicity tolerance in skeletal muscle was the physiological basis for the protection of MCK-DGAT1 mice, albeit incomplete, against HFD-induced whole-body insulin resistance.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIG. 1.</label><caption><p>Whole-body, hepatic, and muscle insulin sensitivity assessed by hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp. <bold><italic>A</italic></bold>: Steady-state whole-body glucose infusion rates in age-, sex-, genetic background&#x02013;, and breeding environment&#x02013;matched wild-type mice on standard rat diet (WT-NC), wild-type mice pretreated with ad lib HFD feeding for 8 weeks (WT-HF), and MCK-DGAT1 mice pretreated with ad lib HFD feeding for 8 weeks (DGAT1-HF). <bold><italic>B</italic></bold>: Steady-state HGO before (basal HGO) and after (clamp HGO) insulin infusion at the rate of 3 mU &#x000b7; kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> &#x000b7; min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in WT-NC, WT-HF, and DGAT1-HF mice under the same clamp conditions as in <bold><italic>A</italic></bold>. <bold><italic>C</italic></bold>: 2-Deoxyglucose uptake in skeletal muscle after bolus injection of the [<sup>14</sup>C]-labeled 2-deoxyglucose under the same clamp conditions as in <bold><italic>A</italic></bold> and <bold><italic>B</italic></bold>. Data are presented as means &#x000b1; SE; <bold><italic>P</italic></bold> and <bold><italic>n</italic></bold> are as indicated; *<bold><italic>P</italic></bold> &#x0003c; 0.05. 2-DG, 2-deoxyglucose.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zdb0110958980001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>DGAT1 overexpression in skeletal muscle leads to improved mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation efficiency as well as increased triglyceride synthesis and storage.</title><p>As expected, muscle DGAT activity was threefold increased in MCK-DGAT1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>A</italic>), which was associated with a &#x0223c;70% increase in muscle triglyceride content (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>B</italic>). To characterize skeletal muscle fatty acid oxidation capacity, we first determined mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) copy number by assessing the ratio of mtDNA ND1 and ND4 to the nuclear DNA &#x003b2;-actin gene in soleus and anterior tibial muscles. There were 30&#x02013;45% fewer mitochondria per copy genome DNA in DGAT1-overexpressing tibial and soleus muscles than those of the wild-type controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>C</italic>). However, analyses of mitochondrial ATP production rates (MAPR) per unit muscle protein revealed no reduction in transgenic mice as compared with wild-type mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>D</italic>). Maximal tissue citrate synthase activity was significantly greater in the DGAT1-overexpressing soleus muscle than the wild-type counterpart was, although no significant difference was detected in tibialis anterior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>D</italic>). Maximal tissue &#x003b2;-HAD activity per unit muscle protein was significantly greater in the transgenic muscle than the wild-type muscle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>E</italic>). Similarly, mitochondrial CPT-I activity per unit mitochondrial protein was significantly greater in the DGAT1-overexpressing muscle than the wild-type muscle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>E</italic>). The unchanged or potentially enhanced mitochondrial oxidative capacity in the presence of fewer mitochondria suggested a higher mitochondrial efficiency in DGAT1-overexpressing muscles. Direct examination of soleus muscles by electron microscopy confirmed that fewer, but bigger, mitochondria were present in the DGAT1-overexpressing muscle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>F</italic>) than in the wild-type muscle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>G</italic>). Additionally, in vitro measurement of maximal fatty acid oxidation rates demonstrated a 20% increase in fatty acid oxidation capacity in the MCK-DGAT1 muscle compared with the wild-type muscle (1,217 vs. 1,019 nmol &#x000b7; min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> &#x000b7; g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mitochondrial protein, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>H</italic>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIG. 2.</label><caption><p>Assessment of anabolic and catabolic fatty acid metabolism in skeletal muscle of MCK-DGAT1 and control wild-type mice. Male mice pretreated with 8-week HFD as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>. <bold><italic>A</italic></bold>: DGAT activity in soleus muscles isolated from the 4-month-old wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold> = 4, each group). <bold><italic>B</italic></bold>: Triglyceride content in soleus muscle from the wild-type (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold> = 5) and MCK-DGAT1 (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold> = 6) mice. <bold><italic>C</italic></bold>: Mitochondrial copy numbers as determined by PCR quantification of ND1 or ND4 as mitochondrial DNA (using &#x003b2;-actin as reference for nuclear DNA) in anterior tibial and soleus muscles of the wild-type (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold> = 7) and MCK-DGAT1 (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold> = 6) mice. <bold><italic>D</italic></bold>: MAPR (determined in isolated mitochondria) and citrate synthase activity (measured in muscle homogenates) of the anterior tibial and soleus muscles from the wild-type (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold> = 7) and MCK-DGAT1 (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold> = 6) mice. <bold><italic>E</italic></bold>: &#x003b2;-HAD activity (measured in muscle homogenates) and CPT-I activity (measured in isolated mitochondria) of the soleus muscles from the wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold> = 6, each group). <bold><italic>F</italic></bold> and <bold><italic>G</italic></bold>: Representative low- and high-power (<bold><italic>inserts</italic></bold>) views of the electron microscopic fields of the soleus muscle from the wild-type (<bold><italic>F</italic></bold>) and MCK-DGAT1 (<bold><italic>G</italic></bold>) mice. Quantification of 6000&#x000d7; EM micrographs using an image analysis system (Imagine-Pro Plus 5.0, Media Cybernetics) showed that wild-type and DGAT1 mice have 149 &#x000b1; 3.6 and 98 &#x000b1; 7.7 mitochondria per 10 &#x000d7; 10 micron muscle area, respectively (<bold><italic>P</italic></bold> &#x0003c; 0.001). The average mitochondrial size is 34,432 &#x000b1; 4,246 pixels for wild-type and 62,418 &#x000b1; 938 pixels for DGAT1 mice (<bold><italic>P</italic></bold> = 0.014). <bold><italic>H</italic></bold>: Maximal mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation rates measured in isolated mitochondria of the soleus muscles from the wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold> = 6, each group). Values are expressed as means &#x000b1; SE; NS, no statistical significance (<bold><italic>P</italic></bold> &#x0003e; 0.05); *<bold><italic>P</italic></bold> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<bold><italic>P</italic></bold> &#x0003c; 0.01 (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold> as indicated). CS, citrate synthase; FA, fatty acid; 28S, 28S rRNA; TG, triglyceride; WT, wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zdb0110958980002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Upregulation of PDK4 and UCP3 in skeletal muscle of MCK-DGAT1 transgenic mice.</title><p>mRNA levels of marker genes in fat metabolism were examined by real-time PCR in soleus muscle from 4-month-old male wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 transgenic mice after 8-week HFD feeding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>A</italic>). DGAT1 mRNA levels were approximately threefold as high in MCK-DGAT1 mice as in wild-type mice (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) as expected, and mRNA levels for PDK4 and UCP3 were doubled in MCK-DGAT1 compared with wild-type mice (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). There was also a trend of approximate doubling of mRNA levels for CD36 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.051), CPT1 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.120), ACC2 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.072), and GLUT4 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.117) in MCK-DGAT1 mice. No significant changes were detected in mRNA levels for DGAT2, fatty acids, ACS1, ADRP, sterol regulatory element&#x02013;binding protein-1c, peroxisome proliferator&#x02013;activated receptor (PPAR)-&#x003b1;, PPAR&#x003b4;, PPAR&#x003b3;, peroxisome proliferator&#x02013;activated receptor &#x003b3; coactivator-&#x003b2;, CRAT, ECHS1, UCP1, UCP2, and PEPCK.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIG. 3.</label><caption><p>Effects of DGAT1 overexpression and exercise on relative levels of gene expression in soleus muscle. <bold><italic>A</italic></bold>: Gene expression levels were measured by RT-PCR in soleus muscles isolated from wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice pretreated with 8-week HFD as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, using primer sets listed in suppl. Table 1. Gene abbreviations are the same as listed in suppl. Table 1. *<bold><italic>P</italic></bold> &#x0003c; 0.05 (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold> = 5&#x02013;7 in each group). <bold><italic>B</italic></bold>: Relative gene expression levels of PDK4 in soleus muscles from HFD-pretreated wild-type versus MCK-DGAT1 mice. <bold><italic>C</italic></bold>: Relative gene expression levels of PDK4 in soleus muscles from sedentary (Sed) versus exercised (Exe) wild-type mice. The swimming exercise regimen is as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>); <bold><italic>P</italic></bold> values and <bold><italic>n</italic></bold> are as indicated. <bold><italic>D</italic></bold>: Western blot analysis of CD36, UCP3, and PDK4 in soleus muscle from the 8-week HFD&#x02013;pretreated wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice. WT, wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zdb0110958980003"/></fig><p>PDK4 is believed to play a critical role in regulating the fuel partitioning between fat and glucose oxidation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). To further understand the changes in PDK4 expression in MCK-DGAT1 muscles, we compared a group of DGAT1-overexpressing mice with a group of wild-type mice after 1-week swimming exercise (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Using sedentary wild-type mice as a baseline control, both DGAT1 overexpression and exercise led to &#x0223c;1.5-fold increases (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) in PDK4 mRNA levels in skeletal muscle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic>), providing two independent cases in which upregulation of PDK4 mRNA expression was dissociated from glucose intolerance. Western blot of CD36, UCP3, and PDK4 showed 1.4- to 1.8-fold increases of these proteins in DGAT1-overexpressing muscle relative to wild-type muscle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>D</italic>).</p></sec><sec><title>MCK-DGAT1 mice display increased energy expenditure without changes in food intake.</title><p>To determine the physiological significance of the above in vitro findings and to help interpret the physiological consequences of the increased triglyceride synthesis and increased mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation capacity (and higher expression levels of the uncoupling protein UCP3) in DGAT1-overexpressing skeletal muscle, we measured whole-body energy metabolism in vivo. Four-month-old weight- and adiposity-matched (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>A</italic>) male MCK-DGAT1 and wild-type mice were analyzed in metabolic chambers after 8-week HFD feeding. MCK-DGAT1 mice appeared less physically active than wild-type mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>B</italic>), although the changes seemed to be unrelated to food-seeking behavior, as food intake was the same between MCK-DGAT1 and wild-type mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>G</italic>). In contrast to the changes in physical activity, oxygen consumption rates were significantly higher in the transgenic mice than in wild-type mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>C</italic>, wild-type vs. MCK-DGAT1, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, repeated-measures ANOVA). No significant difference was detected in respiration exchange rates (RER) under these conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>D</italic>). Further experimental maneuver with two consecutive 24-h measurements of V<sc>o</sc><sub>2</sub> during fasting followed by refeeding revealed that the difference in energy expenditure was accentuated during refeeding. As expected, energy expenditure reduced and increased in response to prolonged fast and refeeding, respectively, in both wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>E</italic>). However, the increase during refeeding was markedly greater in the transgenic mice than in wild-type mice (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, repeated-measures ANOVA) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>F</italic>). As was during regular ad lib feeding, no difference in food intake was observed during the 24-h refeeding period between MCK-DGAT1 and wild-type mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>G</italic>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIG. 4.</label><caption><p>Physical activity and whole-body oxygen consumption. Two-month-old male wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice were treated with 8-week HFD as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> before indirect calorimetry study. Weight-matched mice were used in this study to avoid the need to correct for differences in weight and body composition across the groups (wild-type vs. MCK-DGAT1 mice). <bold><italic>A</italic></bold>: Body composition by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). <bold><italic>B.</italic></bold> locomotor activity. <bold><italic>C</italic></bold>: Twenty-four hour oxygen consumption (V<sc>o</sc><sub>2</sub>). <bold><italic>D</italic></bold>: RER, the above were measured during the study period while the mice had ad lib access to HFD. In a separate experiment, V<sc>o</sc><sub>2</sub> was measured in the same wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice during a 24-h fasting period (<bold><italic>E</italic></bold>), followed by a 24-h period of ad lib refeeding (<bold><italic>F</italic></bold>). Food intake during the 24-h period of ad lib feeding and during the 24-h refeeding period were also measured (<bold><italic>G</italic></bold>). Data are expressed as means &#x000b1; SE; <bold><italic>P</italic></bold> values are as indicated or denoted by &#x0201c;NS&#x0201d; for no statistical significance or **<bold><italic>P</italic></bold> &#x0003c; 0.01. WT, wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zdb0110958980004"/></fig><p>Long-term food intake was followed in mice fed a standard rodent diet (total 11 weeks) or a HFD (total 8 weeks), starting at 2 months of age. Periodic fluctuations in food intake were observed in both transgenic and wild-type mice, more so in standard rodent diet&#x02013;fed mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>A</italic>). However, no difference was found between the two genotypes either on standard rodent diet or on HFD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>). A small but significant body weight difference (5&#x02013;10%) was found between wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice on HFD, which became evident after 5 weeks of HFD feeding and persisted throughout the remaining study period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>C</italic>). In the absence of reduced food intake or increased physical activities, this finding indicates that metabolic energy expenditure in DGAT1-HF mice was higher than that of the WT-HF mice. No differences in weight were observed between wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice on standard rodent diet (data not shown).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>FIG. 5.</label><caption><p>Food consumption and growth curves. Food intake per day was averaged weekly and plotted over time in separate groups of age-matched male wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice either on standard rat diet (<bold><italic>A</italic></bold>) or on HFD (<bold><italic>B</italic></bold>) starting at age of 2 months. The growth curve is plotted using weekly measured body weights in wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice on HFD for 10 weeks starting at age of 2 months (<bold><italic>C</italic></bold>). <bold><italic>P</italic></bold> values are denoted by &#x0201c;NS&#x0201d; for no statistical significance, *<bold><italic>P</italic></bold> &#x0003c; 0.05, and **<bold><italic>P</italic></bold> &#x0003c; 0.01 (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold> as indicated). WT, wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zdb0110958980005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this study, we first demonstrated in vivo that although skeletal muscle of MCK-DGAT1 mice was more resistant to developing HFD-induced lipotoxicity, their liver was as susceptible for lipotoxic insulin resistance as that of wild-type mice. Under hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp conditions, MCK-DGAT1 mice were &#x0223c;45% protected against HFD-induced insulin resistance at the whole-body level compared with wild-type mice. The greater whole-body insulin sensitivity in HFD-fed MCK-DGAT1 mice (compared to HFD-fed wild-type mice) was associated with &#x0223c;30% higher uptake of bolus-injected 2-deoxyglucose in skeletal muscle under the same feeding and clamp conditions, whereas insulin suppression of HGO was similarly impaired in these mice, indicating that liver did not contribute to the improved whole-body insulin sensitivity.</p><p>We showed that although triglyceride synthesis and storage capacities were increased in DGAT1-overexpressing muscle, mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation efficiency was also improved. The latter was initially recognized by decreased mitochondrial copy number in combination with the uncompromised muscle citrate synthase activity and increased maximal &#x003b2;-HAD and CPT-I activities in DGAT1-overexpressing muscles. This was then confirmed by increased maximal mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation capacity per unit mitochondrial protein in DGAT1-overexpressing muscles. Interestingly, MAPR per unit mitochondrial proteins was similar in the two genotypes, suggesting that the increased fatty acid oxidation efficiency does not lead to increased energy efficiency. Gene expression levels of muscle PDK4 and UCP3, normalized to &#x003b2;-actin expression levels, were &#x0223c;100% greater in HFD-fed MCK-DGAT1 mice than in age-, sex-, and diet-matched wild-type mice. Although increased PDK4 has been associated with greater fuel partition into fatty acid oxidation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>), higher levels of UCP3 may also signify increased use of fat as fuel substrate and/or conversion of fat to thermal energy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). It is plausible that the lack of increase in MAPR in DGAT1-overexpressing muscle, in the presence of increased fatty acid oxidation rates, is because of increased uncoupling of oxidative phosphorylation leading to increased heat production. Although heat production was not directly measured, whole-body 24-h V<sc>o</sc><sub>2</sub> production rates were greater in DGAT1-HF than in WT-HF mice in the absence of increased physical activity in the former. The increased energy expenditure in MCK-DGAT1 mice was further substantiated by the modest but significant lower body weight in the transgenic mice relative to wild-type mice without any difference in energy intake; long-term follow-up of the growth curve showed that MCK-DGAT1 mice weighed 5&#x02013;10% less than wild-type mice on an at lib HFD feeding regimen, whereas food consumption was the same in both groups. The reduced body weight may contribute to the improved insulin sensitivity shown in this study. However, the small weight difference appears to result from changed fuel metabolism and is unlikely a primary cause of the observed protection against lipotoxicity. Marked differences in insulin sensitivity were seen between &#x0201c;weight-matched&#x0201d; wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice and between isolated DGAT1 muscle and wild-type muscle in ex vivo experiments, where weight was not a factor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>).</p><p>Insulin resistance is associated with mitochondrial dysfunction in type 2 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>) and in the offspring of parents with type 2 diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). Reduced mitochondrial function and insulin resistance occur in aging in association with reduced mitochondrial DNA copy number (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). However, the issue regarding mitochondrial deficiency and insulin resistance is unresolved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). The present study does not support the hypothesis that reduction in mitochondrial DNA copy number per se results in insulin resistance. In our model, despite a reduction in mitochondrial number, mitochondrial ATP production is maintained (and heat production probably increased) because of increased fatty acid oxidation efficiency. These findings suggest that mitochondrial quality is more critical. In this regard, a recent study by Koves et al. demonstrated that stressed mitochondria with greater but incomplete fatty acid oxidation are only detrimental to insulin sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). The present study further suggests that greater fatty acid oxidation capacity associated with increased uncoupling activity may also be important in maintaining insulin sensitivity. Of course, maintaining adequate oxidative phosphorylation is necessary for muscle contractility, particularly during exercise.</p><p>We have previously shown that skeletal muscle overexpressing DGAT1 behaved similarly to exercise-trained muscle in that it had higher triglyceride content but was more insulin sensitive, a phenomenon referred to as the &#x0201c;athlete paradox&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;exercise paradox.&#x0201d; The decreased myocytic DAG and ceramide levels with increased myocytic triglyceride content are the expected effects of DGAT1 actions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). By converting fatty acyl-CoA and DAG to triglyceride, DGAT1 is believed to be directly responsible for lowering the levels of the lipotoxic fatty acid derivatives. The key finding of the present study is that DGAT1-overexpressing muscle, like exercised muscle, had increased fatty acid oxidation capacity, which was associated with increased steady-state metabolic rates at the whole body level and a smaller HFD-induced weight gain compared with wild-type mice. Importantly, because these findings are made in the muscle-specific DGAT1 transgenic mice, DGAT1 overexpression must be primarily responsible for these paradoxical changes. Because increased DGAT1 expression is also observed with exercise, we further postulate that DGAT1 may play a key mediatory role in exercise-induced augmentation of both triglyceride synthesis and, indirectly, mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation. Together, the increased anabolic (triglyceride synthesis/storage) and catabolic (fatty acid oxidation/degradation) capacities may both help remove fatty acid intermediates that can be overproduced during fatty acid overload. Reducing intramyocellular DAG levels to below the &#x0201c;threshold of lipotoxicity&#x0201d; is believed necessary to prevent the induction of a cascade of signaling events including activation of PKC isoforms and Jun NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal kinase-1 and inhibition of IRS-1, Akt, and GLUT4 in HFD-fed mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>).</p><p>Parallel upregulated triglyceride synthesis and fatty acid oxidation seemed perplexing at the first glance because anabolic and catabolic pathways usually undergo changes in the opposite directions, determined by cellular substrate levels and energy status. However, examination of typical myofibers does show interdependency between the two aspects of fatty acid metabolism: myofibers that have a high triglyceride content are typically the &#x0201c;oxidative&#x0201d; type characterized by a high mitochondrial capacity, whereas those with low triglyceride content (and high glycogen content) are typically &#x0201c;glycolytic.&#x0201d; Importantly, compared with glycolytic myofibers, oxidative myofibers with greater capacities for triglyceride synthesis and fatty acid oxidation appear to be intrinsically more insulin sensitive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). The present study provided an example of the &#x0201c;paradoxical&#x0201d; coupling of lipid synthesis and oxidation in the DGAT1-overexpressing muscles.</p><p>Clearly, these are not the usual reciprocal regulations of the two aspects of the fatty acid metabolism driven by the fatty acid substrate availability. DGAT1 overexpression in skeletal muscle increased the capacities of both triglyceride synthesis and fatty acid oxidation and enabled the myocytes to endure fat overload without developing significant lipotoxicity or insulin resistance. However, instead of increasing mitochondrial densities, DGAT1-overexpressing muscle appeared to have greater mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation efficiency. Whether the improved fatty acid oxidation is coupled with increased fatty acid transport (as suggested by upregulation of CD36 and CPT-I) and/or potentially increased de novo fatty acid synthesis will require further investigation. A &#x0201c;futile cycle&#x0201d; of fatty acid metabolism that consists of increased fatty acid oxidation coupled with increased de novo fatty acid synthesis has been proposed as a thermogenic mechanism in muscle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>).</p><p>PDK is a key regulator of fuel partitioning between fatty acid and glucose oxidation, and PDK4 is the major isoform in muscle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>). PDK is acutely regulated, in general, by small molecular effectors generated from fatty acid &#x003b2; oxidation. Gene expression of PDK4 also responds to fuel substrate availability and insulin levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45"/>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>). Additionally, PDK4 gene expression appears to be modulated by several more complex biological processes, such as insulin resistance or exercise. Insulin resistance is generally associated with upregulation of PDK4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>), which may be because of elevated fatty acid overload (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>) or deficient/impaired insulin action (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>). While promoting muscle insulin sensitivity, exercise also &#x0201c;paradoxically&#x0201d; upregulates PDK4 gene expression in skeletal muscle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>). Therefore, it appears that a different mechanism for upregulating PDK4 is involved in exercise-trained skeletal muscle and that this mechanism is not substrate driven (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>). Exercise upregulates PDK4 and fatty acid oxidation but does not inhibit insulin-stimulated glucose oxidation. In the present study, we showed that DGAT1 overexpression produced a result similar to exercise with regard to PDK4 upregulation, increased fatty acid oxidation, and insulin sensitivity, suggesting that the change in PDK4 expression in this model is also not a secondary response to reduced insulin actions. It is currently unclear, in either the exercise model or the DGAT1-overexpression model, what mediates upregulation of PDK4 gene expression and whether increased mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation is directly caused by upregulated PDK4.</p><p>In summary, transgenic expression of DGAT1 in skeletal muscle results in a series of &#x0201c;paradoxical&#x0201d; metabolic changes often seen in the exercise-trained muscle, including increased triglyceride synthesis, increased fatty acid oxidation, and preserved insulin sensitivity during the challenging of fat overload. Although a high triglyceride content and PDK4 expression level may serve as markers of insulin resistance in sedentary and obese individuals, the same parameters may reflect a greater capacity for fat metabolism. In the latter situation, insulin sensitivity is preserved because of reduced levels of intracellular fatty acid derivatives. Because DGAT1 is induced in exercise, and because the MCK-DGAT1 model presents a set of metabolic features similar to the exercise model, we hypothesize that DGAT1 mediates a significant part of exercise-induced metabolic remodeling in skeletal muscle.</p></sec>
      <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
         <title>Supplementary Material</title>
         <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
            <caption>
               <title>Online-Only Appendix</title>
            </caption>
            <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_58_11_2516__index.html"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
                   xlink:href="supp_db08-1096_db08-1096_Online_Appendix.doc"/>
         </supplementary-material>
      </sec>
   </body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>The costs of publication of this article were defrayed in part by the payment of page charges. This article must therefore be hereby marked &#x0201c;advertisement&#x0201d; in accordance with 18 U.S.C. Section 1734 solely to indicate this fact.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This study was supported by National Institutes of Health (NIH) Grants DK-60530, DK-071866, DK-063034, HL-73029, and HL45095. Contributions also came from New York Obesity Research Center Grant DK-026687 and Albert Einstein College of Medicine Diabetes Research and Training Center Grant NIH DK-020541.</p><p>No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodpaster</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Skeletal muscle lipid content and insulin resistance: evidence for a paradox in endurance-trained athletes</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>5755</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11739435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Lipotoxicity: the obese and endurance-trained paradox</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>S66</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15592489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Upregulation of myocellular DGAT1 augments triglyceride synthesis in skeletal muscle and protects against fat-induced insulin resistance</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>1679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17510710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bassel-Duby</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Signaling pathways in skeletal muscle remodeling</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16756483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simoneau</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Colberg</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaete</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Skeletal muscle glycolytic and oxidative enzyme capacities are determinants of insulin sensitivity and muscle composition in obese women</article-title>. <source>Faseb J</source><year>1995</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7781930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simoneau</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Altered glycolytic and oxidative capacities of skeletal muscle contribute to insulin resistance in NIDDM</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol</source><year>1997</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>166</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9216960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation changes in the life span. Molecular aspects and physiopathological implications</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>1996</year>;<volume>1276</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8816944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Thrush</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mertz</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezaire</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chabowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Heigenhauser</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyck</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Endurance training in obese humans improves glucose tolerance and mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation and alters muscle lipid content</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>291</volume>:<fpage>E99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16464906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Short</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vittone</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigelow</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizza</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Coenen-Schimke</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Impact of aerobic exercise training on age-related changes in insulin sensitivity and muscle oxidative capacity</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>1888</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1896</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12882902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Houmard</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pories</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Israel</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohm</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Skeletal muscle fiber composition is related to adiposity and in vitro glucose transport rate in humans</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1995</year>;<volume>268</volume>:<fpage>E453</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7900793</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barakat</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohm</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pories</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Houmard</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Muscle fiber type is associated with obesity and weight loss</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>282</volume>:<fpage>E1191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E1196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12006347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Horowitz</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Acute exercise increases triglyceride synthesis in skeletal muscle and prevents fatty acid-induced insulin resistance</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>1690</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17510709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cline</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergeron</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cushman</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooney</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Atcheson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraegen</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Mechanism by which fatty acids inhibit insulin activation of insulin receptor substrate-1 (IRS-1)-associated phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase activity in muscle</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>50230</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12006582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcucci</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cline</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Barucci</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodyear</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraegen</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Free fatty acid-induced insulin resistance is associated with activation of protein kinase C theta and alterations in the insulin signaling cascade</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>1999</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1270</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10342815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinnamaneni</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Eo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Febbraio</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Saturated, but not n-6 polyunsaturated, fatty acids induce insulin resistance: role of intramuscular accumulation of lipid metabolites</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>1467</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16357064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Garza</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Birnbaum</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Regulation of insulin-stimulated glucose transporter GLUT4 translocation and Akt kinase activity by ceramide</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1998</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>5457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9710629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitz-Peiffer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Biden</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Ceramide generation is sufficient to account for the inhibition of the insulin-stimulated PKB pathway in C2C12 skeletal muscle cells pretreated with palmitate</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year>;<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>24202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10446195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Cellular mechanisms of insulin resistance</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10903330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fillmore</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Distefano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Reznick</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Higashimori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Overexpression of uncoupling protein 3 in skeletal muscle protects against fat-induced insulin resistance</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>1995</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2003</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17571165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Youn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Fasting does not impair insulin-stimulated glucose uptake but alters intracellular glucose metabolism in conscious rats</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>1993</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>757</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8482433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cabrero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alegret</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Adzet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Laguna</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vazquez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Bezafibrate reduces mRNA levels of adipocyte markers and increases fatty acid oxidation in primary culture of adipocytes</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>1883</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11473052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thongboonkerd</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>WM</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Cardiac mitochondrial damage and biogenesis in a chronic model of type 1 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>287</volume>:<fpage>E896</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15280150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Short</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigelow</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Coenen-Schimke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghavakaimal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Decline in skeletal muscle mitochondrial function with aging in humans</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>5618</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15800038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rooyackers</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name><name><surname>Senden</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Soeters</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Saris</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagenmakers</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Prolonged activation of the branched-chain &#x003b1;-keto acid dehydrogenase complex in muscle of zymosan treated rats</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Invest</source><year>1995</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>548</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7589009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Panchal</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzeo</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Alterations in enzymes involved in fat metabolism after acute and chronic altitude exposure</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11133888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Febbraio</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Effect of ovarian hormones on mitochondrial enzyme activity in the fat oxidation pathway of skeletal muscle</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>281</volume>:<fpage>E803</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11551858</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Increasing dietary leucine intake reduces diet-induced obesity and improves glucose and cholesterol metabolism in mice via multimechanisms</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1647</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17360978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Chronological changes in metabolism and functions of cultured adipocytes: a hypothesis for cell aging in mature adipocytes</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>286</volume>:<fpage>E402</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14625202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginsberg</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Whole-body insulin resistance in the absence of obesity in FVB mice with overexpression of DGAT1 in adipose tissue</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>3379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16306352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Oelkers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturley</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rader</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginsberg</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Posttranscriptional control of the expression and function of diacylglycerol acyltransferase-1 in mouse adipocytes</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>50876</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12407108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugden</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Holness</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Recent advances in mechanisms regulating glucose oxidation at the level of the pyruvate dehydrogenase complex by PDKs</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>284</volume>:<fpage>E855</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E862</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12676647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pilegaard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufer</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Transcriptional regulation of pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase 4 in skeletal muscle during and after exercise</article-title>. <source>Proc Nutr Soc</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15294034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pilegaard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufer</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Transcriptional regulation of pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase 4 in skeletal muscle during and after exercise</article-title>. <source>Proc Nutr Soc</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15294034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clapham</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Arch</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Piercy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Beeley</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Godden</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrity</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Skehel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Changani</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hockings</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Squires</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatcher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Trail</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Latcham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rastan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadenas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckingham</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Abuin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Mice overexpressing human uncoupling protein-3 in skeletal muscle are hyperphagic and lean</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>406</volume>:<fpage>415</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10935638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowell</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Befroy</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>de Graaf</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Mitochondrial dysfunction and type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>Science</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>307</volume>:<fpage>384</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15662004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Se Jtump</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Short</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigelow</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Schim</surname><given-names>kM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Effect of insulin on human skeletal muscle mitochondrial ATP production, protein synthesis, and mRNA transcripts</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2003</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>7996</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12808136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Befroy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Impaired mitochondrial activity in the insulin-resistant offspring of patients with type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>350</volume>:<fpage>664</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14960743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holloszy</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Skeletal muscle &#x0201c;mitochondrial deficiency&#x0201d; does not mediate insulin resistance</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>463S</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>466S</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19056574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koves</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ussher</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Noland</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Slentz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosedale</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilkayeva</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bain</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyck</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Newgard</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopaschuk</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Muoio</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Mitochondrial overload and incomplete fatty acid oxidation contribute to skeletal muscle insulin resistance</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source><year>2008</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18177724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dulloo</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Montani</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Seydoux</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Solinas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Substrate cycling between de novo lipogenesis and lipid oxidation: a thermogenic mechanism against skeletal muscle lipotoxicity and glucolipotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>4</volume> (<issue>Suppl.</issue>):<fpage>S29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15592483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowker-Kinley</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Popov</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Evidence for existence of tissue-specific regulation of the mammalian pyruvate dehydrogenase complex</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source><year>1998</year>;<volume>329</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9405293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gudi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowker-Kinley</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kedishvili</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Popov</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Diversity of the pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase gene family in humans</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1995</year>;<volume>270</volume>:<fpage>28989</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7499431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaskiewicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Popov</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Starvation and diabetes increase the amount of pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase isoenzyme 4 in rat heart</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source><year>1998</year>;<volume>329</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9405294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Randle</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Reversible phosphorylation of pyruvate dehydrogenase in rat skeletal-muscle mitochondria. Effects of starvation and diabetes</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source><year>1984</year>;<volume>219</volume>:<fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6331393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Youn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Insulin regulation of skeletal muscle PDK4 mRNA expression is impaired in acute insulin-resistant states</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>2311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16873695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feldhoff</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Oesterling</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vary</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Insulin-induced activation of pyruvate dehydrogenase complex in skeletal muscle of diabetic rats</article-title>. <source>Metabolism</source><year>1993</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>615</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8492717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stace</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fatania</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerbey</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Randle</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Cyclic AMP and free fatty acids in the longer-term regulation of pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase in rat soleus muscle</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>1992</year>;<volume>1135</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1319745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holness</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulmer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugden</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Up-regulation of pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase isoform 4 (PDK4) protein expression in oxidative skeletal muscle does not require the obligatory participation of peroxisome-proliferator-activated receptor alpha (PPAR&#x003b1;)</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source><year>2002</year>;<volume>366</volume>:<fpage>839</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>846</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12099888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pilegaard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ordway</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Saltin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufer</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tunstall</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McAinch</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Loon</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron-Smith</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Transcriptional regulation of gene expression in human skeletal muscle during recovery from exercise</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>279</volume>:<fpage>E806</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E814</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11001762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tunstall</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McAinch</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Loon</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron-Smith</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Reduced plasma free fatty acid availability during exercise: effect on gene expression</article-title>. <source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>485</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17186295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>