<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Syst Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol. Syst. Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Systems Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1744-4292</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21811229</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3202792</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">msb201152</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/msb.2011.52</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Metabolic network reconstruction of <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> offers insight into light-driven algal metabolism</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Roger L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ghamsari</surname><given-names>Lila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Manichaikul</surname><given-names>Ani</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hom</surname><given-names>Erik F Y</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balaji</surname><given-names>Santhanam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Weiqi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Yun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Tong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>Bernhard &#x000d8;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salehi-Ashtiani</surname><given-names>Kourosh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a7">7</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Papin</surname><given-names>Jason A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">b</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Bioengineering, University of California, San Diego</institution>, La Jolla, CA, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Center for Cancer Systems Biology (CCSB) and Department of Cancer Biology, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</institution>, Boston, MA, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Genetics, Harvard Medical School</institution>, Boston, MA, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="a4"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Virginia</institution>, Charlottesville, VA, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="a5"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Molecular and Cellular Biology, Harvard University</institution>, Cambridge, MA, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="a6"><label>6</label><institution>Center for Systems Biology, University of Iceland</institution>, Reykjavik, <country>Iceland</country></aff><aff id="a7"><label>7</label><institution>New York University Abu Dhabi</institution>, Abu Dhabi, <country>UAE</country></aff><aff id="a8"><label>8</label><institution>Center for Genomics and Systems Biology, Department of Biology, New York University</institution>, New York, NY, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label>New York University Abu Dhabi, Abu Dhabi, UAE, and Center for Genomics and Systems Biology, Department of Biology, New York University, New York, NY, USA. Tel.: +1 212 992 6964; Fax: +1 212 995 4015; <email>ksa3@nyu.edu</email></corresp><corresp id="c2"><label>b</label>Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA 22908, USA. Tel.: +1 434 924 8195; Fax: +1 434 982 3870; <email>papin@virginia.edu</email></corresp><fn id="n1"><label>*</label><p>RL Chang led the network reconstruction and computational modeling; L Ghamsari led the transcript verification</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>02</day><month>08</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>02</day><month>08</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><fpage>518</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>02</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>06</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2011, EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial Share Alike 3.0 Unported License, which allows readers to alter, transform, or build upon the article and then distribute the resulting work under the same or similar license to this one. The work must be attributed back to the original author and commercial use is not permitted without specific permission.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="web-summary"><p>A comprehensive genome-scale metabolic network of <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic>, including a detailed account of light-driven metabolism, is reconstructed and validated. The model provides a new resource for research of <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> metabolism and in algal biotechnology.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="hidden-highlights"><p><list id="l1" list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The genome-scale metabolic network of <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> (<italic>i</italic>RC1080) was reconstructed, accounting for &#x0003e;32&#x00025; of the estimated metabolic genes encoded in the genome, and including extensive details of lipid metabolic pathways.</p></list-item><list-item><p>This is the first metabolic network to explicitly account for stoichiometry and wavelengths of metabolic photon usage, providing a new resource for research of <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> metabolism and developments in algal biotechnology.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Metabolic functional annotation and the largest transcript verification of a metabolic network to date was performed, at least partially verifying &#x0003e;90&#x00025; of the transcripts accounted for in <italic>i</italic>RC1080. Analysis of the network supports hypotheses concerning the evolution of latent lipid pathways in <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic>, including very long-chain polyunsaturated fatty acid and ceramide synthesis pathways.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A novel approach for modeling light-driven metabolism was developed that accounts for both light source intensity and spectral quality of emitted light. The constructs resulting from this approach, termed prism reactions, were shown to significantly improve the accuracy of model predictions, and their use was demonstrated for evaluation of light source efficiency and design.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="hidden-synopsis"><p>Algae have garnered significant interest in recent years, especially for their potential application in biofuel production. The hallmark, model eukaryotic microalgae <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> has been widely used to study photosynthesis, cell motility and phototaxis, cell wall biogenesis, and other fundamental cellular processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Harris, 2001</xref>). Characterizing algal metabolism is key to engineering production strains and understanding photobiological phenomena. Based on extensive literature on <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> metabolism, its genome sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">Merchant et al, 2007</xref>), and gene functional annotation, we have reconstructed and experimentally validated the genome-scale metabolic network for this alga, <italic>i</italic>RC1080, the first network to account for detailed photon absorption permitting growth simulations under different light sources. <italic>i</italic>RC1080 accounts for 1080 genes, associated with 2190 reactions and 1068 unique metabolites and encompasses 83 subsystems distributed across 10 cellular compartments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1A</xref>). Its &#x0003e;32&#x00025; coverage of estimated metabolic genes is a tremendous expansion over previous algal reconstructions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Boyle and Morgan, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">Manichaikul et al, 2009</xref>). The lipid metabolic pathways of <italic>i</italic>RC1080 are considerably expanded relative to existing networks, and chemical properties of all metabolites in these pathways are accounted for explicitly, providing sufficient detail to completely specify all individual molecular species: backbone molecule and stereochemical numbering of acyl-chain positions; acyl-chain length; and number, position, and <italic>cis</italic>&#x02013;<italic>trans</italic> stereoisomerism of carbon&#x02013;carbon double bonds. Such detail in lipid metabolism will be critical for model-driven metabolic engineering efforts.</p><p>We experimentally verified transcripts accounted for in the network under permissive growth conditions, detecting &#x0003e;90&#x00025; of tested transcript models (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1B</xref>) and providing validating evidence for the contents of <italic>i</italic>RC1080. We also analyzed the extent of transcript verification by specific metabolic subsystems. Some subsystems stood out as more poorly verified, including chloroplast and mitochondrial transport systems and sphingolipid metabolism, all of which exhibited &#x0003c;80&#x00025; of transcripts detected, reflecting incomplete characterization of compartmental transporters and supporting a hypothesis of latent pathway evolution for ceramide synthesis in <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic>. Additional lines of evidence from the reconstruction effort similarly support this hypothesis including lack of ceramide synthetase and other annotation gaps downstream in sphingolipid metabolism. A similar hypothesis of latent pathway evolution was established for very long-chain fatty acids (VLCFAs) and their polyunsaturated analogs (VLCPUFAs) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1C</xref>), owing to the absence of this class of lipids in previous experimental measurements, lack of a candidate VLCFA elongase in the functional annotation, and additional downstream annotation gaps in arachidonic acid metabolism.</p><p>The network provides a detailed account of metabolic photon absorption by light-driven reactions, including photosystems I and II, light-dependent protochlorophyllide oxidoreductase, provitamin D<sub>3</sub> photoconversion to vitamin D<sub>3</sub>, and rhodopsin photoisomerase; this network accounting permits the precise modeling of light-dependent metabolism. <italic>i</italic>RC1080 accounts for effective light spectral ranges through analysis of biochemical activity spectra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3A</xref>), either reaction activity or absorbance at varying light wavelengths. Defining effective spectral ranges associated with each photon-utilizing reaction enabled our network to model growth under different light sources via stoichiometric representation of the spectral composition of emitted light, termed prism reactions. Coefficients for different photon wavelengths in a prism reaction correspond to the ratios of photon flux in the defined effective spectral ranges to the total emitted photon flux from a given light source (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref>). This approach distinguishes the amount of emitted photons that drive different metabolic reactions. We created prism reactions for most light sources that have been used in published studies for algal and plant growth including solar light, various light bulbs, and LEDs. We also included regulatory effects, resulting from lighting conditions insofar as published studies enabled. Light and dark conditions have been shown to affect metabolic enzyme activity in <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> on multiple levels: transcriptional regulation, chloroplast RNA degradation, translational regulation, and thioredoxin-mediated enzyme regulation. Through application of our light model and prism reactions, we were able to closely recapitulate experimental growth measurements under solar, incandescent, and red LED lights. Through unbiased sampling, we were able to establish the tremendous statistical significance of the accuracy of growth predictions achievable through implementation of prism reactions. Finally, application of the photosynthetic model was demonstrated prospectively to evaluate light utilization efficiency under different light sources. The results suggest that, of the existing light sources, red LEDs provide the greatest efficiency, about three times as efficient as sunlight. Extending this analysis, the model was applied to design a maximally efficient LED spectrum for algal growth. The result was a 677-nm peak LED spectrum with a total incident photon flux of 360 &#x003bc;E/m<sup>2</sup>/s, suggesting that for the simple objective of maximizing growth efficiency, LED technology has already reached an effective theoretical optimum.</p><p>In summary, the <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> metabolic network <italic>i</italic>RC1080 that we have reconstructed offers insight into the basic biology of this species and may be employed prospectively for genetic engineering design and light source design relevant to algal biotechnology. <italic>i</italic>RC1080 was used to analyze lipid metabolism and generate novel hypotheses about the evolution of latent pathways. The predictive capacity of metabolic models developed from <italic>i</italic>RC1080 was demonstrated in simulating mutant phenotypes and in evaluation of light source efficiency. Our network provides a broad knowledgebase of the biochemistry and genomics underlying global metabolism of a photoautotroph, and our modeling approach for light-driven metabolism exemplifies how integration of largely unvisited data types, such as physicochemical environmental parameters, can expand the diversity of applications of metabolic networks.</p></abstract><abstract><p>Metabolic network reconstruction encompasses existing knowledge about an organism's metabolism and genome annotation, providing a platform for omics data analysis and phenotype prediction. The model alga <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> is employed to study diverse biological processes from photosynthesis to phototaxis. Recent heightened interest in this species results from an international movement to develop algal biofuels. Integrating biological and optical data, we reconstructed a genome-scale metabolic network for this alga and devised a novel light-modeling approach that enables quantitative growth prediction for a given light source, resolving wavelength and photon flux. We experimentally verified transcripts accounted for in the network and physiologically validated model function through simulation and generation of new experimental growth data, providing high confidence in network contents and predictive applications. The network offers insight into algal metabolism and potential for genetic engineering and efficient light source design, a pioneering resource for studying light-driven metabolism and quantitative systems biology.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic></kwd><kwd>lipid metabolism</kwd><kwd>metabolic engineering</kwd><kwd>photobioreactor</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Algae have garnered significant interest in recent years for their potential commercial applications in biofuels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Hu et al, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">Hemschemeier et al, 2009</xref>) and nutritional supplements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b58">Spolaore et al, 2006</xref>). Among eukaryotic microalgae, <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> has arisen as the hallmark, model organism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Harris, 2001</xref>). <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> has been widely used to study photosynthesis, cell motility and phototaxis, cell wall biogenesis, and other fundamental cellular processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Harris, 2001</xref>).</p><p>Commercial use and basic scientific research of photosynthetic organisms could benefit from better understanding of how light is absorbed and affects cellular systems. The quality of light sources implemented in photobioreactors largely determines the efficiency of energy usage in industrial algal farming (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">Fernandes et al, 2010</xref>). Light spectral quality also affects how photon absorption induces various metabolic processes: photosynthesis, pigment and vitamin synthesis, and the retinol pathway required for phototaxis.</p><p>Metabolic network reconstruction provides a framework to integrate diverse experimental data for investigation of global properties of metabolism, and as such, can provide clear advantages as a mode of studying the effects of light upon a photosynthetic biological system if light input is accounted for explicitly. The standardized reconstruction process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62">Thiele and Palsson, 2010</xref>) yields a biochemically and genomically structured knowledgebase and, coupled with the standard simulation approach of flux balance analysis (FBA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">Orth et al, 2010</xref>), provides a basis for predictive phenotype modeling; both contexts have been used for a variety of applications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">Durot et al, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">Oberhardt et al, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">Gianchandani et al, 2010</xref>), among them the design of genetic engineering strategies for production strains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">Bro et al, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">Park et al, 2011</xref>). To date, however, photon flux, with associated spectral constraints, has not been integrated into a metabolic network reconstruction.</p><p>Characterizing algal metabolism is key to engineering production strains and framing the study of photosynthesis. Extensive literature on <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> metabolism, reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59">Stern et al (2008)</xref>, and multiple metabolic mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">Harris et al, 2008</xref>) provide a solid foundation for detailed characterization of its metabolic functions. The availability of complete genome sequence data for <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">Merchant et al, 2007</xref>) and its functional annotation have enabled bioinformatic approaches to inform the presence of genome-encoded enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">Grossman et al, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Boyle and Morgan, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">Manichaikul et al, 2009</xref>). We have employed these resources to reconstruct and experimentally validate a genome-scale metabolic network of <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic>, the first network to account for detailed photon absorption permitting growth simulations under different light sources. This network accounts for the activity of substantially more genes with metabolic functions than existing reconstructions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Boyle and Morgan, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">Manichaikul et al, 2009</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Reconstruction contents and advances</title><p>The genome-scale <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> metabolic network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Model S1</xref>) accounts for 1080 genes, associated with 2190 reactions and 1068 unique metabolites, and encompasses 83 subsystems distributed across 10 compartments. As per convention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">Reed et al, 2003</xref>), we call this network <italic>i</italic>RC1080 based on the primary reconstructionist and the scope of genomic content. Of the putative protein-coding genes in the <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> genome (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://augustus.gobics.de/predictions/chlamydomonas/augustus.u5.aa">http://augustus.gobics.de/predictions/chlamydomonas/augustus.u5.aa</ext-link>), an estimated 20&#x00025; function in metabolism (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S3</xref>). <italic>i</italic>RC1080 accounts for the activity of &#x0003e;32&#x00025; of the estimated genes with metabolic functions, a significant expansion over existing reconstructions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Boyle and Morgan, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">Manichaikul et al, 2009</xref>). <italic>i</italic>RC1080 is the most comprehensive metabolic network reconstruction of <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> to date based on inclusion of pathways and a level of detail absent from previous reconstructions.</p><p>A major emergent feature of <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> metabolism, apparent in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1A</xref>, is the relative centrality of the chloroplast and its importance in light-driven metabolism. The chloroplast, including the thylakoid and eyespot subcompartments, accounts for &#x0003e;30&#x00025; of the total reactions in the network and 9 of the 10 photon-utilizing reactions. The thylakoid contains essential pathways for photoautotrophic growth including photosynthesis, chlorophyll synthesis, and carotenoid synthesis, producing photoprotective pigments also valuable as fish feed additives and nutritional supplements for human consumption. The eyespot accounts for retinol metabolism, the mechanistic basis for phototaxis. Several pathways are partially duplicated across the chloroplast and other cellular compartments, in agreement with known biochemistry. A few crucial pathways are divided between the chloroplast and cytosol, including glycolysis and glycerolipid metabolism. Among the glycerolipids, triacylglycerides carrying high energy, long-chain fatty acids relevant for biofuel production accumulate substantially in microalgae. <italic>i</italic>RC1080 provides a thorough resource for studying these and other metabolic products and a basis for strain design for genetic engineering.</p><p><italic>i</italic>RC1080 considerably expands lipid metabolic pathways over previous reconstructions. We compared the lipid pathways of <italic>i</italic>RC1080 with several previously published metabolic reconstructions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">Duarte et al, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Feist et al, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Boyle and Morgan, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">Mo et al, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">Montagud et al, 2010</xref>) counting the number of genes, reactions, and chemically distinct lipid molecules included in pathways for each lipid class (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table I</xref>). The extent of gene, reaction, and metabolite content of lipid pathways in <italic>i</italic>R1080 is, in general, greater than previous reconstructions. The coverage of ketoacyl lipid chemical properties represented in each network was also analyzed for all metabolites in fatty acyl, glycerolipid, glycerophospholipid, and sphingolipid classes; the fraction of lipid metabolites in the networks that account for a given applicable property was determined (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table I</xref>). Lower coverage signifies incompletely specified molecular species and often lumped lipid reactions and metabolites. <italic>i</italic>RC1080 accounts explicitly for all metabolites in these pathways, providing sufficient detail to completely specify all individual molecular species: backbone molecule and its stereochemical numbering of acyl-chain positions; acyl-chain length; and number, position, and <italic>cis</italic>&#x02013;<italic>trans</italic> stereoisomerism of carbon&#x02013;carbon double bonds. This level of detail enables a significantly higher degree of precision in lipid studies and in metabolic engineering design involving these pathways.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Experimental transcript verification</title><p>We have analyzed <italic>i</italic>RC1080 via experimental transcript verification under permissive growth conditions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S4</xref>), representing the largest genome-scale transcript validation effort to date. More than 75&#x00025; of included transcripts were verified at &#x0003e;90&#x00025; sequence coverage, and 92&#x00025; of tested transcripts were at least partially validated experimentally (i.e. a portion of the sequence was recovered in the sequenced transcripts) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1B</xref>). We also analyzed the strength of transcript verification by specific metabolic subsystems (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>, a representative subset; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>, the full set). The full lengths of all transcripts associated with 10 subsystems were verified, notably including biosynthesis of unsaturated fatty acids, histidine metabolism, and phenylalanine, tyrosine and tryptophan biosynthesis, with 12, 12, and 24 transcripts, respectively. Many more subsystems were also well verified, 61 out of 76 gene-associated subsystems with &#x0003e;90&#x00025; of associated transcripts at least partially validated. It should be noted that only sequencing reads that uniquely map to reference transcript sequences were counted toward the percentage of length validation; thus, sequencing reads unique enough to unambiguously specify the corresponding reference transcript were detected for every transcript with &#x0003e;0&#x00025; validation. A few subsystems stood out as being more poorly verified, including chloroplast and mitochondrial transport systems and sphingolipid metabolism, all of which exhibited &#x0003c;80&#x00025; of transcripts validated to any extent. This may reflect low expression level or imperfect structural annotation of these genes, particularly compartmental transporters. Low expression levels or complete deactivation of these genes is consistent with a hypothesized evolutionary trend (see below) in the case of sphingolipid metabolism.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Evolution of latent lipid pathways</title><p>The comprehensive reconstruction of lipid metabolism in <italic>i</italic>RC1080 revealed hypothetical latent pathways, the functions of which have likely been lost through evolution. Previous studies established that <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> lacks the practically ubiquitous membrane lipids phosphatidylcholine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">Giroud et al, 1988</xref>) and phosphatidylserine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53">Riekhof et al, 2005</xref>). Similarly, our reconstruction suggests that <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> also lacks very long-chain fatty acids (VLCFAs), their polyunsaturated analogs (VLCPUFAs) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1C</xref>), and ceramides.</p><p>Surveys of <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> lipid species have not detected VLCFAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">Giroud et al, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">Giroud and Eichenberger, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b61">Tatsuzawa et al, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">Dubertret et al, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">Kajikawa et al, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">Lang, 2007</xref>), likely due to a lack of functional VLCFA elongase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b63">Weers and Gulati, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">Guschina and Harwood, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">Kajikawa et al, 2006</xref>). No candidate VLCFA elongase was identified in our comprehensive functional annotation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S3</xref>), and our annotation suggests several downstream gaps in arachidonic acid metabolism as well, corroborating this hypothesis. Arachidonic acid, the 20-carbon parent fatty acid of all VLCFAs and VLCPUFAs, is synthesized by a VLCFA elongase-catalyzed extension of &#x003b3;-linolenic acid, which is present in <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">Griffiths et al, 2000</xref>). Notably, <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> does encode a fatty acid desaturase that accepts arachidonic acid as substrate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">Kajikawa et al, 2006</xref>) and, based on our functional annotation, encodes several other enzymes that act upon this substrate, indicating that algal ancestors likely had a functional VLCFA elongase.</p><p>Multiple lines of evidence uncovered during the reconstruction also support the absence of ceramides in <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic>. Our functional annotation did not uncover a convincing candidate for ceramide synthetase (EC:2.3.1.24), a required enzyme for ceramide synthesis, nor, to our knowledge, has one been discovered by previous efforts, including <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> enzyme annotations of the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes. Similarly, our functional annotation suggests substantial gaps downstream in the sphingolipid metabolic pathway. As aforementioned, <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> also lacks VLCFAs, and VLCFA-CoA is a required substrate for the ceramide synthetase reaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">Hills and Roscoe, 2006</xref>). Finally, our experimental transcript analysis failed to verify 2 out of 8 transcripts associated with sphingolipid metabolism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>) that were included in <italic>i</italic>RC1080, 1 of 2 serine C-palmitoyltransferases and a putative sphingosine 1-phosphate aldolase. This result may reflect still further gene function loss in this pathway, perhaps occurring more recently in evolutionary time given that our functional annotation actually detected candidate sequences for these enzymes. Considering this evidence, we suggest that the evolutionary history of <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> includes the loss of ceramide metabolism, although this hypothesis remains to be verified. Annotated enzymes in this pathway separated from the broader network by gaps may represent multifunctional proteins or proteins that have evolved to function in a pathway distinct from ceramide synthesis. These gaps in <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> metabolism not only increase understanding of the evolution of algal lipid pathways but also represent potential targets for genetic engineering in an effort to expand the diversity of lipids this alga can synthesize. Such engineering efforts serve as valuable test cases for engineering industrial strains and could improve <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> as a model alga for biofuel development.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Modeling metabolic light usage</title><p>Our reconstruction accounted for effective light spectral ranges by analyzing biochemical activity spectra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3A</xref>), either reaction activity or absorbance at varying light wavelengths. Defining effective spectral bandwidths associated with each photon-utilizing reaction enabled our network to model growth under different light sources via stoichiometric representation of the spectral composition of emitted light, which we term prism reactions. The coefficients for different photon wavelengths in prism reactions correspond to the ratios of photon flux in the defined effective spectral ranges to the total photon flux in the visible spectrum emitted by a given light source (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3A and B</xref>). In this manner, it is possible to distinguish the amount of emitted photons that drive different metabolic reactions. We created prism reactions for 11 distinct light sources (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>), covering most sources that have been used in published studies for algal and plant growth including solar light, various light bulbs, and LEDs.</p><p>The network reconstruction provides a detailed account of metabolic photon absorption by light-driven reactions. Photosystems I and II in <italic>i</italic>RC1080 stoichiometrically absorb photons according to the <italic>Z</italic>-scheme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">Berg et al, 2007</xref>). The light-dependent protochlorophyllide oxidoreductases require a single photon per catalysis as demonstrated in wheat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">Griffiths et al, 1996</xref>). Extrapolation of UVB energy requirements for spontaneous provitamin D<sub>3</sub> conversion to vitamin D<sub>3</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">Bjorn, 2007</xref>) based on the average photon energy in the UVB range suggests a stoichiometric ratio of approximately one. Two phototactic rhodopsins, reactants of the rhodopsin photoisomerase reaction, are encoded by <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic>, one requiring a single photon and one requiring two photons for activation; the average effective stoichiometric photon count was measured to be 1.6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">Hegemann and Marwan, 1988</xref>).</p><p>A prism reaction is the intermediate step between light input and the specific photon-utilizing metabolic reactions mentioned above. Flux through the photon exchange reaction &#x02018;EX_photonVis(e)' represents the total metabolically active photon flux incident upon the cell. Flux passing through this exchange reaction then passes through a single user-specified prism reaction, for example &#x02018;PRISM_solar_litho,' and is distributed across specific spectral ranges. These ranges are specified explicitly in the photon-dependent metabolic reaction formulas (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>), thereby making these reactions wavelength specific. Flux through the photon-dependent metabolic reactions is then propagated through the network. Excess wavelength-specific photon fluxes that are not absorbed metabolically leave the system via demand reactions, for example &#x02018;DM_photon298(c),' completing the pathway of light through the network.</p><p>To accurately model metabolic activity of a photosynthetic organism, it is also important to consider regulatory effects resulting from lighting conditions. Indeed, light and dark conditions have been shown to affect metabolic enzyme activity in <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> at multiple levels: transcriptional regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Bohne and Linden, 2002</xref>), chloroplast RNA degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54">Salvador et al, 1993</xref>), translational regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">Cahoon and Timko, 2000</xref>), and thioredoxin-mediated enzyme regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">Lemaire et al, 2004</xref>). As a preliminary attempt to incorporate light and dark regulatory effects, literature was reviewed to identify such regulation upon enzymes in <italic>i</italic>RC1080 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S5</xref>), focusing mainly on thioredoxin regulation of chloroplast enzymes since most published data relate to this mode. In the absence of activity spectra for these effects, it is not yet possible to represent these effects via prism reactions. Therefore, we modeled regulation with Boolean reaction flux constraints following published approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">Covert et al, 2001</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Environmental and genetic validation of <italic>i</italic>RC1080</title><p>Implementing light-regulated constraints and basic environmental exchange constraints (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S6</xref>) yielded photoautotrophic, heterotrophic, and mixotrophic models from <italic>i</italic>RC1080. We simulated various growth conditions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S7</xref>) and all gene knockouts for which phenotypes have been published and are assessable in our network (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S8</xref>) to validate the predictive ability of the models. All 30 validations involving environmental parameters displayed very close agreement with experimental results (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S7</xref>). Of particular note is the ability of our photosynthetic model in sunlight to accurately recapitulate O<sub>2</sub>-PAR (photosynthetically active radiation) energy conversion efficiency, predicting an efficiency of 2&#x00025; compared with the experimental result (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Greenbaum, 1988</xref>) of 1.3&#x02013;4.5&#x00025;. Of the 14 gene knockouts simulated, 7 were partially or completely validated relative to experimental results (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S8</xref>). The unconfirmed gene knockout phenotypes may result from network errors or an incomplete set of constraints in the model (e.g. enzyme capacity, regulatory, thermodynamic, or other constraints). No internal model reactions were constrained in the models except indirectly via constraints on the input exchanges and the few explicitly noted Boolean regulatory constraints imposed (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S5</xref>). The unconfirmed knockout phenotypes were investigated through model analysis and literature search, although in most cases, current literature evidence could not completely explain these discrepancies, leaving them to be fully accounted for by future studies.</p><p>Two discrepancies may result from incomplete genome functional annotation or missing constraints. Knockout of mitochondrial NADH:ubiquinone oxidoreductase complex I (EC:1.6.5.3) in the model fails to recapitulate a reduced heterotrophic growth phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51">Remacle et al, 2001a</xref>). The NDA2 and NDA3 genes can substitute completely for this activity in the current model. Sequence-based localization analysis places both proteins in the mitochondria, but this may be incorrect as a recent study suggests that both may be plastid localized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">Desplats et al, 2009</xref>). Two other network reactions can also substitute for the reduction of ubiquinone, succinate dehydrogenase (ubiquinone) (EC:1.3.5.1) and electron transfer flavoprotein-ubiquinone oxidoreductase (EC:1.5.5.1). The cytochrome c oxidase complex IV (EC:1.9.3.1) knockout does not result in an obligate photoautotrophic phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52">Remacle et al, 2001b</xref>) in the model because the cytochrome c peroxidase (EC:1.11.1.5) reaction is capable of compensating. The <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> CCPR1 protein is homologous to mitochondrial cytochrome c peroxidases from a number of species, but no focused studies have been carried out to provide further evidence for this enzyme. In the model, the complex IV and CCPR1 double knockout is an obligate photoautotroph. These discrepancies point out important genes that should be the focus of subsequent experimentation in order to more clearly understand these metabolic phenotypes.</p><p>Another discrepancy may result from missing thermodynamic constraints. The zeaxanthin epoxidase (EC:1.14.13.90) knockout does not preclude antheraxanthin, violaxanthin, or neoxanthin production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">Baroli et al, 2003</xref>) in the model because violaxanthin de-epoxidase (EC:1.10.99.3) reactions compensate. This substitution depends on the reversibility of these de-epoxidase reactions and may point to missing thermodynamic constraints or to undiscovered regulation under this condition.</p><p>Two discrepancies result from the lack of accounting for kinetics of the reactions of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase oxygenase (RuBisCO) from the model. Both phosphoglycolate phosphatase (EC:3.1.3.18) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b60">Suzuki et al, 1990</xref>) and glycolate dehydrogenase (EC:1.1.99.14) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">Nakamura et al, 2005</xref>) deficient mutants require high CO<sub>2</sub> for photoautotrophic growth <italic>in vivo</italic>, not recapitulated in simulations. This phenotype results from dominance of the oxygenase over carboxylase activity of RuBisCO under lower CO<sub>2</sub> conditions, both reactions sharing the same catalytic site. <italic>In vivo</italic>, these two mutants are deficient in the salvage of carbon from 2-phosphoglycolate, a product of the oxygenase activity of RuBisCO. Although these two reactions are carried out by the same enzyme in the model, their fluxes are treated as independent and not competitive; due to an absence of kinetic parameters in the model, the effect of relative CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> concentrations upon RuBisCO activity cannot be explicitly expressed. Because the carboxylase activity more efficiently promotes growth, both high and low CO<sub>2</sub> conditions drive only this reaction and not the oxygenase reaction in the model; therefore, the salvage pathway is unnecessary in the model to achieve wild-type growth rates.</p><p>Finally, two mutant phenotype discrepancies in the model result from complex compensatory pathways that convert an input carbon source to the mutant-required carbon source. The high CO<sub>2</sub> requirement for photoautotrophic growth due to knockout of the chloroplast carbonic anhydrase (EC:4.2.1.1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b57">Spalding et al, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Funke et al, 1997</xref>) can be compensated for in the model by activity of a six-reaction pathway of pyrimidine metabolism leading from bicarbonate incorporation via carbamoyl-phosphate synthase (EC:6.3.5.5) to conversion to CO<sub>2</sub> via orotidine-5&#x02032;-phosphate decarboxylase (EC:4.1.1.23). The chloroplast ATP synthase (EC:3.6.3.14) deficient mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56">Smart and Selman, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">Dent et al, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">Drapier et al, 2007</xref>) with an acetate-requiring phenotype can be compensated for in the model by a complex pathway consisting of &#x0003e;15 reactions by which CO<sub>2</sub> is converted to acetate, which is then used in pathways similar to those supporting heterotrophic growth. Although this complex pathway has many branch points, it is notable that chloroplast malate dehydrogenase (EC:1.1.1.40) and the diffusion of pyruvate between the cytosol and chloroplast are essential to coupling the CO<sub>2</sub> fixation reactions to pyruvate metabolism and ultimate conversion to acetate but are not essential to the wild-type photoautotrophic or heterotrophic models. Loss of either of these conditionally essential reactions prevents the CO<sub>2</sub>-to-acetate conversion and recapitulates the acetate-requiring phenotype. Given the complexity of these compensatory pathways, a number of possible missing constraints could explain their inactivity <italic>in vivo</italic> under photosynthetic conditions, and the model offers a starting point to explore possible targets of regulation under these conditions.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Gene essentiality analysis</title><p>To demonstrate the prospective use of <italic>i</italic>RC1080 in predicting phenotypic outcomes of genetic manipulations of <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic>, comprehensive essentiality analysis of all simulated single-gene knockouts was performed in models under four basic environmental conditions: growth in sunlight with and without acetate, aerobic growth in dark on acetate, and anaerobic subsistence in dark on starch. Phenotypes were defined as growth equivalent to wild-type, reduced growth relative to wild-type, or lethal based on the comparative objective fluxes of the mutant and wild-type models (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S9</xref>). A lethal phenotype was defined as no flux through the biomass reaction (defined as the objective function) in the mutant. Simulation results exhibited distinct metabolic system dependencies under each condition. There were 201 and 144 lethal knockouts in the model with sunlight and with and without acetate, respectively. There were 147 and only 3 lethal knockouts in the aerobic and anaerobic dark model, respectively. The metabolic processes associated with essential genes were ranked, and the three subsystems associated with the essential genes were compared under each condition. Photosynthesis, porphyrin and chlorophyll metabolism, and phenylalanine, tyrosine, and tryptophan biosynthesis were the most essential subsystems in light without acetate. Phenylalanine, tyrosine, and tryptophan biosynthesis, porphyrin and chlorophyll metabolism, and purine metabolism were the most essential subsystems in light with acetate. Expectedly, photosynthesis is most crucial for photoautotrophic growth and not required in the presence of acetate. The dark, aerobic condition had the same top ranked essential subsystems as in the mixotrophic condition, which is also expected as amino acids, chlorophyll, and nucleotides make up a high proportion of the required biomass components under both conditions. For subsistence in dark on starch, glycolysis/gluconeogenesis, starch metabolism, and starch and sucrose metabolism were the most essential subsystems, paralleling the expected core pathways for ATP maintenance with starch breakdown. While these predicted genotype&#x02013;phenotype relationships demonstrate a compelling prospective use of the network, the majority of the mutant phenotypes remain to be validated experimentally; however, these predictions could be used to help define the scope and expected outcomes of such future studies.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Light-source-specific model validations</title><p>Next, we performed more extensive validations of light models grown under specific light sources at varying intensities. Varying sunlight intensity in our model and evaluating photosynthetic O<sub>2</sub> evolution, we observed that the model reached photosynthetic saturation at light intensity consistent with experimental measurement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49">Polle et al, 2003</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4A</xref>). Our model under red LED light (653 nm) also showed fair agreement with our experimentally measured maximum growth rate across the range of unsaturated photon flux (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4B</xref>), despite divergence above the experimental saturation point. The principal explanation for this divergence lies in the relative CO<sub>2</sub> supplies of the experimental setup and the model. All reported photoautotrophic model simulations utilize the same maximum CO<sub>2</sub> exchange constraint corresponding to the maximum-measured cellular uptake rate under non-CO<sub>2</sub>-limiting conditions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S6</xref>), while the CO<sub>2</sub> supply in our bioreactor setup was clearly growth-limiting given that the light-saturated maximum growth rate was 0.01 gDW/h, much lower than the maximum growth rate of 0.14 gDW/h under non-CO<sub>2</sub>-limiting conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">Janssen et al, 2000</xref>). It should also be noted that the linearity of the simulation trends is a property of steady-state system modeling, which is incapable of kinetic representation of growth shifts observable in the <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments. For further validation, we present that the maximum biomass yield under incandescent white light is 5.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup> gDW/mE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">Janssen et al, 2000</xref>), in close agreement with our analogous prediction of 2.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup> gDW/mE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4C</xref>). Similarly, our predicted biomass yield on 674 nm peak LED light of 1.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> gDW/mE is on the same order of magnitude as our experimental results for <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> under 660 nm peak LED light near growth-saturating photon flux, 4.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> gDW/mE. This agreement is striking given that the network explicitly accounts for the spectral photon flux of these light sources and the subsequent processing of this energy to generate all of the constituents of biomass without any parameter fitting to the experimental data. Together, these results constitute an important validation of our models using three different light sources.</p><p>To quantitatively evaluate the significance of the agreement between our reported model simulations using prism reactions derived through analysis of irradiance spectra and experimental measurements under the three light sources reported above, we compared the reported simulation results for each of these light sources with an unbiased sample of results representative of potential solutions achievable using our network. We sampled the space of possible light models by generating random prism reactions with the same total metabolically active photon flux. To obtain stoichiometric coefficients for a random prism reaction, a set of random fractions of the sum of stoichiometric coefficients of the prism reaction representing the evaluated light source was generated, contingent upon resulting in the same sum of coefficients. The simulations as reported above for sunlight, red LED, and white incandescent light were repeated using such random prism reactions. The Euclidean distance between the simulated and experimental results was compared with the distribution of distances for 10 000 randomly sampled results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref>). The probability of randomly achieving experimental agreement closer than seen in our simulations was determined empirically based on these distributions of distances. Only 77 of 10 000 randomized simulations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5A</xref>) had experimental agreement better than the simulated oxygen photoevolution under sunlight (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4A</xref>), yielding an empirical <italic>P</italic>-value of 0.0077, and indicating our model had experimental agreement statistically significantly better than a random model constrained to have the same total metabolically active photon flux. Simulated growth under 665 nm peak LED (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4B</xref>) had a suggestive <italic>P</italic>-value of 0.1947 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5B</xref>), although the reported simulation was still closer to experiment than the mean of randomized simulations. Our simulated growth under white incandescent light was statistically significantly closer to experiment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">Janssen et al, 2000</xref>) than random (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5C</xref>) with a <italic>P</italic>-value of 0.0285. This analysis shows that the reported model for each of these light sources is exceptionally close to recapitulating experimental results and thus serves as an excellent validation. These results indicate that the network has the capacity to broadly differentiate light-dependent growth based on spectral properties and that the formulation of a prism reaction serves to accurately narrow the space of possible flux distributions relevant to a specific light source.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Application of <italic>i</italic>RC1080 to evaluate light source efficiency and design</title><p>Our photosynthetic model was applied prospectively to evaluate the efficiency of light utilization under different light sources. The photon energy conversion efficiency (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Equation 1</xref>) and biomass yield on light (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Equation 2</xref>) were computed for each light source given the minimum incident photon flux required to achieve maximum growth rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4C</xref>); the minimum photon flux for maximum growth rate is the growth-saturating photon flux value for a given light source. One clear result is that red LEDs provide the greatest efficiency in terms of both absorbed photon energy and biomass yield, about two and three times as efficient as can be optimally achieved in sunlight by these respective measures. Although experimental growth data for validation is only presented for three light sources, simulation results are presented for all 11 light sources for which irradiance spectra were obtainable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4C</xref>). This analysis demonstrates the prospective extensibility of the network and modeling approach to any possible lighting condition, natural or manmade, for which an irradiance spectrum can be measured.</p><p>Given the capability of our photosynthetic model to evaluate light source efficiency, we applied it to design an LED spectrum providing maximum photon utilization efficiency for growth (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>). The result was a 677-nm peak LED spectrum with a total incident photon flux of 360 &#x003bc;E/m<sup>2</sup>/s (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4C</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>), which is quite close to the 674-nm LED with a minimum incident photon flux of 362 &#x003bc;E/m<sup>2</sup>/s for maximum growth. This result suggests that for the simple objective of maximizing growth efficiency, LED technology has already reached an effective theoretical optimum, which is further supported by experimental measurements of the spectral peak of light absorption for green algae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">Akkerman et al, 2002</xref>) and the quantum action spectrum of land plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Barta et al, 1992</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S7</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>We have presented a genome-scale network reconstruction of <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> metabolism, well validated in content and function, and its application for detailed modeling of diverse light sources. Initial model validations also highlight the need for more experimental studies to uncover regulatory mechanisms in order to expand understanding of the complexity of light regulation of algal metabolism. This open research topic presents important challenges and opportunities in enumerating such effects on a genome scale.</p><p>Given the importance of lipid metabolism in biofuel production, <italic>i</italic>RC1080 was reconstructed enumerating all lipids supported by evidence in the literature and genome functional annotation. The capacity of <italic>i</italic>RC1080 as a knowledgebase was demonstrated through analysis of lipid metabolism to generate novel hypotheses about latent metabolic pathways resulting from algal evolution. In particular, the exclusion of certain enzymatic reactions in VLCFA and sphingolipid pathways from <italic>i</italic>RC1080 suggests evolutionary recession of these pathways in <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic>, a hypothesis supported by undetected lipids in experimental measurements, gaps in genome functional annotation for these enzymes, and incomplete transcript verification for other enzymes included in these pathways. Not only do these network gaps reflect the relatively simple lipid biosynthetic capabilities of <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> among microalgae, but their identification suggests gene insertions that could expand its lipid metabolic repertoire, relevant for industrial and scientific purposes. Of particular interest may be the potential for enabling algal synthesis of essential fatty acids for human health such as docosahexaenoic acid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b64">Yashodhara et al, 2009</xref>). Candidate enzymes for the conversion of arachidonic acid to essential fatty acids downstream of the apparently absent VLCFA elongase reaction are present in our functional annotation.</p><p>The models developed from <italic>i</italic>RC1080 provide a platform for prediction of phenotypic outcomes of system perturbations, light source evaluation and design, and genetic engineering design for production of biofuels and other commodity chemicals. We demonstrated an approach applying <italic>i</italic>RC1080 to the design of an energetically efficient light source for growth, a novel application of metabolic networks. Other light sources may be more efficient for other metabolic objectives or under other environmental conditions or genetic backgrounds. This result could be of significant interest to the metabolic engineering and bioreactor-design communities because it demonstrates that our network and light-modeling approach are capable of accurately predicting light source efficiencies in terms of a metabolic objective.</p><p>The prism reactions developed and applied in this study to quantitatively integrate spectral quality with biological activity represent a significant integration of diverse data types for biological system modeling, which hopefully will encourage a new paradigm for systems biology. This modeling approach could be used for applications beyond light source design, including as a metabolic basis for studying and simulating phototaxis. Given the acquisition of appropriate biological spectral activity data, this approach could be extended to other biological light-response phenomena and other organisms. The importance of understanding how light parameters affect biological systems may also extend beyond natural phenomena with recent progress in protein engineering leading to chimeric light-inducible proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b55">Shimizu-Sato et al, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">Levskaya et al, 2005</xref>).</p><p>The <italic>i</italic>RC1080 network and presented metabolic modeling represent a milestone in systems biology. Our network provides a broad knowledgebase of the biochemistry and genomics underlying global metabolism of a photoautotroph, and our modeling of light-driven metabolism exemplifies how integration of largely unvisited data types, such as physicochemical environmental parameters, can expand the diversity of applications of metabolic networks.</p></sec><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Metabolic network reconstruction</title><p>Building from our previously published reconstruction of <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> central metabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">Manichaikul et al, 2009</xref>), <italic>i</italic>AM303, the <italic>i</italic>RC1080 network was reconstructed in a bottom&#x02013;up manner according to current standards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62">Thiele and Palsson, 2010</xref>) on a pathway-by-pathway basis, drawing biochemical, genomic, and physiological evidence from &#x0003e;250 publications (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). The genomic evidence was derived from our own functional annotation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S3</xref>) of metabolic enzymes, coenzymes, and transport proteins. Network gap-filling was performed to make pathways functional and account for dead-end metabolites. Global quality control checks were then performed, including elemental balancing and elimination of as many internal thermodynamically infeasible loops and new photon-driven, input-only pathways as possible (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S4</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref>). We also accounted for subcellular compartment pH in the protonation states of metabolites as much as possible.</p><p><italic>i</italic>RC1080 is publicly available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels</ext-link> (Accession: MODEL1106200000) and as <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Model S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Functional annotation of transcripts</title><p>Functional annotation for <italic>i</italic>RC1080 was performed using a consensus of two separate approaches. In the first approach, gene models (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://augustus.gobics.de/predictions/chlamydomonas/augustus.u5.aa">http://augustus.gobics.de/predictions/chlamydomonas/augustus.u5.aa</ext-link>) from the Augustus update 5 (Au5) of <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> genome assembly version JGI v4.0 were functionally annotated by assigning enzyme classification (EC) terms using BLASTP results against UniProt (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org/">http://www.uniprot.org/</ext-link>) and AraCyc (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org/biocyc/">http://www.arabidopsis.org/biocyc/</ext-link>) enzyme protein sequences and their EC annotations as the basis. The second approach followed from mapping of Au5 gene models to annotated JGI v3.1 gene models, for which EC terms and Gene Ontology annotation were assigned using a combination of BLASTP, AutoFACT, InterProScan, and PRIAM. The comprehensive annotation is presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S3</xref>. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref> for full details.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Growth simulations</title><p>Simulation procedures consisted of FBA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">Orth et al, 2010</xref>) and flux variability analysis (FVA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">Mahadevan and Schilling, 2003</xref>) as implemented in the COBRA toolbox (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">Becker et al, 2007</xref>), testing model capabilities while optimizing biomass functions to simulate growth (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S10</xref>) or subsistence on starch by optimizing ATP maintenance. FBA is a widely used simulation approach for large-scale, constraint-based metabolic models and has become a standard method in the systems biology field with a long history of success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">Gianchandani et al, 2010</xref>). Different environmental conditions were modeled by appropriately setting reaction flux constraints in <italic>i</italic>RC1080 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S6</xref>) including environmental exchanges, non-growth associated ATP maintenance, O<sub>2</sub> photoevolution, starch degradation, and light- or dark-regulated enzymatic reactions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S5</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> strains and growth conditions</title><p>For transcript verification experiments, <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> strain CC-503 was grown in tris-acetate-phosphate medium containing 100 mg/l carbamicillin without agitation, at room temperature (22&#x02013;25&#x000b0;C) and under continuous illumination with cool white light at a photosynthetic photon flux of 60 &#x003bc;E/m<sup>2</sup>/s.</p><p>For growth experiments under 660 nm peak LED light (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S5</xref>), <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> strain UTEX2243 was grown in a bubble column photobioreactor at 23&#x02013;27&#x000b0;C with P49 medium. The total volume of algal culture was 300 ml, and the gas supply was 180 ml/min air with 2.5&#x00025; CO<sub>2</sub>. The 660-nm peak LED light supply was set at 10 kHz frequency and different duty cycles to get varied average photon fluxes.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Transcript verification by sequencing</title><p>ORF amplicons were generated from <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> cells by RT&#x02013;PCR from RNA or PCR from Gateway clones. The Roche 454FLX Titanium sequencing system was used for sequencing of the generated ORF amplicons according to the manufacturer's instructions. The generated data were processed using the GS FLX data analysis software v2.3. Minimum overlap length of 40 nucleotides and minimum overlap identity of 90&#x00025; were used to align the sequencing reads against the Au5 reference sequences. ORFs encoding transporter proteins were verified by capillary Sanger sequencing.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Prism reaction derivation</title><p>Spectral bandwidths that effectively drive each photon-utilizing reaction in <italic>i</italic>RC1080 were determined from published experimental activity spectral data or absorbance data. Effective spectral bandwidths were defined as the full width half maximum of activity, denoted by color-paired dashed lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3A</xref>. The effective spectral bandwidths were used to derive stoichiometric coefficients of the prism reactions used to quantitatively represent different light sources from the composition of their published irradiance spectra, converted to photon flux units according to <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Equations 3 and 4</xref>. Coefficients for each of the effective spectral bandwidths were computed based on <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq1">Equation 1</xref>.</p><p><disp-formula id="eq1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1607" xlink:href="msb201152-m1.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>Each coefficient represents the ratio of photon flux in the defined effective bandwidth to total visible photon flux. Definite integrals in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq1">Equation 1</xref> were approximated using the trapezoidal rule. For each light source, all effective bandwidth coefficients were compiled into a single reaction in the form of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq2">Equation 2</xref>.</p><p><disp-formula id="eq2"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1618" xlink:href="msb201152-m2.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>Constraints on prism reaction fluxes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S6</xref>) were derived from the total visible photon flux, the definite integral of the spectrum from 380 to 750 nm. The total experimentally measured emitted visible photon flux was converted to model units of incident photon flux using the values in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S11</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Equations 5 and 6</xref>. Prism reactions for 11 different light sources (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>) were generated.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Random sampling of prism reaction space and significance test</title><p>For a given prism reaction, first the sum of the stoichiometric coefficients was calculated, representing the total quantity of metabolically active photons per incident photon from the specified light source. Next, to sample the space of prism reactions, 10 000 random prism reactions with the same sum of stoichiometric coefficients were generated and used in growth simulations. In these simulations, input photon flux was constrained to the reported experimental values, generating a set of simulated results (biomass or photosynthetically evolved O<sub>2</sub> flux, depending on the experimental parameter) with one value corresponding to each experimental data point. The Euclidean distance between the sampled and experimental results was calculated for each of the 10 000 randomized prism reactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref>). The significance of the experimental agreement with simulations reported for a given prism reaction derived directly from analysis of irradiance spectra was established by comparison between the corresponding Euclidean distance and the distribution of distances from the randomly sampled prism reactions. Probability of achieving equal or closer results to experiments by chance was computed as the proportion of smaller values in the randomly sampled distribution of 10 000 distances.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Procedure for efficient LED design</title><p>Multiple iterations of FVA were used to maximize growth while minimizing the energy of the sum of individual wavelengths of model photon flux. The ratios of these individual wavelength photon fluxes to total photon flux were set as stoichiometric coefficients for a theoretical maximum-efficiency prism reaction. The Euclidean vector distance was computed (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S6</xref>) between this set of coefficients and prism reaction coefficients calculated for an LED spectrum of the same shape as the experimentally measured 674 nm peak LED but centered at varying wavelengths across the visible spectrum, with a total photon flux equal to the total theoretical maximum-efficiency photon flux. The spectrum corresponding to the minimum distance was taken as the solution and subsequently tested through growth simulation.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="d32e26" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Supplementary Methods, Supplementary Figures S4&#x02013;6, Supplementary Table S1</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s1.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e32" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Figure S1</title><p>High-resolution network diagram. This network diagram displays all metabolites (nodes) and reactions (complex edges) included in <italic>i</italic>RC1080. Metabolites are color-coded based on compartment localization. Reversibility and irreversibility are represented by the placement of arrows at the ends of edges connecting metabolites (i.e. substrates of irreversible reactions do not have arrows on the edges connecting to them). Labels follow the abbreviation conventions used in <italic>i</italic>RC1080 (<bold>Supplementary Table S2</bold>). Visually resolving node and edge labels requires zooming to at least 6400&#x00025; on most displays.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e47" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Figure S2</title><p>Complete transcript verification by subsystem. The transcript verification status for all gene-associated subsystems of <italic>i</italic>RC1080 is displayed. The graph follows the same format as <bold>Figure 2</bold>.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s3.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e59" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Figure S3</title><p>Complete activity and irradiance spectra. The irradiance spectra are shown for all light sources used in this study. The graphs follow the same format as <bold>Figure 3A</bold>.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s4.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e68" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Table S2</title><p>Complete <italic>i</italic>RC1080 network data. All data included in the <italic>i</italic>RC1080 network are presented here including but not limited to lower and upper flux bounds (LB and UB, respectively) and all literature references used during the reconstruction. The flux bounds highlighted in yellow represent model input and output parameters that were varied when performing the various simulations presented in this study, and the values in these columns only represent defaults and not the actual values used in any specific simulation.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s5.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e80" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Table S3</title><p>Transcript functional annotation. The full set of metabolic functional annotation of transcripts is presented, including but not limited to those functions and transcripts represented in <italic>i</italic>RC1080. The rightmost column denotes the method by which the annotation was obtained: 1 corresponds to the first method we implemented for annotation, 2 corresponds to the second method we implemented for annotation, 3 corresponds to both methods, TCDB signifies annotation resulting from a bidirectional BLAST search comparing TCDB to the <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic> genome (JGI v4.0), and literature references signify those annotations taken directly from published literature.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s6.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e92" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Table S4</title><p>Transcript verification status. The percentage of sequence length verification is given for all experimentally tested transcripts included in <italic>i</italic>RC1080 (see Transcript verification experiments in the <bold>Supplementary Methods</bold> for more details). Those transcripts verified by capillary Sanger sequencing are denoted by an asterisk.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s7.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e104" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Table S5</title><p>Light and dark-regulated reaction constraints. Reaction regulation under light and dark conditions, used in this study for constraint-based modeling, are summarized.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s8.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e110" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Table S6</title><p>Basic modeling constraints. Precise values of parameters used to constrain models in simulations are presented.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s9.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e116" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Table S7</title><p>Environmental validations. Outcomes of simulations are compared to experimentally measured results to validate model function with respect to environmental parameters.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s10.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e122" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Table S8</title><p>Genetic validations. Outcomes of knock-out simulations are compared to the analogous experimentally measured mutant phenotypes to validate model function with respect to genetic parameters.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s11.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e129" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Table S9</title><p>Gene-knockout lethality. Growth or subsistence, in the case of anaerobic dark growth, phenotypes of all single-gene knockout simulations are presented. Phenotypes are classified in relation to the objective flux achieved relative to the wild type simulation: wild type phenotype (WT), reduced relative to wild type phenotype (R), and lethal (L).</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s12.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e135" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Table S10</title><p>Biomass functions. Stoichiometric coefficients for all biomass components accounted for to simulate growth in this study are presented under three growth conditions: photoautotrophic, heterotrophic, and mixotrophic.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s13.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e141" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Table S11</title><p>Constants for calculations. The basic cellular parameters assumed for calculations in this study and the derived conversion factors (see <bold>Dimensional and effective photon flux conversion factor derivation</bold> in the <bold>Supplementary Methods</bold>) are presented.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s14.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e153" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>SBML Model</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s15.xml" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="xml"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e156" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Review Process File</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-s16.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Harish Nagarajan for his critical assessment of this work. This research was supported by the Office of Science (Biological and Environmental Research), US Department of Energy, Grant DE-FG02-07ER64496 (to JP and KS-A), New York University Abu Dhabi Research funds (to KS-A), and Institute Sponsored Research funds from the Dana-Farber Cancer Institute Strategic Initiative (to CCSB). RLC was supported by the National Science Foundation IGERT training Grant DGE0504645, and EFYH was supported by the Jane Coffin Childs Memorial Fund for Medical Research.</p><p><italic>Author contributions</italic>: RLC wrote the manuscript and developed the light-modeling approach. RLC and AM reconstructed the metabolic network and performed model simulations and analysis. LG, YS and TH performed transcript verification experiments and associated computational analyses. EFYH and SB performed genome functional annotation. WF performed bioreactor growth experiments. B&#x02205;P, JAP, and KS-A designed the study.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Akkerman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wijffels</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Photobiological hydrogen production: photochemical efficiency and bioreactor design</article-title>. <source>Int J Hydrogen Energy</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1208</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baroli</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamane</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niyogi</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Zeaxanthin accumulation in the absence of a functional xanthophyll cycle protects <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> from photooxidative stress</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>992</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12671093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barta</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tibbitts</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bula</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of light emitting diode characteristics for a space-based plant irradiation source</article-title>. <source>Adv Space Res</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11537060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feist</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hannum</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herrgard</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Quantitative prediction of cellular metabolism with constraint-based models: the COBRA Toolbox</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>727</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17406635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tymoczko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stryer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Biochemistry</source>. New York, USA: W.H. Freeman</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bjorn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Photobiology: The Science of Life and Light</source>. Dordrecht, Netherlands: Springer</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bohne</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Linden</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Regulation of carotenoid biosynthesis genes in response to light in <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic></article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1579</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12401216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Flux balance analysis of primary metabolism in <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Syst Biol</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19128495</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Regenberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>In silico aided metabolic engineering of Saccharomyces cerevisiae for improved bioethanol production</article-title>. <source>Metab Eng</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>102</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16289778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cahoon</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Timko</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>yellow-in-the-dark mutants of <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> lack the CHLL subunit of light-independent protochlorophyllide reductase</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>559</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10760244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Covert</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Regulation of gene expression in flux balance models of metabolism</article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source>
<volume>213</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11708855</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dent</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haglund</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niyogi</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Functional genomics of eukaryotic photosynthesis using insertional mutagenesis of <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>137</volume>: <fpage>545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15653810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Desplats</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mus</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cuine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Billon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cournac</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peltier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Characterization of Nda2, a plastoquinone-reducing type II NAD(P)H dehydrogenase in <italic>chlamydomonas</italic> chloroplasts</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>284</volume>: <fpage>4148</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19056727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Drapier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rimbault</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vallon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wollman</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choquet</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Intertwined translational regulations set uneven stoichiometry of chloroplast ATP synthase subunits</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>3581</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17660748</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jamshidi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vo</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Srivas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Global reconstruction of the human metabolic network based on genomic and bibliomic data</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>104</volume>: <fpage>1777</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17267599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dubertret</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gerard-Hirne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tr&#x000e9;moli&#x000e8;res</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Importance of trans-&#x00394;3-hexadecenoic acid containing phosphatidylglycerol in the formation of the trimeric light-harvesting complex in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>829</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>836</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Durot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bourguignon</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schachter</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genome-scale models of bacterial metabolism: reconstruction and applications</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>164</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19067749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Feist</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krummenacker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Broadbelt</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hatzimanikatis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A genome-scale metabolic reconstruction for <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 MG1655 that accounts for 1260 ORFs and thermodynamic information</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17593909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dragone</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Light regime characterization in an airlift photobioreactor for production of microalgae with high starch content</article-title>. <source>Appl Biochem Biotechnol</source>
<volume>161</volume>: <fpage>218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20221863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Funke</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kovar</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Intracellular carbonic anhydrase is essential to photosynthesis in <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> at atmospheric levels of CO<sub>2</sub>. Demonstration via genomic complementation of the high-CO2-requiring mutant ca-1</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>114</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9159949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gianchandani</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chavali</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Papin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The application of flux balance analysis in systems biology</article-title>. <source>Wiley Interdiscip Rev Syst Biol Med</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>372</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20836035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Giroud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eichenberger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Lipids of <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic>. Incorporation of [14C]acetate, [14C]palmitate and [14C]oleate into different lipids and evidence for lipid-linked desaturation of fatty acids</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Giroud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eichenberger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Lipids of <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic>. Analysis of molecular species and intracellular site(s) of biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>595</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Greenbaum</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Energetic efficiency of hydrogen photoevolution by algal water splitting</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source>
<volume>54</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19431729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leverentz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silkowski</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanchez-Serrano</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Lipid hydroperoxide levels in plant tissues</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>
<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10944149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blankenship</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The light intensity dependence of protochlorophyllide photoconversion and its significance to the catalytic mechanism of protochlorophyllide reductase</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>
<volume>398</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8977114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Posewitz</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prochnik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spalding</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Novel metabolism in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> through the lens of genomics</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>190</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17291820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guschina</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Lipids and lipid metabolism in eukaryotic algae</article-title>. <source>Prog Lipid Res</source>
<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>160</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16492482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Witman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <source>The Chlamydomonas Sourcebook: Introduction to Chlamydomonas and Its Laboratory Use</source>. Amsterdam, Netherlands: Academic Press</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title><italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> as a model organism</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11337403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hegemann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marwan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Single photons are sufficient to trigger movement responses in <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic></article-title>. <source>Photochem Photobiol</source>
<volume>48</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>106</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hemschemeier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Melis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Happe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Analytical approaches to photobiological hydrogen production in unicellular green algae</article-title>. <source>Photosynth Res</source>
<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19291418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hills</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roscoe</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Synthesis of Structural and Storage Lipids by the ER</source>. Berlin/Heidelberg: Springer</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sommerfeld</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghirardi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Posewitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seibert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Darzins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Microalgal triacylglycerols as feedstocks for biofuel production: perspectives and advances</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>54</volume>: <fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18476868</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Winter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tramper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mur</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wijffels</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Efficiency of light utilization of <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> under medium-duration light/dark cycles</article-title>. <source>J Biotechnol</source>
<volume>78</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10725536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kajikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamato</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kohzu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shoji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fukuzawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A front-end desaturase from <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> produces pinolenic and coniferonic acids by omega13 desaturation in methylotrophic yeast and tobacco</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16267098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <source>New Fatty Acids, Oxylipins and Volatiles in Microalgae</source>, PhD Thesis, G&#x000f6;ttingen: Mathematisch-naturwissenschaftliche Fakult&#x000e4;ten, Georg-August-Universit&#x000e4;t G&#x000f6;ttingen</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lemaire</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guillon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Le Marechal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keryer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miginiac-Maslow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Decottignies</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>New thioredoxin targets in the unicellular photosynthetic eukaryote <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>101</volume>: <fpage>7475</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15123830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Levskaya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chevalier</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tabor</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>ZB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lavery</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scouras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ellington</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marcotte</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Voigt</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Synthetic biology: engineering <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> to see light</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>438</volume>: <fpage>441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16306980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mahadevan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The effects of alternate optimal solutions in constraint-based genome-scale metabolic models</article-title>. <source>Metab Eng</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>264</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14642354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Manichaikul</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghamsari</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hom</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balaji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chavali</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salehi-Ashtiani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Papin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Metabolic network analysis integrated with transcript verification for sequenced genomes</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19597503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prochnik</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vallon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karpowicz</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Witman</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Terry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salamov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fritz-Laylin</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marechal-Drouard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanderfoot</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spalding</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kapitonov</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lindquist</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> genome reveals the evolution of key animal and plant functions</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>318</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17932292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herrgard</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Connecting extracellular metabolomic measurements to intracellular flux states in yeast</article-title>. <source>BMC Syst Biol</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19321003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Montagud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fernandez de Cordoba</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Urchueguia</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Reconstruction and analysis of genome-scale metabolic model of a photosynthetic bacterium</article-title>. <source>BMC Syst Biol</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21083885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Teko</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mitsui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanazawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Four Na&#x0002b;/H&#x0002b; exchanger isoforms are distributed to Golgi and post-Golgi compartments and are involved in organelle pH regulation</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>280</volume>: <fpage>1561</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15522866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oberhardt</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Papin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Applications of genome-scale metabolic reconstructions</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>320</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19888215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Orth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>What is flux balance analysis?</article-title>
<source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20212490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Fed-batch culture of Escherichia coli for L-valine production based on in silico flux response analysis</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source>
<volume>108</volume>: <fpage>934</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21404266</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Polle</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanakagiri</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Melis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>tla1, a DNA insertional transformant of the green alga <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> with a truncated light-harvesting chlorophyll antenna size</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>
<volume>217</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12721848</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vo</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>An expanded genome-scale model of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 (iJR904 GSM/GPR)</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>R54</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12952533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Remacle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baurain</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cardol</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matagne</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name> (<year>2001a</year>) <article-title>Mutants of <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> deficient in mitochondrial complex I: characterization of two mutations affecting the nd1 coding sequence</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>
<volume>158</volume>: <fpage>1051</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1060</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11454754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Remacle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duby</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cardol</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matagne</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name> (<year>2001b</year>) <article-title>Mutations inactivating mitochondrial genes in <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic></article-title>. <source>Biochem Soc Trans</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>442</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11498005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Riekhof</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Annotation of genes involved in glycerolipid biosynthesis in <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic>: discovery of the betaine lipid synthase BTA1Cr</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>242</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15701786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Salvador</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bogorad</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Light-regulated and endogenous fluctuations of chloroplast transcript levels in <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic>. Regulation by transcription and RNA degradation</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8220443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shimizu-Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huq</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tepperman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A light-switchable gene promoter system</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1041</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12219076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smart</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Selman</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Isolation and characterization of a <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> mutant lacking the gamma-subunit of chloroplast coupling factor 1 (CF1)</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>5053</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1833630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Spalding</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spreitzer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ogren</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Carbonic anhydrase-deficient mutant of <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardii</italic> requires elevated carbon dioxide concentration for photoautotrophic growth</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>268</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16663206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Spolaore</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joannis-Cassan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Isambert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Commercial applications of microalgae</article-title>. <source>J Biosci Bioeng</source>
<volume>101</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16569602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Witman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <source>The Chlamydomonas Sourcebook: Organellar and Metabolic Processes</source>. Amsterdam, Netherlands: Academic Press</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marek</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spalding</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>A photorespiratory mutant of <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>93</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16667440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tatsuzawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takizawa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Fatty acid and lipid composition of the acidophilic green alga <italic>Chlamydomonas</italic> sp</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>598</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>601</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A protocol for generating a high-quality genome-scale metabolic reconstruction</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20057383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Weers</surname><given-names>PMM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gulati</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Growth and reproduction of <italic>Daphnia galeata</italic> in response to changes in fatty acids, phosphorus, and nitrogen in <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic></article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1584</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1589</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yashodhara</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Umakanth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pappachan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choo</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Omega-3 fatty acids: a comprehensive review of their role in health and disease</article-title>. <source>Postgrad Med J</source>
<volume>85</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19329703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Contents of the <italic>i</italic>RC1080 metabolic network reconstruction. (<bold>A</bold>) Compartmentalized network diagram. The full genome-scale metabolic network is depicted, denoting compartments. A high-resolution diagram without compartment labels is also available (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>). (<bold>B</bold>) Global transcript verification status. The graph shows the distribution of transcripts accounted for in the network categorized by their verification status. Color codes correspond to the noted percentage of transcript sequence verified experimentally. For example, 42&#x00025; of transcripts in the network were verified experimentally by 100&#x00025; sequence coverage. (<bold>C</bold>) Latent VLCPUFA pathway diagram. Blue nodes represent metabolites included in <italic>i</italic>RC1080, and orange nodes represent metabolites not included in <italic>i</italic>RC1080, hypothesized to be absent in <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic>. Green edges represent enzyme activities accounted for in our functional annotation, and the red edge represents the VLCFA elongase missing from our annotation and hypothesized to have been lost in <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic>'s evolution. This pathway diagram also demonstrates the detail of the high-resolution network diagram (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-f1"/></fig><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Experimental transcript verification by subsystem. The graph summarizes transcript verification status (see Materials and methods and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary information</xref> for details) for 30 of the 76 gene-associated subsystems of <italic>i</italic>RC1080. Identical analysis for the full complement of 76 subsystems is also available (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>). The <italic>x</italic> axis corresponds to the percentage of subsystem-associated transcripts that were experimentally verified to the extent noted by the color code.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-f2"/></fig><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Analysis of light spectra. (<bold>A</bold>) Activity and irradiance spectra. The top graph displays activity spectra for photon-utilizing reactions included in <italic>i</italic>RC1080. The abbreviated reactions are defined as follows: VITD3, vitamin D<sub>3</sub> synthesis; OPSIN, rhodopsin photoisomerase; PCHLD, both protochlorophyllide photoreductase and divinylprotochlorophyllide photoreductase; PSI, photosystem I; PSII, photosystem II. The <italic>y</italic> axis for the activity spectra is the fraction of maximum-measured activity with respect to each noted reaction. Four of the eleven sample irradiance spectra (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>) are depicted with <italic>y</italic> axes set as the percentage of total visible photon flux at each wavelength (<italic>x</italic> axis). Effective spectral bandwidths are denoted by vertical dashed lines color coded to match the activity spectra for each reaction. (<bold>B</bold>) Prism reaction derivation. The photon flux from wavelengths <italic>a</italic> to <italic>b</italic> is normalized by the total visible photon flux from 380 to 750 nm to yield the effective spectral bandwidth coefficient <italic>C</italic>. The coefficients for each range are compiled into a single prism reaction for a given light source, representing the composition of emitted light as defined by photon-utilizing metabolic reactions. Equation variables are defined at top.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-f3"/></fig><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Photosynthetic model simulation results. (<bold>A</bold>) O<sub>2</sub> photoevolution under solar light. Simulated (blue line) and experimentally measured (green dots) O<sub>2</sub> evolution are compared. (<bold>B</bold>) Photosynthetic growth under red LED light. Simulations were performed using the 653-nm prism reaction, and experimentally grown culture was exposed to 660 nm LED light. Simulated (blue line) and experimentally measured (green dots) growth are compared. (<bold>C</bold>) Efficiency of light utilization. The minimum photon flux required for maximum-simulated growth (bottom), biomass yield (middle), and energy conversion efficiency (top) are presented for 11 light sources derived from measured spectra and for the designed growth-efficient LED.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-f4"/></fig><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Distributions of randomly sampled distances from experimental measurements. (<bold>A</bold>) O<sub>2</sub> photoevolution under solar light. (<bold>B</bold>) Photosynthetic growth under red LED light. (<bold>C</bold>) Photosynthetic growth under white incandescent light. All three distance distributions result from 10 000 unbiased sampling results in which random prism reactions were generated with the same total metabolically active photon flux as the given light source. Each distribution is depicted in 25 equal-sized bins. The red dot in each plot is placed over the bin in which the distance of the reported simulation result for the given light source falls; the vertical placement of each red dot indicates the number of randomly sampled distances within the same bin that are less than that of the reported result.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="msb201152-f5"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Lipid pathway reconstruction properties in <italic>i</italic>RC1080 in comparison to other metabolic network reconstructions</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="6" align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">Reconstructions<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>i</italic>RC1080 <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">[<italic>i</italic>NB305] <italic>C. reinhardtii</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>i</italic>Syn669 <italic>Synechocystis</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>i</italic>MM904 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>i</italic>AF1260 <italic>E. coli</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">Recon 1 <italic>Homo sapiens</italic></th></tr></thead><tfoot valign="top"><tr><th colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><sup>a</sup>Values are the fraction of lipid metabolites in each network that account for each property, when applicable.</th></tr><tr><th colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><sup>b</sup>Gene transcripts (can be duplicated across lipid classes).</th></tr><tr><th colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><sup>c</sup>Lipid pathway reactions (non-transport).</th></tr><tr><th colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><sup>d</sup>Lipid metabolites (unique lipids).</th></tr></tfoot><tbody valign="top"><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Ketoacyl lipid chemical properties</italic><sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Backbone molecule</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.94</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Stereochemical numbering</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.60</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.85</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Acyl-chain length</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.72</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.90</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.91</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;C=C number</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.72</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.75</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.91</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;C=C positions</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.80</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.42</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.91</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;E&#x02013;Z stereoisomerism</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.80</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.50</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.42</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Fatty acyls</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;G<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">64</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">7</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">13</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">32</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">26</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;R<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">167</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">41</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">71</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">108</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">139</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">233</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;M<sup>d</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">104</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">21</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">55</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">55</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">95</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">137</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Glycerolipids</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;G<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">40</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">18</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;R<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">292</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">12</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;M<sup>d</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">135</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">2</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">7</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Glycerophospholipids</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;G<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">47</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">8</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">46</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">22</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;R<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">126</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">5</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">7</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">52</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">227</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;M<sup>d</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">56</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">3</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">102</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Sphingolipids</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;G<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">8</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">21</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">54</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;R<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">10</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">63</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">79</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;M<sup>d</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">6</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">31</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">59</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Sterol lipids</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;G<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">22</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">32</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;R<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">34</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">3</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">49</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">156</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;M<sup>d</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">26</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">22</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">105</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Prenol lipids</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;G<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">37</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">15</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">9</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">16</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;R<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">59</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">5</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">53</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">17</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">20</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;M<sup>d</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">43</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">4</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">42</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">15</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">17</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Total lipids</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;G<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">218</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">11</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">37</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">158</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">64</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">367</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;R<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">688</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">55</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">134</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">301</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">386</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">582</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;M<sup>d</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">370</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">33</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">106</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">131</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">221</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">368</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>