<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Braz J Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Braz. J. Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bjm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">bjm</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Brazilian Journal of Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1517-8382</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1678-4405</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Microbiologia</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24031293</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3768479</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1517-838220080004000020</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1517-838220080004000020</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Industrial Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Identification of an antifungal metabolite produced by a potential biocontrol Actinomyces strain A01</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Cai Ge</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Wei Cheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Ji Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Hui Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor2"><sup>**</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Ting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>De Liu</surname><given-names>Wen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Plant Pathology, China Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing 100094</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Institute of Plant and Environment Protection, Beijing Academy of Agriculture and Forestry Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing 100097</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><sup>*</sup>Corresponding Author. Mailing address: Institute of Plant and Environment Protection, Beijing Academy of Agriculture and Forestry Sciences, Beijing 100097, China. Phone: +86 10 51503337, Fax: +86 10 51503899. E-mail: <email>liuwccn@yahoo.com.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><sup>**</sup>Departament of Plant Pathology, China Agricultural University, Beijing 100094, China. Phone: +86 10 62733018; Fax: +86 10 62733532. E-mail: <email>wanghm69@cau.edu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Oct-Dec</season><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>39</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>701</fpage><lpage>707</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>20</day><month>2</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Sociedade Brasileira de Microbiologia</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>All the content of the journal, except where otherwise noted, is licensed under a <underline>Creative Commons License</underline></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Actinomyces strain A01 was isolated from soil of a vegetable field in the suburb of Beijing, China. According to the morphological, cultural, physiological and biochemical characteristics, and 16S rDNA sequence analysis, strain A01 was identified as <italic>Streptomyces lydicus</italic>. In the antimicrobial spectrum test strain A01 presented a stable and strong inhibitory activity against several plant pathogenic fungi such as <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic>, <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic>, <italic>Monilinia laxa</italic>, etc. However, no antibacterial activity was found. In pot experiments in greenhouse, the development of tomato gray mold was markedly suppressed by treatment with the fermentation broth of the strain A01, and the control efficacy was higher than those of Pyrimethanil and Polyoxin. A main antifungal compound (purity 99.503%) was obtained from the fermentation broth of strain A01 using column chromatography and HPLC. The chemical structural analysis with U V, IR, MS, and NMR confirmed that the compound produced by the strain A01 is natamycin, a polyene antibiotic produced by <italic>S. chattanovgensis, S. natalensis, and S. gilvosporeus</italic>, widely used as a natural biological preservative for food according to previous reports. The present study revealed a new producing strain of natamycin and its potential application as a biological control agent for fungal plant diseases.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Streptomyces lydicus</italic></kwd><kwd>natamycin</kwd><kwd>fungal plant disease</kwd><kwd>biological control</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Plant diseases caused by fungi are one of the major reasons for causing agricultural losses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>). Gray mold disease, caused by the fungus <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic>, has now become a limiting factor in the vegetable production in many areas of China. The disease used to be and is still being mainly controlled by chemical fungicides, such as aminobenzimidazoles, phthalimide, and carbamates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>). However, resistance has been found in <italic>B. cinerea</italic> to several of these chemicals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>). Furthermore, long term application of chemicals have caused serious food and environment pollutions, and brought attention to the search for alternative measures in controlling plant fungal diseases.</p><p>The development and application of microbial agents is one of the alternative measures. Several <italic>Streptomyces</italic> strains that suppressed the growth of <italic>B. cinerea</italic> were shown to produce antibiotic compounds such as phosphazomyzin, albopeptin B, tautomycin, tautomycein, and ezomycin S (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>). The diverse chemical structures of these metabolites would reduce the chance for pathogens to develop resistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>). In addition, the searching for antimicrobial metabolites has also been spurred on by the possibilities that they could be developed into new classes fungicides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>). In the present study, we report a study on the extraction and identification of the metabolic substance of actinomyces strain A01 and its antifungal spectrum and the control efficacy to tomato gray mold under greenhouse conditions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Strains</title><p>Actinomyces strain A01 was isolated from the soil of vegetable field in Beijing suburb by the Institute of Plant and Environment Protection, Beijing Academy of Agriculture and Forestry Sciences (IPEP-BAAFS), and has been deposited in the Chinese General Microbiological Collection Centre (Beijing, China) as strain CGMCC No.1653. Fungal pathogens, <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>vasinfectum</italic>, <italic>F. oxysporum f.sp. niveu, F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>conglutinans</italic>. <italic>B.cinerea</italic>, <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic>, <italic>Cladosporium fulvum</italic>, <italic>Exserohilum turcicum</italic>, <italic>Alternaria solani</italic>, <italic>Alternaria mali</italic>, <italic>Monilinia laxa and Colletotrichum capsici</italic> were provided by IPEP-BAAFS. The bacterial strains, <italic>Agrobacterium rhizogenes, Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv. <italic>lachrymans</italic>, <italic>Bacillus cereus, Xanthomonas vesicatoria</italic> and <italic>Ralstonia solanacearum</italic>, were obtained from Department of Plant Pathology, China Agricultural University. And the yeast strain <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> (ACCC No. A20063) was obtained from Agricultural Culture Collection of China.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of the antibiotic fermentation broth of strain A01</title><p>Strain A01 was cultured on GAOs no. 1 agar slant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>) at 28&#x000b0;C for 2-wk. The mature spores were washed from the slant with sterilized distilled water and diluted into the suspension in the concentration of 10<sup>6</sup> spores mL<sup>-1</sup>. Two mL of this suspension was then inoculated into a 500 mL Erlenmeyer flask containing 100mL fermentation medium (dextrose 2 g, soybean meal 2 g, soluble starch 0.5 g, peptone 0.5 g, corn steep liquor 0.25 g, (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> 0.25 g, MgSO<sub>4</sub> 7H<sub>2</sub>O 0.025 g, K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> 0.002 g, NaCl 0.4 g, CaCO<sub>3</sub> 0.2 g, tap water 100 mL) and incubated at 28&#x000b0;C on a rotary shaker at 180 rpm for 96 h. The fermented broth was centrifuged at 5,000 g, 4&#x000b0;C for 15 min, and the supernatant was filtered using a 0.45-&#x003bc;m-pore-size membrane filter (Millipore). The filtrate was collected as the antibiotic sample.</p></sec><sec><title>Bioassay of the antimicrobial activity</title><p>For determining the antimicrobial spectrum, spore suspensions from pathogenic fungi were prepared according to the method described by Soares <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>) as follows. Plant pathogenic fungi were cultured on PDA slants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>) at 25&#x02013;28&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02013;7 d. The fungal spores were harvested by washing with 5 mL sterilized distilled water and diluted into the suspension in the concentration of 10<sup>6</sup> spores mL<sup>-1</sup>. About 200 &#x003bc;l of the spore suspension was then inoculated onto a PDA plate (9 cm in diameter). The plant pathogenic bacteria inoculated on beef peptone agar slants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>), <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> on PDA, were cultured at 28&#x000b0;C for 2 d, and then washed up and diluted into the suspension in the concentration of 10<sup>4</sup> CFU mL<sup>-1</sup> with sterile physiological salt solution (0.85% NaCl) and 5 mL of the suspension was mixed into 100 mL molten PDA at 45&#x000b0;C. 30 mL of the mixture was poured into a Petri dish (9 cm in diameter) to give a solid plate. Three wells (7 mm in diameter) were prepared in each seeded agar plate and each well was filled with 100 &#x003bc;l of the antibiotic fermentation broth of strain A01. The plates were incubated at 25&#x000b0;C for 2 d. The diameter of the inhibition zones were measured with a vernier caliper. Each treatment had three replications.</p><p>For estimating the antifungal activity of the bioactive extracts dissolved in organic solvents, the paper disc agar diffusion bioassay modified from the method of Valgas <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>) was used. The sterile filter paper disk (10 mm in diameter) was saturated with the bioactive extract solution, and then dried up. Repeat this three times. The paper disk treated with bioactive solution was placed on the surface of a seeded agar plate prepared as described above. The clear inhibition zone around the paper disk was measured after incubation for 2 d at 25&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Evaluation of the control effect in greenhouse</title><p>Autoclaved soil (121&#x000b0;C for 2 h) was mixed with peat moss (1:1) and placed into 5 &#x000d7; 9 &#x000d7; 12 cm plastic pots. Two germinated tomato seeds (<italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic> Mill. cv. Zhongshu No.6) were planted into each pot and grown in a greenhouse at 25 &#x000b1; 2&#x000b0;C under natural light. The experiment included four treatments: 1) 1:5 dilution of the filtrate from fermented broth of strain A01; 2) chemical fungicide Pyrimethanil (Qinggyuanbao Biotech Ltd., Inner Mongolia, China) in the concentration of 500 &#x003bc;g mL<sup>-1</sup>; 3) wettable powder of the fungicide Polymyxin (Yanbian Chunlei Biopharmcieuticals Ltd., China) in the concentration of 30 &#x003bc;g mL<sup>-1</sup>; and 4) water as the negative control. 45 tomato plants for each treatment and three replicates were performed.</p><p>Each of the solutions was sprayed on the surface of tomato plants at the first bloom stage. While the surface of the leaves become dry, the plants were sprayed with the spore suspension (10<sup>6</sup> spores mL<sup>-1</sup>) of <italic>B. cinerea</italic>, and then were placed in an enclosed plastic chamber in which the humidity was kept at 100% for 48 h. Plants were then incubated at 22&#x000b0;C in the greenhouse until symptoms appeared on leaves of the control plants. The disease rate and disease index was surveyed based on the criteria given by Bioassay Division of Institute for the Control of Agrochemicals, Ministry of Agriculture, China (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Taxonomic determination of strain A01</title><p>For the morphological characterization, strain A01 was cultured on GYM agar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>) and oatmeal agar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>) at 28&#x000b0;C for 7 d, and observed using a microscope (Nikon ECLIPSE TE2000-U, Japan). Cultural characteristics were determined by growing the strain on 6 media namely GAOs no.1 agar, starch agar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>), GYM agar, oatmeal agar, Bennett&#x02019;s agar, and nutrient agar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>) plates at 28&#x000b0;C for 2 wk to observe mycelia color and diffusible pigments. The physiological and biochemical characteristics were tested using the media and methods described by Ruan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>) and Shirling &#x00026; Gottlieb (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>).</p><p>The 16S rDNA sequence of strain A01 was analyzed using the method of Hopwood <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>). The PCR was carried out using the universal bacterial 16S rDNA primers and the PCR product was sequenced directly with the Taq DyeDeoxy Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit (Biosystem, INC, USA). Electrophoresis and data collection was performed with an automated DNA Sequencer (model 377, Applied Biosystems, USA). The 16S rDNA sequence was assembled and blasted against sequences in the GenBank database to determine the identity.</p></sec><sec><title>Purification and chemical characterization of the bioactive substance</title><p>The fermented broth of strain A01 was mixed with 100% ethanol (1:1, v/v) and placed at 4&#x000b0;C for 2 h. The mixture was then stirred up and centrifuged at 5,000 g for 20 min. The supernatant was concentrated at 45&#x000b0;C under vacuum. The concentrate was adsorbed into macroporous resin D4006 (Chemical factory of Nankai University, Tianjin, China) and then eluted seriatim with deionized water, 50% methanol and 80% ethanol at a rate of 0.5 mL min<sup>-1</sup>. The eluent were collected into tubes in fractions of 5 mL with a BSZ-100 automatic fraction collector (Shanghai Huxi Analytical Instrumentation Factory, Shanghai). After being bio-assayed using the paper disc agar diffusion method with <italic>B. cinerea</italic> as the indicator, the active fractions were combined and concentrated under vacuum at 45&#x000b0;C, then diluted with twice volume of methanol:water (7:3, v/v) and separated again by using a 26.0 mm &#x000d7; 400 mm chromatography column of 200 mesh silica gel (Beijing Chemical Reagent Co., Beijing, China) with the mobile phase consisting of chloroform-methanol-water (2:3:1, v/v/v). The eluent was collected, concentrated and bio-assayed again. The active fractions were finally separated by a cycled preparative HPLC (Japan Analytical Industry Co., Ltd., Japan) with C18 reverse phase column (LC-9101-JAIGEL-ODS, Japan), using the mobile phase of 70% methanol (Fisher, USA) at a rate of 3 mL min<sup>-1</sup>, and monitored at 305 nm with a UV detector (JAI UV 3702, Japan). The fractions corresponding to each absorption peak were collected separately with a fraction collector (JAI FC-206, Japan) and bio-assayed. The main active fraction was picked out as the terminal sample and concentrated with a SpeedVac centrifuging concentrator (Thermo SPD1010, USA). The purity of the concentrate was examined using analytical HPLC (LC-10AT, Shimadzu Corporation, Japan) with analytical C18 reverse phase column.</p><p>The chemical structure of the terminal antimicrobial compound was determined with spectroscopy methods. The nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) analysis was performed using a Bruker AVANCE DRX-500 NMR spectrometer (Bruker Instruments Inc., Germany) with N, N-dimethylformamide (d-DMF) as a solvent. High resolution FT-mass spectrometry was conducted using a 9.4T Apex Q-FT-MS spectrometer (Bruker Instruments Inc., Germany) under the following conditions: capillary 4000 v, dry gas 4.0 L/s, ion source temperature 180&#x000b0;C, scan range 300&#x02013;2000 amu, syringe pump 1.5 mL min<sup>-1</sup>. The infrared spectrum within 4000 cm<sup>-1</sup>&#x02013; 400 cm<sup>-1</sup> was measured using a Tensor 27 Nicolet spectrometer (Bruker Instruments Inc., Germany), and the ultra-violet spectrum within 190&#x02013;400 nm using a UV-VIS 3010 spectrophotometer (Hitachi Ltd., Japan).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The experiment data of the antimicrobial activities <italic>in vitro</italic> and control efficacies to tomato gray mold in greenhouses were analyzed using SPSS 13.0 for Windows.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>The antimicrobial spectrum of A01</title><p>The result of mycelial growth inhibition assay showed that the fermented broth of strain A01 presented a strong inhibitory activity against all of the 14 plant pathogenic fungi and one yeast <italic>S. cervisia</italic>e tested in the experiment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). The average diameter of inhibition zones for the pathogens (about 4.0 cm) was greater than that for the yeast (about 3.0 cm). Especially the inhibition zone for the pathogens <italic>M. laxa</italic> and <italic>E. turcicum</italic> reached respectively up to 4.8 cm and 4.7 cm. However, no antibacterial activity was found against the tested bacteria.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Antifungal activities of fermentation broth of strain A01.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathogens</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average inhibition diameter (cm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f. sp. <italic>vasinfectum</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30&#x000b1; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f. sp. <italic>niveum</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13&#x000b1; 0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic>. f. sp. <italic>conglutinans</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.47&#x000b1; 0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> (on grape)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30&#x000b1; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> (on tomato)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.03&#x000b1; 0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> (on eggplant)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50&#x000b1; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pyricularia oryzae</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00&#x000b1; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cladosporium fulvum</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40&#x000b1; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Exerphilum turcicum</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63&#x000b1; 0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternaria solani</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50&#x000b1; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Monilinia laxa</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.77&#x000b1; 0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternaria mali</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07&#x000b1; 0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Colletotrichum capsici</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.10&#x000b1; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97&#x000b1; 0.09</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>The control effect in greenhouse</title><p>Five days after being inoculated with <italic>B. cinerea</italic>, the plants treated with Pyrimethanil and water were wilted, some leaves were chlorotic, covered with gray mold in some surface areas, and fall off. While the negative control plants were severely diseased, there was a reduction in the level of severity in the plants treated with this fungicide (about 80 vs 45 disease index, <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). However, all plants died 10 days after treatment in both cases. In contrast plants sprayed with Polyoxin and the fermented broth of strain A01 had much lower levels of disease incidence than control plants (about 100 vs 35, respectively) and lower disease severities (about 80 vs 15). Both the fungicide and the filtrate provided about 85% disease reduction.</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Biocontrol effects of fermentation broth of strain A01 against tomato gray mold in greenhouse.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Days after treatment</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disease rate<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-1">*</xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disease index<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-1">*</xref></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control efficacy</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4&#x000b1; 0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.5&#x000b1; 0.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.7&#x000b1; 0.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.4&#x000b1; 0.82</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyrimethanil (500 &#x003bc;g mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.9&#x000b1; 0.71</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.1&#x000b1; 0.65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.9&#x000b1; 0.20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.7&#x000b1; 0.46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polyoxin (30 &#x003bc;g mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5&#x000b1; 0.27</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">e</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3&#x000b1; 0.38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.9&#x000b1;1.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5&#x000b1; 0.58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fermentation broth</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.1&#x000b1; 0.57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1&#x000b1; 0.52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7&#x000b1; 0.26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0&#x000b1; 0.87</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf2-1"><label>*</label><p>The data are the average of three replicates &#x000b1; SE. Data in the same column followed by the same letter are not significantly different (P &#x0003c;0.05) according to analysis of variance.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Taxonomic classification of strain A01</title><p>The cultural, biochemical and physiological characteristics of strain A01 are typical properties of genus <italic>Streptomyces</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">Table 4</xref>). A 1,270 bp 16S rDNA partial sequence of strain A01 was determined. The DNA sequence was deposited in GenBank under accession no.EF532323. A standard nucleotide-nucleotide BLAST search (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>) against the GenBank database using this sequence showed that there is the highest homology in the 16S rDNA sequence between strain A01 and <italic>S. lydicus</italic> Y15507.1. According to the polyphasic studies, strain A01 was identified as <italic>S. lydicus</italic>.</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Cultural characteristics of strain A01 on different media.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agar media</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aerial mycelium</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substrate mycelium</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soluble pigments</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAOs no.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white/gray</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yellow</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">light yellow</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bennett&#x02019;s</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">light gray</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">brown</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">light yellow</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nutrient</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ + +</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gray</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">light brown</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GYM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ + +</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">light gray</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">brown</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">yellow</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oatmeal</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gray</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">light brown</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">light brown</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Starch</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">white /gray</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">brown</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">light yellow</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib>Note: +++, very well; ++, well.</attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Physiological and biochemical characteristics of strain A01.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gram stain</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrate reduction</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melanin production</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>S production</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citrate acidolysis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Degradation of :</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gelatin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Starch</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellulose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Esculin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth on sole carbon sources:</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fructose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mannose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maltose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rhamnose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xylose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arabinose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sorbose</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth at:</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1% NaCl</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3% NaCl</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5% NaCl</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7% NaCl</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib>Note: +, positive reaction; -, negative reaction.</attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Purification and structure elucidation of the antifungal compound</title><p>The results of the bioassay showed that the active constituents were mainly collected from the mobile phase of 80% ethanol in the case of the macroporous resin separation and the adjacent fractions of the eluate of chloroform-methanol-water (2:3:1, v/v/v) from the silica gel column. The active fractions resulted in 6 peaks on the first HPLC separation spectrum, and the fraction corresponding to the peak appearing at the elution time of 57.399 min was identified as the active one. The active fraction was separated again by second HPLC. A fraction with higher activity was obtained as the terminal constituent, which corresponded to the peak at the elution time of 38.399 min on the last HPLC spectrum. Only one peak was detected for the terminal constituent by analytical HPLC, which revealed that the constituent contained a single compound. The relative area of the peak suggested a purity up to 99.503% for the compound, sufficiently meeting the requirement for structural analysis. The terminal active constituent was dried in a vacuum into white powder that was partially soluble in N, N-dimethylformamide (DMF), dimethyl sulphoxide (DMSO), pyridine, acetic acid with water, methanol or ethanol with water, but insoluble in acetone, chloroform, diethyl ether, ethyl acetate, and water.</p><p>The UV spectrum showed that the active compound dissolved in methanol-water presented four typical absorbance peaks at wavelengths 281 nm, 291 nm, 305 nm and 319 nm, which is the typical characteristic of conjugated polyene chemicals. In the IR spectrum, the peaks at &#x003bd;&#x0003e;3000 cm<sup>-1</sup> indicated that there is a typical carboxyl-structure; the &#x003bd;=1716 cm<sup>-1</sup> peak revealed a conjugated ester; the &#x003bd;=1570 cm<sup>-1</sup> peak corresponded to a primary amine; and the &#x003bd;=1270&#x02013;1150 cm<sup>-1</sup> peaks showed the existence of different C-O-. The molecular weight 665 and the molecular formula C<sub>33</sub>H<sub>47</sub>NO<sub>13</sub> of the antibiotic compound of strain A01 were deduced by high resolution FT &#x02013; mass spectroscopy (M+Na, m/z 688.2938, calculated 688.2940) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). In the <sup>1</sup>H-NMR spectrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>), the hydrogen on the carboxyl- was neutralized in the solvent DMF, causing the disappearance of peak &#x003b4;=12and the presence of two solvent peaks of &#x003b4;=3 and 8 at the same time; the group of peaks next to &#x003b4;=6 represented the hydrogen bonded on the conjugated ester, and the group of peaks around &#x003b4;=5 presented a &#x02013;OH. In the <sup>13</sup>C-NMR spectrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>), the peaks of &#x003b4;=180 and 165 are indicative of the existence of carboxyl and ester groups, the peak of &#x003b4;=130 was produced by polyethylene, and the most intensive peak was given by the solvent DMF. In addition, COSY, TOCSY, DEPT, NOE, HMBC and HMQC spectrometry were also conducted on the compound. Based on the analysis of NMR data and other chemical characteristics, the antibiotic compound of A01 turned out to have the same structure as natamycin as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>High resolution FT &#x02013; mass spectrum of the bioactive compound of strain A01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bjm-39-701-g001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><sup>1</sup>H NMR spectrum of the bioactive compound of strain A01 recorded at <sup>1</sup>H-500MHz and 25&#x000b0;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bjm-39-701-g002"/></fig><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><sup>13</sup>C NMR spectrum of the bioactive compound of strain A01 recorded at <sup>13</sup>C-500MHz and 25&#x000b0;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bjm-39-701-g003"/></fig><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The structure of the bioactive compound of strain A01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bjm-39-701-g004"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Actinomycetes are major producer of pharmaceuticals and agricultural pesticides due to its ability to produce antibiotics. Among the 10,000 antimicrobial active compounds produced by microorganisms, over 50% were from Actinomycete (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>). Many <italic>S. lydicus</italic> strains have been reported to produce different types of secondary metabolites, such as Chandramycin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>), Lydicamycin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>), Ganefromycin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>), and Streptolydigin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>). <italic>S. lydicus</italic> WYEC108 has been studied extensively for agricultural applications in recent years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>). It is produced commercially to control soil-borne and leaf surface diseases in turf and greenhouse crops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>). WYEC108 produces chitinase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>), which functions synergistically with several antibiotics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>) to kill other fungi.</p><p>In this study, strain A01 presented a strong antifungal effect <italic>in vitro</italic> and effectiveness in controlling tomato gray mold in pot experiments in greenhouse. On the basis of morphological, cultural, physiological and biochemical characteristics, and 16S rDNA sequence analysis, the strain was identified to be <italic>S. lydicus</italic>. It could produce high antifungal substance by liquid fermentation. The chemical structural analysis with UV, IR, MS, and NMR confirmed that the main antifungal compound produced by A01 is natamycin.</p><p>Natamycin is a macrolide polyene antifungal drug, which is widely used for the treatment of fungal keratitis and also in the food industry to prevent mold contamination of cheese and other nonsterile foods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>). Now, it has been used as a natural biological preservative and anti-microbial additive for food in more than 30 countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>). Up to now, the antibiotic was reported to be produced by <italic>S. chattanovgensis, S. natalensis, and S. gilvosporeus</italic>. To the best of our knowledge, no documented record indicated that the antibiotic natamycin was produced by <italic>S. lydicus</italic>, and there is no systematic report on the use of natamycin to control plant fungal diseases.</p><p>Our research results revealed that the antibiotic natamycin can be produced by <italic>S. lydicus</italic>. This provided a new producing microorganism resource for natamycin. Furthermore, the bioactive compound was proved having a broad antifungal spectrum to plant pathogenic fungi. The findings from this study suggest the potential of using natamycin as a biocontrol agent for plant fungal diseases. Further evaluations are needed for the biocontrol efficiency to plant diseases in the fields.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>This research was jointly supported by the National Natural Scientific Foundation of China (No.30671346), Beijing Natural Scientific Foundation (No.6072010), and Beijing Municipal Science &#x00026; Technology Program (D0706005000091 and D0706005040231).</p><sec><title>RESUMO</title><sec><title>Identifica&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de um metab&#x000f3;lito antif&#x000fa;ngico produzido pela cepa Actinomyces A01</title><p>A cepa Actinomyces A01 foi isolada do solo de um campo agr&#x000ed;cola no sub&#x000fa;rbio de Beijing, China. De acordo com as caracter&#x000ed;sticas morfol&#x000f3;gicas, culturais, fisiol&#x000f3;gicas e bioqu&#x000ed;micas, e an&#x000e1;lise da sequ&#x000ea;ncia 16S rDNA , a cepa A01 foi identificada como <italic>Streptomyces lydicus</italic>. Nos testes de espectro antimicrobiano, a cepa A01 apresentou atividade inibit&#x000f3;ria intensa e est&#x000e1;vel contra v&#x000e1;rios fungos patog&#x000ea;nicos para plantas, como <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic>, <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic>, <italic>Monilia laxa</italic>, etc. Entretanto, n&#x000e3;o foi encontrada atividade antibacteriana. Em experimentos em estufas, o desenvolvimento do fungo cinza do tomate foi fortemente inibido pelo tratamento com o caldo de fermenta&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da cepa A01, com efici&#x000ea;ncia superior &#x000e0; do pyremethanil e polyoxin. Por cromatografia em coluna e HPLC, obteve-se um composto f&#x000fa;ngico (pureza 99,503%), cuja an&#x000e1;lise estrutural por UV, IR, MS e NMR revelou ser natamicina, um antibi&#x000f3;tico polienico produzido por <italic>S. chattanovgensis</italic>, <italic>S. natalensis</italic> e <italic>S.gilvosporeus</italic>, empregado como conservador biol&#x000f3;gico natural em alimentos. O presente estudo relata a detec&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de uma nova cepa produtora de natamicina e sua aplica&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o potencial como um agente de controle biol&#x000f3;gico de doen&#x000e7;as f&#x000fa;ngicas em plantas.</p><p><bold>Palavras-chave:</bold>
<italic>Streptomyces lydicus</italic>, natamicina, doen&#x000e7;as f&#x000fa;ngicas em plantas, controle biol&#x000f3;gico</p></sec></sec></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;ffer</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>3389</fpage><lpage>3402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellington</surname><given-names>E.M.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The taxonomy of <italic>Streptomyces</italic> and related genera</article-title><source>Int. J. Syst. Evol. Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>814</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11411701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anton</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aparicio</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of PimR as a positive regulator of pimaricin biosynthesis in <italic>Streptomyces natalensis</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>2004</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>2567</fpage><lpage>2575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15090496</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basilico</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Basilico</surname><given-names>M.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiericatti</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinderola</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization and control of thread mould in cheese</article-title><source>Lett. Appl. Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11412355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Betina</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Bioactive secondary metabolites of microorganisms</source><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Bioassay Division of Institute for the Control of Agrochemicals, Ministry of Agriculture</collab><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>China</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Pesticide guidelines for the field efficacy trials</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Standard Press of China</publisher-name><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>G.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillipson</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borders</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemistry and structure of Ganefromycin</article-title><source>J. Org. Chem</source><year>1993</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>6588</fpage><lpage>6595</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cornelissen</surname><given-names>B.J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Melchers</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strategies for control of fungal diseases with transgenic plants</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1993</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12231724</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whipps</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ousley</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of actinomycete antagonists of a fungal root pathogen</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbial</source><year>1993</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>3899</fpage><lpage>3905</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godfrey</surname><given-names>C.R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Godfrey</surname><given-names>C.R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungicides and bactericides</article-title><source>Agrochemical from natural products</source><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Marcel Dekker Inc</publisher-name><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>340</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanamaru</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimazu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lydicamycin, a new antibiotic of a novel skeletal type. I. Taxonomy, fermentation, isolation and biological activity</article-title><source>J. Antibiot</source><year>1991b</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2026553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hopwood</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bibb</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chater</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieser</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruton</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieser</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lydiate</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrempf</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Isolation of Streptomyces &#x0201c;Total&#x0201d; DNA: Procedure 3. Genetic Manipulation of Streptomyces: A laboratory manual</source><year>1985</year><publisher-loc>Norwich, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Innes Foundation</publisher-name><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>78</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000fc;ster</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outline of a comparative study of criteria used in characterization of the actinomycetes</article-title><source>Intern. Bull. Bact. Nomen. Taxon</source><year>1959a</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>104</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahadevan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Properties of the chitinase of the antifungal biocontrol agent <italic>Streptomyces lydicus</italic> WYEC108</article-title><source>Enzyme Microb. Technol</source><year>1997</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>493</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pridham</surname><given-names>T.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindenfelser</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hesseltine</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benedit</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A selection of media for maintenance and taxonomic study of <italic>Streptomyces</italic></article-title><source>Antibiotics Ann</source><year>1956&#x02013;57</year><fpage>947</fpage><lpage>953</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13425486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tokala</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strap</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salove</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deobald</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morra</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel plant-microbe Rhizosphere interaction involving <italic>Streptomyces lydicus</italic> WYEC108 and the pea plant (<italic>pisum sativum</italic>)</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>2161</fpage><lpage>2171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11976085</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>The basis of taxonomy of actinomycetes</source><year>1977</year><publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Chinese Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>146</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent progress on the research and development in agricultural antibiotic</article-title><source>Plant Prot. Technol. Ext</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>37</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirling</surname><given-names>E.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods for characterization of <italic>Streptomyces</italic> species</article-title><source>Int. J. Syst. Bacteriol</source><year>1966</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>340</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siddhikol</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erbstoeszer</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisblum</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mode of action of streptolydigin</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol</source><year>1969</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4308412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurusiddaiah</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production, purification, and characterization of chandramycin, a polypeptide antibiotic from <italic>Streptomyces lydicus</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agent Chemother</source><year>1984</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>400</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>A.C.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrido</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos de Almeida</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil <italic>streptomycetes</italic> with <italic>in vitro</italic> activity against the yam pathogens <italic>Curvularia eragrostides</italic> and <italic>Colletotrichum gloeosporioides</italic></article-title><source>Braz. J. Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>456</fpage><lpage>461</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Streptomyces WYEC108 as a bio-control agent against Pythium seed rot and emergence damping-off</source><year>1992</year><publisher-loc>Moscow</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Idaho</publisher-name><comment>Ph.D. thesis</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Z.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Research progress on biocontrol of gray mould</article-title><source>Chin. J. Biol. Control</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>135</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valgas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Machado de Souza</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smania</surname><given-names>E.F.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smanis</surname><given-names>Jr. A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening methods to determine antibacterial activity of natural products</article-title><source>Braz. J. Microbial</source><year>2007</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>380</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vining</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Function of secondary metabolites</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Microbial</source><year>1990</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>427</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of <italic>Streptomyces lydicus</italic> WYEC108 as a potential biocontrol agent against fungal root and seed rot</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbial</source><year>1995</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>3119</fpage><lpage>3128</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview on the gray mould (<italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic>) and the control of it in tomato</article-title><source>J. Inner Mongolia Agri. Uni</source><year>2005</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>128</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening of biocontrol strains against vegetable gray mould and their bio-control efficiency</article-title><source>Chin. J. Appl. Environ. Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>