<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ger Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ger Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GMS Ger Med Sci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>GMS German Medical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1612-3174</issn><publisher><publisher-name>German Medical Science GMS Publishing House</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23255877</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3525882</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">000165</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3205/000165</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">Doc14</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">urn:nbn:de:0183-0001653</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Epiploic appendagitis of caecum: a diagnostic dilemma</article-title><trans-title-group xml:lang="de"><trans-title>Appendicitis epiploica des Blinddarms: ein diagnostisches Dilemma</trans-title></trans-title-group></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>Arshad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nazir</surname><given-names>Saima</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hakim</surname><given-names>Suhail Yaqoob</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chalkoo</surname><given-names>Manzoor Ahamad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Surgery, Government Medical College, Srinagar, India</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Minimal Access Surgery, Maulana Azad Medical College, New Delhi, India</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Pathology, Government Medical College, Srinagar, India</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Post Graduate, Department of Community Medicine, Maharishi Markendeshwar Institute of Medical Sciences &#x00026; Research, Mullana, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed: Arshad Rashid, 413 - Old Resident Doctor's Hostel, Maulana Azad Medical College Campus, Bahadur Shah Zafar Marg, New Delhi 110002, India, Phone +91-7838194782, Fax +91-8882988092, E-mail: <email>arsh002@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>Doc14</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>04</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2012 Rashid et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link>). You are free to copy, distribute and transmit the work, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.egms.de/en/journals/gms/2012-10/000165.shtml">This article is available from http://www.egms.de/en/journals/gms/2012-10/000165.shtml</self-uri><abstract><p>Epiploic appendagitis is a rare cause of acute abdomen. Depending on the site of occurrence, it can mimic any cause of acute abdomen or disease of the colon and caecal appendix; making its preoperative diagnosis very difficult. We present here a case of a 7-year-old boy misdiagnosed preoperatively as acute appendicitis and later on, upon surgical exploration, found to have caecal appendagitis. The affected epiploic appendage was removed and the patient had an uneventful recovery. We also review the relevant literature and discuss the measures to overcome this diagnostic dilemma. General surgeons should be aware of this self-limiting disease and consider it as a differential diagnosis of acute abdomen.</p></abstract><trans-abstract xml:lang="de"><p>Appendicitis epiploica oder epiploische Appendagitis ist eine seltene Ursache des akuten Abdomens. Je nach Ort des Auftretens kann sie jede Ursache f&#x000fc;r akuten Unterleibsschmerz oder Erkrankungen des Dickdarms und Appendix vermiformis imitieren, was ihre pr&#x000e4;operative Diagnose sehr schwierig macht. Wir pr&#x000e4;sentieren hier den Fall eines 7 Jahre alten Jungen, bei dem pr&#x000e4;operativ akute Blinddarmentz&#x000fc;ndung diagnostiziert wurde. Beim chirurgischen Eingriff stellte sich dann eine Appendicitis epiploica des Blinddarms als Befund heraus. Der betroffene Appendix epiploica wurde entfernt und der Patient erholte sich ohne besondere Vorkommnisse. Wir geben auch eine &#x000dc;bersicht &#x000fc;ber die relevante Literatur und diskutieren die Ma&#x000df;nahmen, um dieses diagnostische Dilemma zu &#x000fc;berwinden. Allgemeine Chirurgen sollten sich dieser selbstlimitierenden Krankheit bewusst sein und sie als eine Differentialdiagnose bei akutem Abdomen in Betracht ziehen. </p></trans-abstract><kwd-group><kwd>caecal appendagitis</kwd><kwd>appendices epiploicae</kwd><kwd>torsion</kwd><kwd>acute appendicitis</kwd><kwd>epiploic appendagitis</kwd><kwd>acute abdomen</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Appendices epiploicae are small pouches of fat protruding from the serosal surface of colon distributed axially from caecum to rectosigmoid. They are usually arranged in two longitudinal rows along the tinea libera and omentalis and are supplied by one or two arterioles from the vasa recta of the colon, and are drained by a single venule [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>]. Inflammation of these appendices epiploicae, also known as epiploic appendagitis, is a very rare cause of acute abdomen. Depending on the site of occurrence, it can mimic any cause of acute abdomen and can be a source of diagnostic dilemma. Mostly, epiploic appendagitis involves the sigmoid colon and is confused with diverticulitis. If it involves the caecum, it may mimic acute appendicitis or any other cause of acute pain in the right lower abdomen like regional enteritis, ovarian torsion, salpingoophoritis, typhillitis and perityphillitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>]. Epiploic appendagitis occurs usually beyond the fourth decade of life; and only few anecdotal reports of caecal epiploic appendagitis involving young children have been published till date [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]. We present here a case of a 7-year-old boy misdiagnosed preoperatively as acute appendicitis; who was later upon surgical exploration found to have caecal epiploic appendagitis. The relevant literature has been reviewed and we also discuss the measures to overcome this diagnostic dilemma.</p></sec><sec><title>Case description</title><p>A 7-year-old boy, with a body mass index of 28.72 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, presented to the emergency department of a tertiary care hospital in Kashmir with dull pain in the right lower abdomen for one day, progressively increasing in intensity to become sharper, and was accompanied by nausea and anorexia. Patient&#x02019;s temperature was 37.6&#x000b0;C and pulse rate was 104 beats per minute. On abdominal examination, he had guarding, tenderness, and rebound tenderness in the right iliac fossa. The blood counts were unremarkable except for leukocytosis (14,300 cells/&#x000b5;L) with predominance of neutrophils (82%). Urine examination was normal. A presumptive diagnosis of acute appendicitis was made. Ultrasonography of the abdomen documented minimal inter-loop fluid and few dilated gut loops in the right iliac fossa. </p><p>In view of the clinical presentation, the patient was planned for emergency appendectomy. Abdomen was accessed through Mcburney&#x02019;s incision. During surgery, minimal serous fluid was seen in the right paracolic gutter and the appendix was grossly normal. However, an inflamed and gangrenous appendix epilploica was noticed on the caecum (Figure 1 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">(Fig. 1)</xref>). Other neighboring viscera were grossly normal. This gangrenous epiploic appendage was removed and seromuscular inversion was done at that site (Figure 2 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">(Fig. 2)</xref>). Appendectomy was also accomplished. Patient had an uneventful recovery and was discharged on the second postoperative day. Histopathology confirmed the diagnosis of epiploic appendagitis with normal vermiform appendix.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Appendices epiploicae are pedunculated fatty outpouchings lining the colon. Apart from adipose tissue, they also contain blood vessels, and typically have a length of 0.5&#x02013;5 cm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>]. A normal adult human being usually has about 50&#x02013;100 appendices epiploicae increasing progressively in size and number towards the rectosigmoid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>]. Thus, not surprisingly, most cases of epiploic appendagitis are seen on the left side [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>]. Epiploic appendagitis is a very rare occurrence. In a series of 1,320 cases of acute abdominal pain by Golash et al. only eight cases were due to acute epiploic appendagitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. </p><p>Epiploic appendagitis is seldom diagnosed preoperatively due to the lack of pathognomonic clinical features. The clinical features are nonspecific and include sharp pain localized to a part of the abdomen, mostly the left lower quadrant. The site of pain varies with the position of the appendage involved. The temperature may be normal or slightly elevated. White blood cell count is marginally elevated. There can be signs of peritoneal irritation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]. All these nonspecific features coupled with the fact that epiploic appendagitis is a very rare occurrence, make its inclusion in the differential diagnosis of acute abdomen a rarity. In the study by van Breda Vriesman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>], acute appendagitis was included in the clinical differential diagnosis in only two of 49 patients of acute abdomen. </p><p>Mostly involving middle aged people, this disease peaks at 40 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>]. This disease does not seem to have a sex predilection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]; however Szunyogh et al. found an abnormally high incidence in females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>]. Epiploic appendagitis is rarely seen in patients younger than 19 years and is almost unknown in children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]. Only few case reports of epiploic appendagitis involving caecum in children have been published in literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]. One report has suggested obesity as a risk factor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>]. Our patient was a 7-year-old obese boy and is the youngest one to be reported.</p><p>Epiploic appendagitis is often confused with diverticulitis of the sigmoid colon but can mimic acute appendicitis when it occurs on the right side and poses a diagnostic dilemma. It was in 1908 when Briggs first reported a case of torsion of an appendices epiploicae (appendagitis) mimicking appendicitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]. Epiploic appendagitis may also mimic acute cholecystitis if proximal part of transverse colon is involved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>] and ovarian torsion if caecum or sigmoid colon is involved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>].</p><p>A thorough and careful radiological workup may help in resolving this diagnostic dilemma. An ultrasound of the abdomen reveals a hyperechoic, non-compressible pericolonic mass, frequently surrounded by a hypoechoic border [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>]. Since epiploic appendagitis is usually an ischemic event, a lack of central flow is seen on colour Doppler [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>]. Singh AK et al. reported that the most common CT appearance of acute epiploic appendagitis is the presence of 1.5 to 3.5 cm diameter fat-density lesion with surrounding inflammatory changes abutting the anterior wall of the colon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. The colonic wall thickness is usually normal. There may be an associated thickening of visceral peritoneum. The ovoid fat density lesion seen in epiploic appendagitis is generally surrounded by a hyperdense ring and may have a central high intensity dot [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. These findings differentiate it from omental infarction. Magnetic resonance findings include an ovoid fat intensity with a central dot on T1 and T2 weighted images, which possess an enhancing rim with gadolinium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]. The above mentioned findings have been seen in adults and, experience with these investigations is limited in children. But there is no reason why the data from these studies cannot be extrapolated to children.</p><p>The optimum treatment for epiploic appendagitis is a matter of contention. Most of the studies that have been published agree that if diagnosed preoperatively, it should be managed conservatively with antibiotics and analgesics. The symptoms usually resolve within 1 week (mean of 4.7 days) without surgical treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]. The CT findings take about 6 months to get resolved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. If the diagnosis is made upon exploration, the best strategy is to remove the affected appendage and do seromuscular inversion of the affected portion of gut [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]. Laparoscopy offers an excellent option for the management of epiploic appendagitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]. In addition to diagnosing the problem, laparoscopy can also be used to treat it. In our case we performed an open exploration through Mcburney&#x02019;s incision and after resecting the involved appendage, performed a seromuscular inversion of the affected part of the bowel.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, caecal epiploic appendagitis can pose a diagnostic dilemma and may be confused with acute appendicitis. General surgeons should be aware of this self-limiting disease and keep it as a differential diagnosis in acute abdomen. Contrast enhanced CT of the abdomen may prove beneficial in the preoperative assessment of the patient.</p></sec><sec><title>Notes</title><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Parental consent</title><p>A written and informed consent was taken from the father of the patient for this publication since the patient was a minor.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; contribution</title><p>A. Rashid and S.Y. Hakim operated the patient. S. Nazir provided the histological details. A. Rashid, M.A. Chalkoo, S.Y. Hakim had a role in the pre- and postoperative management of the patient. A. Rashid, S. Nazir, M.A. Chalkoo and S.Y. Hakim were involved in literature search and drafted the manuscript. All the authors have read and approved the manuscript.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Vascular loops in the appendices epiploicae; their anatomy and surgical significance, with a review of the surgical pathology of appendices epiploicae</article-title>
<source>Br J Surg</source>
<month>4</month>
<year>1950</year>
<volume>37</volume>
<issue>148</issue>
<fpage>464</fpage>
<lpage>466</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bjs.18003714807</pub-id>
<comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/bjs.18003714807">http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/bjs.18003714807</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15414301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Dockerty</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Waugh</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A clinicopathologic study of the epiploic appendages</article-title>
<source>Surg Gynecol Obstet</source>
<month>10</month>
<year>1956</year>
<volume>103</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>423</fpage>
<lpage>433</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13360649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Christianakis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Paschalidis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Filippou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smailis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chorti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Filippou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cecal epiploica appendix torsion in a female child mimicking acute appendicitis: a case report</article-title>
<source>Cases J</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>8023</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1757-1626-2-8023</pub-id>
<comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1757-1626-2-8023">http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1757-1626-2-8023</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19830045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Appendicitis epiploicae: An unusual cause of acute abdomen in children</article-title>
<source>J Indian Assoc Pediatr Surg</source>
<month>4</month>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>83</fpage>
<lpage>84</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0971-9261.43035</pub-id>
<comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4103/0971-9261.43035">http://dx.doi.org/10.4103/0971-9261.43035</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20011477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Rioux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Langis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Primary epiploic appendagitis: clinical, US, and CT findings in 14 cases</article-title>
<source>Radiology</source>
<month>5</month>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>191</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>523</fpage>
<lpage>526</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcu.1870220212</pub-id>
<comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/jcu.1870220212">http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/jcu.1870220212</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8153333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ur Rehman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Primary epiploic appendagitis: 3 case reports</article-title>
<source>J Pak Med Assoc</source>
<month>1</month>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>61</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>83</fpage>
<lpage>85</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22368911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Organ</surname><given-names>CH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>
<article-title>Epiploic disorders. Conditions of the epiploic appendages</article-title>
<source>Arch Surg</source>
<month>10</month>
<year>1985</year>
<volume>120</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<fpage>1167</fpage>
<lpage>1172</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archsurg.1985.01390340063012</pub-id>
<comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/archsurg.1985.01390340063012">http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/archsurg.1985.01390340063012</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4038060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Golash</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Willson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Early laparoscopy as a routine procedure in the management of acute abdominal pain: a review of 1,320 patients</article-title>
<source>Surg Endosc</source>
<month>7</month>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>882</fpage>
<lpage>885</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00464-004-8866-1</pub-id>
<comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00464-004-8866-1">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00464-004-8866-1</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15920682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Shirokikh</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="ru">Zavorot zhirovogo pridatka poperechnoi obodochnoi kishki, simulirovavshii ostryi kholetsistit.</article-title>
<trans-title>Torsion of an epiploic appendage of the transverse colon simulating acute cholecystitis</trans-title>
<source>Vestn Khir Im I I Grek</source>
<month>12</month>
<year>1972</year>
<volume>109</volume>
<issue>12</issue>
<fpage>102</fpage>
<lpage>103</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4664071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>van Breda Vriesman</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>de Mol van Otterloo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Puylaert</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="nl">Appendagitis epiploica: een onderbelichte zelflimiterende acute buikaandoening.</article-title>
<trans-title>Epiploic appendagitis: an underestimated self-limiting acute abdominal condition</trans-title>
<source>Ned Tijdschr Geneeskd</source>
<month>6</month>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>147</volume>
<issue>23</issue>
<fpage>1113</fpage>
<lpage>1118</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12822521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Fieber</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Appendices epiploicae: clinical and pathological considerations; report of three cases and statistical analysis on one hundred five cases</article-title>
<source>AMA Arch Surg</source>
<month>3</month>
<year>1953</year>
<volume>66</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>329</fpage>
<lpage>338</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archsurg.1953.01260030344008</pub-id>
<comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/archsurg.1953.01260030344008">http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/archsurg.1953.01260030344008</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13030059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Szunyogh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Palla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="hu">Az appendix epiploic&#x000e1;k csavarod&#x000e1;s&#x000e1;r&#x000f3;l 28 eset kapcs&#x000e1;n.</article-title>
<trans-title>Torsion of the epiploic appendicis in 28 cases</trans-title>
<source>Orv Hetil</source>
<month>11</month>
<year>1982</year>
<volume>123</volume>
<issue>48</issue>
<fpage>2953</fpage>
<lpage>2955</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7155568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Torsion of appendices epiploicae and its consequences</article-title>
<source>Am J Med Sci</source>
<year>1908</year>
<volume>135</volume>
<fpage>864</fpage>
<lpage>870</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000441-190806000-00008</pub-id>
<comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/00000441-190806000-00008">http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/00000441-190806000-00008</ext-link></comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Hollerweger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Macheiner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000fc;bner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rettenbacher</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gritzmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title xml:lang="de">Spontane Nekrose einer Appendix epiploica: Sonographische Zeichen in 28 F&#x000e4;llen.</article-title>
<trans-title>Epiploic appendagitis: sonographic findings in 28 cases</trans-title>
<source>Ultraschall Med</source>
<month>8</month>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>23</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>239</fpage>
<lpage>244</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2002-34057</pub-id>
<comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1055/s-2002-34057">http://dx.doi.org/10.1055/s-2002-34057</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12226761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gervais</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhea</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>CT appearance of acute appendagitis</article-title>
<source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>
<month>11</month>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>183</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>1303</fpage>
<lpage>1307</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15505294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Chowbey</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Khullar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Soni</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Baijal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Torsion of appendices epiploicae presenting as acute abdomen: laparoscopic diagnosis and therapy</article-title>
<source>Indian J Gastroenterol</source>
<season>Mar-Apr</season>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>22</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>68</fpage>
<lpage>69</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00129689-200304000-00008</pub-id>
<comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/00129689-200304000-00008">http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/00129689-200304000-00008</ext-link></comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12696833</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Inflamed appendix epiploica of the caecum with grossly normal appendix</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="GMS-10-14-g-001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Detorsion of the appendix epiploica was done. Also seen is the grossly normal vermiform.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="GMS-10-14-g-002"/></fig></floats-group></article>