<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Braz J Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Braz. J. Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bjm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">bjm</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Brazilian Journal of Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1517-8382</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1678-4405</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Microbiologia</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24031380</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3769723</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1517-838220090002000035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1517-838220090002000035</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>General Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Comparative growth of <italic>trichoderma</italic> strains in different nutritional sources, using bioscreen c automated system</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi-Rodrigues</surname><given-names>Bianca Caroline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brochetto-Braga</surname><given-names>M&#x000e1;rcia Regina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tauk-Tornisielo</surname><given-names>S&#x000e2;mia Maria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carmona</surname><given-names>Eleonora Cano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>Valeska Marques</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chaud Netto</surname><given-names>Jos&#x000e9;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>Departamento de Bioqu&#x000ed;mica, Universidade Estadual de Campinas</institution>, <addr-line>Campinas, SP</addr-line>, <country>Brasil</country></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Departamento de Biologia, Universidade Estadual Paulista</institution>, <addr-line>Rio Claro, SP</addr-line>, <country>Brasil</country></aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label><institution>Centro de Estudos Ambientais, Universidade Estadual Paulista</institution>, <addr-line>Rio Claro, SP</addr-line>, <country>Brasil</country></aff><aff id="au4"><label>4</label><institution>Departamento de Bioqu&#x000ed;mica e Microbiologia, Universidade Estadual Paulista</institution>, <addr-line>Rio Claro, SP</addr-line>, <country>Brasil</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><sup>*</sup>Corresponding Author. Mailing address: Dept. of Biology, Institute of Biosciences, Sao Paulo State University - UNESP. 24-A Av., 1515 - Bela Vista, Rio Claro, SP, Brazil. ZiP Code: 13506-900. Phone: 55-19-3526-4135; Fax: 55-19-3526-4136. Email: <email>mrbbraga@rc.unesp.br</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Apr-Jun</season><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>5</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Sociedade Brasileira de Microbiologia</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>All the content of the journal, except where otherwise noted, is licensed under a <underline>Creative Commons License</underline></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><italic>Trichoderma</italic> is one of the fungi genera that produce important metabolites for industry. The growth of these organisms is a consequence of the nutritional sources used as also of the physical conditions employed to cultivate them. In this work, the automated Bioscreen C system was used to evaluate the influence of different nutritional sources on the growth of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> strains (<italic>T. hamatum, T. harzianum, T. viride,</italic> and <italic>T. longibrachiatum</italic>) isolated from the soil in the Jur&#x000e9;ia-Itatins Ecological Station (JIES), S&#x000e3;o Paulo State - Brazil. The cultures were grown in liquid culture media containing different carbon- (2%; w/v) and nitrogen (1%; w/v) sources at 28&#x000ba;C, pH 6.5, and agitated at 150 rpm for 72 h. The results showed, as expected, that glucose is superior to sucrose as a growth-stimulating carbon source in the <italic>Trichoderma</italic> strains studied, while yeast extract and tryptone were good growth-stimulating nitrogen sources in the cultivation of <italic>T. hamatum</italic> and<italic> T. harzianum</italic>.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Bioscreen C system</kwd><kwd>growth</kwd><kwd><italic>Trichoderma</italic></kwd><kwd>tryptone</kwd><kwd>yeast extract</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Fungi, in general, possess diverse abilities that form the basis for industrial research. Fungi are used in medical/ pharmaceutical industries for the manufacture of antibiotics, such as penicillin, produced by <italic>Penicillium chrysogenum</italic>, of enzymes such as amylases, pectinases, and of cellulases produced by <italic>Aspergillus</italic> spp. and by <italic>Trichoderma</italic> spp., as well as in food processing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>).</p><p>Strains of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> can produce a great number of metabolites like antibiotics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>), degrade complex substrates such as cellulose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>), chitin, xylan, and lignin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>), and also possess proteolytic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>). Because of these properties, this genus has high biotechnological potential and is found in almost all ecosystems. Several studies have been carried out on Brazilian soil, such as in the Paranapiacaba Biological Reserve, SP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>). In order to improve knowledge of the biodiversity of soil microbiota, 112 fungi species were isolated and identified from the Jur&#x000e9;ia-Itatins Ecological Station (JIES), S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Brazil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>). These species are currently being studied with respect to their potential for producing macromolecules of interest to medicine and industry. The same authors determined that some of these strains are able to produce enzymes like xylanases and fatty acids including &#x003b3;-linolenic acid (GLA), and observed that the species of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> probably plays an important role in soil nutrient recycling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>).</p><p>Like in the Bioscreen system, turbidimetric methods have been used for studies on microbial growth, providing fast results that are expressed in Optical Density (O.D.) units (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>). This equipment has been used for many purposes in microbiology, including basic research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>), to study the effects of chemical compounds on microbial growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>), for quality control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>), and in pollutant degradation tests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>).</p><p>Considering the importance of a knowledge of the factors that influence the growth of fungi and the biotechnological potential of the genus <italic>Trichoderma</italic>, four strains were chosen (<italic>Trichoderma hamatum, Trichoderma harzianum, Trichoderma viride,</italic> and<italic> Trichoderma longibrachiatum</italic>) and isolated from the Jur&#x000e9;ia-Itatins Ecological Station- SP, Brazil (JIES) soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>), in order to compare their potential to grow in submersed cultures, in the presence of a carbon source (glucose or sucrose) and a nitrogen source (tryptone or yeast extract), by means of the Bioscreen C automated system.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Microorganisms</title><p>Four strains were studied -<italic>T. hamatum, T. harzianum, T. viride,</italic> and<italic> T. longibrachiatum</italic> - that were isolated from the soil (0 - 15 cm deep) in the Banhado Grande area from JIES (LAT 24&#x000ba; 18' to 24&#x000ba; 37' S - LONG 47&#x000ba; 00' to 47&#x000ba; 31' W) in both natural- and secondary vegetation areas. The samples were collected, packaged into plastic bags, transported to the laboratory, and processed immediately to avoid storing them. These samples were sifted using 2.38 mm screens and homogenized. Isolation involved processing the soil samples by saline sterilization, followed by centrifugation, and a series of dilutions. Later, each sample was placed in Petri dishes (<italic>n</italic> = 3) followed by the respective culture medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>).</p><p>These strains are kept in culture medium of MEA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>) (malt extract agar of composition (in w/v): malt extract 2%; bacteriological agar 2%; glucose 2%; peptone 0.1%; yeast extract 2% at pH 4.0 and 4&#x000ba;C), in the laboratory of Centro de Estudos Ambientais (CEA), UNESP, Rio Claro, SP, Brazil.</p><p>The inoculum of these strains was prepared from cultures grown in 7 days at 25&#x000ba;C, with a spore suspension of 10<sup>6</sup> to 10<sup>7</sup> spores.mL<sup>-1</sup> in Tween (T-80) 0.1% (v/v). The counting was done in a Neubauer chamber in NaCl, 0.85% (w/v).</p></sec><sec><title>Cultures</title><p>Strains were cultivated in a Bioscreen C system (Lab Systems Helsinki, Finland), in GY Medium, pH 6.5, with a single carbon source at 2% (w/v) (glucose or sucrose), and a single nitrogen source at 1% (w/v) (tryptone or yeast extract) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>). Accordingly, four different cultures were tested, namely Culture 1a (tryptone + glucose); Culture 1b (tryptone + sucrose); Culture 2a (yeast extract + glucose), and Culture 2b (yeast extract + sucrose). The working volume in the Bioscreen plate was 400 &#x003bc;L/well comprising 360 &#x003bc;L of each culture medium and 40 &#x003bc;L of each spore solution. Temperature was controlled at 28&#x000ba;C and O.D. at 540 nm. Absorbance values of the cell suspensions were automatically read at regular intervals of 2 h, over a 72 h period, and before each measurement, the cell cultures were automatically shaken for 60 seconds. All experiments were performed in quadruplicate. The control tubes contained only the culture medium.</p></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><sec><title>1. Comparative analysis of the strains&#x000b4;growth</title><p>The O.D. values from Bioscreen C were analyzed using spreadsheet software (Microsoft Excel 97) and the averages calculated of the quadruplicates for each type of culture medium. These averages were used to generate growth curves for each type of culture (O.D. 540 nm of the cultures <italic>versus</italic> incubation time). Figures present the data from the average of readings (from quadruplicates) taken from every fourth hour of cultivation.</p><p>Because the spore solution of each strain presented different colors, at time zero, the initial O.D. values were distinctive to each culture in relation to the control culture. This coloration difference (defined here as &#x0201c;specific color influence factor&#x0201d; for each strain) was calculated as follows:</p></sec><sec><title>Color influence = O.D. of each culture (t<sub>0</sub>) - O.D. of the control (t<sub>0</sub>)</title><p>Next, the influence factor specific to each strain was subtracted from all O.D values from 0 to 72 h of each culture, in order to express the real growth of the strains. The analysis of variance (Kruskal-Wallis test, BioEstat 4.0 software) was applied using the data obtained, and confirmed by Dunn <italic>post hoc</italic> test, which was used to verify the significance of the strain&#x02019;s growth compared to the control and among the strains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>). The experimental results were separated into four classes based on the time taken for growth: I) 0 to 18 h, II) 18 to 36 h, III) 36 to 54 h, and IV) 54 to 72 h. The results were analyzed by triangulation of the statistical data with the differences of O.D. per period.</p></sec><sec><title>2. Analyses of the growth of individual strains in different conditions of cultivation</title><p>After excluding the color influence factor, the growth of each strain was calculated as the difference (&#x00394;) between the average values of the O.D. 540 nm, final and initial, taking into account the fact that each average value of O.D. came from the replicas.</p><p>The relative growth of each strain, expressed in percentage, was obtained by comparing the performance of a single strain in every two different cultivation conditions, considering the smallest O.D. value as 100% and the highest O.D. value (greater than 100%) as the highest rate of relative growth among them.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><p>The quick determination of optimal growth of industrially interesting microorganisms, accompanied by the optimum production of economical value molecules, is very important for industry. The method used in this study is neither time consuming nor requires high costs, since it is no longer necessary to perform numerous tests like it is done by the traditional method of dilutions in series, while also enabling determination of optimal growth that is of industrial interest.</p><p>In optimizing the growth of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> sp<italic>.,</italic> some parameters were reported for instance, the 72 h period required for cultivation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref>). As for the temperature, studies on the activity of xylanases from mesophilic fungi showed that, the activity of these enzymes were optimized between 25&#x000ba;C and 30&#x000ba;C for submerse cultures (under constant agitation) and for stationary cultures with solid substrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>).</p><p>Studies also verified the effect of different temperatures on the production of several enzymes, among them carboxymethylcellulases and xylanases, on strains of several species isolated from JIES - SP - Brazil soil, such as <italic>Aspergillus</italic> and <italic>Trichoderma</italic>, and found 28&#x000ba;C to be the optimum temperature and which was the temperature chosen for the cultures prepared in this study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2</xref> show the growth curves of the <italic>Trichoderma</italic> strains studied, obtained by their cultivation from 0 to 72 h and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref> records the results of the statistical analysis.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Growth differences of the strains for culture periods in different culture media. The z values were obtained from variance analysis (Kruskal-Wallis test) and confirmed by Dunn <italic>post hoc</italic> test (BioEstat 4.0 software).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="none"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Culture 1a</bold> (tryptone and glucose)</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Culture 1b</bold> (tryptone and sucrose)</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Culture 2a</bold> (yeast extract and glucose)</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Culture 2b</bold> (yeast extract and sucrose)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0-18h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20-36h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>38-54h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>56-72h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0-18h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20-36h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>38-54h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>56-72h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0-18h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20-36h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>38-54h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>56-72h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0-18h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20-36h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>38-54h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>56-72h</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T hamatum x T. harzianum</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.010</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.082</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.759</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.561</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.525</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.628</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.969</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.737</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.261</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.431</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.400</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.530</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.323</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.346</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. hamatum x T. longibrachiatum</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.916</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.279</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.602</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.800</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.288</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.835</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.333</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.665</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.351</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.118</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.315</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.880</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.697</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.225</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.507</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. hamatum x T. viride</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.133</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.361</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.361</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.361</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.508</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.361</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.894</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.119</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.016</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.343</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.822</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.334</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.862</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.092</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.961</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.907</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. hamatum x controle</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.477</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.814</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.814</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.814</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.025</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.814</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.348</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.572</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.343</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.814</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.276</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.788</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.447</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.545</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.415</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.361</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. harzianum x T. longibrachiatum</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.906</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.197</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.843</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.238</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.073</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.310</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.705</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.696</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.386</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.884</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.481</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.166</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.897</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.853</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.907</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. harzianum x T. viride</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.271</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.279</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.602</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.800</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.293</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.835</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.266</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.149</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.279</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.082</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.392</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.934</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.332</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.764</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.307</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.361</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. harzianum x controle</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.468</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.733</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.056</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.253</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.809</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.289</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.720</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.603</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.606</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.553</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.845</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.388</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.916</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.217</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.761</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.814</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. longibrachiatum x T. viride</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.216</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.082</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.759</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.561</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.220</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.525</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.561</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.665</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.225</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.507</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.834</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.866</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. longibrachiatum x controle</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.561</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.535</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.212</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.015</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.737</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.979</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.015</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.907</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.992</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.697</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.961</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.907</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.750</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.320</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.907</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.907</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. viride x controle</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.655</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.516</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.673</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.472</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.584</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.454</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Criptical z value for p is 2.807</p></fn><fn><p>z values in bold are significant (p&#x0003c;0.05)</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Growth curves (O.D. 540 nm) of <italic>T. hamatum, T. longibrachiatum, T. viride</italic>, and <italic>T. harzianum</italic> in medium containing tryptone and glucose (a) or tryptone and sucrose (b) incubated at 28&#x000ba;C from 0 until 72 h in an automated Bioscreen C system.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bjm-40-404-g001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Growth curves (O.D. 540nm) of <italic>T. hamatum, T. longibrachiatum, T. viride</italic>, and <italic>T. harzianum</italic> in medium containing yeast extract and glucose (a) or yeast extract and sucrose (b) incubated at 28&#x000ba;C from 0 until 72 h in an automated Bioscreen C system.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bjm-40-404-g002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>1. Comparative analysis of the growth of strains</title><p>In the cultures with tryptone and glucose, the growth among the strains of <italic>T. hamatum, T. harzianum, T. viride</italic> and<italic> T. longibrachiatum</italic> was significantly different in all the periods (H<sub>0-18h</sub>=33.36; H<sub>20-36h</sub>=40.21; H<sub>36-54h</sub>=40.90; H<sub>56-72h</sub>=41.83, and p&#x0003c;0.0001). With regard to the differences among the average scores per period (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>), it can be seen when individually analyzed against the control that in <italic>T. hamatum vs. T. viride</italic> and in the strains of <italic>T. hamatum, T. harzianum,</italic> and<italic> T. longibrachiatum</italic>, all presented values of p&#x0003c;0.05 in most periods, and their growth rates were considered highly significant. Besides, <italic>T. hamatum</italic> differed not only from the control but also from <italic>T. viride</italic>, which did not happen with <italic>T. harzianum</italic> and <italic>T. longibrachiatum</italic>; whereas, growth rates of both <italic>T. harzianum</italic> and <italic>T. longibrachiatum</italic> differed only from the control, but not from each other. Thus, it can be concluded from these observations that <italic>T. hamatum</italic> presented the highest value of R and consequently higher growth in all periods (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). This was followed by <italic>T. harzianum</italic> and <italic>T. longibrachiatum</italic> that exhibited similar growth rates, and lastly by <italic>T. viride</italic>, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>R-values of each strain obtained from variance analysis (Kruskal-Wallis test) confirmed by Dunn post hoc test (BioEstat 4.0 software).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="none"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Culture 1a</bold> (tryptone and glucose)</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Culture 1b</bold> (tryptone and sucrose)</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Culture 2a</bold> (yeast extract and glucose)</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Culture 2b</bold> (yeast extract and sucrose)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0-18h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20-36h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>38-54h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>56-72h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0-18h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20-36h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>38-54h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>56-72h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0-18h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20-36h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>38-54h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>56-72h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0-18h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20-36h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>38-54h</bold></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>56-72h</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T hamatum</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">369</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">369</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">369</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">369</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">330</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">369</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">343</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">355.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">369</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">339</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">367.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">369</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">354</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">291</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">288</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. harzianum</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">257</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">271</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">282</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">318</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">284</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">308</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">301.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">315</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">289.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">366</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">369</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. longibrachiatum</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">242</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>T. viride</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>In the cultures with tryptone and sucrose, the growth rates of the strains were also significantly different in all the periods (H<sub>018h</sub>=36.96; H<sub>20-36h</sub>=41.93; H<sub>36-54h</sub>=39.65; H<sub>56-72h</sub>=41.24; and p&#x0003c;0.0001). The differences among the average scores were not significant, especially between <italic>T. hamatum vs T. viride, T. hamatum vs</italic> control, <italic>T. harzianum vs T. viride, T. harzianum vs</italic> control, and <italic>T. logibrachiatum vs</italic> control. These findings can also be confirmed from the growth curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>) in which <italic>T. hamatum</italic> and <italic>T. harzianum</italic> presented similar growth. Nevertheless, <italic>T. logibrachiatum</italic> exhibited a slightly smaller growth rate, while <italic>T. hamatum</italic> and <italic>T. harzianum</italic> showed the highest growth among the strains, followed by <italic>T. logibrachiatum</italic>, which is also confirmed by their respective values of R (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>It can be seen that <italic>T. harzianum</italic> showed a similar growth rate in the cultures containing tryptone with glucose or sucrose. The same was observed of <italic>T. longibrachiatum</italic>, but the growth rate of <italic>T. hamatum</italic> was higher in the medium containing glucose as carbon source than in the one with sucrose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><p>Only few studies use tryptone as growth culture medium for fungi, as it is frequently used as nitrogen source for bacteria growth. Peptone is a similar molecule frequently used for growth of fungi such as <italic>Mucor</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>), <italic>Aspergillus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>), and <italic>Trichoderma</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>). Studies involving <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic> growth report that tryptone is as effective as peptone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>), and is cheaper. Due to the absence of studies related to the growth of fungi using tryptone, it was chosen as the nitrogen source in the present study.</p><p>In our study, differences in the growth rates among the strains could also be noticed (H<sub>0-18h</sub>=30.63; H<sub>20-36h</sub>=40.07; H<sub>3654h</sub>=39.90; H<sub>56-72h</sub>=42.15 and p&#x0003c;0.0001) in the cultures containing yeast extract and glucose. The results of the average scores showed that only <italic>T. hamatum</italic> exhibited a significant difference in the growth in the period of 0 up to 18 h of cultivation. From the 38th hour of cultivation, the growth rate of the strains of <italic>T. hamatum, T. harzianum,</italic> and<italic> T. longibrachiatum</italic> increased (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>), and a significant difference in growth could be seen from that period for <italic>T. harzianum vs T. viride, T. harzianum vs</italic> control, and <italic>T. logibrachiatum vs</italic> control (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). Considering that the average scores of <italic>T. hamatum</italic> exhibited a significant rate in all the periods and also presented the highest value of R (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>), it can be assumed that this strain too presented the highest growth rate among those tested, followed by <italic>T. harzianum</italic> and <italic>T. logibrachiatum</italic>.</p><p>In cultures containing yeast extract and sucrose, different growth rates were also detected among the strains (H<sub>0-18h</sub>=31.38; H<sub>20-36h</sub>=38.97; H<sub>36-54h</sub>=42.12; H<sub>56-72h</sub>=42.42 and p&#x0003c;0.0001). The average scores of <italic>T. hamatum vs T. viride</italic> and the scores of <italic>T. hamatum</italic> and of <italic>T. harzianum</italic> when individually analyzed, against the control, were significantly different in all the periods (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>), while <italic>T. harzianum vs T. longibrachiatum</italic> and <italic>T. harzianum vs T. viride</italic> exhibited significant differences only after 38 h of cultivation. On comparing these data, it can be seen in the <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref> that, from the 38th hour, the growth curve of <italic>T. harzianum</italic> surpassed that of <italic>T. hamatum</italic> and, consequently, the R-value of <italic>T. harzianum</italic> increased in that period too (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>2. Analyses of the growth of each individual strain in different cultivation conditions</title><p>On comparing the cultivation conditions tested here, it can be concluded that in the cultivation of <italic>T. harzianum</italic> there was an increase in the growth rate at approximately the 36th hour in all the conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2</xref>). From this period, the strain started to differ significantly from both <italic>T. viride</italic> (in the cultivation with yeast extract and glucose) and <italic>T. longibrachiatum</italic> (when cultivated in yeast extract and sucrose) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). Analyzing only the nitrogen sources in function of the carbon sources used, it was observed that the growth of <italic>T. harzianum</italic> was 30% higher with yeast extract plus glucose than with tryptone plus glucose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2</xref>). The same pattern was observed with regard to media with sucrose, where the growth with yeast extract was 65% higher than with tryptone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2</xref>). Thus, yeast extract appears to be the best nitrogen source for <italic>T. harzianum</italic>, compared to tryptone, apart from the carbon source used in this study. Studies involving xylanase production indicated that <italic>T. harzianum</italic> is a good producer of xylanases in media containing yeast extract (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>). The comparative analysis of the carbon sources in function of the nitrogen sources showed that in the presence of tryptone, growth of <italic>T. harzianum</italic> in the cultures with glucose was 15% higher than that in sucrose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), while in presence of yeast extract the growth was 10% higher in the cultures with sucrose than in those with glucose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><p>The data above show that yeast extract is better for growth of <italic>T. harzianum</italic>, especially when combined with sucrose, and differs in this respect from <italic>T. viride</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>As expected with all cultures, the growth of <italic>T. hamatum</italic> in glucose was much better than in sucrose, as glucose is a simpler metabolite than sucrose. Considering only the influence of sugar, it can be seen that growth of <italic>T. hamatum</italic> was 40% higher in glucose than in sucrose in presence of tryptone as nitrogen source (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). Likewise, the growth of <italic>T. hamatum</italic> was 45% higher in glucose than in sucrose in the medium with yeast extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). These results indicate that for <italic>T. hamatum</italic> cultivation, glucose is better than sucrose as carbon source, irrespective of the nitrogen source used. Analyzing influence of the nitrogen source on the growth rate of <italic>T. hamatum,</italic> a slightly higher growth (20%) could be observed in yeast extract than in tryptone, when glucose was present in the medium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2</xref>). Almost the same result was detected when sucrose was used as carbon source, in which growth of <italic>T. hamatum</italic> was 15% higher than in yeast extract, indicating that in this strain yeast extract induces a higher growth rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2</xref>).</p><p><italic>T. longibrachiatum</italic> presented similar growth rates in all the cultivation conditions tested here (with small differences ranging from 10 to 15%) which can be observed in both Figures. According to the statistical data, this strain differed from the control only from the 20th hour of growth, and did not differ from <italic>T. viride</italic> in any period. This last strain did not show a growth pattern different from the control or exhibit a significant growth rate. This suggests that for these two strains, <italic>T. longibrachiatum</italic> and <italic>T. viride</italic>, further studies are necessary because the nutritional sources tested here may not be suitable for their cultivation.</p><p>Different carbon sources were also used in analysis of fungi and production of total lipids, as well as &#x003b3;-linoleic acid, maintaining the nitrogen source (yeast extract) constant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>). The results showed a five times higher growth rate in the culture medium containing glucose, compared to that with sucrose.</p><p>Yeast extract has effectively been the best nitrogen source for growing filamentous fungi and is the best inducer for production of different macromolecules, a characteristic also observed, in recent studies, for thermophilic fungi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>). It was confirmed that significant mycelial growth resulted in <italic>T. aureoviride, T. viride,</italic> and<italic> T. harzianum</italic> strains when cultivated in media containing yeast extract and agricultural soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>), this last being a nitrogen source considered very stimulating for production of enzymes , such as proteases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>) and cellulases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>), by <italic>Trichoderma</italic>.</p><p>Studies performed with the Bioscreen C automated system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>) on <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> and <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic> revealed that both of them presented a good growth rate in medium containing yeast extract. In another study using Bioscreen C, the researchers were able to demonstrate that despite belonging to the same species, four strains of <italic>Mucor hiemalis</italic> differed with respect to their capacities for growth with the same carbon-or nitrogen source (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>).</p><p>In our study, other sources of nitrogen were also tested, such as casein, gelatin, and ammonium nitrate, in the presence of glucose or sucrose, but no significant growth rate was observed with any of them (data not shown). Ammonium nitrate has been used as a stimulating agent for synthesis of different enzymes in fungi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>). However, as the ammonium ion and its derivates, in general, tend to behave as enzyme inhibitors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>), and it may have negatively influenced the fungi growth tested here when ammonium nitrate was used in the media.</p><p><italic>Trichoderma</italic> is a fungus used for industrial production of enzymes such as xylanases and glucanases and many other metabolites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>), besides having clinical importance, causing infections, as reported for <italic>T. viride</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>), <italic>T. longibrachiatum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>) and for <italic>T.harzianum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>). Thus, the verification of nutritional parameters for the strains tested in our study is promising for optimizing their biotechnological- and industrial uses.</p><p>Some studies on microorganisms&#x02019; growth compared the Bioscreen automated system and the traditional cultivation method, and many patterns of similarity between them were found. One of these studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>) confirmed that the Bioscreen automated system is a promising and reliable method for several uses in microbiology.</p><p>Considering that the microorganism cultivation in industries must be carried out on large scale for production of innumerable commercially interesting metabolites, our results indicate that the Bioscreen system provides a fast- and economical way to test and optimize growth conditions for further use in such large-scale production.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>Rossi-Rodrigues, B.C was a fellow from the Scholarship Institutional Program in Scientific Initiation from PIBIC/CNPq (Brazilian Research Council) in the S&#x000e3;o Paulo State University (UNESP).</p></ack><sec><title>RESUMO</title><sec><title>Crescimento de linhagens de <italic>Trichoderma</italic> em diferentes fontes nutricionais, empregando o sistema automatizado Bioscreen C.</title><p><italic>Trichoderma</italic> &#x000e9; um dos g&#x000ea;neros de fungos produtores de metab&#x000f3;litos de interesse industrial. O crescimento destes organismos &#x000e9; conseq&#x000fc;&#x000ea;ncia das fontes nutricionais utilizadas, juntamente com as condi&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es f&#x000ed;sicas de cultivo. Neste trabalho, o sistema automatizado Bioscreen C foi utilizado para avaliar a influ&#x000ea;ncia de diferentes fontes nutricionais sobre o crescimento de linhagens de <italic>Trichoderma</italic> (<italic>T. hamatum, T. harzianum, T. viride</italic> e<italic> T. longibrachiatum</italic>) isoladas do solo da Esta&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Ecol&#x000f3;gica da Jur&#x000e9;ia-Itatins (JIES), S&#x000e3;o Paulo - Brasil. Os cultivos foram feitos em meios l&#x000ed;quidos de cultura contendo diferentes fontes de carbono (2%; w / v) e nitrog&#x000ea;nio (1%; w / v) a 28&#x000ba;C, pH 6,5 e agitados a 150 rpm durante 72 h. Os resultados mostraram, conforme esperado, que a glicose &#x000e9; melhor do que a sacarose como fonte de carbono indutora de crescimento das linhagens de <italic>Trichoderma</italic> testadas, enquanto que, o extrato de leveduras e a triptona foram boas fontes de nitrog&#x000ea;nio indutoras de crescimento para os cultivos de <italic>T. hamatum</italic> e<italic> T. harzianum.</italic></p><p><bold>Palavras chave:</bold> Bioscreen C, crescimento,<italic> Trichoderma</italic>, triptona, extrato de leveduras.</p></sec></sec><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez-Barrientos</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arroyo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canton</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nombela</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Applications of flow cytometry to clinical microbiology.</article-title><source>Clin. Microbiol. Rev.</source><year>2000</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10755996</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antal</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manczinger</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szakacs</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tengerdy</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferenczy</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colony growth, in vitro antagonism and secretion of extracellular enzymes in cold-tolerant strains of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> species.</article-title><source>Mycol. Res.</source><year>2000</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>549</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>M.F.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ninomiya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoenlein-Crusius</surname><given-names>I.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efeitos da queimada sobre a micota de solo na Mata Atl&#x000e2;ntica na Reserva Biol&#x000f3;gica do Alto da Serra de Paranapiacaba, SP.</article-title><source>Hoehnea.</source><year>1994</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apsmo</surname><given-names>S.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eijsink</surname><given-names>G.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrolysates from Atlantic c&#x000f3;d (<italic>Gadus morhua L.</italic>) viscera as components of microbial growth media.</article-title><source>Process Biochem.</source><year>2005</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>3714</fpage><lpage>3722</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayres</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayres</surname><given-names>D.l.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>A.A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Biostat 4.0 - Aplica&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es estat&#x000ed;sticas nas &#x000e1;reas de Ci&#x000ea;ncias Biom&#x000e9;dicas.</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Bel&#x000e9;m, PA.</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Sociedade Mamirau&#x000e1;</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>R.L.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dix</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilization of ferulic acid by microfungi from litter and soil.</article-title><source>Transations of the British Mycologial Society.</source><year>1976</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>311</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ca&#x000e7;ais</surname><given-names>A.O.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silveira</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Filho</surname><given-names>E.X.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of xylan-degrading enzymes by a T<italic>richoderma harzianum</italic> strain <italic>Braz</italic>.</article-title><source>J. Microbiol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>32</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>143</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corabi-Adell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Biodiversidade do g&#x000ea;nero Trichoderma (Hypocreales - Fungi) mediante t&#x000e9;cnicas moleculares e an&#x000e1;lise ecofisiogr&#x000e1;fica.</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Rio Claro - Brazil</publisher-loc><publisher-name>(Dr. Tesis. Instituto de Bioci&#x000ea;ncias, Unesp).</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delgado-Jarana</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pintor-Toro</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben&#x000ed;tez</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overproduction of &#x003b2;-1,6-glucanase in <italic>Trichoderma harzianum</italic> is controlled by extracellular acid proteases and pH.</article-title><source>Acta Biochim. Biophys.</source><year>2000</year><volume>1481</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>296</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antagonistic properties of species-groups of <italic>Trichoderma</italic>. 1. Production of non-volatile antibiotics.</article-title><source>Transactions of the British Mycologial Society.</source><year>1971</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>39</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goller</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoisswohl</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parriche</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubicek</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of endoproteolytic dibasic proprotein processing in maturation of secretory in <italic>Trichoderma reesei</italic>.</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>64</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>3202</fpage><lpage>3208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9726860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guiserix</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramdane</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Finielz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michault</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajaonarivelo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Trichoderma harzianum</italic> peritonitis in peritoneal dialysis.</article-title><source>Nephron.</source><year>1996</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8893195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haltrich</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of fungal xylanases.</article-title><source>Bioresour. Technol.</source><year>1996</year><volume>58</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>161</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawksworth</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirsop</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Living resources for biotechnology: filamentous fungi.</source><year>1988</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><fpage>209</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jatinder</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chadha</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimization of medium components for production of cellulases by<italic> Melanocarpus</italic> sp. MTCC3922 under solid-state fermentation.</article-title><source>World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kredics</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manczinger</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antal</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;nzes</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szekeres</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kevei</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro water activity and pH dependence of micelial growth and extracellular enzyme activities of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> strains with biocontrol potencial.</article-title><source>J. Appl. Microbiol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14962129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lisowska</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palexz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dlugonski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microcalorimetry as a possible tool for phenanthrene toxicity evaluation to eukaryotic cells.</article-title><source>Thermochim. Acta</source><year>2004</year><volume>411</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>186</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loeppky</surname><given-names>C.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprouse</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Everett</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Trichoderma viride</italic> peritonitis.</article-title><source>South. Med. J.</source><year>1993</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>798</fpage><lpage>799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6857312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandels</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Wilke</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial sources of cellulose.</article-title><source>Cellulose as a chemical and energy resource.</source><year>1975</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>105</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marois</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonoda</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological control of <italic>Fusarium</italic> crown rot of tomato under field conditions.</article-title><source>Phytopatology</source><year>1981</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>1257</fpage><lpage>1260</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mattila</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x000b4;Boyle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The growth of compact and diffuse variants of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in bovine mastitic and normal whey.</article-title><source>Microbiol. Immunol.</source><year>1988</year><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3264046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>J.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hocking</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An improved medium for the detection of <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic> and <italic>A. parasiticus</italic>.</article-title><source>J. Appl. Bact.</source><year>1983</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6406419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Randhawa</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowshik</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>T.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandhu</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhary</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peptone glucose fluconazole agar, a selective medium for rapid and enhanced isolation of <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> from aqueous suspensions and sputum seeded with <italic>Candida albicans</italic>.</article-title><source>Curr. Sci.</source><year>2005</year><volume>88</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>454</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ridout</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith-Coley</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fractation of extracellular enzymes from a mycoparasitic strain of <italic>Trichoderma harzianum</italic>.</article-title><source>Enzyme. Microb. Technol.</source><year>1988</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>187</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez-Kabana</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>W.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curl</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteolytic activity of <italic>Trichoderma viride</italic> in mixed culture with <italic>Sclerotium rolfsii</italic> n soil.</article-title><source>Can. J. Microbiol.</source><year>1978</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruegger</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tauk-Tornisielo</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atividade da celulase de Fungos isolados do solo da Esta&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Ecol&#x000f3;gica de Jur&#x000e9;ia-Itatins, S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Brasil.</article-title><source>Rev. Bras. Bot.</source><year>2004</year><volume>27</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>211</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinmen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akimoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of eicosapentaenoic acid by <italic>Mortierella</italic> fungi.</article-title><source>J. Am. Oil Chem. Soc.</source><year>1988</year><volume>65</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1455</fpage><lpage>1459</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sivasithamparam</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macnish</surname><given-names>G.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microflora of soil and wheat rhizosfere in a field following fumigation.</article-title><source>Aust. J. Soil Res.</source><year>1987</year><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>498</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Onions</surname><given-names>A.H.S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>The preservation and maintenance of living fungi.</source><year>1983</year><publisher-loc>Norwick</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Page Bros</publisher-name><fpage>51</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tauk-Tornisielo</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Govone</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of Bioscreen C for growth of <italic>Mucor hiemalis</italic> in different carbon and nitrogen sources.</article-title><source>Braz. J. Microbiol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>117</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tauk-Tornisielo</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garlipp</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruegger</surname><given-names>M.J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Attili</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malagutti</surname><given-names>E.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soilborne filamentous fungi in Brazil.</article-title><source>J. Basic Microbiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15678565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tauk-Tornisielo</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Govone</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of Bioscreen C for Growth of <italic>Mucor Hiemalis</italic> in different Carbon and Nitrogen sources.</article-title><source>Braz. J. Microbiol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>117</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Triveni</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamala</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clarification of xanthan gum with extracellular enzymes secreted by <italic>Trichoderma koningii</italic>.</article-title><source>Process Biochem.</source><year>1999</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>53</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tvrzova</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prokop</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navratilova</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullerova</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neca</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a microtiter plate-based method for determination of degradation profile of nitrophenolic compounds.</article-title><source>J. Microbiol. Methods</source><year>2006</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16289394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiater</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szczodrak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pleszczyn&#x000b4;Ska</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pr&#x000f3;chniak</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production and use of Mutanase from <italic>Trichoderma harzianum</italic> for effective degradation of <italic>Streptococcal Mutans</italic>.</article-title><source>Braz. J. Microbiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>146</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>