<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ViewNLM-v2.3.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genomics Inform</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genomics Inform</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GNI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genomics &#x00026; Informatics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1598-866X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2234-0742</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korea Genome Organization</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23613681</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3630384</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5808/GI.2013.11.1.38</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Annotation of Genes Having Candidate Somatic Mutations in Acute Myeloid Leukemia with Whole-Exome Sequencing Using Concept Lattice Analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Kye Hwa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Jae Hyeun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Ju Han</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1">Division of Biomedical Informatics, Seoul National University Biomedical Informatics (SNUBI) and Systems Biomedical Informatics National Core Research Center, Seoul National University College of Medicine, Seoul 110-799, Korea.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding author: Tel: +82-2-740-8920, Fax: +82-2-747-8928, <email>juhan@snu.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2013 by the Korea Genome Organization</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>It is identical to the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>In cancer genome studies, the annotation of newly detected oncogene/tumor suppressor gene candidates is a challenging process. We propose using concept lattice analysis for the annotation and interpretation of genes having candidate somatic mutations in whole-exome sequencing in acute myeloid leukemia (AML). We selected 45 highly mutated genes with whole-exome sequencing in 10 normal matched samples of the AML-M2 subtype. To evaluate these genes, we performed concept lattice analysis and annotated these genes with existing knowledge databases.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>acute myeloid leukemia</kwd><kwd>biolattice</kwd><kwd>concept lattice analysis</kwd><kwd>DNA mutational analysis</kwd><kwd>DNA sequence analysis</kwd><kwd>oncogenes</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Acute myeloid leukemia (AML) is one of the most wellstudied diseases in the genomic research area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. AML occurs usually in middle-aged people and is diagnosed by increasing leukemic myeloblasts in blood over 30% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. AML is a genetically heterogeneous disease, since 1/3 of AML patients have chromosomal rearrangements, like t(8;21) and t(15;17), but other AML patients have normal karyotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. With recent advances of high-throughput genomic technology, a favorable prognosis has been observed with some genetic changes in cytogenetically normal AML [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. These results were reflected by the World Health Organization (WHO) diagnostic criteria; the <italic>NMP1</italic> and <italic>CEBPA</italic> mutations were included in the 2008 revision of these criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The molecular change of AML is considered to be the accumulation of somatic mutations in hematopoietic progenitor cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Next-generation sequencing technology gave us new insights into the clonal heterogeneity of leukemic mutations so that we can make an explanation why some of these mutations are highly reproducible but others are very rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Still, in 30% of cytogenetically normal AML, the genetic causality origin or strongly associated genetic changes have not yet been discovered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><p>With advances of high-throughput technology, discovery of disease-associated genes is growing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. As a consequence, the genetic knowledge databases are growing rapidly. Accordingly, the annotation of candidate causal genes in genetic studies is a very challenging process for researchers. We propose a workflow of the detection of somatic mutation candidates in 10 normal matched AML samples and introduce concept lattice analysis for clustering the samples that have highly mutated genes in common.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Primacy sequence analysis</title><p>We received the fastq files of whole-exome sequencing results of tumor and matched normal sample data of 10 AML patients from the Korea Genome Organization in December 2012. There were no patient-related medical or characteristic data. We aligned the sequencing reads to the human reference genome (hg 19, GRCh37) from USCC by BWA 0.6.2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). To filter the known single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), we used dbSNP bulid 137. We removed PCR duplicates and filtering low-quality SNPs by Samtools 0.1.18 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], Picard 1.68 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], and GATK 2.3.4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. After the filtering process, the SAM file was converted to VCF file by VCF Tools 0.1.10 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. For detecting somatic mutation candidates, we obtained the difference in VCF files between tumor and normal samples. For annotation of these somatic mutation candidates, we used the ANNOVAR tool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Formal concept analysis</title><p>We used formal concept analysis (FCA) for the construction of hierarchical relationships among samples sharing highly mutated genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. FCA is a useful method in conceptual clustering of objects, attributes, and their binary relationship. In FCA, the sets of formal objects and formal attributes together with their relation to each other form a "formal context," which can be represented by a crosstable. In our case, the objects are 10 AML samples, and the attributes are 45 highly mutated genes. We defined the formal context as K = (G, M, I), where G is a set of objects (i.e., samples), M is a set of attributes (i.e., mutated genes), and I &#x02286; G &#x000d7; M is the incidence relations where (g, m) &#x02286; I if object g has attribute m. For A &#x02286; G and B &#x02286; M, we define the operators A' = {m &#x02208; M|gIm for all g &#x02208; A} (i.e., the set of attributes common to the objects in A) and B' = {g &#x02208; G|gIm for all m &#x02208; B} (i.e., the set of objects common to the attributes in B). A pair of (A, B) is a formal concept of k(G, M, I) if and only if A &#x02286; G, B &#x02286; M, A' = B, and A = B'. A is called the extent and B is the intent of the concept (A, B). The extent consists of all objects belonging to the concept while the intent contains all attributes shared by the objects. The concept of a given context is naturally ordered by the subconcept-superconcept relation, defined by (A1, B1) &#x02264; (A2, B2): &#x0003c;=&#x0003e; <italic>A1</italic> &#x02286; <italic>A2</italic> (&#x0003c;=&#x0003e; <italic>B2</italic> &#x02286; <italic>B1</italic>).</p><p>The ordered set of all concepts of the context (G, M, I) is denoted by C(G, M, I) and is called the concept lattice of (G, M, I). We represent the structure of this concept lattice with a Hasse diagram, in which nodes are the concepts and the edges correspond to the neighborhood relationship among the concepts. All concepts above an object label (below the attribute label) include that object (attribute). The top element of a lattice is a unit concept, representing a concept that contains all objects. The bottom element is a zero concept having no object.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Overview of mutations</title><p>We have identified 12,908 somatic mutation candidates in 10 AML sequenced exomes, including 1,281 point mutations, 625 insertion/deletions (Indels) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). The point mutations include 7,483 synonymous single nucleotide variations (SNVs), 4,297 nonsynonymous SNVs, 282 stopgain SNVs, 14 stoploss SNVs, and 5 frameshift substitutions, and the Indels include 247 frame shift insertions, 310 frameshift deletions, and 68 nonframe shifts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). For each patient, the average nonsynonymous mutation count was 429.7 (SD, 97.16).</p><p>About 342 to 665 genes have nonsynonymous somatic mutation candidates at least once in each AML sample (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Recurrent mutated genes were observed in all samples.</p></sec><sec><title>Mutation analysis</title><p>The most frequently mutated genes across all samples were <italic>USP9Y</italic> and <italic>MUC5B</italic>; these genes were mutated in 5 samples. These genes were also highly mutated in each sample; for <italic>USP9Y</italic> genes, it had 6 nonsynonymous mutations in sample 3. We have selected 45 highly mutated genes (1.5%) from 2981 mutated genes. We defined highly mutated genes as genes having 3 or more nonsynonymous mutations in each sample (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). In a comparison of mutations with the COSMIC database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], among 45 highly mutated genes, 21 genes matched to hematopoietic and lymphoid tissue malignancy terms, and 21 genes matched to other cancer types. In 3 genes, there was no matched term in COSMIC (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>).</p><p>We used the concept lattice to construct the hierarchical relationship between the samples that had 45 highly mutated genes. Concept Biolattice analysis is a mathematical framework based on concept lattice analysis for better biological interpretation of genomic data. The top element of a lattice is a unit concept, representing a concept that contains all objects. The bottom element is a zero concept having no object [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. For comparing with the Concept lattice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>), we also performed hierarchical clustering analysis by Ward method. In hierarchical clustering, cluster 1 has 5 samples (nos. 1, 2, 5, 9, and 10), cluster 2 has 2 samples (nos. 4 and 7), and others have 1 sample each (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). We divided the samples into 4 subgroups by interpretation of the concept lattice result (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). Lattice subgroup 1 shared <italic>SYNE1</italic> gene mutation, and samples 3, 4, and 7 were included in this subgroup. Subgroup 2 was comprised of 5 samples (nos. 1, 2, 5, 6, and 9) that had MUC5 gene mutations in common. Samples 10 and 8 could be isolated by the uniqueness of their mutated gene sharing pattern.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we proposed a workflow of matched normal AML exome sequencing analysis and the framework for defining sample subgroups. We observed every sample having a nonsynonymous mutation associated with hematological and lymphoid malignancy genes, but the candidate oncogenes showed diverse characters.</p><p>We selected 45 genes that had 3 or more nonsynonymous mutations and performed hierarchical clustering analysis of the samples by these genes. In classic hierarchical clustering analysis by Ward's method, we could not identify the genetic relationship of those clusters. On the other hand, the result of concept lattice analysis gave us insight into the mutational pattern of each sample.</p><p>In subgroup 1, samples 3, 4, and 7 shared <italic>SYNE1</italic> gene mutations. <italic>SYNE1</italic> gene encodes a spectrin repeat-containing protein expressed in skeletal and smooth muscle and peripheral blood lymphocytes that localizes to the nuclear membrane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. This gene is not a well-known leukemic gene but is observed in some hematological malignancies and other cancer types [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. In glioblastoma, <italic>SYNE1</italic> mutation is significantly correlated with the overexpression of several known glioblastoma survival genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. In the case of sample 3, the <italic>ITGAX</italic> gene, encoding ankyrin repeat domain 18A, was mutated. This gene is well known by the association with leukemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] and lung cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. For sample 4, the possible oncogene is <italic>LAMC3</italic>. <italic>LAMC3</italic> gene encodes laminins, which are the major non-collagenous constituent of basement membrane. <italic>LAMC3</italic> mutations are associated with several cancers, including colon cancer, lung cancer, and melanoma, and candidate tumor suppressor genes in bladder transitional cell carcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. LAMC3 is involved in the phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase.Akt signaling pathway, since it has a role in cell adhesion. The <italic>ANKRD18A</italic> gene is the oncogene candidate for sample 7 and is a novel epigenetic regulation gene in lung cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Therefore, it is possible that the pair relationship of those genes (<italic>ITGAX-SYNE1</italic>, <italic>LAMC3- SYNE1</italic>, and <italic>ANKRD18A-SYNE1</italic>) could contribute together to evolve the leukemic cell transformation.</p><p>The major limitation of our study is that we could not validate the mutation results by Sanger method or deep sequencing. We selected highly mutated genes having 3 mutations or more, but this definition is arbitrary, so we might have lost candidate oncogenes in some patients.</p><p>In this study, we suggest the concept of clustering samples that have diverse mutated genes. AML is very heterogeneous genetic disease. Despite the small number of samples we have studied, the genetic variation patterns were not common for all samples. It could have been better to evaluate more sample data for analysis by clustering analysis.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was supported by the basic science research program through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF), funded by the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology (2012-0000994). This material is based upon work supported by the Korea Genome Organization.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ley</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mardis</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>McLellan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DNA sequencing of a cytogenetically normal acute myeloid leukaemia genome</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>456</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18987736</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hebestreit</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gr&#x000f6;ttrup</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Emden</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Veerkamp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruckert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Leukemia gene atlas: a public platform for integrative exploration of genome-wide molecular data</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e39148</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22720055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f6;wenberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Downing</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>341</volume><fpage>1051</fpage><lpage>1062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10502596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fr&#x000f6;hling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics of myeloid malignancies: pathogenetic and clinical implications</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2005</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>6285</fpage><lpage>6295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16155011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;nen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Racevskis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognostic relevance of integrated genetic profiling in acute myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>1079</fpage><lpage>1089</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22417203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vardiman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arber</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunning</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Borowitz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Porwit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The 2008 revision of the World Health Organization (WHO) classification of myeloid neoplasms and acute leukemia: rationale and important changes</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2009</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>937</fpage><lpage>951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19357394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcucci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Haferlach</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000f6;hner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular genetics of adult acute myeloid leukemia: prognostic and therapeutic implications</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21220609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ley</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McLellan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamprecht</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DNMT3A mutations in acute myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>363</volume><fpage>2424</fpage><lpage>2433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21067377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graubert</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mardis</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomics of acute myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>Cancer J</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>491</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22157292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiu</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gondek</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Keefe</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekeres</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Elson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New lesions detected by single nucleotide polymorphism array-based chromosomal analysis have important clinical impact in acute myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2009</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>5219</fpage><lpage>5226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19770377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jostins</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic risk prediction in complex disease</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>R182</fpage><lpage>R188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21873261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1754</fpage><lpage>1760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Handsaker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wysoker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fennell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Homer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>2078</fpage><lpage>2079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Picard</collab><source>Souceforge.net</source><year>2009</year><date-in-citation>Accessed 2012 Nov 30</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://picard.sourceforge.net/">http://picard.sourceforge.net/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivachenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cibulskis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kernytsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Genome Analysis Toolkit: a Map-Reduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing data</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1297</fpage><lpage>1303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20644199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danecek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Auton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abecasis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Albers</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>DePristo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The variant call format and VCFtools</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2156</fpage><lpage>2158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21653522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakonarson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ANNOVAR: functional annotation of genetic variants from high-throughput sequencing data</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>e164</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20601685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wille</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>Formal Concept Analysis: Mathematical Foundations</source><year>1999</year><publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer Verlag</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bindal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bamford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kok</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Beare</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COSMIC: mining complete cancer genomes in the Catalogue of Somatic Mutations in Cancer</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>D945</fpage><lpage>D950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20952405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BioLattice: a framework for the biological interpretation of microarray gene expression data using concept lattice analysis</article-title><source>J Biomed Inform</source><year>2008</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18093880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stelzer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalah</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><name><surname>Satanower</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nativ</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In-silico human genomics with GeneCards</article-title><source>Hum Genomics</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>717</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22155609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bindal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bamford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COSMIC (the Catalogue of Somatic Mutations in Cancer): a resource to investigate acquired mutations in human cancer</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>D652</fpage><lpage>D657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19906727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masica</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Karchin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation of somatic mutation and expression identifies genes important in human glioblastoma progression and survival</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>4550</fpage><lpage>4561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21555372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Master</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kendall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Limbert</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flow cytometric analysis of membrane CD11b, CD11c and CD14 expression in acute myeloid leukaemia: relationships with monocytic subtypes and the concept of relative antigen expression</article-title><source>Eur J Haematol</source><year>1990</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1689668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>ANKRD18A</italic> as a novel epigenetic regulation gene in lung cancer</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2012</year><volume>429</volume><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23131552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amira</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cancel-Tassin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernardini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochand-Priollet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bittard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression in bladder transitional cell carcinoma by real-time quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction array of 65 genes at the tumor suppressor locus 9q34.1-2: identification of 5 candidates tumor suppressor genes</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2004</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15239131</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Primary sequence analysis pipeline.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-11-38-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Workflow of detection of somatic mutation candidate from exome sequencing of normal matched samples from 10 acute myeloid leukemia.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-11-38-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Distribution of somatic mutation candidates in all samples. NS SNV, nonsynonymous single nucleotide variation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-11-38-g003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Distribution of nonsynonymous somatic mutations in 10 acute myeloid leukemia samples. NS SNPs, nonsynonymous single nucleotide polymorphisms.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-11-38-g004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Concept lattice of 45 genes and 10 acute myeloid leukemia patients having 3 or more nonsynonymous mutations, annotated by COSMIC database. Red rectangles represent annotated hematopoietic and lymphoid tissue malignancy; yellow rectangles represent other cancer type annotated in the COSMIC database.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-11-38-g005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Hierarchical clustering of samples by binarized score of 45 highly mutated gene states.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-11-38-g006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Subgroup analysis by concept lattice. (A) Subgroup 1 shares <italic>SYNE1</italic> mutation in samples 3, 4 and 7. (B) Subgroup 2 shares <italic>MUC5B</italic> mutation in samples 1, 2, 5, 6, and 9. (C) Subgroup 3 sample 8 only has mutated genes, such as <italic>MUC2</italic> and <italic>HELZ2</italic>. (D) Subgroup 4 has sample 10, having only mutated genes, like <italic>MUC6</italic>, <italic>CDH23</italic>, <italic>BRD2</italic>, <italic>OR6V1</italic>, and <italic>DNAH17</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-11-38-g007"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The distribution of somatic mutation candidates in 10 AML samples</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-11-38-i001"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>AML, acute myeloid leukemia; SNP, single nucleotide polymorphism; NS, nonsynonymous; SNV, single nucleotide variation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Classification of genes according to the count of mutations in each sample</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-11-38-i002"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>List of 3 more mutated genes in 10 AML samples</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-11-38-i003"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>a</sup>Genes mutated in 5 samples; <sup>b</sup>Genes mutated in 3 samples; <sup>c</sup>Genes mutated in 2 samples.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of list of 3 more mutated genes with COMIC database</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gni-11-38-i004"/></table-wrap></floats-group></article>