<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21775341</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3203616</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr595</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkr595</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Nucleic Acid Enzymes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Role of tRNA amino acid-accepting end in aminoacylation and its quality control</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Xiao-Long</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gkr595-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Dao-Hai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gkr595-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gkr595-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>Hui-Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gkr595-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>Liang-Liang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gkr595-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eriani</surname><given-names>Gilbert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gkr595-AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>En-Duo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gkr595-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="gkr595-COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="gkr595-AFF1"><sup>1</sup>State Key Laboratory of Molecular Biology, Institute of Biochemistry and Cell Biology, Shanghai Institutes for Biological Sciences, The Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shanghai 200031, China and <sup>2</sup>Architecture et R&#x000e9;activit&#x000e9; de l&#x02019;ARN, Institut de Biologie Mol&#x000e9;culaire et Cellulaire du CNRS, Universit&#x000e9; de Strasbourg, 67084 Strasbourg, France</aff><author-notes><corresp id="gkr595-COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>+86 21 5492 1241</phone>; Fax: <fax>+86 21 5492 1011</fax>; Email: <email>edwang@sibs.ac.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><!--For NAR both ppub and collection dates generated for PMC processing 1/27/05 beck--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>39</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>8857</fpage><lpage>8868</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2011. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Aminoacyl&#x02013;tRNA synthetases (aaRSs) are remarkable enzymes that are in charge of the accurate recognition and ligation of amino acids and tRNA molecules. The greatest difficulty in accurate aminoacylation appears to be in discriminating between highly similar amino acids. To reduce mischarging of tRNAs by non-cognate amino acids, aaRSs have evolved an editing activity in a second active site to cleave the incorrect aminoacyl&#x02013;tRNAs. Editing occurs after translocation of the aminoacyl&#x02013;CCA<sub>76</sub> end to the editing site, switching between a hairpin and a helical conformation for aminoacylation and editing. Here, we studied the consequence of nucleotide changes in the CCA<sub>76</sub> accepting end of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> during the aminoacylation and editing reactions. The analysis showed that the terminal A<sub>76</sub> is essential for both reactions, suggesting that critical interactions occur in the two catalytic sites. Substitutions of C<sub>74</sub> and C<sub>75</sub> selectively decreased aminoacylation keeping nearly unaffected editing. These mutations might favor the regular helical conformation required to reach the editing site. Mutating the editing domain residues that contribute to CCA<sub>76</sub> binding reduced the aminoacylation fidelity leading to cell-toxicity in the presence of non-cognate amino acids. Collectively, the data show how protein synthesis quality is controlled by the CCA<sub>76</sub> homogeneity of tRNAs.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Protein synthesis is a central process in organisms from all three domains of life, providing the link between the genetic information encoded in DNA and functional proteins. This process critically relies on the correct formation of aminoacyl&#x02013;tRNA (aa&#x02013;tRNA) by aminoacyl&#x02013;tRNA synthetase (aaRS) to establish the genetic code through rigorous control of the two-step aminoacylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B2">2</xref>). The amino acid is first activated with ATP to synthesize the aa-AMP intermediate with the release of pyrophosphate; the amino acid moiety of the intermediate is subsequently transferred to the tRNA bearing the cognate nucleotide triplet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B1">1</xref>). Mis-translation arising from disruption in the fidelity of these interactions has profound consequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B3">3</xref>). However, the presence of various types of amino acids and their analogs, and the fact that amino acids only differ in the side chain, greatly challenge the specificity of aaRS. About half of the aaRSs misactivate non-cognate amino acids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B4">4</xref>). To solve this problem, the proofreading (editing) mechanism of aaRS has evolved to hydrolyze the mis-products. Editing can occur at the aa-AMP level (pre-transfer editing) and/or mischarged tRNA level (post-transfer editing), depending on the specific aaRS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B4">4</xref>).</p><p>Leucyl&#x02013;tRNA synthetase (LeuRS), isoleucyl&#x02013;tRNA synthetase (IleRS) and valyl&#x02013;tRNA synthetase (ValRS) belong to the class Ia of aaRSs, characterized by the connective peptide 1 (CP1) and 2 (CP2) in the Rossmann fold nucleotide binding domain where the synthetic active site is located (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B5">5</xref>). The CP1 domain of LeuRS is located 35&#x02009;&#x000c5; away from the Rossmann fold domain and is responsible for post-transfer editing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B7">7</xref>). Recent studies have revealed that <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic>Aquifex aeolicus</italic> and human cytoplasmic LeuRSs (<italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS, <italic>Aa</italic>LeuRS and hcLeuRS) all employ three different pathways (tRNA-independent, tRNA-dependent pre-transfer editing and post-transfer editing), but in different proportions relative to the total editing activity, to remove non-cognate amino acids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B9">9</xref>). Similar results were also found with <italic>E. coli</italic> IleRS and ValRS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B10">10</xref>).</p><p>X-ray crystal structures of LeuRS and tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> in aminoacylation and post-transfer editing states clearly revealed that the tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> main body conformation is indistinguishable between the two states (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B11">11</xref>). However, the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end shifts to the CP1 domain from the aminoacylation active site and is specifically recognized by several conserved residues, including Lys300, Tyr330, Arg344 and Leu327 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B11">11</xref>). Therefore, these residues in CP1 collectively constitute the tRNA entrance pathway in post-transfer editing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B6">6</xref>). <italic>In vitro</italic> studies have shown that the interaction between the Tyr330 and tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> CCA<sub>76</sub>-end is critical for both tRNA-dependent pre-transfer editing and post-transfer editing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B8">8</xref>). However, the role of other crucial resides in editing and their significance <italic>in vivo</italic> are unclear. In addition, the contribution of the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end to the aminoacylation and editing still remains elusive.</p><p>The CCA<sub>76</sub> sequence is conserved at the 3&#x02032;-end of all mature tRNA molecules to function as the site of amino acid attachment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B12">12</xref>). This sequence is gene encoded in <italic>E. coli</italic> and related bacteria or acquired in eukaryotes and maintained by stepwise nucleotide addition by the ubiquitous CCA-adding enzyme (tRNA nucleotidyltransferase, CCase), which is an unusual RNA polymerase that does not use a nucleic acid template for nucleotide addition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B14">14</xref>).</p><p>The CCA<sub>76</sub> sequence is a universal ligand during several critical steps of protein biosynthesis. It is successively recognized by aaRSs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B12">12</xref>), elongation factor (EF-Tu) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B15">15</xref>) and rRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B17">17</xref>). In F. Crick's adaptor hypothesis, the CCA<sub>76</sub> sequence is the ultimate adaptor group that carries the amino acid to the decoding center of the ribosome, whereas at the other end of the molecule, the anticodon triplet is needed to fit with the codon triplet of the mRNA. Because all the tRNAs have to fit to the unique ribosome decoding center, evolution has selected a unique CCA<sub>76</sub> sequence shared by all tRNAs. Additional constraints for CCA<sub>76</sub> conservation result from the interactions with the EF-Tu and the 20 aaRSs. With the later enzymes, the CCA<sub>76</sub> acceptor end is the substrate of two successive reactions starting with the aminoacylation reaction then followed by a proofreading reaction catalyzed in a second catalytic site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B11">11</xref>). A critical conformational change, resulting from the flexibility of the single-stranded CCA<sub>76</sub> sequence, is required to allow transition from the synthetic to the editing site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B11">11</xref>).</p><p>The starting point of the present study was to clarify the role of the ubiquitous CCA<sub>76</sub>-end in the leucine aminoacylation system. Therefore, we generated a series of CCA<sub>76</sub>-end mutants and tested their impact on the aminoacylation and editing reactions catalyzed by <italic>E. coli</italic> LeuRS (<italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS). Furthermore, mutants were generated in the CP1 editing domain of LeuRS in order to disrupt the interaction with the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end during the editing process. The <italic>in vivo</italic> effect of the mutations was then analyzed in a LeuRS-deficient strain in stress conditions under the pressure of elevated concentrations of non-cognate amino acid. Combining <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> results of protein and tRNA mutagenesis showed how life can regulate protein synthesis and control the aminoacylation quality by using the universally conserved sequence.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title><p><sc>l</sc>-leucine, dithiothreitol, NTP, 5&#x02032;-GMP, tetrasodium pyrophosphate, inorganic pyrophosphate, ATP, Tris&#x02013;HCl, MgCl<sub>2</sub>, NaCl, mouse anti-His<sub>6</sub> antibody and activated charcoal were purchased from Sigma (USA). [<sup>3</sup>H]leucine, [<sup>3</sup>H]isoleucine and [&#x003b1;-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP were obtained from Amersham Biosciences (England). <italic>Pfu</italic> DNA polymerase, the DNA fragment rapid purification kit and a plasmid extraction kit were purchased from Biotech Company (China). KOD-plus mutagenesis kit was obtained from TOYOBO (Japan). T4 ligase and restriction endonucleases were obtained from MBI Fermentas. Phusion high-fidelity DNA polymerase was purchased from New England Biolabs (USA). Ni<sup>2+</sup>&#x02013;NTA Superflow was purchased from Qiagen, Inc. (Germany). Polyethyleneimine cellulose plates were purchased from Merck (Germany). Pyrophosphatase was obtained from Roche Applied Science (China). Pyrobest DNA polymerase and the dNTP mixture were obtained from Takara (Japan). Oligonucleotide primers were synthesized by Invitrogen (China). <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) cells were purchased from Stratagene (USA). The <italic>E. coli</italic> KL231 strain [<italic>F<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic>, <italic>leuS31</italic>(ts), <italic>thyA6</italic>, <italic>rpsL120</italic>(strR), <italic>deoC1</italic>] was purchased from the <italic>E. coli</italic> genetic stock center (CGSC, Yale University, USA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B18">18</xref>). T7 RNA polymerase was purified from an overproduction strain in our laboratory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B19">19</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Gene cloning and mutagenesis</title><p>The plasmid pET30a-<italic>EcleuS</italic> encoding <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS with N-terminal His<sub>6</sub>-tag previously constructed by our lab (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B8">8</xref>) was used as the template to construct genes encoding various <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS mutants using KOD-plus mutagenesis kit for the <italic>in vitro</italic> activity measurements. <italic>EcleuS</italic> was amplified, cleaved by NcoI and HindIII and cloned into pTrc99a (pre-cleaved by NcoI and HindIII) to produce pTrc99a-<italic>EcleuS</italic>. The 18 nucleotides encoding His<sub>6</sub>-tag at the N-terminus were incorporated into the forward primer during the construction of pTrc99a-<italic>EcleuS</italic>. The pTrc99a-<italic>EcleuS</italic> construct was used as the template to construct genes encoding various <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS mutants using the KOD-plus mutagenesis kit for the <italic>in vivo</italic> complementation assays in the KL231 strain.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> transcription of tRNAs</title><p>Six DNA fragments covering the T7 promoter and tRNA gene double strands were synthesized by Invitrogen, phosphorylated and ligated into pUC19 (pre-cleaved by EcoRI and BamHI) to construct the plasmid pUC19-tRNA. To prepare the wild-type (WT) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i1.jpg"/></inline-formula> transcript, the forward primer (5&#x02032;-ctgcag<italic>taatacgactcactata</italic>gccgaggtggtgg-3&#x02032;, with T7 promoter sequence in italics) and the reverse primer (5&#x02032;-tggtaccgaggacgggacttgaacccgtaagccctattg-3&#x02032;) were synthesized to amplify the T7 promoter and the gene encoding <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i2.jpg"/></inline-formula> using the Phusion high-fidelity DNA polymerase, which does not add an additional adenosine to the PCR product. The PCR product was separated on a 2% agarose gel, extracted by phenol/chloroform and precipitated in the presence of cold ethanol and 0.3&#x02009;M NaAc (pH 5.2). The T7 <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription was carried out at 37&#x000b0;C in a 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;l reaction mixture containing 40&#x02009;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 8.0), 22&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1&#x02009;mM spermidine, 5&#x02009;mM DTT, 0.5% Triton X-100, 60&#x02009;ng&#x02009;&#x003bc;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> tDNA template, 5&#x02009;mM ATP, 5&#x02009;mM CTP, 5&#x02009;mM GTP, 5&#x02009;mM UTP, 0.8&#x02009;U&#x02009;&#x003bc;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> ribonuclease inhibitor, 20&#x02009;mM GMP and 500&#x02009;U&#x02009;&#x003bc;l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> T7 RNA polymerase. One hour later, 2&#x02009;U of pyrophosphatase was added to remove the pyrophosphate for 30&#x02009;min, and then 5&#x02009;U of DNase I (RNase I free) was added and incubated for 1&#x02009;h to digest the transcription template. The transcript was then loaded into a 15% PAGE&#x02013;8M Urea gel of 1-mm thickness and 40&#x02009;cm length, and the gel was run at constant 25&#x02009;W for 10&#x02009;h to carefully remove any non-specific bands. The tRNA was cut from the gel and eluted with 0.5 M NaAc (pH 5.2) at room temperature, ethanol precipitated at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C after phenol/chloroform extraction two times and dissolved in 5&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. The tRNA was denatured at 80&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;min and slowly cooled down to 30&#x000b0;C. The tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> mutants were prepared by the same procedure, except that the different reverse primer was synthesized and used in preparing the DNA template.</p></sec><sec><title>Protein expression and purification</title><p>The WT LeuRS (<italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS) and its mutants were produced by transformation of <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) cells with the corresponding plasmids. A single colony from each of the transformants was chosen and cultured in 500&#x02009;ml of 2&#x000d7; YT medium at 37&#x000b0;C. When the cells were grown to mid-log phase (A<sub>600</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.6), IPTG (isopropyl-1-thio-&#x003b2;-<sc>d</sc>- galactopyranoside) was added to a final concentration of 0.2&#x02009;mM, and cultivation continued for 6&#x02009;h at 22&#x000b0;C<italic>.</italic> The proteins were purified by Ni<sup>2+</sup>&#x02013;NTA chromatography, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B8">8</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Aminoacylation, mis-aminoacylation and deacylation</title><p>The kinetic constants of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS for WT tRNA and its variants were tested in a reaction mixture containing 100&#x02009;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.8), 30&#x02009;mM KCl, 12&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.5&#x02009;mM dithiothreitol, 4&#x02009;mM ATP, 40&#x02009;&#x003bc;M [<sup>3</sup>H]leucine, 0.25&#x02013;12&#x02009;&#x003bc;M <italic>Ec</italic>tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> and 5&#x02009;nM <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS at 37&#x000b0;C. Mis-aminoacylation assays were carried out at 37&#x000b0;C in a reaction mixture containing 100&#x02009;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.8), 30&#x02009;mM KCl, 12&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.5&#x02009;mM dithiothreitol, 4&#x02009;mM ATP, 5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M <italic>Ec</italic>tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>, 40&#x02009;&#x000b5;M [<sup>3</sup>H]isoleucine and 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;M <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS. Preparation of mischarged Ile-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> was carried out in a similar system with mis-aminoacylation, except that 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;M <italic>Ec</italic>tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> and 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;M <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS-T252E were used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B20">20</xref>). Hydrolytic editing assays of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS or its mutants were performed at 37&#x000b0;C in 100&#x02009;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.5), 30&#x02009;mM KCl, 12&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.5&#x02009;mM dithiothreitol and 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;M [<sup>3</sup>H]Ile-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>, and the reactions were initiated with 5&#x02009;nM enzyme. Nine microliter aliquots of the reaction solution were added to Whatman filter pads and quenched with cold 5% trichloroacetic acid (TCA) at various time intervals. The pads were washed three times for 15&#x02009;min each with cold 5% TCA and then three times for 10&#x02009;min each with 100% ethanol. The pads were dried under a heat lamp. The radioactivities of the precipitates were quantified with a scintillation counter (Beckman Coulter).</p></sec><sec><title>Charging plateau measurements</title><p>Charging plateau measurements of transcripts were performed in 40&#x02009;&#x000b5;l reaction mixtures each containing 100&#x02009;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.8), 30&#x02009;mM KCl, 12&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.5&#x02009;mM dithiothreitol, 4&#x02009;mM ATP, 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;M [<sup>3</sup>H]leucine (15&#x02009;Ci/mmol), 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;M tRNA (&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>, &#x00394;C<sub>75</sub>A<sub>76</sub>, &#x00394;C<sub>74</sub>C<sub>75</sub>A<sub>76</sub>, &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75A, &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75U and &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75G) and 100&#x02009;nM <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS at 37&#x000b0;C. Aliquots of 9&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of the reaction solution were removed at various time intervals, quenched on Whatman filter pads and processed as mentioned in the procedures above. The blank experiment without tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> was performed under the same conditions. In another control experiment, RNase I (final 0.25&#x02009;U/&#x000b5;l) was added to the aliquot at various time intervals to digest the aminoacylation product and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for another 5&#x02009;min. The plateau value of WT tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> was &#x0003e;1400&#x02009;pmol/A<sub>260</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>AMP formation</title><p>In the editing Nva reaction of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS, AMP formation was measured in a reaction mixture containing 100&#x02009;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.8), 30&#x02009;mM KCl, 12&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 5&#x02009;mM dithiothreitol, 5&#x02009;U&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> pyrophosphatase, 3&#x02009;mM ATP, 20&#x02009;nM [&#x003b1;-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP and 15&#x02009;mM Norvaline (Nva) in the presence or absence of 5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> or its variants. The reaction was initiated by the addition of 0.2&#x02009;&#x000b5;M <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS or its mutants and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C. Aliquots (1.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;l) were quenched in 6&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of 200&#x02009;mM NaAc (pH 5.0). The quenched aliquots (1.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;l each) were spotted in duplicate on polyethyleneimine cellulose plates pre-washed with water. Separation of Nva-[<sup>32</sup>P]AMP, [<sup>32</sup>P]AMP and [<sup>32</sup>P]ATP was performed by developing thin layer chromatography (TLC) on polyethyleneimine cellulose plates in 0.1&#x02009;M NH<sub>4</sub>Ac and 5% acetic acid. The plates were visualized by phosphorimaging, and the data were analyzed using Multi Gauge Version 3.0 software (FUJIFILM). The gray densities of [<sup>32</sup>P]AMP spots were compared with the gray density of known [<sup>32</sup>P]ATP concentrations. Rate constants were obtained from graphs of [<sup>32</sup>P]AMP formation plotted against time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B8">8</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>KL231 complementation assay</title><p>Competent KL231 cells were electro-transformed with various plasmids, including pTrc99a (negative control), pTrc99a-<italic>EcleuS</italic>, pTrc99a-<italic>EcleuS-L327G, -L327R, -K300E, -Y330D, -R344D, -K300E/Y330D, -K300E/R344D, -Y330D/R344D</italic> and -<italic>K300E/Y330D/R344D.</italic> Transformants were grown on solid LB plates supplemented with 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> ampicillin and 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> thymine at 30&#x000b0;C. A single colony was selected and grown in liquid LB medium supplemented with 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> ampicillin, 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> thymine and 0.1&#x02009;mM IPTG at 30&#x000b0;C. The cells harboring these plasmids were diluted and adjusted to the same A<sub>600</sub> value of 0.2. To test the effect of non-cognate Nva on cell growth, 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of the diluted mixture were dropped on a solid LB plate (supplemented with 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> ampicillin, 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> thymine and 0.1&#x02009;mM IPTG) containing 0, 5, 10, 20, 50, 100 or 200&#x02009;mM Nva, and the plates were incubated at 42&#x000b0;C to observe the growth of cells.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Mutation of the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end impacts the tRNA aminoacylation reaction</title><p>All tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> isoacceptors from various species contain the absolutely conserved A<sub>73</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B12">12</xref>), which functions as the discriminator during recognition by LeuRSs in different species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B21">21</xref>). However, the effect of the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end on tRNA aminoacylation has not been reported. Here, each nucleotide of the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i3.jpg"/></inline-formula> was individually mutated to one of the three other nucleotides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F1">Figure 1</xref>A), and the aminoacylation kinetic constants of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS for these tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>s were assayed. In aminoacylation of the tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> A76U and A76C mutants, the catalytic efficiency of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS was obviously decreased (155.8 and 87.2&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1&#x02009;</sup>mM<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively) as compared with that of the WT tRNA transcript (923.1&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1&#x02009;</sup>mM<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). The amino acid-accepting activity of the A76G mutant was too low to accurately measure the kinetics. Similarly, the three C<sub>75</sub> mutants reduced the amino acid-accepting activity to 2&#x02013;46% of the native tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>, with the C75G mutant showing the greatest decrease (14.6&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1&#x02009;</sup>mM<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Additionally, the three tRNA variants from C<sub>74</sub> showed obvious decreases in amino acid-accepting activity; their catalytic constants for <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS ranged from 8% (C74G, 69.4&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1&#x02009;</sup>mM<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), 41% (C74U, 381.8&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1&#x02009;</sup>mM<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) to 50% (C74A, 460.3&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1&#x02009;</sup>mM<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) of that with the WT tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="gkr595-T1">Table 1</xref>). All the decreases were mainly due to a reduced <italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub> value of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS and/or changed <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> for these tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> mutants. These results clearly showed that the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end mutations negatively impacted the aminoacylation of these mutants to various levels, and the presence of guanosine at each of the 3-nt positions resulted in the lowest level of tRNA aminoacylation.
<fig id="gkr595-F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Secondary structures of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>s and location of the mutations. Cloverleaf structures of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i4.jpg"/></inline-formula> (<bold>A</bold>) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i5.jpg"/></inline-formula> (<bold>B</bold>) used in the present work. The point and deletion mutations on the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i6.jpg"/></inline-formula> are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkr595f1"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="gkr595-T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Aminoacylation kinetics of transcripts of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i7.jpg"/></inline-formula> by <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> (&#x000b5;M)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub> (s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub>/<italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> (s<sup>&#x02212;1&#x02009;</sup>mM<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub>/<italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> (relative)</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i8.jpg"/></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">923.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A76U</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.99&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">155.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A76G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;&#x0003c;0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A76C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.90&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C75A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">421.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C75U</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C75G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C74A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">460.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C74U</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">381.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C74G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec><title>LeuRS can aminoacylate tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> lacking the terminal adenosine</title><p>Besides point mutations, we also performed progressive deletions from the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end of tRNA in order to obtain the following three mutants: &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub> (ending with C<sub>75</sub>), &#x00394;C<sub>75</sub>A<sub>76</sub> (ending with C<sub>74</sub>) and &#x00394;C<sub>74</sub>C<sub>75</sub>A<sub>76</sub> (ending with A<sub>73</sub>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F1">Figure 1</xref>A). In initial charging plateau measurements for accepting activity with a large excess of 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;M enzyme, it was surprising to observe that LeuRS could charge &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub> mutant obviously. As it has been reported that some aaRSs can ligate their cognate amino acids to themselves without tRNA (by self-aminoacylation occurring at high enzyme concentration and excess of adenylate formation) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B22 gkr595-B23 gkr595-B24">22&#x02013;24</xref>), we tested the self-aminoacylation of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS at different concentrations without tRNA. We found that self-aminoacylation of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS was negligible at low concentrations (&#x0003c;300&#x02009;nM). However, <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS at higher concentrations &#x0003e;500&#x02009;nM could be self-aminoacylated and was resistant to RNase I (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkr595/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1</ext-link>). Therefore, we tested the &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub> charging plateau value by using 100&#x02009;nM <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS and found that 70% of &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub> could be charged with <sup>3</sup>H-Leu. In the same conditions, no detectable labeled product could be measured at the absence of tRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F2">Figure 2</xref>). To further confirm that, the tRNA but not the enzyme itself was ligated with <sup>3</sup>H-Leu, we treated the aminoacylation product in the presence of RNase I, and the values dropped down to the same level with that in the absence of tRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F2">Figure 2</xref>). These results confirmed that LeuRS could aminoacylate tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> with the terminal A<sub>76</sub> deleted. However, reliable aminoacylation kinetics could not be measured because of the very low <italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub>. However, the other two tRNA mutants, &#x00394;C<sub>75</sub>A<sub>76</sub> and &#x00394;C<sub>74</sub>C<sub>75</sub>A<sub>76</sub>, could not be aminoacylated at 100&#x02009;nM or higher concentrations of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS (data not shown).
<fig id="gkr595-F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Aminoacylation of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>-&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>, -&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75A, -&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75U or -&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75G by <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS.Charging plateaus of <italic>Ec</italic>tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>-&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub> (filled diamond)<bold>, -</bold>&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75A (filled square), -&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75U (filled triangle) or -&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75G (filled inverted triangle) were measured as described in the Materials and methods section. The control (unfilled circle) was performed without tRNA. The charging plateaus were determined using GraphPad Prism software. According to the plateau values (to calculate the amount of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> charged leucine) and total tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> used in the reaction, <italic>Ec</italic>tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>-&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub><bold>, -</bold>&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75A, -&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75U and -&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75G are aminoacylated to 70, 70, 61 and 35%, respectively. Digestion of aminoacyl&#x02013;<italic>Ec</italic>tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>-&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub> by RNase I digestion (unfilled triangle) and no product accumulation in control excluded the self-aminoacylation of the enzyme.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkr595f2"/></fig></p><p>To further analyze the &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub> mutant, we mutated the terminal C<sub>75</sub> to the three other nucleotides in order to identify potential interactions that could be more productive in aminoacylation. The resulting mutants, &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75A, &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75U and &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>/C75G, could be aminoacylated by <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS to plateau levels of 70, 61 and 35%, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F2">Figure 2</xref>). Therefore, more productive interactions were not induced by these nucleotides, and here again, the mutant harboring a guanosine mutation was the least active compared to those with the other nucleotides.</p></sec><sec><title>Role of CCA<sub>76</sub>-end in total editing</title><p>Usually, more than one ATP molecule is consumed by an aaRS in the presence of a non-cognate amino acid due to repetitive cycles of synthesis&#x02013;hydrolysis of the non-cognate products. The excess of ATP consumption can be determined by measuring the release of AMP in the TLC assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B25">25</xref>). In the presence of tRNA, the TLC assay measures the global editing activity, including the tRNA-independent and tRNA-dependent pre-transfer editing in addition to the post-transfer editing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B26">26</xref>). In the absence of tRNA, the assay measures the AMP produced from the sole tRNA-independent pre-transfer editing activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B26">26</xref>).</p><p>In the presence of non-cognate Nva, the observed rate constant (<italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub>) of WT LeuRS for AMP formation without tRNA in the editing reaction was 0.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, accounting for 13% of that in the presence of tRNA transcript (4.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.64&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="gkr595-T2">Table 2</xref>). The tRNA transcript without the modified bases was tested to determine if it was as efficient as the native tRNA in stimulating the editing activity. The <italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub> for AMP formation in the presence of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i15.jpg"/></inline-formula> purified from the overproducing <italic>E. coli</italic> strain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B27">27</xref>) was 5.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.76&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. This value was only slightly larger than that in the presence of transcript (4.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.64&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), indicating that the modified bases in <italic>Ec</italic>tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> did not play a critical role in stimulating editing activity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="gkr595-T2">Table 2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="gkr595-T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p><italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub> of AMP formation by <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS in the presence of Nva and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i9.jpg"/></inline-formula> or its variants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub> (s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative <italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i10.jpg"/></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i11.jpg"/></inline-formula> (<italic>in vivo</italic>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="gkr595-TF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i12.jpg"/></inline-formula> (transcript)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="gkr595-TF2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A76U</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A76G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A76C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C75A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C75U</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C75G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C74A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C74U</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.87&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C74G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="gkr595-TF1"><p><sup>a</sup><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i13.jpg"/></inline-formula> obtained from the overproducing <italic>E. coli</italic> strain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B27">27</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="gkr595-TF2"><p><sup>b</sup><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i14.jpg"/></inline-formula> obtained by T7 <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Different variants of the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end were also tested for their abilities to stimulate AMP formation in editing reactions with <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS. The AMP formation rates for A76U, A76G and A76C mutants dropped down to a level similar to that without tRNA, indicating only tRNA-independent pre-transfer editing remained and the tRNA-dependent editing was abolished (<xref ref-type="table" rid="gkr595-T2">Table 2</xref>). As a consequence of this loss of editing ability, the two A<sub>76</sub>-mutants of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> (A76U and A76C) were obviously mischarged with Ile (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F3">Figure 3</xref>A). The decreased formation of Ile-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> of A76G may be due to its deficiency in accepting the amino acid. Among the other six variants of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>, only C75G with a <italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub> value of 0.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> had tRNA-independent pre-transfer editing and lost the tRNA-dependent editing, indicating that C75G could not play a role in the tRNA-dependent editing; C74G with a <italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub> value of 2.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.32&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> decreased the tRNA-dependent editing to nearly half of that of the WT tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>; the four mutants of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>, C75A, C75U, C74A and C74U stimulated more AMP formation than WT tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>, with the <italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub> values of 8.34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.03, 6.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.81, 7.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.98 and 8.87&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.34&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="gkr595-T2">Table 2</xref>), indicating that these mutations did not affect the tRNA-dependent editing but rather stimulated it. The six variants of nucleotides 74 and 75 did not form any detectable Ile-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> in the misacylation assay (data not shown). Additionally, in the presence of the &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub> mutant, <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS had comparable editing activity with that in the absence of tRNA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="gkr595-T2">Table 2</xref>). Correspondingly, <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS catalyzed the synthesis of an obvious amount of mischarged &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub> mutant (Ile-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>-&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F3">Figure 3</xref>B). These results clearly showed that the terminal A<sub>76</sub> is a critical element in the tRNA-dependent editing activity of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS, and the nucleotides C<sub>74</sub> and C<sub>75</sub> crucial for aminoacylation do not play an indispensible role to the tRNA-dependent editing of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS.
<fig id="gkr595-F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Misacylation of tRNA-A<sub>76</sub> mutants with Ile. (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) WT tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> (filled circle) and mutated derivatives A76U (unfilled circle), A76G (filled inverted triangle) or A76C (unfilled triangle) and &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub> (unfilled inverted triangle) were mischarged with non-cognate Ile.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkr595f3"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Role of CCA<sub>76</sub>-end in post-transfer editing</title><p>It is now universally accepted that after aminoacylation, the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end of the tRNA is translocated &#x0223c;35&#x02009;&#x000c5; from the aminoacylation active site to the editing active site embedded in the CP1 domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B6">6</xref>). Both tRNA CCA<sub>76</sub>-end and mischarged amino acid moieties are recognized by the active site of post-transfer editing within the CP1 domain of LeuRS. To test the contribution of the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end to the post-transfer editing, we first mischarged 10 variants of the tRNA with non-cognate <sup>3</sup>H-Ile using an editing-deficient LeuRS-T252E mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B20">20</xref>). The deacylation of the mischarged Ile-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> by WT LeuRS was then measured. The mutants of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> could be mischarged with Ile by the LeuRS-T252E mutant. However the three mis-acylated mutants of A<sub>76</sub> (A76C, A76G and A76U) were resistant to deacylation catalyzed by LeuRS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F4">Figure 4</xref>A), indicating the crucial role of this nucleotide in post-transfer editing. This result was also consistent with their inability to stimulate total editing in the TLC assay (<xref ref-type="table" rid="gkr595-T2">Table 2</xref>). In addition, Ile-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>-&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub> could not be hydrolyzed by the post-transfer editing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F4">Figure 4</xref>A). This is consistent with the fact that the A<sub>76</sub> base is specifically recognized by the main chain carbonyl- and amino-groups of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS Leu327 in the Nva2AA-containing structure (analog of the post-transfer editing substrate) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B28">28</xref>) and <italic>Thermus thermophilus</italic> LeuRS-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> structure (in post-transfer editing conformation) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B6">6</xref>). Obviously, changing the terminal base affects the proper positioning of the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end into the CP1 domain and thus blocks the hydrolytic editing reaction.
<fig id="gkr595-F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Effect of the CCA<sub>76</sub> mutations on deacylation of mischarged tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>. Mischarged tRNA mutants from A<sub>76</sub>, C<sub>75</sub> or C<sub>74</sub> were prepared by editing-deficient <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS-T252E (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B20">20</xref>). Mischarged tRNA-&#x00394;A<sub>76</sub> mutant was obtained with WT <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS. Deacylation of mischarged WT tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> was indicated (unfilled circle). The deacylation assay of mischarged &#x00394;A<sub>76</sub> (unfilled square), A76U (filled inverted triangle), A76G (unfilled triangle), A76C (filled square) in (<bold>A</bold>), C75A (filled inverted triangle), C75U (unfilled triangle), C75G (filled square) in (<bold>B</bold>) or C74A (filled inverted triangle), C74U (unfilled triangle), C74G (filled square) in (<bold>C</bold>) was performed at 37&#x000b0;C with 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;M [<sup>3</sup>H]Ile-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> and 5&#x02009;nM <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS. The spontaneous hydrolysis of each mischarged tRNA (control) was carried out without enzyme. For clarity, a single representative control is shown (filled circle).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkr595f4"/></fig></p><p>In general, mutations of nucleotides 75 and 74 did not influence the tRNA deacylation properties, except when the guanosine mutations C75G and C74G were introduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F4">Figure 4</xref>B and C). The result suggested that guanine residues at either position of CCA<sub>76</sub>-end may prevent proper interaction with the enzyme and/or tRNA end translocation.</p></sec><sec><title>The tRNA entrance pathway critically contributes to quality control</title><p>According to the crystal structure, the CP1 editing domain binds only with CCA<sub>76</sub>-end residues without any interaction with the main tRNA body. In detail, the equivalent side chains in <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS interacting specifically with the C<sub>74</sub> base and the phosphates of C<sub>75</sub> and A<sub>76</sub> are Lys300, Arg344 and Tyr330, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B6">6</xref>). Additionally, the main chain carbonyl- and amino-group of Leu327 interact with the A<sub>76</sub> base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F5">Figure 5</xref>A). These amino acid residues are absolutely conserved in prokaryotic LeuRSs and thus constitute an entrance pathway to orient the aminoacylated CCA<sub>76</sub>-arm into the editing active site. Previous studies have demonstrated the essential role of Tyr330 of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS in tRNA-dependent editing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B8">8</xref>). However, other sites (Leu327, Lys300 and Arg344) and their functions <italic>in vivo</italic> have not been determined. We studied here the roles of residues Leu327, Lys300, Tyr330 and Arg344 by mutating them individually or in combination. The <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> assays were then performed in order to analyze the effects of these mutations.
<fig id="gkr595-F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>The tRNA entrance pathway contributes critically to the quality control. (<bold>A</bold>) View of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> CCA<sub>76</sub>-end bound to the CP1 domain (gray) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B6">6</xref>), showing the binding pattern between C<sub>74</sub> (yellow), C<sub>75</sub> (cyan), A<sub>76</sub> (blue) and the key amino acids (green) in the CP1 editing domain (upper). The tRNA main body before nucleotide A<sub>73</sub> (orange) and LeuRS main body except for the editing domain were omitted for clarity. The lower panel shows the closer protein&#x02013;CCA<sub>76</sub> interaction network. Distances between the amino-acid residues here studied and the nucleotides are shown. (<bold>B</bold>) Mischarging of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i16.jpg"/></inline-formula> with non-cognate Ile by WT <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS (filled circle), -Y330D (unfilled circle), -K300E/Y330D (filled inverted triangle), -K300E/R344D (unfilled triangle), -Y330D/R344D (filled square), -K300E/Y330D/R344D (unfilled square) and -R344D (filled diamond) with significant misaminoacylation ability. Mutants that did not accumulate Ile-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> are not shown. (<bold>C</bold>) Deacylation curves of Ile-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> by WT <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS (filled circle), -L327G (unfilled circle), -L327R (filled inverted triangle), -K300E/R344D (unfilled triangle), -K300E (filled square) and -R344D (filled diamond). Editing-defective mutants (<italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS-Y330D, -K300E/Y330D, -Y330D/R344D and -K300E/Y330D/R344D) are not shown for clarity. Spontaneous hydrolysis without enzyme addition was carried out as a control (unfilled square) as indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkr595f5"/></fig></p><p>The following single, double and triple mutants were constructed in <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS to form <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS-L327G, -L327R, -K300E, -Y330D, -R344D, -K300E/Y330D, -K300E/R344D, -Y330D/R344D and -K300E/Y330D/R344D. All these mutants displayed intact synthetic activities (Leu activation and aminoacylation) as expected from their location in the discrete CP1 editing domain (data not shown). However, <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS-Y330D, -K300E/Y330D, -Y330D/R344D and the triple mutant were completely defective in post-transfer editing (data not shown), and they produced significant amounts of Ile-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F5">Figure 5</xref>B). The other mutants were impaired in post-transfer editing to different extents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F5">Figure 5</xref>C), and only <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS-R344D and <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS-K300E/R344D synthesized mischarged tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>, but obviously at lower levels than that with <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS-Y330D and the derived double and triple mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F5">Figure 5</xref>B). In the TLC assay, <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS-Y330D, its derived double and triple mutants and <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS-K300E/R344D only retained the tRNA-independent pre-transfer editing activity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="gkr595-T3">Table 3</xref>). Altogether, the data showed that the Tyr330 residue plays a major role in tRNA-dependent editing as previously demonstrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B8">8</xref>). The negative effect of Y330D on editing was dominant, and the derived multiple mutants exhibited similar defects. Only the combination mutant <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS-K300E/R344D could reach the same level of tRNA-independent editing of the single <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS-Y330D mutation. Other individual mutants showed more limited decreases in post-transfer editing activity, inducing no measurable tRNA mischarging (data not shown). These <italic>in vitro</italic> data confirmed that mutating the CCA<sub>76</sub> entrance pathway of the CP1 domain has a negative effect on the accuracy of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> aminoacylation.
<table-wrap id="gkr595-T3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p><italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub> of AMP formation by <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS or mutated derivatives in the presence of Nva</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i17.jpg"/></inline-formula> (transcript)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub> (s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative <italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-L327G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-L327R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-K300E</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-Y330D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-R344D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-K300E/Y330D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-K300E/R344D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-Y330D/R344D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-K300E/Y330D/R344D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>To evaluate if these losses of accuracy could affect the fidelity of protein synthesis <italic>in vivo</italic>, complementation assays using the <italic>leuS</italic> temperature-sensitive strain KL231 were performed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B18">18</xref>). The strain KL231 was transformed with various plasmids encoding <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS and different mutants. At 42&#x000b0;C, all the transformants grew on medium supplemented with 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> ampicillin and 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> thymine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F6">Figure 6</xref>), and the mutants were well expressed at a level similar to that of WT <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkr595/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2</ext-link>). The growth was then observed at 42&#x000b0;C in the presence of increasing concentrations of Nva in the growth medium. No growth difference could be observed below 20&#x02009;mM of Nva. However, in the presence of 50&#x02009;mM Nva, the strains harboring the genes-encoding <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS-Y330D, -K300E/Y330D, -K300E/R344D, -Y330D/R344D and -K300E/Y330D/R344D grew slowly or were inhibited completely, especially those containing the last double and triple mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F6">Figure 6</xref>). With a 100&#x02009;mM of Nva no strains containing mutants were able to grow, except for the strain expressing WT enzyme which only grew at a very slow rate. All strains died in the presence of 200&#x02009;mM Nva.
<fig id="gkr595-F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p><italic>In vivo</italic> toxicity resulting from mutations in the CP1 tRNA entrance pathway of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS. The complementation assay was performed using <italic>E. coli</italic> thermosensitive strain KL231 at 42&#x000b0;C, on solid LB plates supplemented with 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> ampicillin, 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> thymine, 0.1&#x02009;mM IPTG and increasing concentrations of non-cognate Nva. KL231 was transformed with mutated copies of LeuRS-encoding genes, and growth was compared with the negative control (empty pTrc99a vector) and positive control (WT <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS). Expression of all LeuRSs proteins was controlled by Western blot (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkr595/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2</ext-link>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkr595f6a"/></fig></p><p>Altogether, the <italic>in vivo</italic> data are consistent with the <italic>in vitro</italic> results, demonstrating that perturbing the tRNA CCA<sub>76</sub>-end entry pathway in the CP1 domain has a significantly negative effect on the fidelity of protein biosynthesis.</p></sec><sec><title>Different tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> isoacceptors stimulate LeuRS editing with the same efficiency</title><p>In <italic>E. coli</italic>, there are five different tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> isoacceptors with two types of first base pairs in its accepting stem (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkr595-F1">Figure 1</xref>). <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i18.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i19.jpg"/></inline-formula> harbor the wobble base pair (G<sub>1</sub>-U<sub>72</sub>); while <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i20.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i21.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i22.jpg"/></inline-formula> contain the standard Watson&#x02013;Crick one (G<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>72</sub>). It has been shown that <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS has the same specificity and activity toward different isoacceptors in aminoacylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B29">29</xref>). We transcribed the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i23.jpg"/></inline-formula> (with G<sub>1</sub>-U<sub>72</sub>) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i24.jpg"/></inline-formula> (with G<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>72</sub>) to represent two types of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> and compared their capacity to stimulate editing by <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS. The data showed that they stimulated <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS editing activity with nearly identical efficiency (4.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.64 and 4.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.36&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="gkr595-T4">Table 4</xref>). To explore the possible role of the first base pair in <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS editing, we mutated the U<sub>72</sub> to C<sub>72</sub> of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i29.jpg"/></inline-formula> or the C<sub>72</sub> to U<sub>72</sub> of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i30.jpg"/></inline-formula> to change the first base pair pattern. Measurements of AMP formation showed that the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i31.jpg"/></inline-formula>(G<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>72</sub>) had the editing <italic>k<sub>obs</sub></italic> of 3.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.50&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, while the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i32.jpg"/></inline-formula>(G<sub>1</sub>-U<sub>72</sub>) mutant stimulated the editing with <italic>k<sub>obs</sub></italic> of 6.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.81&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="gkr595-T4">Table 4</xref>). The above results suggested that <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS editing has no preference among WT isoacceptors with different first base-pairs. However, changing the first base-pair obviously led to distinct editing-stimulating capacities among isoacceptors. Therefore, the first base pair pattern may cooperate with other sequence differences between the two tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>s to confer the same level of editing-stimulating capacity of the two isoacceptors of WT tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>.
<table-wrap id="gkr595-T4" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p><italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub> of AMP formation in the presence of different transcripts of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> isoacceptors or mutants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub> (s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative <italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i25.jpg"/></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i26.jpg"/></inline-formula> (G<sub>1</sub>-C<sub>72</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i27.jpg"/></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkr595i28.jpg"/></inline-formula> (G<sub>1</sub>-U<sub>72</sub>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><sec><title>The CCA<sub>76</sub>-end sequence is critical for both aminoacylation and editing reactions</title><p>The CCA<sub>76</sub> sequence is conserved at the 3&#x02032;-end of all mature tRNA molecules. Although it is an indispensable prerequisite for a functional tRNA, very few organisms like <italic>E. coli</italic> encode the CCA<sub>76</sub> triplet in their tRNA genes. Most of the time, the CCA<sub>76</sub> tail is to be added post-transcriptionally in eukaryotes, archaea and many bacteria, where the tRNA genes do not encode the CCA<sub>76</sub> terminus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B30">30</xref>). This sequence is acquired and maintained by step-wise nucleotide addition by the ubiquitous tRNA nucleotidyltransferase that synthesizes this specific triplet without a nucleic acid template. The CCA sequence plays key roles during several steps of protein biosynthesis. During tRNA charging catalyzed by aaRSs, the 2&#x02032; or 3&#x02032; hydroxyl of ribose in A<sub>76</sub> is the group involved in the esterification reaction with the carboxyl of the amino acid. Although the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end does not play a critical role in recognition between tRNA and aaRS, it is essential in terms of catalytic efficiency for the aminoacylation reaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B31 gkr595-B32 gkr595-B33">31&#x02013;33</xref>). The universal CCA<sub>76</sub> sequence is also involved in EF-Tu binding and during peptide bond formation by interacting with specific nucleotides of the 23S rRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B17">17</xref>). Little is known about the precise role of the CCA<sub>76</sub> nucleotides during the editing reaction catalyzed by aaRSs. It has been shown that only chargeable tRNA<sup>Val</sup> mutants are able to stimulate the editing reaction of ValRS, suggesting that the enzyme required prior charging of tRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B34">34</xref>). Although tRNA is not a strict prerequisite for the editing of both classes I and II aaRSs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B35 gkr595-B36 gkr595-B37">35&#x02013;37</xref>), its presence strongly stimulates editing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B38">38</xref>). Remarkably, both classes of aaRSs use effectively the ability of the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end of tRNA to switch between a hairpin and a helical conformation during the aminoacylation and editing reactions. Our previous investigations have shown that the interaction between the tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> CCA<sub>76</sub>-end and the CP1 domain of LeuRS is critical for tRNA-dependent editing (post-transfer and pre-transfer editing) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B8">8</xref>). However, the molecular basis of the phenomenon is not yet understood in detail. Here, we extended the investigations to the three CCA<sub>76</sub> nucleotides and assayed the effect of mutations on the tRNA-dependent pre-transfer editing and post-transfer editing.</p><p>We showed that the universally conserved A<sub>76</sub> is essential for tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> to trigger both aminoacylation and editing reaction of LeuRS. The mutants of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> with any base substituted for A<sub>76</sub> showed significant decreases of aminoacylation properties and total loss of the ability to stimulate the editing activity and catalyze deacylation of pre-formed Ile-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>. As a consequence of this loss of editing activity, two of these mutants (A76U, A76C) were misacylated by Ile. Mutations of the other bases of the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end had negative effects on the aminoacylation properties, ranging between 2- and 50-fold decreases of the catalytic efficiency of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS, with the strongest effect being observed when C<sub>75</sub> and C<sub>74</sub> were substituted by G<sub>75</sub> and G<sub>74</sub>, respectively. Correspondingly, the mutant A76G was totally inactive, showing that the bulky guanosine substitutions were the least accepted in the synthetic active site. The three guanosine mutants also decreased the deacylation of the mischarged Ile-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>, but failed in misacylating tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> with Ile. Comparison of the global editing activity of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS in the presence of the tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> mutants revealed that four mutations (C75A, C75U, C74A and C74U) led to an increase in the editing up to 2-fold despite the fact that their accepting capacity with Leu were impaired during the aminoacylation reaction. <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS deacylated these mischarged mutants of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> with Ile with unchanged ability, suggesting that these mutants of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> preferred binding at the editing active site rather than at the synthetic site. Previous studies have shown that both classes of aaRSs use effectively the ability of the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end of tRNA to switch between a hairpin and a helical conformation of aaRSs for aminoacylation and editing. In class I aaRSs, their cognate tRNA CCA<sub>76</sub>-ends adopt a regular helical conformation into the editing site of aaRSs, and a distorted hairpin conformation into the synthetic site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B6">6</xref>). A mirror image is observed in class II aaRSs, as already seen for tRNA binding and amino acid activation. The stimulation of the editing activity of C75A, C75U, C74A and C74U mutants strongly suggests that these mutations may favor the helical conformation, which is more suitable for the editing reaction. Moreover, the fact that these mutated tRNAs are poorly aminoacylated in the synthetic active site may favor stagnation of the non-cognate adenylate into the synthetic active site and its subsequent editing by the tRNA-dependent pre-transfer editing also measured in the global editing assay.</p></sec><sec><title>The CCA<sub>76</sub>-end entrance pathway into editing domain of <italic>Ec</italic>LeuRS critically contributes to protein synthesis fidelity</title><p>Despite the importance of the interaction between CCA<sub>76</sub>-end of tRNA and the CP1 domain of class Ia aaRSs revealed by <italic>in vitro</italic> methods, the corresponding <italic>in vivo</italic> evidence is generally lacking. In the present work, we developed an efficient system with the combination of non-cognate Nva and <italic>leuS</italic> temperature-sensitive <italic>E. coli</italic> strain to assess the significance of LeuRS tRNA-dependent editing <italic>in vivo</italic>. Our evaluation of the tRNA CCA<sub>76</sub>-end entrance pathway using the <italic>leuS</italic> temperature-sensitive KL231 strain revealed the following aspects. (i) Without or at a low concentration of non-cognate amino acid (e.g. 20&#x02009;mM Nva here), mutation of pivotal residues controlling protein biosynthesis fidelity had no obvious effect on the bacterial cell viability. The discrimination by EF-Tu and/or the ribosome may have prevented Nva mis-incorporation, or the <italic>E. coli</italic> cells could endure low level of Nva mis-incorporation at Leu codons; (ii) at extremely high concentrations of non-cognate amino acids, even the WT enzyme had no ability to prevent all the mis-activated amino acids from entering the newly synthesized polypeptide on the ribosome, and the mis-translation led to an obvious inhibitory effect on cell growth; (iii) our <italic>in vitro</italic> results were consistent with <italic>in vivo</italic> data, demonstrating the importance of conserved amino acid residues in aaRS and nucleotides in tRNA in protein synthesis quality control, especially under severe environmental stress.</p></sec><sec><title>Multiple steps to monitor and control the CCA acceptor sequence</title><p>As mentioned above, the trinucleotide CCA<sub>76</sub> sequence is present at the 3&#x02032; terminus of all mature tRNAs. Despite this high conservation, transcripts of <italic>E. coli</italic> tRNA<sup>Val</sup> with altered 3&#x02032; termini are readily aminoacylated and can function in polypeptide synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B32">32</xref>). Accordingly, the present study performed on LeuRS shows that the aminoacylation reaction admits some sequence flexibility at the CCA<sub>76</sub> end. Several CCA-mutated tRNAs can be efficiently aminoacylated, and LeuRS can even aminoacylate a tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> lacking the terminal adenosine, showing a remarkable plasticity of the synthetic site of LeuRS and tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> acceptor end. Several studies suggest that the aminoacylation of similar molecules may occur naturally <italic>in vivo</italic>. Despite the high fidelity of the CCA-adding enzyme, in some conditions, CCase can add a wrong nucleotide to the 3&#x02032;-end of the tRNA, leading to CCA-modified tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B39">39</xref>). Moreover, mutations of CCase may exist <italic>in vivo</italic> with relaxed active sites as those engineered <italic>in vitro</italic> that lead to nucleotide mis-incorporation at the end of tRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B40">40</xref>). In some bacteria the CCA-adding activity is naturally split into a CC-adding enzyme and an A-adding enzyme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B41">41</xref>). Therefore, a tRNA deprived of the terminal A<sub>76</sub> might temporarily exist <italic>in vivo</italic> and may be the substrate of LeuRS.</p><p>However, if under these exceptional circumstances aminoacylation of CCA-mutated tRNAs can occur, these tRNAs would have to face additional discrimination processes based on EF-Tu recognition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B42">42</xref>) and interaction with ribosomal RNA during translation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B43">43</xref>). Both processes would monitor and exclude these molecules according to different nucleotide recognition specificities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkr595-B32">32</xref>).</p><p>In summary, the study highlighted the significant role of the conserved nucleotides from the CCA<sub>76</sub>-end and the strong collaboration with amino acid residues of the CP1 editing domain during the aminoacylation and editing catalysis. The CCA<sub>76</sub> nucleotides are critical for both aminoacylation and editing; and in combination with the amino acids located in the entrance path of the editing domain, they critically contribute to the fidelity of protein synthesis. It is a remarkable example of a control mechanism that prevent damaged tRNAs from entering the protein synthesis based on the single discrimination of a triplet sequence that is universally found in all tRNAs.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkr595/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online.</p></sec><sec><title>FUNDING</title><p><funding-source>Natural Science Foundation of China</funding-source> (Nos. <award-id>30930022</award-id> and <award-id>31000355</award-id>); <funding-source>Committee of Science and Technology in Shanghai</funding-source> (<award-id>No. 09JC1415900</award-id>); <funding-source>a Visiting Professorship for Senior International Scientists from the Chinese Academy of Sciences</funding-source> (No. <award-id>2009S2-19</award-id>); <funding-source>Programme International de Coop&#x000e9;ration Scientifique from CNRS</funding-source> (Grant <award-id>3606</award-id>). Funding for open access charge: <funding-source>Natural Science Foundation of China</funding-source>.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></sec>
      <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
         <title>Supplementary Material</title>
         <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
            <caption>
               <title>Supplementary Data</title>
            </caption>
            <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_39_20_8857__index.html"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
                   xlink:href="supp_gkr595_Supplementary_Figures.pdf"/>
         </supplementary-material>
      </sec>
   </body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>The authors thank Dr Franck Martin for the help during the experiment.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="gkr595-B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000f6;ll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aminoacyl-tRNA synthesis</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source><year>2000</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10966471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schimmel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aminoacyl tRNA synthetases: general scheme of structure-function relationships in the polypeptides and recognition of transfer RNAs</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source><year>1987</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3304131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Beebe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nangle</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Longo-Guess</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davisson</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundberg</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Schimmel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackerman</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Editing-defective tRNA synthetase causes protein misfolding and neurodegeneration</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>443</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16906134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aminoacyl-tRNA synthesis and translational quality control</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19379069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The CP2 domain of leucyl-tRNA synthetase is crucial for amino acid activation and post-transfer editing</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>36608</fpage><lpage>36616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tukalo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaremchuk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukunaga</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cusack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The crystal structure of leucyl-tRNA synthetase complexed with tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> in the post-transfer-editing conformation</article-title><source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>923</fpage><lpage>930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16155583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CP1 domain in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> leucyl-tRNA synthetase is crucial for its editing function</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2000</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>6726</fpage><lpage>6731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10828991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>tRNA-dependent pre-transfer editing by prokaryotic leucyl-tRNA synthetase</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2010</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>3235</fpage><lpage>3244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19940155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modular pathways for editing non-cognate amino acids by human cytoplasmic leucyl-tRNA synthetase</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2011</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20805241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dulic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cvetesic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Perona</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruic-Sovulj</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Partitioning of tRNA-dependent editing between pre- and post-transfer pathways in Class I aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2010</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>23799</fpage><lpage>23809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20498377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fukunaga</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aminoacylation complex structures of leucyl-tRNA synthetase and tRNALeu reveal two modes of discriminator-base recognition</article-title><source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>915</fpage><lpage>922</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16155584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giege</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sissler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Florentz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Universal rules and idiosyncratic features in tRNA identity</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>5017</fpage><lpage>5035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9801296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How the CCA-adding enzyme selects adenine over cytosine at position 76 of tRNA</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2010</year><volume>330</volume><fpage>937</fpage><lpage>940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21071662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unusual synthesis by the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> CCA-adding enzyme</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1031</fpage><lpage>1043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10917598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nissen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kjeldgaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thirup</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Polekhina</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Reshetnikova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>BFC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyborg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of the ternary complex of Phe-tRNAPhe, EF-Tu, and a GTP analog</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>1464</fpage><lpage>1472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7491491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunham</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name><name><surname>Weixlbaumer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Petry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the 70S Ribosome Complexed with mRNA and tRNA</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>313</volume><fpage>1935</fpage><lpage>1942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16959973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schimmel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trial for peptide bond formation using model molecules based on the interactions between the CCA sequence of tRNA and 23S rRNA</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Symp. Ser.</source><year>2000</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12903363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000f6;ll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and partial characterization of temperature-sensitive <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> mutants with altered leucyl- and seryl-transfer ribonucleic acid synthetases</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>1971</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>742</fpage><lpage>750</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4942762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A modified procedure for fast purification of T7 RNA polymerase</article-title><source>Protein Expr. Purif.</source><year>1999</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10419832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Groups on the side chain of T252 in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> leucyl-tRNA synthetase are important for discrimination of amino acids and cell viability</article-title><source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source><year>2004</year><volume>318</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15110746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> by <italic>Aquifex aeolicus</italic> leucyl-tRNA synthetase during the aminoacylation and editing steps</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>2728</fpage><lpage>2738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18367476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gieg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Covalent attachment of aspartic acid to yeast aspartyl-tRNA synthetase induced by the enzyme</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>1982</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6754443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rapaport</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yogeeswaran</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamecnik</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Remy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Covalent modification of phenylalanyl-tRNA synthetase with phenylalanine during the amino acid activation reaction catalyzed by the enzyme</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1985</year><volume>260</volume><fpage>9509</fpage><lpage>9512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3848435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovaleva</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Moroz</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Favorova</surname><given-names>OO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kisselev</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tryptophanyl-tRNA synthetase: evidence for an anhydrous bond involved in the tryptophanyl enzyme formation</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>1978</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gruic-Sovulj</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Uter</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullock</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Perona</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>tRNA-dependent aminoacyl-adenylate hydrolysis by a nonediting Class I aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>23978</fpage><lpage>23986</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15845536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>tRNA-independent pretransfer editing by Class I leucyl-tRNA synthetase</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2009</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>3418</fpage><lpage>3424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19068478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overproduction and purification of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> tRNA<sup>Leu</sup></article-title><source>Sci. China, C, Life Sci.</source><year>1998</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18425626</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lincecum</surname><given-names>TL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Tukalo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaremchuk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mursinna</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sproat</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Den Eynde</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Calenbergh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gr&#x000f8;li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural and mechanistic basis of pre- and posttransfer editing by leucyl-tRNA synthetase</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>963</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12718881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discrimination of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> isoacceptors by the insertion mutant of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> leucyl-tRNA synthetase</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>9084</fpage><lpage>9088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10413482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schurer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiffer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchfelder</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>This is the end: processing, editing and repair at the tRNA 3&#x02032;-terminus</article-title><source>Biol. Chem.</source><year>2001</year><volume>382</volume><fpage>1147</fpage><lpage>1156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11592395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nameki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Himeno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of the CCA terminal sequence of tRNA(Val) in aminoacylation with valyl-tRNA synthetase</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>22173</fpage><lpage>22177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8071341</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Horowitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional transfer RNAs with modifications in the 3&#x02032;-CCA end: differential effects on aminoacylation and polypeptide synthesis</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>10389</fpage><lpage>10393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7937960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eriani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gangloff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yeast aspartyl-tRNA synthetase residues interacting with tRNA(Asp) identity bases connectively contribute to tRNA(Asp) binding in the ground and transition-state complex and discriminate against non-cognate tRNAs</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>291</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>773</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10452887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tardif</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Horowitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transfer RNA determinants for translational editing by <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> valyl-tRNA synthetase</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2538</fpage><lpage>2545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12034843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Splan</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignatov</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Musier-Forsyth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transfer RNA modulates the editing mechanism used by class II prolyl-tRNA synthetase</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>7128</fpage><lpage>7134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18180290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gruic-Sovulj</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokov-Plavec</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weygand-Durasevic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrolysis of non-cognate aminoacyl-adenylates by a class II aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase lacking an editing domain</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>2007</year><volume>581</volume><fpage>5110</fpage><lpage>5114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17931630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minajigi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Francklyn</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aminoacyl transfer rate dictates choice of editing pathway in threonyl-tRNA synthetase</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2010</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>23810</fpage><lpage>23817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20504770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dulic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cvetesic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Perona</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruic-Sovulj</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Partitioning of tRNA-dependent editing between pre- and post-transfer pathways in class I aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2010</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>23799</fpage><lpage>23809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20498377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unusual synthesis by the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> CCA-adding enzyme</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1031</fpage><lpage>1043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10917598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Verlinde</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reengineering CCA-adding enzymes to function as (U,G)- or dCdCdA-adding enzymes or poly(C,A) and poly(U,G) polymerases</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17179213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Collaboration between CC- and A-adding enzymes to build and repair the 3&#x02032;-terminal CCA of tRNA in <italic>Aquifex aeolicus</italic></article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>1334</fpage><lpage>1336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11701927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nissen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kjeldgaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thirup</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Polekhina</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Reshetnikova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyborg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of the ternary complex of Phe-tRNAPhe, EF-Tu, and a GTP analog</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>1464</fpage><lpage>1472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7491491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="gkr595-B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunham</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>FVt</given-names></name><name><surname>Weixlbaumer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Petry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the 70S ribosome complexed with mRNA and tRNA</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>313</volume><fpage>1935</fpage><lpage>1942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16959973</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>