<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="C:\Users\Fernando\Documents\CIPF\Pharm Pract\Pubmed Central\JATS_OXYGEN\jats.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pharm Pract (Granada)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pharm Pract (Granada)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Pharm Pract</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Pharmacy Practice</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1885-642X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1886-3655</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Centro de Investigaciones y Publicaciones
Farmaceuticas</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24367471</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3870176</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PhP-417</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prevalence of hazardous alcohol use among pharmacy students at nine
U.S. schools of pharmacy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>English</surname><given-names>Clayton</given-names></name><aff>Albany College of Pharmacy &#x00026; Health Sciences. Colchester, VT
(<country>United States</country>).</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>Jose A.</given-names></name><aff>College of Pharmacy, <institution>Nova Southeastern
University</institution>. Davie, FL (<country>United
States</country>).</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schlesselman</surname><given-names>Lauren S.</given-names></name><aff>Office of Assessment &#x00026; Accreditation, School of Pharmacy,
<institution>University of Connecticut</institution>. Storrs, CT
(<country>United States</country>).</aff></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub" iso-8601-date="20130331"><season>Jul-Sep</season><year iso-8601-date="2012">2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="20130328"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year iso-8601-date="2012">2011</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="20130129"><day>6</day><month>6</month><year iso-8601-date="2013">2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="20130321"><day>5</day><month>9</month><year iso-8601-date="2013">2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2011, CIPF</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p> This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is
properly cited. </license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec sec-type="intro"><title/><p>Hazardous use of alcohol continues to be recognized as a problem at the
university level. Knowledge regarding alcohol consumption in healthcare
professional students is limited, especially in regards to pharmacy
students. Much of the information available focuses on pharmacy student
drinking patterns in specific geographic regions or is simply outdated. </p></sec><sec sec-type="objective"><title>Objective</title><p>This study was designed to assess levels of alcohol consumption and estimate
the level of hazardous drinking among pharmacy students in a larger sample
size that is representative of US pharmacy schools.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>An anonymous survey regarding alcohol usage was offered to students at nine
schools of pharmacy across the United States. The survey consisted of
demographic questions, the World Health Organization Alcohol Use Disorders
Identification Test (AUDIT), and questions that assess particular
alcohol-induced behaviors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>More than 25% of 1161 respondents had a total AUDIT score &#x02265; 8, which
indicates a risk of alcohol-related problems. Students that were male, in
their first or second professional year of school, not married, and without
children were statistically more likely to have AUDIT scores in the
hazardous drinking range. Grade point average and student housing did not
statistically affect student&#x02019;s AUDIT scores.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusions</title><p>These results indicate that over one-fourth of pharmacy students surveyed
have indicators of harmful alcohol use. Pharmacy schools should continue to
address and confront hazardous alcohol use on campuses in order to curtail
heavy alcohol consumption and reduce the risk of alcohol-related problems in
pharmacy students.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="MESH"><kwd>Alcohol Drinking</kwd><kwd>Students, Pharmacy</kwd><kwd>United States</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>No financial support provided for this
project</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The hazardous use and abuse of alcohol has long been recognized as a potential danger
to the well-being of adults for many years. In recent years, concerns about alcohol
consumption among college students have garnered the public interest due to media
reports of the high levels of alcohol consumed on university campuses and its
potential negative impact. According to the National Survey on Drug Use and Health
in 2009, 63.9% of college students age 18 to 22 were current drinkers, with 43.5%
classified as binge drinkers. Even higher alcohol consumption rates are seen among
young adults age 21-25, with 70.2% being current drinkers and 41.7% are classified
as binge drinkers.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref> Although hazardous alcohol
consumption rates peak during the college age range and gradually taper with
increased age, there are still concerns regarding the rate of hazardous alcohol
consumption among college students since many negative consequences can result from
misuse.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></p><p>The college environment itself may contribute to the dynamics of hazardous drinking
among peers in the 18-24 age range. Eighteen percent of US college students that
participated in the 2001 National Household Survey on Drug Abuse<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref> (n=6352) experienced clinically significant
alcohol-related problems, compared with 15% of their peers of the same age who did
not attend college.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref> College students were
also more likely to meet criteria for a diagnosis of alcohol abuse based on the
Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 4th edition (DSM-IV)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref> criteria, than their non-college attending
counterparts.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref> Similar results were also found in a 2007 publication which
analyzed drinking patterns among adolescents in a longitudinal study. Investigators
followed students in their teens through their mid 20s and found that, compared with
their peers who never attended college, current college students were less likely to
binge drink prior to entering college but more likely to binge drink once they
entered college. This finding is attributed to the college environment.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> Since 2002, college students have consistently
had higher rates of current alcohol use and binge alcohol use compared to their
peers that did not attend college.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></p><p>Current information regarding hazardous alcohol use specifically among health-care
professional students in the university setting is scarce, especially in regards to
students enrolled in pharmacy schools. A recent study published in 2011, assessed
the use of alcohol and other drug use behaviors among pharmacy students at three
schools of pharmacy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref> The pharmacy schools
consisted of two Midwestern universities and one university in the southwest. Of the
respondents, 82.8% (566/864) reported alcohol use within the last year, with 18.2%
of students reporting a blackout secondary to drinking in the past year. Pharmacy
students within this study also reported that alcohol had the potential to
negatively affect their school grades and job performance, with 5.8% of respondents
stating alcohol use over the past year had cause them to perform lower in school or
work. Although this is the most recent study specifically assessing alcohol use
behaviors among pharmacy students published in the literature, it may not precisely
reflect current alcohol use trends among pharmacy students because the survey was
actually administered in the spring of 1999. Other studies have been conducted to
assess alcohol use in student pharmacists, however the majority of these studies
were published in the 1990s or used data obtained from student populations over a
decade ago.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref></p><p>The overall purpose of this study was to assess levels of alcohol consumption and
gauge the degree of hazardous drinking among pharmacy students in a larger sample
size that is representative of US pharmacy schools. Secondary objectives include:
(1) assessing alcohol-induced behaviors that could negatively impact pharmacy
students on the academic and professional level, (2) profile pharmacy student
attitudes regarding drinking in comparison to smoking cigarettes, and (3) identify
specific subgroups of pharmacy students that are significantly more in jeopardy of
having alcohol-related problems based on scores from the Alcohol Use Disorders
Identification Test.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Study Population</title><p>The data from this study was obtained by a prospective 32-item questionnaire that
was administered to nine pharmacy schools across the United States. The study
had at least one pharmacy school participating in each US region as defined by
the United States Census Bureau.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref> The
pharmacy schools participating in the study consisted of the following: one
public northeast pharmacy school, one private northeast pharmacy school, one
private south pharmacy school, two private midwest pharmacy schools, one public
midwest pharmacy school, one public west pharmacy school, and two public south
pharmacy schools. The only geographical divisional region not represented in the
study was the mountain division of the west region.</p><p>The study population included full-time students enrolled in the Doctor of
Pharmacy (PharmD) professional program of each pharmacy school. The only
pharmacy students excluded from the study were those not deemed an adult in the
participating state. The study was approved by Institutional Review Boards (IRB)
at all participating schools of pharmacy, unless not required at the
participating institution. </p></sec><sec><title>Procedures and Measurements</title><p>The questionnaire was conducted during the 2009-2010 academic year at 8 of the
universities and during the 2010-2011 academic year at 1 university. The
questionnaire consisted of basic demographic information, questions regarding
specific alcohol-induced behaviors, a question regarding the risks of smoking
cigarettes versus drinking alcohol, and the 10 question assessment from the
Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT).</p><p>The questionnaire was offered as an anonymous web-based survey, a paper-based
survey, or a mix of both formats, depending on each individual institution&#x02019;s
preference. Institutions that issued the survey via both methods issued
paper-surveys to subjects enrolled in the first 3 years of pharmacy school and
only used the web-based survey to target students in the fourth professional
year who were not easily accessible due to advanced pharmacy practice
experiences.</p><p>The scale used to assess levels of alcohol consumption and gauge the degree of
hazardous drinking among pharmacy students in the study was the Alcohol Use
Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT). The AUDIT, developed by the World Health
Organization, is a 10-item screening tool (available at:
<uri xlink:href="http://whqlibdoc.who.int/hq/2001/who_msd_msb_01.6a.pdf">http://whqlibdoc.who.int/hq/2001/who_msd_msb_01.6a.pdf</uri>) that
assesses alcohol usage over the past 12 months and assesses three domains of
alcohol usage: hazardous alcohol use, dependence symptoms, and harmful alcohol
use. The AUDIT includes 3 questions on frequency and amount of drinking
(questions 1-3), 3 questions on alcohol dependence (questions 4-6), and 4
questions on problems related to alcohol usage (questions 6-10). Each question
is scored from 0-4, with higher scores signifying a higher level of
alcohol-related problems. Composite scores were calculated for each returned
questionnaire.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref> Composite scores of
8 or higher on the AUDIT specify that subjects are at risk for alcohol-related
problems, including dependence. Scores ranging from 16-19 suggest a higher
degree of alcohol-related problems and scores greater than or equal to 20
represent drinkers who are at the most risk and should be evaluated by a
clinical specialist. The use of a score &#x02265;8 as the cutoff was chosen because
it has been validated and produces sensitivity in the mid ninetieth percentile
range.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref> The AUDIT screening also
performs as accurately as other alcohol-use screening test including the
Michigan Alcohol Screening Test (MAST) and CAGE questionnaire and it is one of
the four recommended screening tools to assess alcohol related problems at
colleges and universities.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref> A positive score (1 or
greater) on any of the 3 questions regarding alcohol dependence in the AUDIT may
represent signs of alcohol dependence.</p><p>Other questions regarding alcohol-consumption on the questionnaire included: (1)
Has drinking alcohol ever caused you to get behind in your school work? (2) Has
drinking alcohol ever caused you to be late for school or work? (3) Has drinking
alcohol ever caused you to get poor grades in school? (4) Has drinking alcohol
ever caused you to engage in inappropriate sexual activities? The survey
included a question asking the age when the respondent was first intoxicated.
Students were also asked about their perception of drinking with the question:
Do you feel that other students drink more than you do? Response options
included: &#x0201c;yes&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;no&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;maybe&#x0201d;. Lastly students were asked about whether
they thought drinking alcohol was worse than smoking cigarettes.</p></sec><sec><title>Data Analysis</title><p>Due to institutional IRB restrictions, all of the data was pooled and assessed as
an aggregate to prevent any identification of subjects. Upon completion of the
study, descriptive statistics were performed for the demographic data and other
questions on alcohol-related use, followed by Chi-squared analysis. AUDIT scores
were calculated for all respondents. As recommended by the World Health
Organization, scores of 8-15 were considered consistent with a medium level
alcohol problem and scores greater than or equal to 16 will be considered a high
level alcohol problem. To determine if certain demographic factors significantly
impacted AUDIT scores, Chi-squared analysis was performed with statistical
significance defined as an alpha level of 0.5.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>The questionnaire obtained data from a total of 1161 pharmacy students enrolled at
nine different schools of pharmacy. Demographic characteristics are reported in
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. There was a significant higher
ratio of females (64.1%) responding to the study then males (p=0.005). Students in
their twenties accounted for the largest portion of respondents (&#x0003e;80%), with
students in the age range of 21-23 holding the majority (45.7%). Most students
participating in the study were single (81.7%), lived off campus (84.6%), and did
not have children (91.5%). Over 82% of respondents reported having a grade point
average (GPA) &#x0003e;3.0 on a scale of 0-4. More survey respondents were in their second
year of professional study (35.7%), which was significantly higher than other
professional years (p&#x0003c;0.0005). Student respondents who did not have a prior
bachelor, masters, or doctorate degree represented 53.8% of the survey
population.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Student Demographics (n=1161).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="all"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Number (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Graduation Year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Professional Year 1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">297 (25.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Professional Year 2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">414 (35.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Professional Year 3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286 (24.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Professional Year 4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156 (13.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Response</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (0.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401 (34.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">744 (64.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Response</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (1.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age Range</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (7.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21-23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">530 (45.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24-25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">260 (22.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26-29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178 (15.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">= 30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (8.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Response</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (0.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous non-pharmacy degree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">501 (43.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No </td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">625 (53.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Response</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (3.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0-2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (2.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.51-3.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144 (12.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01-3.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">526 (45.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51-4.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">428 (36.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Response</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (2.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-Campus</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169 (14.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Off-Campus</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">982 (84.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Response</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (0.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital Status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married/Partnership</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187 (16.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single, Never Married</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">948 (81.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Divorced/Separated</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (1.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Widowed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Response</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (0.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Children</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (7.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1062 (91.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Response</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (0.6%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Of the 1161 student respondents, 86.4% currently consume alcohol based on the first
question of the AUDIT survey. The mean AUDIT score was 5.2, with scores ranging from
0 to 28. The median score among survey respondents was 4, with a score of 1 being
the most common score. Consumption of hazardous amounts of alcohol, as defined by an
AUDIT score greater than 8, was seen in 25.2% of respondents. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) Nearly 3% of respondents had an AUDIT score between
the ranges of 16-19, whereas 1.6% of respondents had a score greater than or equal
to 20. Over 25% of student respondents may show signs of alcohol dependence based on
the AUDIT specific questions for dependence (Questions 4-6). A score of 1 or greater
on these questions may represent signs of dependence.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Hazardous levels of drinking among pharmacy students.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pharmpract-09-162-g1"/></fig><p>Seventy-nine percent of respondents reported being intoxicated at some time in their
life, with 5.5% reporting being intoxicated the first time when they were less than
14 years old. The majority of respondents (41.8%) reported being intoxicated the
first time when they were between the ages of 14-18. Students who became intoxicated
at an earlier age (&#x0003c;14 years old) were statistically more likely to have AUDIT
scores that represented hazardous use (scores &#x02265; 8) compared to students who first
became intoxicated when they were &#x02265;14 years of age (p&#x0003c;0.0005). Students who
became intoxicated for the first time during their adolescence or childhood (&#x02264;18
years old) were also more likely to have an AUDIT score &#x02265; 8 compared to students
who did not become intoxicated until after turning 19 years old (p&#x0003c;0.0005).</p><p>Students in their first or second professional year were statistically more likely to
have AUDIT scores in the hazardous drinking range versus students in their third or
fourth professional year (p&#x0003c;0.0005). Compared to female survey respondents, male
respondents were statistically more likely to have an AUDIT score &#x02265;8
(p&#x0003c;0.0005). Student respondents that were not married were more likely to have an
AUDIT score &#x02265;8 compared to student respondents that were married or in
partnerships (p&#x0003c;0.0005). Pharmacy students without children were also more likely
to have AUDIT scores in the hazardous drinking range versus students with children
(p=0.001). GPA and housing did not statistically affect student&#x02019;s AUDIT scores.</p><p>Nearly a quarter of student respondents (24.2%) reported having engaged in
inappropriate sexual activities secondary to alcohol use. Students reporting alcohol
behaviors having a negative effect on school grades represented 6.5% of the
population surveyed, however 15.4% stated that alcohol use had lead them to falling
behind in their academic work. Tardiness to work or school because of alcohol was
reported in 17.3% of the respondents.</p><p>Eighty percent of students who completed the survey thought other students definitely
consumed more alcohol than they did, while 13% of the survey population said that
other students might drink more than they do. Four percent of students thought they
drank more alcohol than other subjects. As for which vice student respondents
thought was worse, 77% of student respondents thought smoking cigarettes was worse
than drinking alcohol.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study represents the most recent evaluation of alcohol usage among student
pharmacists. The AUDIT screening within the survey provided us with a standardized
scale to assess hazardous drinking behaviors in pharmacy students. Utilizing the
self-questionnaire approach with the AUDIT screening, rather than administered by an
interviewer, may prove a limitation of the study. Using the AUDIT as an interview
helps clarify ambiguous answers and may reduce errors in composite scores. The
self-questionnaire creates the possibility that some students may over-report or
under-report their alcohol usage.</p><p>Although the AUDIT screening has been validated in both genders and all age groups,
to the best of our knowledge this scale has not been used in studies assessing
alcohol-related behaviors in student pharmacists before. By using this tool we found
more than 25% of pharmacy students had AUDIT scores indicative of hazardous use of
alcohol. Due to their high AUDIT scores, many pharmacy students in this study may
also be &#x0201c;at risk&#x0201d; for alcohol dependence. Although the AUDIT scale does not formally
diagnose individuals with particular alcohol problems, it does serve as screening
tool to detect potential individuals who may be &#x0201c;at risk&#x0201d;. As future health
professionals with stressful jobs and easy access to alcohol, prescription, and
over-the-counter medications, this high incidence of misuse and risky behavior is
concerning. The risks associated with alcohol misuse needs to be addressed with
pharmacy students.</p><p>Regardless of their AUDIT scores, our findings also show a high percentage of
pharmacy students consume alcohol (86.4%). This percentage rate is higher compared
to college students evaluated in the 2009 National Drug Survey on Drug Use and
Health which showed that 63.9% of college students consume alcohol.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref> The percentage of students drinking in the
past year is also similar when compared to past studies that analyzed drinking
patterns among pharmacy students at individual institutions. Studies with data from
the 1990s showed that the percentage of pharmacy students who currently drank
alcohol ranged from 81.2% to 90.5%, which is comparable to results from this
study.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref> It was hypothesized by the authors that alcohol usage among pharmacy
students would be less than other college students due to the rigorous academic
workload required in pharmacy schools. The incidence of high AUDIT scores in
students without a previous degree or in their first two professional years may be
indicative of the fact that they are technically still undergraduates. Maturity may
be a contributor to seeing lower scores in upper classmen since alcohol consumption
tends to decrease as students progress out of their undergraduate years.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref> The majority of pharmacy schools included in
the survey are located directly on campuses with a large undergraduate presence
instead of being located at an academic medical center. This could have also
contributed to similar usage levels of alcohol between pharmacy students and
undergraduate students.</p><p>Although there is a lack of studies using the AUDIT as a screen for alcohol use in
pharmacy students, the AUDIT screening has been employed to assess at risk drinking
in students in other healthcare professionals. A recent study evaluated the
prevalence of at-risk drinking across 36 schools of medicine in the United
States.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref> This study included a larger
sample of schools and students (n=2710) compared to our study. Of the medical
students surveyed, 15.4% had AUDIT scores greater than 8. Due to the similarities in
length and rigor between pharmacy and medical schools, it is concerning that
pharmacy students had a higher percentage of students with AUDIT scores indicative
of hazardous alcohol use compared to medical students. Since medical school
attendees have a previous academic degree and medical school enrollees tend to be
older, they may have a higher level of maturity compared to entering pharmacy
students who may only be a few years out of high school.</p><p>Some findings in our study were not surprising. The higher average AUDIT score in
males, compared to females, was expected as alcohol abuse and dependence is commonly
higher in males.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref> AUDIT scores were higher
among pharmacy students who became intoxicated at a younger age. These results are
similar to a previous study which showed that individuals who became intoxicated for
the first time prior to the age of 19 were at a greater risk for heavy drinking and
alcohol-related problems.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref> Alcohol
influencing grades or work was also similar to previous studies that analyzed
alcohol-induced behaviors. Baldwin and colleagues reported that 6.3% of pharmacy
students received a lower grade or job evaluation because of alcohol.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref> In our study, 6.5% reported receiving poor
grades due to alcohol intake. Inappropriate sexual activity secondary to alcohol use
was seen in almost one-fourth of respondents. The investigators did not specify what
was considered inappropriate. Unintended sex after binge drinking was reported to
range from 13%-26% of pharmacy students at three pharmacy schools in 1998.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref> Our finding in this study may actually be
lower and more comparable to the 1998 study, since the question used in our survey
was not as specific and may include responses that reflect a more broad inclusion of
various sexual activities.</p><p>A limitation of this study was the inability to calculate a precise response rate for
the questionnaire. Due to logistical challenges with administering the survey at 9
different schools, not all students at every school were provided the opportunity to
take the survey. For schools offering only the online version, emails were sent to
all students. Some schools offering the paper version were able to offer the survey
to all professional years while other schools were only able to reach a smaller
percentage of their student population. The principal investigators were unable to
determine the exact number of students offered the opportunity to participate,
making calculation of response rate impossible.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In conclusion, more than 25% of pharmacy students at nine different pharmacy schools
have markers of dangerous and harmful alcohol use. The usage of alcohol among
pharmacy students is similar to students in undergraduate degree programs, but
hazardous usage is greater than students enrolled in medical schools. Male students,
those without a previous degree, and those with intoxication before the age of 19
show the greatest risk. Schools of pharmacy should continue to address and combat
alcohol use and misuse in order to reduce the risk of alcohol-related problems in
pharmacy students and future pharmacists.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The investigators of the study would like to acknowledge the following individuals
for their assistance with survey conduction: S Ali, C Fox, A Garcia, JS Gortney, PW
Jungnickel, M Lloy, MA Poepping-Faulkner, S Srivastava, and J Tilleman.</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p>Competing interests: The authors declare no conflicts of interest or financial
interests in any products or services mentioned in this article, including
grants, employment, gifts, stock holdings, or honoraria.</p><p>The AUDIT Questionnaire&#x02122; is a trademark of the World Health
Organization</p><p>SurveyMonkey&#x02122; is a trademark of SurveyMonkey.com, LLC.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services
Administration</collab> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Results from the 2009
National Survey on Drug use and Health: Volume I. Summary of National
Findings</source> (Office of Applied Studies, NSDUH Series H-38A, HHS
Publication No. SMA 10-4586 Findings). Rockville, MD.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surveying the damage: a review of research on consequences of
alcohol misuse in college populations</article-title><source>J Stud Alcohol Suppl</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12022733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services
Administration</collab> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Results from the 2001
National Household Survey on Drug Abuse: Volume I. Summary of National
Findings</source> (Office of Applied Studies, NHSDA Series H-17, DHHS
Publication No. SMA 02-3758). Rockville, MD.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Slutske</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol use disorders among US college students and their
non-college-attending peers</article-title><source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source><year>2005</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15753245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab>, <collab>American
Psychiatric Association</collab> Task Force on DSM-IV. <source>Diagnostic
and statistical manual of mental disorders</source> : DSM-IV-TR. 4th ed.
<publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American
Psychiatric Association</publisher-name>;
<year>2000</year></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Timberlake</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopfer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Haberstick</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lessem</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>College attendance and its effect on drinking behaviors in a
longitudinal study of adolescents</article-title><source>Alcohol Clin Exp Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1020</fpage><lpage>1030</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17403064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Desimone Ii</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Forrester</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substance use attitudes and behaviors at three pharmacy
colleges</article-title><source>Subst Abus</source><year>2011</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21302181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartek</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis-Hall</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Reardon</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>DeSimone</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of alcohol and other drug use behaviors in health
professions students</article-title><source>Subst Abus</source><year>2006</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17135178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kriegler</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of alcohol and other drug use behaviors and risk factors
in health profession students</article-title><source>J Am Coll Health</source><year>1994</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8046165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Noormohamed</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Baghaie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol use, drug use, and sexual activity among pharmacy
students at three institutions</article-title><source>J Am Pharm Assoc (Wash)</source><year>1998</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9782695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>McAuliffe</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Breer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyshak</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Santangelo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnuson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol use and abuse in random samples of physicians and medical
students</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><year>1991</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1990855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Banahan</surname><given-names>BF</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Borne</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparison of alcohol and illicit drug use between pharmacy
students and the general college population</article-title><source>Am J Pharm Educ</source><year>1990</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Murawski</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Juergens</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of longitudinal pharmacy student alcohol and other drug
use survey data</article-title><source>Am J Pharm Educ</source><year>2001</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Honeycutt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Sullivan</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Light</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingfield</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing substance abuse among health care students and the
efficacy of educational interventions</article-title><source>J Prof Nurs</source><year>1997</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9183110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kenna</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substance use by pharmacy and nursing practitioners and students
in a northeastern state</article-title><source>Am J Health Syst Pharm</source><year>2004</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>921</fpage><lpage>930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15156968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">U.S. Department of Commerce Economics and Statistics Administration
U.S. Census Bureau. Accessed at <uri xlink:href="http://www.census.gov/">http://www.census.gov/</uri><date-in-citation><month>1</month><day>25th</day><year>2011</year></date-in-citation></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group><name><surname>Babor</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins-Biddle</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group> The Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test.
Guidelines for Use in Primary Care. <year>2001</year></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Aasland</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Babor</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>de la Fuente</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test
(AUDIT): WHO Collaborative Project on Early Detection of Persons with
Harmful Alcohol Consumption--II</article-title><source>Addiction</source><year>1993</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8329970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bohn</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Babor</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kranzler</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT): validation
of a screening instrument for use in medical settings</article-title><source>J Stud Alcohol</source><year>1995</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7674678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Merz</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response burden, reliability, and validity of the CAGE, Short
MAST, and AUDIT alcohol screening measures</article-title><source>Behavioral Research Methods, Instruments &#x00026; Computers</source><year>1995</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>280</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Winters</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Toomey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miazga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening for alcohol problems among 4-year colleges and
universities</article-title><source>J Am Coll Health</source><year>2011</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>350</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21500052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sher</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotham</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transitioning into and out of large-effect drinking in young
adulthood</article-title><source>J Abnorm Psychol</source><year>2001</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11502081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazargan-Hejazi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of at-risk drinking among a national sample of medical
students</article-title><source>Subst Abus</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19347753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Ceylan-Isik</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex difference in alcoholism: who is at a greater risk for
development of alcoholic complication?</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20598716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Hingson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Heeren</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zakocs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age of first intoxication, heavy drinking, driving after drinking
and risk of unintentional injury among U.S. college students</article-title><source>J Stud Alcohol</source><year>2003</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12608480</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>