<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21097883</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3064789</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq1164</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkq1164</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Nucleic Acid Enzymes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Stoichiometry and affinity for thymine DNA glycosylase binding to specific and nonspecific DNA</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>Michael T.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maiti</surname><given-names>Atanu</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>Megan E.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Drohat</surname><given-names>Alexander C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology and Greenebaum Cancer Center, School of Medicine, University of Maryland, Baltimore, MD 21201, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 410 706 8118; Fax: +1 410 106 8297; Email: <email>adrohat@som.umaryland.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><!--For NAR both ppub and collection dates generated for PMC processing 1/27/05 beck--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>39</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2319</fpage><lpage>2329</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Deamination of 5-methylcytosine to thymine creates mutagenic G&#x000b7;T mispairs, contributing to cancer and genetic disease. Thymine DNA glycosylase (TDG) removes thymine from these G&#x000b7;T lesions, and follow-on base excision repair yields a G&#x000b7;C pair. A previous crystal structure revealed TDG (catalytic domain) bound to abasic DNA product in a 2:1 complex, one subunit at the abasic site and the other bound to undamaged DNA. Biochemical studies showed TDG can bind abasic DNA with 1:1 or 2:1 stoichiometry, but the dissociation constants were unknown, as was the stoichiometry and affinity for binding substrates and undamaged DNA. We showed that 2:1 binding is dispensable for G&#x000b7;U activity, but its role in G&#x000b7;T repair was unknown. Using equilibrium binding anisotropy experiments, we show that a single TDG subunit binds very tightly to G&#x000b7;U mispairs and abasic (G&#x000b7;AP) sites, and somewhat less tightly G&#x000b7;T mispairs. Kinetics experiments show 1:1 binding provides full G&#x000b7;T activity. TDG binds undamaged CpG sites with remarkable affinity, modestly weaker than G&#x000b7;T mispairs, and exhibits substantial affinity for nonspecific DNA. While 2:1 binding is observed for large excess TDG concentrations, our findings indicate that a single TDG subunit is fully capable of locating and processing G&#x000b7;U or G&#x000b7;T lesions.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>A large percentage of point mutations in cancer and genetic disease are C&#x02192;T transitions at CpG sites, resulting largely from replication of G&#x000b7;T mispairs created by deamination of 5-methylcytosine (m<sup>5</sup>C) to thymine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1 B2 B3 B4">1&#x02013;4</xref>). Thymine DNA glycosylase (TDG) is charged with finding these G&#x000b7;T lesions and removing thymine to initiate base excision repair, which ultimately restores a G&#x000b7;C base pair (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). Methyl binding domain IV (MBD4) is another DNA glycosylase that processes G&#x000b7;T mispairs arising from m<sup>5</sup>C deamination at CpG sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). About 4% of cytosines in mammalian DNA are methylated, selectively at CpG sites, and this key modification promotes transcriptional silencing and is essential for many cellular processes and for embryonic development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). It is known that cytosine 5-methyltransferases catalyze the conversion of C to m<sup>5</sup>C at CpG sites in DNA, but the mechanism for &#x02018;demethylation&#x02019; of m<sup>5</sup>CpG has remained elusive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). Several recent studies indicate a BER-mediated pathway for active demethylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>); many indicate a mechanism for active m<sup>5</sup>C deamination, giving a G&#x000b7;T mispair that could be processed by TDG (or MBD4) and BER to restore a G&#x000b7;C pair (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12 B13 B14 B15 B16">12&#x02013;16</xref>). A preliminary report that inactivation of TDG causes embryonic lethality in mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>), the first such finding for any DNA glycosylase, is consistent with an essential role for TDG in transcriptional regulation, in addition to processing G&#x000b7;T mispairs arising from spontaneous m<sup>5</sup>C deamination.</p><p>Given the critical role of TDG in protecting against C&#x02192;T mutations and its emerging role(s) in transcriptional regulation, it is important to obtain a detailed understanding of how TDG recognizes and processes lesions, how its activity is stimulated by the follow-on BER enzyme, APE1 and to characterize its interaction with undamaged CpG sites and nonspecific DNA. Our recent crystal structure of TDG (catalytic domain) bound to abasic DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>) revealed a remarkable 2:1 complex, with one TDG subunit bound at the abasic site and an adjacent subunit bound to undamaged DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Such 2:1 binding had not previously been observed for TDG, MUG or UNG. Our previous biochemical studies showed TDG, full length and catalytic domain, can bind abasic DNA with 1:1 or 2:1 stoichiometry, depending on TDG concentration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). However, the affinity for each TDG subunit (<italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>) remained unknown. Determining these values is important for understanding the catalytic mechanism of TDG and how its activity is stimulated by APE1, i.e. how the first steps of BER are coordinated. In addition, the stoichiometry for binding G&#x000b7;T or G&#x000b7;U substrates had not been examined. Although we previously showed 1:1 binding provides full catalytic activity for G&#x000b7;U lesions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>), TDG exhibits much weaker binding and catalysis for G&#x000b7;T relative to G&#x000b7;U substrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19 B20 B21 B22">19&#x02013;22</xref>), raising the question of whether 2:1 binding could be needed for efficient G&#x000b7;T repair. This is important, because G&#x000b7;T lesions are considered the predominant biological substrate for TDG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Our previous studies demonstrate TDG can excise bulky cytosine analogs from a CpG site in DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>), suggesting TDG may have substantial affinity for undamaged CpG sites, but this had not been determined. Additionally, previous studies suggest TDG possesses significant affinity for nonspecific DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>), but this has not been quantitatively examined. Determining the affinity and stoichiometry of TDG for binding CpG sites and nonspecific DNA is important for understanding its functions in DNA repair and transcriptional regulation. We address these important questions here using pre-steady-state kinetics and equilibrium binding experiments.
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>TDG can form a 2:1 complex with DNA. (<bold>A</bold>) Our previous crystal structure shows TDG (catalytic domain) can form a 2:1 complex with abasic DNA, one subunit (dark gray) binds the flipped abasic nucleotide and the adjacent subunit (light gray) binds to undamaged DNA. The protein&#x02013;protein interface buries &#x0223c;300&#x02009;&#x000c5;<sup>2</sup> of accessible surface area per subunit. (<bold>B</bold>) Cartoon depicting the contacts to DNA phosphates made by the specific TDG subunit (black triangles) and the nonspecific subunit (gray triangles) with respect to the lesion site (red). The DNA constructs used for the studies reported here are 16X11 (28&#x02009;bp) and 3X11 (15&#x02009;bp), where X represents the target nucleotide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). The 16X11 DNAs can accommodate 2:1 binding as observed in the crystal structure, but the 3X11 DNAs cannot.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1164f1"/></fig></p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>DNA synthesis and purification</title><p>The DNA used for this work is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. Duplex DNA was hybridized by rapid heating to 80&#x000b0;C followed by slow cooling to room temperature. DNA oligonucleotides were synthesized at the Keck Foundation Biotechnology Resource Laboratory of Yale University (trityl-on), purified using Glen-Pak purification cartridges (Glen Research), and quantified by absorbance (260&#x02009;nm) as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). Purity was verified by analytical anion-exchange high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) under denaturing (pH 12) conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>).
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>DNA used in this work. We used two non-cleavable substrate analogs, 2&#x02032;-deoxy-2&#x02032;-flouroarabinothymidine (T<sup>F</sup>) and 2&#x02032;-deoxy-2&#x02032;-flouroarabinouridine (U<sup>F</sup>) to monitor TDG binding to substrate in the absence of base excision. Two DNA constructs were used; 16X11 can accommodate 2:1 binding as seen in the crystal structure, while 3X11 cannot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). The target nucleotide (x&#x02009;=&#x02009;U<sup>F</sup>, T<sup>F</sup>, AP, T or C) is paired with guanine (bold) and placed in a CpG dinucleotide context, in keeping with the specificity of TDG. The DNA contains no other CpG site. The DNA was labeled at the 5&#x02032; end of the non-target strand (<bold>*</bold>) with sulforhodamine (also called Texas Red or TR) for anisotropy experiments or with fluorescein for EMSAs. The 28&#x02009;bp nonspecific DNA (NS28) contains no mispair or CpG site.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1164f2"/></fig></p><p>The oligonucleotides containing substrate analogs 2&#x02032;-deoxy-2&#x02032;-flouroarabinothymidine (T<sup>F</sup>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) or 2&#x02032;-deoxy-2&#x02032;-flouroarabinouridine (U<sup>F</sup>) were obtained as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). Control experiments demonstrate DNA containing U<sup>F</sup> or T<sup>F</sup> is completely resistant to cleavage by TDG (saturating concentration) for &#x0003e;48&#x02009;h, consistent with previous findings for TDG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>) and MUG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). Previous studies and our findings here indicate T<sup>F</sup> and U<sup>F</sup> are excellent mimics of dT and dU, and do not significantly perturb the structure of B-type DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26 B27 B28 B29">26&#x02013;29</xref>).</p><p>The DNA used for fluorescence anisotropy experiments was labeled with sulphorhodamine (Texas Red, TR) in the non-target strand (5&#x02032; amino C6 modifier), and was synthesized and purified (RP-HPLC) by the Midland Certified Reagent Co. (Midland, TX, USA).</p><p>Abasic (AP) DNA was generated by incubating 16U11 or 3U11 (2000&#x02009;nM) with a 1000-fold lower concentration (2&#x02009;nM) of uracil DNA glycosylase (UNG) at 23&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;min, sufficient time for complete conversion of substrate to abasic product (16AP11 or 3AP11), and used immediately for anisotropy or electrophoretic mobility shift assay (EMSA) experiments. After dilution of AP DNA (4000-fold) to the concentration used for anisotropy (0.5&#x02009;nM), the residual UNG (0.0005&#x02009;nM) is far too dilute to bind the AP DNA (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;15&#x02009;uM) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) or effect the binding of TDG. Although the higher AP&#x02013;DNA concentration used for EMSA (0.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) resulted in a higher residual UNG concentration (0.5&#x02009;nM), given its weak affinity for AP DNA, and the 1000-fold excess concentration of AP DNA, UNG will have no effect on TDG binding.</p></sec><sec><title>Enzyme purification</title><p>Human thymine DNA glycosylase (TDG) was expressed and purified as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>), flash frozen, and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C. The enzyme concentration is determined by absorbance, using a molar absorption coefficient of <italic>&#x003b5;</italic><sup>280&#x02009;</sup>=&#x02009;31.5&#x02009;mM<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, measured using the Edelhoch method, as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). We typically find TDG is fully active, as indicated by observation that for pre-steady-state multiple turnover kinetic experiments collected for G&#x000b7;U and G&#x000b7;FU substrates, the amplitude of the exponential phase is equal to the TDG concentration, (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1164/DC1">Supplementary Figures S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1164/DC1">S2</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>Kinetics experiments</title><p>We used single turnover kinetics experiments under saturating enzyme conditions ([E]&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;[S]&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x0003e;&#x02009;<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>) to obtain a rate constant (<italic>k</italic><sub>max</sub>) that is not influenced by product release or product inhibition. This is important because TDG exhibits very slow product release and strong product inhibition, which dominates <italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub> values determined using steady-state kinetics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). Experiments were collected at room temperature (23&#x000b0;C) in HEMN.1 buffer (0.02&#x02009;M HEPES, 0.2&#x02009;mM EDTA, 2.5&#x02009;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.1&#x02009;M NaCl). Experiments were initiated by adding concentrated TDG to buffered substrate, followed by rapid mixing. At various time points, aliquots were removed, quenched with 50% (v:v) 0.3&#x02009;M NaOH and 0.03&#x02009;M EDTA, and heated at 85&#x000b0;C for 15&#x02009;min to cleave the DNA backbone at enzyme-produced abasic sites. The fraction product was determined by HPLC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). The data were fitted to Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="M1">1</xref>) using nonlinear regression with Grafit 6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>):
<disp-formula id="M1"><label>(1)</label><graphic xlink:href="gkq1164m1"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>A</italic> is the amplitude, <italic>k</italic> is the rate constant and <italic>t</italic> is the reaction time (min). The DNA substrate concentration was 0.5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M, and the TDG concentration, 5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M, was nearly 300-fold higher than the <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> for G&#x000b7;T substrate binding determined here (see below). These saturating enzyme conditions provide the maximal rate constant for product formation (<italic>k</italic>&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;<italic>k</italic><sub>max</sub>).</p><p>We also determined the maximal rate of product formation using kinetics experiments as described above, but with saturating substrate conditions ([S]&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x0003e;&#x02009;<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>, and [S]&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x0003e;&#x02009;[E]) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). The data were fitted to Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="M2">2</xref>) using nonlinear regression with Grafit 6:
<disp-formula id="M2"><label>(2)</label><graphic xlink:href="gkq1164m2"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>A</italic> and <italic>k</italic> are the amplitude and rate constant of the exponential phase, <italic>v</italic> is steady-state velocity and <italic>t</italic> is time. The steady-state rate constant (<italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub>) is calculated by dividing steady-state velocity by enzyme concentration.</p></sec><sec><title>Fluorescence anisotropy experiments and data fitting</title><p>Equilibrium binding of TDG to DNA was studied by fluorescence anisotropy using a QuantaMaster 40 spectrofluorometer (PTI), monitoring the fluorescence of sulphorhodamine (Texas Red, or TR) conjugated to the 5&#x02032;-end of the non-target strand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Previous studies show the benefits of using X-rhodamine or sulphorhodamine for monitoring protein nucleic acid interactions by fluorescence anisotropy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35 B36 B37">35&#x02013;37</xref>). TDG was titrated into HEMN.1 buffer (above) that contained TR-labeled DNA, supplemented with 1% glycerol and 1&#x02009;uM BSA. The DNA concentration was maintained at a fixed value throughout the titration by adding concentrated enzyme in buffer that also contained DNA. After each addition of TDG, the sample was incubated for at least 2&#x02009;min before data collection to ensure binding was at equilibrium. This was confirmed by observation that the anisotropy was constant for at least 5&#x02009;min (for some data points). Anisotropy data were collected in T-format, where one PMT is connected directly to the sample compartment (no monochromator) with wavelength selection provided by a 628-nm band pass filter (Semrock, Inc.). The excitation wavelength was 590&#x02009;nm (3-nm band pass) and the single-emission monochromator was set to 615&#x02009;nm (5-nm band pass). Wavelength selection for the monochromators was enhanced with 586 and 624&#x02009;nm band-pass filters (Semrock, Inc.) for excitation and emission, respectively.</p><p>The equilibrium dissociation constants for TDG binding to TR-labeled DNA were determined by fitting the fluorescence anisotropy data to appropriate models using DynaFit 4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). The models and DynaFit scripts used for data fitting are given in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1164/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link>. The fitted parameters included dissociation constants for one or two binding sites on the DNA, and anisotropy values for free DNA (<italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>) and for 1:1 and 2:1 complexes with TDG (<italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub> and <italic>r</italic><sub>EED</sub>). In many cases, the data clearly indicate two nonequivalent binding sites. Model discrimination was also informed by the probability value of the Fisher&#x02019;s <italic>F</italic>-statistic, obtained from data fitting, where <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 is considered significant. The reported parameters are derived from global fitting of at least two independent binding experiments. We determined the equilibrium dissociation constant for TDG binding to unlabeled DNA using equilibrium competition anisotropy experiments, where TDG binding to TR-labeled 16U<sup>F</sup>11 was monitored in the presence of varying concentrations of unlabeled DNA. DynaFit was used for global fitting of the data to a model involving one or two TDG binding sites for the unlabeled DNA and two binding sites for TR-labeled 16U<sup>F</sup>11. A benefit of using DynaFit for the data presented here is that data fitting does not require an analytical equation, which could involve assumptions that are not compatible with experimental restraints. Indeed, the standard model for two nonequivalent binding sites assumes the species being monitored (DNA) is present at much lower concentration than the dissociation constant. This is not feasible for monitoring TDG binding to 16U<sup>F</sup>11, because the minimal DNA concentration needed for sufficient sensitivity in the anisotropy experiment (0.5&#x02009;nM) approximates the dissociation constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.6&#x02009;nM, see below).</p></sec><sec><title>Electrophoretic mobility shift assays</title><p>EMSAs were performed, essentially as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>), to provide an independent method for determining the stoichiometry of TDG&#x02013;DNA complexes. The EMSAs were performed with precast 6% polyacrylamide native gels (Invitrogen) and analyzed using a Typhoon 9400 imager (GE Healthcare).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Experimental approach</title><p>We used fluorescence anisotropy and EMSAs to determine the affinity and stoichiometry for TDG binding to DNA containing a U<sup>F</sup> or a T<sup>F</sup> substrate analog, an abasic (or AP) site, an undamaged CpG site, and nonspecific DNA. We and others have shown the U<sup>F</sup> and T<sup>F</sup> analogs are excellent mimics of the natural dU and dT substrates, because they allow formation of the catalytically competent enzyme&#x02013;substrate complex in the absence of base excision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). The U<sup>F</sup> and T<sup>F</sup> analogs differ from dU and dT only by replacement of 2&#x02032;-H with fluorine (2&#x02032;-fluoro<italic>arabino</italic>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>), which renders the base-sugar (<italic>N</italic>-glycosylic bond) of these and other nucleotides highly resistant to spontaneous and enzymatic cleavage. Previous studies show the 2&#x02032;-fluoroarabino substitution, in dT and other deoxynucleotides, promotes an O4&#x02032;-<italic>endo</italic> sugar pucker (rather than C2&#x02032;-<italic>endo</italic>), which is fully compatible with B-DNA geometry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). Although the O4&#x02032;-<italic>endo</italic> conformation in a substrate analog could potentially alter the binding of a DNA glycosylase, our previous studies indicate the effect is small for TDG binding to DNA containing a T<sup>F</sup> analog (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>).</p><p>Our studies employed two different DNA lengths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>), one that can accommodate 2:1 binding as observed in the TDG AP&#x02013;DNA crystal structure (16X11, X&#x02009;=&#x02009;target nucleotide) and a shorter construct (3X11) that lacks the nonspecific binding site seen in the crystal structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). For all DNAs used here, the target base is paired with guanine (i.e. G&#x000b7;T<sup>F</sup>), in keeping with the specificity of TDG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>).</p><p>For the fluorescence anisotropy experiments, the DNA was labeled with sulphorhodamine (Texas Red, TR) as indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. Previous studies indicate sulphorhodamine and X-rhodamine are well suited for characterizing protein&#x02013;DNA interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35 B36 B37">35&#x02013;37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>). When conjugated to DNA, these fluorophores are bright and typically exhibit fluorescence decay that is dominated by a single lifetime and relatively independent of conditions and protein binding, and their anisotropy is strongly correlated with DNA rotation, with minimal contribution from independent fluorophore mobility. These properties are highly desirable for studying protein&#x02013;DNA interactions, particularly for complex binding mechanisms as shown below for TDG.</p></sec><sec><title>TDG binding to a G&#x000b7;U mispair</title><p>We first consider equilibrium binding of TDG to 16U<sup>F</sup>11, which is long enough to accommodate 2:1 binding as observed in the TDG&#x000b7;AP&#x02013;DNA crystal structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B, the fluorescence anisotropy data clearly indicate two nonequivalent binding sites, and fitting to a two-site model reveals a huge difference in affinity, <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.16&#x02009;nM and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;662&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;108&#x02009;nM (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Thus, TDG forms a very tight 1:1 complex with the G&#x000b7;U<sup>F</sup> site, and a second TDG subunit binds with 1000-fold weaker affinity to give a 2:1 complex at high TDG concentrations. TDG binding to 16U<sup>F</sup>11 was qualitatively assessed using an EMSA, which confirms the binding stoichiometry indicted by the anisotropy data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C).
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>TDG binding to G&#x000b7;U<sup>F</sup> substrate analogs monitored by fluorescence anisotropy and EMSA. (<bold>A</bold>) Model for sequential 2:1 binding of TDG to two different sites on a 28&#x02009;bp DNA with a 16X11 construct. (<bold>B</bold>) Anisotropy data for equilibrium binding of TDG to the 16U<sup>F</sup>11 substrate analog (0.5&#x02009;nM), obtained from two independent experiments (open circle, open rectangle). Fitting the data to a two-site binding model using DynaFit 4 gives <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.16&#x02009;nM and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;662&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;108&#x02009;nM, and anisotropy values of <italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.182, <italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.220, <italic>r</italic><sub>EED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.275. (<bold>C</bold>) EMSA for TDG binding to 16U<sup>F</sup>11 (0.5&#x02009;uM), with the [TDG]:[DNA] ratio indicated. Arrows indicate anisotropy values or gel bands corresponding to free DNA (D), the 1:1 complex (ED), and the 2:1 complex (EED). (<bold>D</bold>) Anisotropy data for TDG binding to the 3U<sup>F</sup>11 analog (0.5&#x02009;nM) from two independent experiments (open circle, open rectangle). Fitting to a two-site binding model gives <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.9&#x02009;nM and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2650&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;463&#x02009;nM (and <italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.144, <italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.170, <italic>r</italic><sub>EED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.247). (<bold>E</bold>) EMSA for TDG binding to 3U<sup>F</sup>11 (0.5&#x02009;uM).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1164f3"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Equilibrium dissociation constants for TDG binding to specific and nonspecific DNA</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub> (nM)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub> (nM)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub><italic>/K</italic><sub>d1</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16U<sup>F</sup>11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">662&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1051</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3U<sup>F</sup>11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2650&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;463</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">315</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16T<sup>F</sup>11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1279&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;279</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3T<sup>F</sup>11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">818&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16AP11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1926&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;762</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1376</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3AP11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3480&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1173</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">561</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16C11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">965&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;148</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">293&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1172&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;254</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p><sup>a</sup>Parameters obtained from equilibrium competition experiments fitted to a model for two equivalent and independent binding sites (restrained to <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4*<italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>We also examined TDG binding to 3U<sup>F</sup>11, a DNA construct which lacks the entire binding site for the second TDG subunit of the 2:1 complex, as seen in the crystal structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. The anisotropy data show TDG forms a tight 1:1 complex with the G&#x000b7;U<sup>F</sup> site of 3U<sup>F</sup>11, <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.9&#x02009;nM, and a second TDG subunit can bind with very weak affinity, <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2650&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;463&#x02009;nM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D). The results of an EMSA confirm this binding stoichiometry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>E). Although 2:1 binding to 3U<sup>F</sup>11 is observed at high TDG concentrations, the second subunit must bind an alternate site from that seen in the crystal structure, as discussed below. Kinetics experiments show this alternate 2:1 complex does not contribute to G&#x000b7;U binding or processing, because catalytic activity is nearly the same for conditions that give 2:1 binding (saturating TDG) or 1:1 binding (saturating substrate, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1164/DC1">Supplementary Figure S.2</ext-link>). The finding that TDG binds tightly to 3U<sup>F</sup>11 shows the 2:1 complex observed in the crystal structure is not required for specific recognition of a G&#x000b7;U lesion, consistent with previous kinetics experiments showing 2:1 binding is not needed for full G&#x000b7;U catalytic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>).</p><p>A number of observations suggest the alternate 2:1 complex for 3U<sup>F</sup>11 (and other 3X11 DNAs) involves transient and nonspecific binding of the catalytic domain and/or the N-terminal region of TDG to DNA, and perhaps some degree of protein-protein interactions. Sedimentation velocity experiments show TDG is predominantly a monomer at concentrations of 20 and 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;M (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1164/DC1">Supplementary Figure S3</ext-link>). This indicates the alternate 2:1 complex, with <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.7&#x02009;&#x000b5;M (for 3U<sup>F</sup>11), is not comprised solely of protein&#x02013;protein interactions (though such interactions might be enhanced for DNA-bound TDG). Previous studies show the disordered N-terminal domain of TDG (residues 1&#x02013;120) forms nonspecific interactions with DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>), which may contribute to the alternate 2:1 complex. Consistent with this, <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub> is much weaker for the catalytic domain (TDG-core, 111&#x02013;308), which binds 3U<sup>F</sup>11 with <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;83&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;46&#x02009;nM and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x02009;&#x000b5;M (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1164/DC1">Supplementary Figure S4</ext-link>). Previous sedimentation velocity experiments show TDG-core is fully monomeric at 120&#x02009;&#x000b5;M (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Thus, <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;21&#x02009;&#x000b5;M for TDG-core binding to 3U<sup>F</sup>11 suggests the catalytic domain also exhibits nonspecific DNA interactions, because DNA binding seems unlikely to promote protein&#x02013;protein interactions for TDG-core (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>). Although the detailed nature of the alternate 2:1 complex is not presently clear, it only arises for large and excess concentrations of TDG, and it does not substantially alter catalytic activity.</p></sec><sec><title>TDG binding to a G&#x000b7;T mispair</title><p>The anisotropy and EMSA data for TDG binding to 16T<sup>F</sup>11, a G&#x000b7;T substrate analog that can accommodate 2:1 binding, are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A and B. Inspection of the anisotropy data suggests two nonequivalent sites, and fitting to a two-site model reveals tight binding of one TDG subunit to the G&#x000b7;T<sup>F</sup> site, <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x02009;nM, and weak binding of a second TDG subunit to give a 2:1 complex, <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1279&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;279&#x02009;nM. The total change in anisotropy (&#x00394;<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.090) is nearly identical to that observed for 16U<sup>F</sup>11 (&#x00394;<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.093). The EMSA for TDG binding to 16T<sup>F</sup>11 confirms 1:1 binding at lower TDG:DNA ratios and 2:1 binding at high TDG concentrations. The anisotropy data for TDG binding to 3T<sup>F</sup>11 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C), which cannot accommodate 2:1 binding (crystallographic), indicates relatively tight binding to the G&#x000b7;T site, <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;124&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;25&#x02009;nM, and weak binding of a second TDG subunit, <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;818&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;80&#x02009;nM, to give an alternate 2:1 complex. The EMSA for TDG binding to 3T<sup>F</sup>11 is consistent with this binding stoichiometry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>D). The relatively tight binding of TDG to 3T<sup>F</sup>11 shows the 2:1 complex in the crystal structure is not required for specific binding of TDG to a G&#x000b7;T mispair.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>TDG binding to G&#x000b7;T<sup>F</sup> substrate analogs monitored by fluorescence anisotropy and EMSAs. (<bold>A</bold>) Anisotropy data for equilibrium binding of TDG to 16T<sup>F</sup>11 (0.5&#x02009;nM), obtained from two independent experiments (open circle, open rectangle). Fitting to a two-site binding model gives <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x02009;nM, and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1279&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;279&#x02009;nM (and anisotropy of <italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.189, <italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.237, <italic>r</italic><sub>EED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.278). (<bold>B</bold>) EMSA for TDG binding to 16T<sup>F</sup>11 (0.5&#x02009;uM); the [TDG]:[DNA] ratio is indicated. (<bold>C</bold>) Anisotropy data for TDG binding to 3T<sup>F</sup>11 (0.5&#x02009;nM) obtained from two independent experiments (open circle, open rectangle). Fitting to a two-site model gives <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;124&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;25&#x02009;nM, and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;818&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;80&#x02009;nM (and <italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.150, <italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.176, <italic>r</italic><sub>EED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.273). To obtain a proper fit it was necessary to fix <italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.176, which is based on <italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.150 (fitted for 3T<sup>F</sup>11) and &#x00394;<italic>r</italic> for 1:1 binding to 3U<sup>F</sup>11 (&#x00394;<italic>r</italic><sub>1:1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub>&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;<italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.026). (If <italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub> is not fixed, <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub> and <italic>r</italic><sub>EED</sub> are poorly constrained and unreasonably high). The data are better fitted to a two-site rather than one-site binding model (<italic>P</italic> &#x02009;=&#x02009;0.011). Moreover, 2:1 binding to 3T<sup>F</sup>11 is indicated by observation that the total anisotropy change is slightly larger for 3T<sup>F</sup>11 (<italic>r</italic><sub>EED</sub>&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;<italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x00394;<italic>r</italic><sub>tot</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.123) than for 3U<sup>F</sup>11 (&#x00394;<italic>r</italic><sub>tot</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.103), for which 2:1 binding is demonstrated by anisotropy and EMSA. (<bold>D</bold>) EMSA for TDG binding to 3T<sup>F</sup>11 (0.5&#x02009;uM). Low population of the 2:1 complex at the highest TDG:DNA ratio is likely due to dissociation during electrophore2sis, as 3T<sup>F</sup>11 exhibits very rapid dissociation (<italic>k</italic><sub>off</sub>) from TDG (unpublished data).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1164f4"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>2:1 binding is not required for G&#x000b7;T repair activity</title><p>Our results indicate 2:1 binding to G&#x000b7;T mispairs is highly unlikely under limiting enzyme conditions, because <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub> is weak, and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x0003e;&#x02009;<italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>. Nevertheless, we sought to determine whether 2:1 binding, if it occurs, could enhance catalytic activity for G&#x000b7;T substrates. We showed previously that 2:1 binding is dispensable for G&#x000b7;U activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>), but the result could potentially differ for G&#x000b7;T activity, since binding and catalysis is much weaker for G&#x000b7;T relative to G&#x000b7;U substrates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). We used single turnover kinetics experiments with saturating TDG (5000&#x02009;nM) and limiting G&#x000b7;T substrate (500&#x02009;nM) such that 2:1 binding predominates. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A, the maximal rate of base excision is the same for a G&#x000b7;T substrate that can accommodate 2:1 binding (<italic>k</italic><sub>max</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and one that cannot (<italic>k</italic><sub>max</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). We conclude 2:1 binding does not enhance catalytic activity for G&#x000b7;T substrates.
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Kinetics experiments show 2:1 binding is not needed for processing G&#x000b7;T substrates. (<bold>A</bold>) Single turnover kinetics collected with saturating TDG (5000&#x02009;nM) and limiting G&#x000b7;T substrate (500&#x02009;nM), one of which can accommodate 2:1 binding (16T11, open circle) and one that cannot (4T11, open rectangle). Fitting the data (multiple experiments) to Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="M1">1</xref>) gives <italic>k</italic><sub>max</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (16T11) and <italic>k</italic><sub>max</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (4T11). We note that 4T11 is the minimal DNA construct that provides full G&#x000b7;T activity, due likely to non-specific interactions between the DNA (5&#x02032; of the dT target) and the N-terminal region of TDG (unpublished data). However, 4T11 still lacks the entire binding site for the second TDG subunit as seen in the crystal structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). (<bold>B</bold>) Pre-steady-state multiple-turnover kinetics collected with saturating G&#x000b7;T substrate (2000&#x02009;nM) and limiting TDG (200&#x02009;nM). Fitting the data (multiple experiments) for 16T11 (open circle) to Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="M2">2</xref>) gives a rate constant of <italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and amplitude <italic>A</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;134&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x02009;nM for the exponential phase, and a rate constant of <italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0006&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0003&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for the steady-state phase. The parameters are very similar for 4T11 (open rectangle); <italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <italic>A</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;117&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x02009;nM, and <italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0002&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0001&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Observation of slightly greater amplitude for 16T11 indicates 1:1 binding to both substrates, because 4T11 cannot accommodate 2:1 binding, consistent with other results above. For G&#x000b7;T substrates, we typically find <italic>A</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;[TDG]. However, for G&#x000b7;U and G&#x000b7;FU substrates, we find <italic>A</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x0223c;[TDG], indicating TDG is fully active (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1164/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1</ext-link>). We are currently investigating the basis of the diminished amplitude for G&#x000b7;T substrates. However, this does not alter our conclusion that 2:1 binding is not needed for G&#x000b7;T activity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1164f5"/></fig></p><p>We also approached this question using pre-steady-state multiple turnover kinetics, collected with saturating G&#x000b7;T substrate (2000&#x02009;nM) and limiting TDG (200&#x02009;nM), such that 2:1 binding is negligible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B). Under these conditions, TDG exhibits an exponential phase, <italic>k</italic><sub>obs</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, reflecting the maximal rate of base excision, followed by a much slower steady-state phase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). Observation that the maximal base excision rate is nearly the same for conditions of saturating TDG or saturating G&#x000b7;T substrate confirms that 2:1 binding, if it occurs, does not substantially enhance G&#x000b7;T activity.</p></sec><sec><title>TDG binding to abasic DNA product</title><p>It is also important to determine the stoichiometry and affinity for TDG binding to its abasic (or AP) DNA product. Anisotropy data for TDG binding to 16AP11 DNA, which contains a G&#x000b7;AP site and is long enough to accommodate 2:1 binding, are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A. The anisotropy data indicate two nonequivalent sites, and fitting to a two-site model reveals tight binding of one TDG subunit to the AP site, <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4&#x02009;nM and very weak binding of a second TDG subunit to give a 2:1 complex, <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1926&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;762&#x02009;nM. The EMSA for TDG binding to 16AP11 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B) confirms the binding stoichiometry indicated by anisotropy; 1:1 binding at lower TDG:DNA ratios and 2:1 binding for large and excess TDG concentrations.
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>TDG binding to abasic (AP) DNA product monitored by fluorescence anisotropy and EMSA. (<bold>A</bold>) Anisotropy data for equilibrium binding of TDG to 16AP11 (0.5&#x02009;nM). Fitting to a two-site binding model gives <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4&#x02009;nM and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1926&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;762&#x02009;nM (and anisotropy of <italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.178, <italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.233, <italic>r</italic><sub>EED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.276). Due to slow dissociation of AP DNA from TDG, the anisotropy data were collected using individual samples that were incubated for at least 2&#x02009;h prior to data collection to ensure equilibration. Our unpublished data by stopped-flow and other kinetic methods show 2&#x02009;h is sufficient for equilibration (confirmed in some cases by repeating measurements after additional equilibration time). (<bold>B</bold>) EMSA for TDG binding to 16AP11 (0.5&#x02009;uM), with the [TDG]:[DNA] ratio indicated. (<bold>C</bold>) Anisotropy data for TDG binding to 3AP11 (0.5&#x02009;nM) obtained from two independent experiments (open circle, open rectangle). Fitting to a two-site binding model gives <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3&#x02009;nM and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3480&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1173&#x02009;nM (and anisotropy of <italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.144, <italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.200 and <italic>r</italic><sub>EED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.271). (<bold>D</bold>) EMSA for TDG binding to 3AP11 (0.5&#x02009;uM).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1164f6"/></fig></p><p>Anisotropy data for TDG binding to 3AP11 indicates relatively tight binding to the G&#x000b7;AP site, <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3&#x02009;nM, and very weak binding of a second TDG subunit to give an alternate 2:1 complex, <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3480&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1173&#x02009;nM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C). The stoichiometry and relative affinities indicated by the anisotropy experiments are qualitatively confirmed by an EMSA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>D). The tight binding of a single TDG subunit to 3AP11 shows that a second TDG subunit is not required for specific binding to a G&#x000b7;AP product site.</p></sec><sec><title>TDG binding to an undamaged CpG site</title><p>It is known that TDG is specific for G&#x000b7;T mispairs and other lesions located in a CpG sequence context (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>), but the affinity of TDG for an undamaged CpG site had not been determined. Such knowledge is important for understanding how TDG locates G&#x000b7;T mispairs arising at CpG sites and its role(s) in transcriptional regulation. We previously showed TDG exhibits exceedingly low activity for cleaving cytosine from a CpG site (&#x0003c;1% product in 8&#x02009;h), thus binding studies can be performed in the absence of base cleavage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). Anisotropy and EMSA data for TDG binding to 28-bp DNA containing a CpG site (16C11) are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A and 7B. The anisotropy data indicate that TDG binds the CpG site with remarkably tight affinity, <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10&#x02009;nM, and a second TDG subunit binds with much weaker affinity, <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;965&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;148&#x02009;nM, at high TDG concentrations. The EMSA confirms the stoichiometry indicated by the anisotropy data.
<fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>TDG binding to DNA containing a single CpG site, monitored by fluorescence anisotropy and an EMSA. (<bold>A</bold>) Anisotropy data for equilibrium binding of TDG to the 28-bp 16C11 DNA (0.5&#x02009;nM) obtained from two independent experiments (open circle, open rectangle). Fitting to a two-site binding model gives <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10&#x02009;nM, and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;965&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;148&#x02009;nM (and anisotropy of <italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.180, <italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.223, <italic>r</italic><sub>EED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.275). To obtain a good fit, it was necessary to fix <italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.223. This value is the sum of <italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.180 (fitted for 16C11) and &#x00394;<italic>r</italic><sub>1:1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.043 (average of &#x00394;<italic>r</italic><sub>1:1</sub> values for 16U<sup>F</sup>11 and 16T<sup>F</sup>11). Otherwise, the fitted <italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub> is unreasonably high (0.25), and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub> and <italic>r</italic><sub>EED</sub> are poorly constrained. The data are better fitted to model for two-site versus one-site binding (dashed line, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.010). (<bold>B</bold>) EMSA for TDG binding to 16C11 (0.5&#x02009;uM), with the [TDG]:[DNA] ratios given. (<bold>C</bold>) Equilibrium competition anisotropy experiments for TDG binding to TR-labeled 16U<sup>F</sup>11 (0.5&#x02009;nM) collected in the absence of 16C11 (open circle and open triangle, data from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B) and in the presence of 16C11 at a concentration of 50&#x02009;nM (open rectangle) or 125&#x02009;nM (open rhombus). The data were fitted globally to model with two TDG binding sites for 16U<sup>F</sup>11 and 16C11, giving <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8&#x02009;nM for 16C11, and <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.14&#x02009;nM and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;673&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;100&#x02009;nM for 16U<sup>F</sup>11 (anisotropy for 16U<sup>F</sup>11 of <italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.182, <italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.221, <italic>r</italic><sub>EED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.274). <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub> for 16C11 is poorly constrained by the data (and unreasonably large). Fitting the data to a competition model with one site for 16C11 gives the same <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub> (within error). However, the data in (A) and (B) show TDG can form a 2:1 complex with 16C11.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1164f7"/></fig></p><p>To obtain another measure of TDG affinity for an undamaged CpG site, we performed equilibrium competition experiments, by collecting anisotropy data for TDG binding to 16U<sup>F</sup>11 (labeled) in the presence of two different concentrations of unlabeled 16C11 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>C). Global fitting of all the data to a model describing two TDG binding sites for 16U<sup>F</sup>11 and 16C11 gives <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8&#x02009;nM for 1:1 binding to 16C11, but <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub> is poorly constrained by the data (and unreasonably large). The global fitting provides another measure of TDG affinity for 16U<sup>F</sup>11 in the presence of a DNA competitor, giving dissociation constants identical to those obtained in the absence of 16C11. Our results show TDG binds tightly to undamaged CpG sites, with an affinity that is merely 4-fold lower than for G&#x000b7;T mispairs.</p></sec><sec><title>TDG binding to nonspecific DNA</title><p>To gain perspective on the binding affinity of the second TDG subunit (<italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>) of the 2:1 complex, which binds a nonspecific region of DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>), we determined the affinity of TDG for binding DNA that is entirely nonspecific (contains no mispair or CpG site). We determined the affinity of TDG for 28-bp nonspecific DNA (NS28) using equilibrium competition binding experiments, by collecting anisotropy data for TDG binding to 16U<sup>F</sup>11 (labeled) in the presence of fixed concentrations of unlabeled NS28 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>A). Global fitting of data collected in the presence and absence of NS28 to a competitive model describing two binding sites for 16U<sup>F</sup>11 and two equivalent and independent binding sites for NS28 (i.e. restrained to <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4*<italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>) gives <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;293&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;64&#x02009;nM and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1172&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;254&#x02009;nM. The latter value falls in the range of <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub> values for other DNAs examined here (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Fitting the data to a model with just one site for NS28 gives essentially the same result, <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;279&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;69&#x02009;nM. However, the two-site model is consistent with a binding analysis by EMSA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>B), which shows a 1:1 complex at lower [TDG]/[NS28] ratios and a 2:1 complex for large and excess TDG concentrations. Global fitting of the data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>A also provides a measure of TDG affinity for 16U<sup>F</sup>11 in the presence of nonspecific DNA, and gives essentially the same dissociation constants as obtained in the absence of NS28. Our findings show TDG possesses substantial affinity for nonspecific DNA.
<fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>TDG binding to nonspecific DNA monitored fluorescence anisotropy and an EMSA. (<bold>A</bold>) Equilibrium competition anisotropy experiments for TDG binding to TR-labeled 16U<sup>F</sup>11 (0.5&#x02009;nM) collected in the absence of NS28 (open circle, open triangle) and with NS28 concentrations of 200&#x02009;nM (open rectangle) or 500&#x02009;nM (open rhombus). Global fitting of all data to model involving two TDG binding sites for 16U<sup>F</sup>11 and two equivalent and independent sites for NS28 (i.e. restrained to <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4*<italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>) gives <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;293&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;64&#x02009;nM and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1172&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;254&#x02009;nM for NS28. For 16U<sup>F</sup>11, the fitting gives <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.88&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13&#x02009;nM and <italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;654&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;62&#x02009;nM (and anisotropy of <italic>r</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.189, <italic>r</italic><sub>ED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.221, <italic>r</italic><sub>EED</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.278). Fitting the data to a model involving a single site for NS28 gives essentially the same result for NS28 binding, <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;279&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;69&#x02009;nM, and for the 16U<sup>F</sup>11 parameters (data not shown). (<bold>B</bold>) EMSA for TDG binding to 28&#x02009;bp nonspecific DNA (NS28, 0.5&#x02009;uM) with the [TDG]:[DNA] ratio indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkq1164f8"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The remarkable observation from previous structural and biochemical studies that TDG can bind abasic DNA with 1:1 or 2:1 stoichiometry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>) raised the important questions of whether 2:1 binding contributes to the ability of TDG to find and initiate the repair of G&#x000b7;T and G&#x000b7;U lesions or to the mechanism by which APE1 stimulates TDG activity. We investigated these questions by determining the stoichiometry and affinity for TDG binding to a G&#x000b7;U or G&#x000b7;T substrate analog, an abasic site, an undamaged CpG site, and to nonspecific DNA.</p><p>Our findings provide insight into how TDG recognizes and processes G&#x000b7;U mispairs. TDG forms a very tight 1:1 complex with a G&#x000b7;U mispair (<italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.6&#x02009;nM, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), and a second subunit can bind with much weaker affinity (<italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;660&#x02009;nM) for high concentrations of TDG that are in great excess over G&#x000b7;U DNA. The tight binding to a G&#x000b7;U mispair observed here is consistent with previous results using DNA containing a G&#x000b7;U<sup>F</sup> analog (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). TDG also binds tightly to 3U<sup>F</sup>11 (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8&#x02009;nM), showing the 2:1 complex observed in the TDG crystal structure is not needed for specific recognition of a G&#x000b7;U mispair. This is consistent with our previous kinetics experiments showing 1:1 binding provides full G&#x000b7;U catalytic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). The 1000-fold difference in binding affinity for the two sites of the 2:1 complex, and the weak affinity of the second site relative to nonspecific DNA (NS28), indicates that under conditions of limiting enzyme and a huge excess of nonspecific DNA, TDG processes G&#x000b7;U lesions with 1:1 stoichiometry. This conclusion is supported by previous footprinting experiments, which indicated 1:1 binding to DNA containing a G&#x000b7;U<sup>F</sup> analog under conditions of limiting TDG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). However, given that other glycosylases process G&#x000b7;U lesions much more efficiently than TDG, the more relevant question is whether 2:1 binding contributes to repair of G&#x000b7;T lesions, the primary biological target of TDG.</p><p>Our results indicate that TDG also binds and processes G&#x000b7;T lesions with 1:1 stoichiometry. TDG binds tightly to 28&#x02009;bp DNA containing a G&#x000b7;T substrate analog (<italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;18&#x02009;nM), and a second subunit binds with much weaker affinity (<italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1280&#x02009;nM) for large and excess concentrations of TDG. The large difference in affinity for the two sites (<italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>/<italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;71) and the weak affinity of TDG for the second site (<italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>) relative to nonspecific DNA indicates 2:1 binding to G&#x000b7;T mispairs is unlikely for cellular conditions of limiting TDG and a large excess of nonspecific DNA. Moreover, the relatively tight affinity of TDG for 3T<sup>F</sup>11 indicates the 2:1 complex is not needed for specific recognition of G&#x000b7;T lesions. Finally, our kinetics experiments show that 1:1 binding provides full catalytic activity for G&#x000b7;T processing.</p><p>We find TDG binds a G&#x000b7;T mispair with about 30-fold weaker affinity than a G&#x000b7;U mispair. This is likely explained by the methyl group at C5 of thymine (uracil has hydrogen at C5), which may diminish the lifetime of the dT nucleotide in the flipped state due to steric hindrance in the TDG active site, as suggested by our previous kinetics results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). Given that G&#x000b7;T lesions arising at CpG sites are likely the predominant biological target of TDG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>), one might expect TDG to have evolved to bind more tightly to G&#x000b7;T mispairs. The weaker affinity for G&#x000b7;T mispairs may reflect a compromise between the competing needs for efficient processing of G&#x000b7;T lesions and avoiding the excision of T from the huge excess of A&#x000b7;T base pairs, which is governed in part by the 18&#x02009;000-fold specificity of TDG for excising T from G&#x000b7;T versus A&#x000b7;T pairs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>).</p><p>Previous studies show TDG binds tightly to its AP DNA product, and that AP DNA is a potent inhibitor of the TDG reaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>). Our anisotropy results here show TDG forms a very tight 1:1 complex with its reaction product, a G&#x000b7;AP site (<italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.4&#x02009;nM), and a second subunit binds with much weaker affinity (<italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.9&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) for large and excess concentrations of TDG. The huge difference in affinity for the two sites (<italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>/<italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1376) and the weak affinity of TDG for the second site (<italic>K</italic><sub>d2</sub>) relative to nonspecific DNA indicates 2:1 binding to abasic sites is unlikely for cellular conditions of limiting TDG and excess nonspecific DNA. The conclusion that a second TDG subunit is not needed for tight binding to G&#x000b7;AP sites is supported by the high affinity of TDG for 3AP11 (<italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6&#x02009;nM).</p><p>Our findings have important implications for the stimulation of TDG activity by the follow-on base excision repair enzyme, APE1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). We previously showed that APE1 greatly enhances TDG activity, increasing its rate of steady-state turnover (<italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub>) by 42- and 26-fold for G&#x000b7;T and G&#x000b7;U substrates, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). Our results here indicate that under the conditions used for these previous studies, limiting concentrations of TDG (and APE1) and a saturating amount of TDG substrate, TDG binds its product with 1:1 stoichiometry. Thus, the stimulatory effect of APE1 does not involve a TDG product complex with 2:1 stoichiometry. Consistent with this conclusion, we previously observed potent stimulation of TDG by APE1 for a short DNA that cannot accommodate two TDG subunits (3U12 substrate or 3AP12 product) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). Together, these studies indicate the stimulatory effect of APE1 involves a TDG product complex with 1:1 stoichiometry.</p><p>The affinity of TDG for an undamaged CpG site had not been quantitatively examined, despite the strong specificity of TDG for G&#x000b7;T mispairs (and other lesions) that are located in a CpG sequence context. We find TDG binds DNA containing a CpG site (16C11) with remarkable affinity, <italic>K</italic><sub>d1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;63&#x02009;nM, about 4-fold weaker than its affinity for the same DNA containing a G&#x000b7;T lesion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The specificity for a CpG site is also indicated by observation that TDG binds 4-fold tighter to 16C11 than to nonspecific DNA (NS28) that contains no CpG site but is otherwise identical. On an experimental note, our findings indicate that studies of TDG binding to a particular site (i.e. a G&#x000b7;T mispair) should use DNA that does not contain an undamaged CpG site.</p><p>Preferential binding to CpG requires a mechanism for recognizing these sites within a large background of nonspecific DNA. Previous studies suggest TDG may accomplish this by transiently flipping 2&#x02032;-deoxycytidine (dC) out of a CpG site and into its active site (or flipping it partially into the active site). Our crystal structure indicates specificity for excising lesions from a CpG site involves interactions with the 3&#x02032;-guanine (5&#x02032;-Xp<underline>G</underline>, X&#x02009;=&#x02009;lesion) that cannot be formed in the absence of nucleotide flipping (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>), which suggests nucleotide (dC) flipping may be required for recognizing undamaged CpG sites. The ability of TDG to flip dC into its active site is indicated by our previous finding that TDG can cleave analogs of dC that have a weakened <italic>N</italic>-glycosylic bond (e.g. 5-fluoro-dC, 5-hydroxy-dC, etc.) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). However, these results do not rule out a mechanism whereby TDG recognizes CpG sites in the absence of nucleotide flipping. Further studies are needed to resolve this question.</p><p>The ability of TDG to bind CpG sites and transiently flip dC into its active site, suggested by the findings herein and in our previous studies, may be important in the search for G&#x000b7;T lesions arising from deamination of m<sup>5</sup>C, a modified base found selectively at CpG sites. In addition, the affinity of TDG for undamaged CpG sites and nonspecific DNA may be important for its ability to modulate the activity of transcription factors including retinoic acid and retinoid X receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>), estrogen receptor &#x003b1; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>) and thyroid transcription factor 1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>), and co-activators such as CBP/p300 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>). Additional studies are needed to explore these ideas further.</p><p>In summary, we find TDG binds tightly to G&#x000b7;U and G&#x000b7;T mispairs, with subnanomolar and low nanomolar affinity, respectively, and that 1:1 binding provides full G&#x000b7;T repair activity. TDG forms a very tight 1:1 complex with abasic (G&#x000b7;AP) sites, indicating the stimulatory effect of APE1 does not require 2:1 binding of TDG to its product. TDG binds tightly to undamaged CpG sites, about 4-fold weaker than to G&#x000b7;T mispairs, and it exhibits substantial affinity for nonspecific DNA. While 2:1 binding to DNA is observed <italic>in vitro</italic> for large and excess concentrations of TDG, our results indicate that a single TDG subunit is fully capable of finding and processing G&#x000b7;U and G&#x000b7;T lesions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkq1164/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online.</p>
      
         <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
            <caption>
               <title>Supplementary Data</title>
            </caption>
            <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_39_6_2319__index.html"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
                   xlink:href="supp_gkq1164_Morgan_Drohat_Supplementary_Data.pdf"/>
         </supplementary-material>
      </sec><sec><title>FUNDING</title><p>The <funding-source>National Institutes of Health</funding-source> (<award-id>R01-GM-072711</award-id>). Funding for open access charge: <funding-source>National Institutes of Health</funding-source>, USA.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We thank Petr Kuzmic for assistance with DynaFit, Jim Stivers (Johns Hopkins University) for providing purified human uracil DNA glycosylase, L. Eisele (NY State Department of Health) for collecting sedimentation velocity analytical ultracentrifugation data and the reviewers for excellent suggestions.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rideout</surname><given-names>WM</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name><surname>Coetzee</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Olumi</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>5-Methylcytosine as an endogenous mutagen in the human LDL receptor and p53 genes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1990</year><volume>249</volume><fpage>1288</fpage><lpage>1290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1697983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Youssoufian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The CpG dinucleotide and human genetic disease</article-title><source>Hum. Genet.</source><year>1988</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3338800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sjoblom</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandelker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Leary</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ptak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Silliman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The consensus coding sequences of human breast and colorectal cancers</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>314</volume><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16959974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Besaratinia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutational spectra of human cancer</article-title><source>Hum Genet</source><year>2009</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19308457</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiebauer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mismatch-specific thymine DNA glycosylase and DNA polymerase beta mediate the correction of G.T mispairs in nuclear extracts from human cells</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1990</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>5842</fpage><lpage>5845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2116008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiebauer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro correction of G.T mispairs to G.C pairs in nuclear extracts from human cells</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1989</year><volume>339</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2716851</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellacosa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cicchillitti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schepis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Riccio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Golemis</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Genuardi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Neri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MED1, a novel human methyl-CpG-binding endonuclease, interacts with DNA mismatch repair protein MLH1</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>3969</fpage><lpage>3974</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10097147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hendrich</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardeland</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The thymine glycosylase MBD4 can bind to the product of deamination at methylated CpG sites</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1999</year><volume>401</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10499592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klose</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic DNA methylation: the mark and its mediators</article-title><source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source><year>2006</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16403636</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hajkova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeffries</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Surani</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide reprogramming in the mouse germ line entails the base excision repair pathway</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2010</year><volume>329</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20595612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wossidlo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sebastiano</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepikhov</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Boiani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhardt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic link of DNA demethylation, DNA strand breaks and repair in mouse zygotes</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2010</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1877</fpage><lpage>1888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20442707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhutani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Damian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbel</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Blau</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reprogramming towards pluripotency requires AID-dependent DNA demethylation</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2010</year><volume>463</volume><fpage>1042</fpage><lpage>1047</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20027182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popp</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cokus</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Reik</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide erasure of DNA methylation in mouse primordial germ cells is affected by AID deficiency</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2010</year><volume>463</volume><fpage>1101</fpage><lpage>1105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20098412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metivier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallais</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiffoche</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Peron</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurkowska</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmouche</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibberson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Barath</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Demay</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cyclical DNA methylation of a transcriptionally active promoter</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>452</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18322525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kangaspeska</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stride</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Metivier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Polycarpou-Schwarz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibberson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmouche</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Benes</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gannon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transient cyclical methylation of promoter DNA</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>452</volume><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18322535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jost</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Angliker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuller-Pace</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A chicken embryo protein related to the mammalian DEAD box protein p68 is tightly associated with the highly purified protein&#x02013;RNA complex of 5-MeC-DNA glycosylase</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>3245</fpage><lpage>3252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10454630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cortazar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinacher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The enigmatic thymine DNA glycosylase</article-title><source>DNA Repair</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17116428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maiti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozharski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Drohat</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of human thymine DNA glycosylase bound to DNA elucidates sequence-specific mismatch recognition</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>8890</fpage><lpage>8895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18587051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Swann</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetics of the action of thymine DNA glycosylase</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>20007</fpage><lpage>20014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9685338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hardeland</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentele</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Separating substrate recognition from base hydrolysis in human thymine DNA glycosylase by mutational analysis</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>33449</fpage><lpage>33456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10938281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Drohat</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Excision of 5-halogenated uracils by human thymine DNA glycosylase: robust activity for DNA contexts other than CpG</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2007</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>27578</fpage><lpage>27586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17602166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maiti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Drohat</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of two strictly conserved residues in nucleotide flipping and N-glycosylic bond cleavage by human thymine DNA glycosylase</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2009</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>36680</fpage><lpage>36688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19880517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The main role of human thymine-DNA glycosylase is removal of thymine produced by deamination of 5-methylcytosine and not removal of ethenocytosine</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>8739</fpage><lpage>8744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12493755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruslander</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisele</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Drohat</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specificity of human thymine DNA glycosylase depends on N-glycosidic bond stability</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2006</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>12510</fpage><lpage>12519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16984202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steinacher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functionality of human thymine DNA glycosylase requires SUMO-regulated changes in protein conformation</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>616</fpage><lpage>623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15823533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scharer</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawate</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallinari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdine</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the mechanisms of DNA binding of the human G/T glycosylase using designed inhibitors</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>4878</fpage><lpage>4883</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9144158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Scharer</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name><name><surname>Savva</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdine</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearl</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of a thwarted mismatch glycosylase DNA repair complex</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>6599</fpage><lpage>6609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10581234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tereshko</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Egli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structures of B-DNA with incorporated 2&#x02032;-deoxy-2&#x02032;-fluoro- arabino-furanosyl thymines: implications of conformational preorganization for duplex stability</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>2473</fpage><lpage>2480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9580702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drohat</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagadeesh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stivers</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of electrophilic and general base catalysis in the mechanism of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> uracil DNA glycosylase</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>11866</fpage><lpage>11875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Stivers</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of uracil DNA glycosylase by an oxacarbenium ion mimic</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2002</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>7116</fpage><lpage>7124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12033946</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>von Hippel</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calculation of protein extinction coefficients from amino acid sequence data</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem.</source><year>1989</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2610349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallinari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Swann</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human thymine DNA glycosylase binds to apurinic sites in DNA but is displaced by human apurinic endonuclease 1</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9867812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Drohat</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coordinating the initial steps of base excision repair. Apurinic/apyrimidinic endonuclease 1 actively stimulates thymine DNA glycosylase by disrupting the product complex</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>32680</fpage><lpage>32690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18805789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leatherbarrow</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Grafit 6</italic>, Erithacus Software Ltd</article-title><year>1998</year><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Staines</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perez-Howard</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Weil</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Beechem</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yeast TATA binding protein interaction with DNA: fluorescence determination of oligomeric state, equilibrium binding, on-rate, and dissociation kinetics</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1995</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>8005</fpage><lpage>8017</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7794913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unruh</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gokulrangan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fluorescence properties of fluorescein, tetramethylrhodamine and Texas Red linked to a DNA aptamer</article-title><source>Photochem. Photobiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15686442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unruh</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gokulrangan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lushington</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Orientational dynamics and dye&#x02013;DNA interactions in a dye-labeled DNA aptamer</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2005</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>3455</fpage><lpage>3465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15731389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzmic</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Program DYNAFIT for the analysis of enzyme kinetic data: application to HIV proteinase</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem.</source><year>1996</year><volume>237</volume><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8660575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzmic</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DynaFit - a software package for enzymology</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>467</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19897096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdine</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the E-coli DNA glycosylase AlkA bound to the ends of duplex DNA: A system for the structure determination of lesion-containing DNA</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>2008</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1166</fpage><lpage>1174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18682218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdine</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and structure of duplex DNA containing the genotoxic nucleobase lesion N7-methylguanine</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2008</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>11570</fpage><lpage>11571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18686953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelman</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Beechem</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of loading the beta sliding clamp of DNA polymerase III onto DNA</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>30699</fpage><lpage>30708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8940047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gokulrangan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Unruh</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Holub</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA aptamer-based bioanalysis of IgE by fluorescence anisotropy</article-title><source>Anal. Chem.</source><year>2005</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1963</fpage><lpage>1970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15801725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Madabushi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Drohat</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The human checkpoint sensor Rad9-Rad1-Hus1 interacts with and stimulates DNA repair enzyme TDG glycosylase</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>6207</fpage><lpage>6218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17855402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Maita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jee</surname><given-names>J-G</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Saitoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugasawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanaoka</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tochio</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiroaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirakawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of thymine DNA glycosylase conjugated to SUMO-1</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>435</volume><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15959518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sibghat</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallinari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>RS</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Base analog and neighboring base effects on substrate specificity of recombinant human G:T mismatch-specific thymine DNA-glycosylase</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1996</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>12926</fpage><lpage>12932</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8841138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scharer</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiricny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Laval</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdine</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specific binding of a designed pyrrolidine abasic site analog to multiple DNA glycosylases</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>8592</fpage><lpage>8597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9535832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Um</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harbers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Benecke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierrat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Losson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinoic acid receptors interact physically and functionally with the T:G mismatch-specific thymine-DNA glycosylase</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>20728</fpage><lpage>20736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9694815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Phoenix</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Garcia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Losson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Buluwela</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Coombes</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>T:G mismatch-specific thymine-DNA glycosylase potentiates transcription of estrogen-regulated genes through direct interaction with estrogen receptor {alpha}</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>38586</fpage><lpage>38592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12874288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Missero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirro</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Simeone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pischetola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Lauro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The DNA glycosylase T:G mismatch-specific thymine DNA glycosylase represses thyroid transcription factor-1-activated transcription</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>33569</fpage><lpage>33575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11438542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Benecke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Um</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Torchia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of CBP/p300 acetylase and thymine DNA glycosylase links DNA repair and transcription</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11864601</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>