<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="book-review"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">GMS Z Med Ausbild</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">GMS Z Med Ausbild</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GMS Z Med Ausbild</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>GMS Zeitschrift f&#x000fc;r Medizinische Ausbildung</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1860-7446</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1860-3572</issn><publisher><publisher-name>German Medical Science GMS Publishing House</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3935165</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zma000896</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3205/zma000896</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">Doc4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">urn:nbn:de:0183-zma0008963</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Michael Koenen, Rupert Martin (Ed): Wege und Umwege zum Beruf des Psychotherapeuten - Entwicklungsprozesse psychotherapeutischer Identit&#x000e4;t</article-title><trans-title-group xml:lang="de"><trans-title>Michael Koenen, Rupert Martin (Hrsg): Wege und Umwege zum Beruf des Psychotherapeuten - Entwicklungsprozesse psychotherapeutischer Identit&#x000e4;t</trans-title></trans-title-group></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kiesewetter</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saravo</surname><given-names>Barbara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Klinikum der Universit&#x000e4;t M&#x000fc;nchen, Institut f&#x000fc;r Didaktik und Ausbildungsforschung in der Medizin, M&#x000fc;nchen, Deutschland</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed: Jan Kiesewetter, Klinikum der Universit&#x000e4;t M&#x000fc;nchen, Institut f&#x000fc;r Didaktik und Ausbildungsforschung in der Medizin, Ziemssenstra&#x000df;e 1, 80336 M&#x000fc;nchen, Deutschland, Tel.: +49 (0)89/5160-7204, Fax: +49 (0)89/5160-7202, E-mail: <email>jan.kiesewetter@med.uni-muenchen.de</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>Doc4</elocation-id><product product-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koenen</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Rupert</given-names></name></person-group><x>&#x000a0;</x><break/><source>Wege und Umwege zum Beruf des Psychotherapeuten &#x02013; Entwicklungsprozesse psychotherapeutischer Identit&#x000e4;t</source><x>. </x><break/><publisher-loc>Gie&#x000df;en</publisher-loc><x>: </x><publisher-name>Psychosozial Verlag</publisher-name><x>. </x><year>2013</year><x>. </x><size units="page">280</size><x> p.</x><comment>&#x020ac; 29,90</comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><x> ISBN: </x><isbn>9783837922783</isbn><x>. </x></product><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Kiesewetter et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link>). You are free to copy, distribute and transmit the work, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.egms.de/en/journals/zma/2014-31/zma000896.shtml">This article is available from http://www.egms.de/en/journals/zma/2014-31/zma000896.shtml</self-uri></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Recension</title><p>This book describes the results of a research project (mainly but not exclusively) about the situation of psychoanalytic training. It addresses all readers who are interested in the profession of psychotherapist.</p><p>At first, background information relevant to professional policy issues of psychotherapist education is given, especially with regard to differently developing numbers of applicants for recognised methods of psychotherapy (increase of applicants in behaviour therapy training with concurrent decrease in psychoanalytic treatment modalities). After briefly summarizing the results of the research project, the book focuses on the concept of identity, initially approaching it from a general theoretical point of view and ending with an in-depth discussion of the &#x0201c;psychoanalytic identity&#x0201c;. Eventually, the notion identity is being conceptualized from the perspective of behaviour therapy.</p><p>In the subsequent section, the research project is depicted in more detail. For examining and clarifying the question as to how the increase in candidates for behaviour therapy education opposing the decrease in psychoanalytic techniques can be explained, interviews were conducted with different groups of persons (candidates for training and psychological psychotherapists of both recognised methods of psychotherapy). Precisely, these people were asked to describe how they found their way into the profession of psychotherapist. Of a total of 58 narratives, ten narratives are presented cross-sectionally in the following part of the book. Despite the highly distinct nature of the narratives, the subsequent chapter manages to identify and describe &#x0201c;processes of cristallization on the way to a psychotherapist&#x0201c;.</p><p>In the final two chapters the authors give a summary of the results and draw a line back to their considerations focusing on identity theory as well as to the reply to their leading question. Finally, they give an &#x0201c;outlook to psychoanalysis and psychoanalytic training against the backdrop of societal change&#x0201c;.</p><p>By means of this book Michael Koenen and Rupert Martin succeeded in presenting an abundance of information about the psychotherapeutic profession to many groups of readers in a comprehensive way. While being inspiring and well readably written, the book still contains detailled scientific research and own data. </p><p>Indeed, the authors&#x02019; fascination for psychoanalysis becomes evident to the reader, yet without fully losing sight of the other recognised methods of psychotherapy. However, the book is particularly worthwile reading for those who are interested in the education of a medical or psychological psychotherapist in one of the psychoanalytic treatment modalities. The book distinctly portrays the diversity that characterizes the profession of psychotherapist and illustrates how different stages can be passed through despite all differences before making the decision to become a psychotherapist.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The author declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></body></article>