<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Br J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bjo</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bjophthalmol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The British Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-1161</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1468-2079</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Group</publisher-name><publisher-loc>BMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3404709</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bjophthalmol-2012-301602</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjophthalmol-2012-301602</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>PostScript</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject></subj-group><series-title>Letter</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Author's response</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Spiteri</surname><given-names>Anthony</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp><bold>Correspondence to</bold> Dr Anthony Spiteri, Department of Ophthalmology, Frimley Park Hospital NHS Foundation Trust, Portsmouth Road, Camberley, Surrey GU16 7UJ, UK; <email>antspit@yahoo.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Linked articles:</bold>
<related-article xlink:href="10.1136/bjophthalmol-2012-301588" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" id="d34e58">301588</related-article>.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>96</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage seq="b">1145</fpage><lpage>1145</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2012, Published by the BMJ Publishing Group Limited. For permission to use (where not already granted under a licence) please go to http://group.bmj.com/group/rights-licensing/permissions.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-commercial License, which permits use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non commercial and is otherwise in compliance with the license. See: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/legalcode">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/legalcode</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="bjophthalmol-2012-301602.pdf"/><kwd-group><kwd>Cornea</kwd><kwd>lens and zonules</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>I would like to thank Khalifa <italic>et al</italic>. We too believe that simulation technology is here to stay and that it can only improve with its further development and more research in software validation, highlighting its strengths and weaknesses. To this aim, our group has completed one such validation trial which we hope to share with the published community shortly.</p><p>Regarding the cost of these systems, we agree that these are currently restrictive (although we have already witnessed a substantial drop in price). We think that, for this reason, simulation based training works better on a regional training basis rather than individual hospitals investing heavily for a limited number of trainees. However, the increased demand caused by higher trainee to machine ratios will raise issues regarding how much minimum training will be required and for how long. Studies plotting learning curves required to reach standards set by validation trials are thus beckoning. These will produce more targeted training rather than simply &#x02018;the-more-the-better&#x02019; practising.</p><p>Although we are not there yet, once these initial obstacles are overcome there are multiple advantages to look forward to. Running costs are minimal; reduced complication rates due to out-of-theatre training would provide financial benefits and the more obvious reduction in morbidity; inbuilt validated scores would obviate the need for assessment by independent assessors thus minimising time constraints on more senior surgeons. Finally, we would be addressing the main issue highlighted regarding the growing number of factors that are limiting opportunities for resident surgical education.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing interests:</bold>
None.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; internally peer reviewed.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>