<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">FEBS J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">FEBS J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1111/(ISSN)1742-4658</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">FEBS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Febs Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1742-464X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1742-4658</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Published by Blackwell Pub. on behalf of the Federation of European Biochemical Societies</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24961997</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4163634</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/febs.12890</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">FEBS12890</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Magnesium&#x02010;dependent folding of a picornavirus <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> element modulates <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> conformation and eIF4G interaction</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">G. Lozano <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="febs12890-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>Gloria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="febs12890-aff-0001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib id="febs12890-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>Noemi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="febs12890-aff-0001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib id="febs12890-cr-0003" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname><given-names>Encarnacion</given-names></name><xref ref-type="correspondence-address" rid="correspondenceTo">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="febs12890-aff-0001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="febs12890-aff-0001"><label><sup>1</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">Centro de Biolog&#x000ed;a Molecular Severo Ochoa</named-content><institution>Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas &#x02013; Universidad Aut&#x000f3;noma de Madrid</institution><named-content content-type="city">Cantoblanco</named-content><country country="ES">Spain</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold><break/>
E.&#x000a0;Martinez&#x02010;Salas, Centro de Biolog&#x000ed;a Molecular Severo Ochoa, Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas &#x02013; Universidad Aut&#x000f3;noma de Madrid, Nicolas Cabrera&#x000a0;1, Cantoblanco, 28049 Madrid, Spain<break/>
Fax: +34 911964420<break/>
Tel: +34 911964619<break/>
E&#x02010;mail: <email>emartinez@cbm.csic.es</email><break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>281</volume><issue>16</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/febs.2014.281.issue-16</issue-id><fpage>3685</fpage><lpage>3700</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Federation of European Biochemical Societies <copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2014 The Authors. FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd on behalf of FEBS.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy-nc-nd"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution&#x02010;NonCommercial&#x02010;NoDerivs</ext-link> License, which permits use and distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non&#x02010;commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:febs-281-3685.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="main" id="febs12890-abs-0001"><p>Internal ribosome entry site (<styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content>) elements are high&#x02010;order <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> structures that promote internal initiation of translation to allow protein synthesis under situations that compromise the general cap&#x02010;dependent translation mechanism. Picornavirus <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> elements are highly efficient elements with a modular <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> structure organization. Here we investigated the effect of Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration on the local flexibility and solvent accessibility of the foot&#x02010;and&#x02010;mouth disease virus (<styled-content style="fixed-case">FMDV</styled-content>) <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> element measured on the basis of selective 2&#x02032;&#x02010;hydroxyl acylation analyzed by primer extension (<styled-content style="fixed-case">SHAPE</styled-content>) reactivity and hydroxyl radical cleavage. We have found that Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration affects the organization of discrete <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> regions, mainly the apical region of domain&#x000a0;3, the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4, and the pyrimidine tract of domain&#x000a0;5. In support of the effect of <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> structure on <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> activity, substitution or deletion mutants of the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4 impair internal initiation. In addition, divalent cations affect the binding of eIF4G, a eukaryotic initiation factor that is essential for <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content>&#x02010;dependent translation that interacts with domain&#x000a0;4. Binding of eIF4G is favored by the local <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> flexibility adopted at low Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration, while eIF4B interacts with the <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> independently of the compactness of the RNA structure. Our study shows that the <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> element adopts a near&#x02010;native structure in the absence of proteins, shedding light on the influence of Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions on the local flexibility and binding of eIF4G in a model <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> element.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="febs12890-kwd-0001">eIF4G&#x02010;binding</kwd><kwd id="febs12890-kwd-0002"><styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content>&#x02010;dependent translation initiation</kwd><kwd id="febs12890-kwd-0003">magnesium ions</kwd><kwd id="febs12890-kwd-0004"><styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> structure</kwd><kwd id="febs12890-kwd-0005"><styled-content style="fixed-case">SHAPE</styled-content> footprint</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Ministerio de Econom&#x000ed;a y Competitividad</funding-source><award-id>BFU2011&#x02010;25437</award-id><award-id>CSD2009&#x02010;00080</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Fundaci&#x000f3;n Ram&#x000f3;n Areces</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>component-id</meta-name><meta-value>febs12890</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>August 2014</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLM version:4.1.1 mode:remove_FC converted:10.09.2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><def-list list-content="abbreviations" id="febs12890-dl-0001"><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>DMS</term><def><p>dimethyl&#x02010;sulfate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Ebp1</term><def><p>ErbB3&#x02010;binding protein 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>eIFs</term><def><p>eukaryotic initiation factors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FMDV</term><def><p>foot&#x02010;and&#x02010;mouth disease virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IRES</term><def><p>internal ribosome entry site</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NMIA</term><def><p><italic>N</italic>&#x02010;methylisatoic anhydride</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PTB</term><def><p>Polypyrimidine tract&#x02010;binding protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SHAPE</term><def><p>selective 2&#x02032;&#x02010;hydroxyl acylation analyzed by primer extension</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WC</term><def><p>Watson&#x02010;Crick</p></def></def-item></def-list><sec sec-type="intro" id="febs12890-sec-0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>RNA structure plays a fundamental role in biological processes guided by RNA regulatory elements <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0001 febs12890-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">1</xref>. As for most RNA regulatory elements, the RNA structure dictates the function of the internal ribosome entry site (IRES) <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0003 febs12890-bib-0004 febs12890-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">3</xref>. IRES elements, which were discovered in picornavirus genomic RNAs, are in charge of driving translation initiation in various RNA viruses and a subset of cellular mRNAs <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0006 febs12890-bib-0007 febs12890-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">6</xref>. Indeed, IRES&#x02010;driven translation initiation represents an alternative mechanism to start protein synthesis under situations that compromise cap&#x02010;dependent translation initiation, typically occurring in infected cells. However, under normal situations, most eukaryotic mRNAs initiate translation by a mechanism that depends on recognition of the m<sup>7</sup>GpppN residue (termed the cap) located at the 5&#x02032; end of most mRNAs <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>.</p><p>IRES elements exhibit a wide diversity of nucleotide sequences, RNA secondary structures and <italic>trans</italic>&#x02010;acting factor requirements, as illustrated by the IRES elements present in the genome of picornaviruses, the intergenic region of dicistroviruses and hepatitis&#x000a0;C virus <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>. Earlier studies of the IRES element of foot&#x02010;and&#x02010;mouth&#x02010;disease virus (FMDV), a member of the <italic>Picornaviridae</italic> family, revealed a modular organization of domains, termed 1&#x02013;5 in the 5&#x02032;&#x02192;3&#x02032; direction <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref>. These RNA domains contain specific structural motifs that are responsible for recruitment of eIFs (eIF4G, eIF4B and eIF3) and several IRES&#x02010;binding factors <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0012 febs12890-bib-0013 febs12890-bib-0014 febs12890-bib-0015 febs12890-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">12</xref>.</p><p>We have recently used selective 2&#x02032;&#x02010;hydroxyl acylation analyzed by primer extension (SHAPE) to assess the RNA structure of IRES elements <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0003 febs12890-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">3</xref>. This methodology has the advantage over other high&#x02010;resolution approaches of allowing analysis of long RNA molecules and providing information at single&#x02010;nucleotide resolution <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref>. Our studies have shown that domain&#x000a0;3 is a self&#x02010;folding region that harbors conserved motifs whose disruption impairs IRES activity. These motifs have been proposed to be involved in distant interactions on the basis that altering one of them affects the RNA structural organization of this domain, leading to defective IRES elements <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0019 febs12890-bib-0020 febs12890-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">19</xref>. However, three&#x02010;dimensional models of the picornavirus IRES RNA structure are not yet available. Although a high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration inactivated the IRES&#x02010;dependent activity in cell&#x02010;free lysates of the closely related encephalomyocarditis virus <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref>, the influence of divalent cations on the IRES structure, and, in particular, whether the concentration of Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions affects the binding of factors needed for IRES activity, are unknown.</p><p>Adoption of RNA tertiary structure is strongly dependent on Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions, although a mixture of monovalent cations (K<sup>+</sup> and Na<sup>+</sup>) with Mg<sup>2+</sup> is required for efficient folding <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0023 febs12890-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">23</xref>. In the case of the FMDV IRES, long&#x02010;distance RNA&#x02013;RNA interactions were dependent on the concentration of the divalent ion in the folding buffer <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0019 febs12890-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">19</xref>. Cations reduce the charge repulsion generated by phosphate anions of the backbone, stabilizing the folded conformation of RNA <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">26</xref>. It is well established that Mg<sup>2+</sup>, which has a high charge density, is the dominant divalent cation in biological systems <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">24</xref>. Moreover, Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions perform both catalytic and structural roles, including mediation of helical packaging, promotion of long&#x02010;range interactions, and stabilization of RNA motifs <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">27</xref>.</p><p>In this study, we investigated the effect of Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration on the local flexibility and solvent accessibility of the IRES RNA measured by SHAPE reactivity and hydroxyl radical cleavage. We show that Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration affects the organization of discrete regions located in the apical region of domain&#x000a0;3, the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4, and the pyrimidine tract of domain&#x000a0;5. Based on these results, we analyzed the effect of divalent cations on the binding of eIF4G and eIF4B, two initiation factors that are involved in FMDV IRES&#x02010;dependent translation <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0012 febs12890-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">12</xref>. We have found that eIF4B interacts with the IRES independently of the rigidity of the RNA structure, while binding of eIF4G is favored by RNA flexibility in this region. Collectively, this study provides new insights into the influence of Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions on the local flexibility and protein binding of a picornavirus IRES, shedding light on the structure of a model IRES element.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="febs12890-sec-0002"><title>Results</title><sec id="febs12890-sec-0003"><title>Magnesium ions determine the RNA structure of discrete IRES regions</title><p>This study was designed to investigate the conformation of the IRES element under various ionic conditions. To this end, <italic>in&#x000a0;vitro</italic>&#x02010;synthesized RNA containing the functional FMDV IRES (nucleotides 1&#x02013;462) upstream of the luciferase coding region (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A) was denatured, snap&#x02010;cooled, and renatured in folding buffer under a range of MgCl<sub>2</sub> concentrations, keeping the buffer concentration (HEPES pH 8, 100&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc>) and monovalent cation concentrations (NaCl, 100&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc>; KCl, 140&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc>) constant. This procedure was followed to minimize intermolecular interactions, release mis&#x02010;folded molecules from kinetic traps and promote the most stable secondary structure. Refolded RNA was treated with <italic>N</italic>&#x02010;methylisatoic anhydride (NMIA), which preferentially acylates the 2&#x02032;&#x02010;OH of riboses associated with conformational flexible nucleotides <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">29</xref>. Heavily modified positions correspond to nucleotides that are primarily single&#x02010;stranded, while non&#x02010;reactive nucleotides are involved in base pairs. Inflexible regions may also correspond to non&#x02010;WC base pairs, tertiary interactions, or a single stacking interaction in the C2&#x02032;&#x02010;endo conformation <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0030 febs12890-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">30</xref>. After NMIA treatment, the IRES region was examined by reverse transcriptase extension using primers spaced along the RNA sequence to obtain overlapping readings <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref>. Then, cDNA products derived from the untreated and NMIA&#x02010;treated RNAs were resolved in denaturing acrylamide urea gels in parallel with a sequence ladder obtained using the same primer (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B). Gross modifications of SHAPE reactivity where observed in specific regions of domains 3 and 4 of the IRES folded at low Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration (0.5&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc>) compared with RNA folded at high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration (6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc>). Compared with the absence of Mg<sup>2+</sup> in the folding buffer, the apical region of domain&#x000a0;3 showed a decreased SHAPE reactivity in residues 200&#x02013;202 in the presence of 0.5 and 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B, left panel, black arrowheads). Likewise, a decrease in reactivity at positions 337&#x02013;348 within domain&#x000a0;4 was observed at high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B, right panel, black arrowheads).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="febs12890-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><styled-content style="fixed-case">SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity of the <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> element as a function of the concentration of divalent ions in the folding buffer. (A) Schematic of the <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> harboring the <styled-content style="fixed-case">FMDV IRES</styled-content> element. Numbers indicate the IRES nucleotides, with approximate locations of <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> structural domains 1&#x02013;5. Domain 1 is not shown in subsequent figures because it corresponds to the right arm of the <italic>cre</italic> element and contributes very weakly to IRES activity. (B) Representative examples of primer extension assays corresponding to domains 3 and 4 of the <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content>. The Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration and <styled-content style="fixed-case">NMIA</styled-content> treatment are indicated at the top. Nucleotide positions are indicated on the left. <styled-content style="fixed-case">AGCU</styled-content> indicate the sequence lanes used as ladders. Black arrowheads on the right indicate positions whose reactivity decreases upon increasing the concentration of Mg<sup>2+</sup> in the folding buffer. (C) <styled-content style="fixed-case">SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity profiles of the <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> at 0, 0.5 and 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup>. Values correspond to the mean <styled-content style="fixed-case">SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity (&#x000b1;SD) for six independent assays. <styled-content style="fixed-case">SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity is represented using a colored scale in which 0 indicates unreactive nucleotides and the mean intensity at highly reactive nucleotides is set to 1.0. Nucleotide positions are indicated on the <italic>x</italic>&#x000a0;axis. Domains 2, 3, 4 and 5 of the <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> are indicated below the corresponding nucleotide positions. Boxes I, II and III indicate the regions that show the main reactivity changes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="febs-281-3685-g01"><alt-text>image</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>To precisely measure the effect of varying Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration on the IRES structure, six independent assays were used to quantify SHAPE reactivity along the IRES region. The resulting profiles (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C) revealed that the major reactivity changes were located in specific regions of domains 3, 4 and 5 (boxes I, II and III in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C).</p><p>The local RNA flexibility displayed on the secondary IRES structure is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. Relative to the RNA folded in the absence of Mg<sup>2+</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A), changes in the IRES structure affecting several nucleotides under low and high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentrations (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B,C) were located in three regions (boxes I, II and III in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A&#x02013;C). Specifically, nucleotides AAAA(199&#x02013;202) (corresponding to the RAAA motif on the apical stem&#x02010;loop of domain&#x000a0;3) exhibited a decrease in reactivity upon Mg<sup>2+</sup> addition (box&#x000a0;I in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A&#x02013;C). Additionally, a moderately increased reactivity was observed in residues belonging to the bulges AACUCC(166&#x02013;171) and CGCCCACACG(207&#x02013;216), as well as the C&#x02010;rich loop UGCAACCCCAGCAC(230&#x02013;243). On the other hand, nucleotides GUAACACGCGAC(337&#x02013;348) corresponding to the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4 (box&#x000a0;II in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A&#x02013;C) showed a significant decrease in reactivity under high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration. Reactivity changes affecting more than one position were also observed at positions UUUCCU(440&#x02013;445), corresponding to the pyrimidine&#x02010;rich tract of domain&#x000a0;5 (box&#x000a0;III in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A&#x02013;C). Some changes of reactivity were also observed at individual residues (A361 and G389).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="febs12890-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effect of Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration on the secondary structure of the <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content>. The <styled-content style="fixed-case">SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity obtained using <styled-content style="fixed-case">NMIA</styled-content> and 5&#x02032;&#x02010;radiolabeled primers is represented using the colored scale shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C. The <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> structure was visualized using <styled-content style="fixed-case">VARNA</styled-content>
<xref rid="febs12890-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">61</xref>. Boxes I, II and III represent the regions that display the main changes in the presence of 0 (A), 0.5 (B) or 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> (C) Mg<sup>2+</sup> in the folding buffer. Nucleotides are numbered every 50 positions; a dot indicates the every 10th nucleotide; lines with arrowheads in (A) indicate the approximate location of <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> structural domains 2&#x02013;5.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="febs-281-3685-g02"><alt-text>image</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>Independent measurements of the local RNA flexibility were performed using fluorescent primers and capillary electrophoresis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A). The results displayed on the IRES secondary structure (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B) are largely coincident with those obtained using radiolabeled primers, in agreement with previous studies <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">32</xref>. In fact, only minor differences were observed in some positions, which may be due to the different methodology necessary to quantify the reverse transcriptase stop signals.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="febs12890-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>(A) <styled-content style="fixed-case">SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity profiles of the <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> using fluorescent&#x02010;labeled primers and capillary electrophoresis. <styled-content style="fixed-case">SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity is represented using a colored scale in which 0 indicates unreactive nucleotides and the mean intensity at highly reactive nucleotides is set to 1.0. Nucleotide positions are indicated on the <italic>x</italic>&#x000a0;axis. Domains 2, 3, 4 and 5 of the <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> are indicated below the corresponding nucleotide positions. Boxes I, II and III indicate the regions that show the main reactivity changes. (B, C) The <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> structure at 0.5 Mg<sup>2+</sup> (B) and 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> (C). The symbols used are described in the legend to Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="febs-281-3685-g03"><alt-text>image</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>Further analysis of the effect of Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration on the IRES structure folded in the presence of K<sup>+</sup>, the predominant monovalent cation in the cell cytoplasm, indicated that the main change occurred at around 2&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A). Very few differences were found in individual positions, and these did not modify the overall pattern of SHAPE reactivity at the same Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration irrespective of the presence of Na<sup>+</sup> or K<sup>+</sup> ions (compare Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B,C with Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B,C). We therefore used 0.5 and 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> as the low and high concentrations of Mg<sup>2+</sup> for further studies on IRES structure.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="febs12890-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> structure analysis of the <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> renatured in the presence of the monovalent ion K<sup>+</sup>. (A). <styled-content style="fixed-case">SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity profiles of the <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> in the presence of 140&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> KCl at increasing concentrations of Mg<sup>2+</sup> (0, 0.5, 2 and 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc>). Values correspond to the mean <styled-content style="fixed-case">SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity (&#x000b1;SD). The <styled-content style="fixed-case">SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity is represented using the colored scale shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C. Boxes I, II and III indicate the regions that show the main reactivity changes. (B, C) The RNA structure at 0.5 Mg<sup>2+</sup> (B) and 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> (C). The symbols used are described in the legend to Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="febs-281-3685-g04"><alt-text>image</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>Thus, we conclude that the Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration profoundly affects the organization of discrete IRES regions, i.e. the apical region of domain&#x000a0;3 and the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4, in addition to moderate reorganization of the pyrimidine tract of domain&#x000a0;5.</p></sec><sec id="febs12890-sec-0004"><title>Mutational analysis reveals involvement of the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4 in IRES activity</title><p>Regarding the involvement in IRES function of the regions showing changes in local flexibility upon Mg<sup>2+</sup> increase, previous data from our laboratory have shown that the apical loop of domain&#x000a0;3 is involved in IRES activity, and its sequence composition affects the RNA structure of the flanking stem&#x02010;loops <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0003 febs12890-bib-0020 febs12890-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">3</xref>. However, no information was available regarding the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4. Alignment of the IRES sequences from 180 FMDV isolates available in GenBank indicated that the sequence of the 10&#x000a0;nt loop at nucleotides 337&#x02013;348 is conserved, with the exception of C343 and C345, which tolerated transitions and transversions (A or U and U or G, respectively) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A). Occasional substitutions were observed at positions U338 and A347. Indeed, a conserved motif GUAACANGNGAC(337&#x02013;348) was inferred from sequence conservation. In contrast, flanking nucleotides that are engaged in base pairs according to SHAPE probing (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A) were either invariant or covariant (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="febs12890-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Contribution of the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4 to <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> activity. (A) Alignment of variant sequences within the 306&#x02013;380 region of the <styled-content style="fixed-case">FMDV IRES</styled-content>. A total of 180 sequences available in GenBank were aligned using <sc>clustalx</sc>. For simplicity, one representative of each variant is shown in the alignment. The pattern of nucleotide conservation (measured in bits) of the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4 is represented by a sequence logo obtained from alignment of nucleotides 337&#x02013;348 (boxed in red). (B). Mutational analysis of the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4. The secondary structure of the wild&#x02010;type (wt) stem&#x02010;loop as well as the deletion mutant (&#x00394;338&#x02013;347) and the substitution mutant (A339C/A340G) are shown at the top. Relative <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> activity was determined as the ratio of luciferase to chloramphenicol acetyltransferase expressed from a bi&#x02010;cistronic construct in transfected <styled-content style="fixed-case">BHK</styled-content>&#x02010;21 cells and normalized to the activity observed for the wild&#x02010;type <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> (set to 1). Values are means&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;<styled-content style="fixed-case">SD</styled-content>. The experiment was performed in triplicate and repeated at least three times.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="febs-281-3685-g05"><alt-text>image</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>Thus, to obtain information about the implication of the 10&#x000a0;nt loop at nucleotides 337&#x02013;348 on IRES activity, we generated two mutants. The first one (&#x00394;338&#x02013;347) carried a deletion of the entire loop, and the second one (A339C/A340G) carried a double substitution that was intended to close the loop (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B). Determination of the efficiency of internal initiation of translation of these mutants relative to the wild&#x02010;type IRES showed a decrease of activity of approximately 80% (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B). These data demonstrate that the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4 contributes to IRES activity to a significant extent.</p></sec><sec id="febs12890-sec-0005"><title>Assembly of eIF4G&#x02013;IRES and eIF4B&#x02013;IRES complexes reveals the protection of specific residues in domains 4 and 5</title><p>The IRES domains 4 and 5, which showed important changes in RNA structure upon folding at high concentration of Mg<sup>2+</sup>, provide the binding sites for eIF4G and eIF4B during internal initiation <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref>. Thus, we analyzed the influence of Mg<sup>2+</sup> on the IRES&#x02013;protein interaction on the basis of the SHAPE footprint, a methodology that allows the study of RNA molecules assembled in ribonucleoprotein complexes <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0018 febs12890-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">18</xref>. In this assay, the protections correspond to RNA regions involved RNA&#x02013;protein interactions or changes in RNA conformation induced by the RNA&#x02013;protein interaction.</p><p>To determine the effect of Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions on the interaction of eIF4G with the IRES, RNA folded at 0.5&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> was incubated with increasing amounts of purified His&#x02010;tagged eIF4G protein (0, 40 and 80&#x000a0;n<sc>m</sc>) prior to NMIA treatment. Primer extension analysis of the complexes assembled <italic>in&#x000a0;vitro</italic> allowed measurement of the SHAPE reactivity of the IRES region in RNA incubated with or without eIF4G (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A, lanes 2&#x02013;4). Relative to the SHAPE reactivity observed with free RNA, eIF4G protein induces the protection of sequences that lie within domain&#x000a0;4 of the IRES. Specifically, nucleotides 400&#x02013;418 were protected from NMIA attack upon addition of His&#x02010;tagged eIF4G at low Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration (blue bar/box in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A,B). These results are in agreement with independent approaches, such as assembly of 48S pre&#x02010;initiation complexes and RNA&#x02013;protein pull&#x02010;down and UV&#x02010;crosslink assays performed using a range of Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentrations between 0.3 and 2.5&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc>, which mapped the binding site of eIF4G to domain&#x000a0;4 of the encephalomyocarditis virus and FMDV IRES elements <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0016 febs12890-bib-0035 febs12890-bib-0036 febs12890-bib-0037 febs12890-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">16</xref>. In addition, nucleotides 340&#x02013;350 were reorganized upon addition of the protein, with noticeable changes in the primer extension pattern (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A,B, blue bar/box). However, residues 75, 293&#x02013;303 and 447&#x02013;454 were more reactive towards NMIA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>B, red boxes), indicating modified organization of the regions flanking the protein&#x02010;binding site on the IRES structure. Reactivity changes around position 380 were observed independently of the RNA treatment. Additionally, nucleotides 53&#x02013;66 within domain&#x000a0;2 were protected (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>B, blue box). However, none of the eIF4G&#x02010;induced protections observed at low Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration were detected for RNA folded at high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>C). These results led us to conclude that eIF4G&#x02013;IRES interaction is sensitive to the RNA structure reorganization induced by divalent cations.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="febs12890-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Impact of eIF4G on <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity. (A) Primer extension analysis of <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content>&#x02013;protein complexes assembled at increasing concentrations of eIF4G (40 and 80&#x000a0;n<sc>m</sc>) using <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> folded at 0.5&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> treated (+) or untreated (&#x02013;) with <styled-content style="fixed-case">NMIA</styled-content> was performed using a 5&#x02032;&#x000a0;end radiolabeled primer. Nucleotide positions are indicated on the left based on the sequencing lanes (<styled-content style="fixed-case">AGCU</styled-content>) obtained using the same primer; c<styled-content style="fixed-case">DNA</styled-content> full&#x02010;length (<styled-content style="fixed-case">FL</styled-content>) products are shown at the top of each lane. Blue and red bars indicate protected or more reactive nucleotides, respectively. (B) <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity for free <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> renatured in the presence of 0.5&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> (top) and upon addition of purified His&#x02010;tagged eIF4G (40&#x000a0;n<sc>m</sc>) (bottom). (C) <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity for free <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> renatured in the presence of 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> (top) and upon addition of purified His&#x02010;tagged eIF4G (40&#x000a0;n<sc>m</sc>) (bottom). Values are means&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;<styled-content style="fixed-case">SD</styled-content>. Bars are colored according to reactivity based on the colored scale shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C. Blue boxes indicate protected regions, and red boxes indicate regions with higher reactivity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="febs-281-3685-g06"><alt-text>image</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>The RNA&#x02010;binding protein eIF4B interacts with picornavirus IRES elements, stimulating IRES activity <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0012 febs12890-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">12</xref>. Interaction of eIF4B with the IRES element was first analyzed using RNA folded at 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> incubated with increasing amounts of purified His&#x02010;tagged eIF4B protein (0, 60, 300 and 500&#x000a0;n<sc>m</sc>). Of interest, a concentration of 300&#x000a0;n<sc>m</sc> (lane&#x000a0;4 in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A) was sufficient to induce protection of residues belonging to domain&#x000a0;5, although the protection increased with protein concentration (blue bar in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A). However, some nucleotides near the 3&#x02032; boundary of the IRES were more reactive in the presence of eIF4B (red bar in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="febs12890-fig-0007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Impact of eIF4B on <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity. (A) Primer extension analysis of <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content>&#x02013;protein complexes, assembled using <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> folded at 0.5&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> and increasing concentrations of eIF4B (60, 300 and 500&#x000a0;n<sc>m</sc>) and treated (+) or untreated (&#x02013;) with <styled-content style="fixed-case">NMIA</styled-content>, was performed with a 5&#x02032;&#x000a0;end radiolabeled primer. Nucleotide positions are indicated on the left based on the sequencing lanes (<styled-content style="fixed-case">CU</styled-content>) obtained using the same primer; c<styled-content style="fixed-case">DNA</styled-content> full&#x02010;length products (<styled-content style="fixed-case">FL</styled-content>) are shown at the top of each lane. Blue and red bars indicate protected or more reactive nucleotides, respectively. (B) <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity for free <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> renatured in the presence of 0.5&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> (top) and upon addition of purified His&#x02010;tagged eIF4B (300&#x000a0;n<sc>m</sc>) (bottom). (C) <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA SHAPE</styled-content> reactivity for free <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> renatured in the presence of 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> (top) and upon addition of purified His&#x02010;tagged eIF4B (300&#x000a0;n<sc>m</sc>) (bottom). Values are means&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SD. Bars are colored according to reactivity based on the colored scale shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C. Blue boxes indicate protected regions, and red boxes indicate regions with higher reactivity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="febs-281-3685-g07"><alt-text>image</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>Next, the SHAPE reactivity values observed on free RNA at both 0.5 and 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> were compared with those obtained upon addition of eIF4B. Interestingly, the hairpin of domain&#x000a0;5 (nucleotides 416&#x02013;433) was protected by eIF4B from NMIA attack at both low and high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentrations (blue boxes in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>B,C). In contrast, two short regions spanning nucleotides 293&#x02013;297 (domain&#x000a0;3) and 447&#x02013;454 (domain&#x000a0;5) became more reactive towards NMIA (red boxes in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>B,C). Residues belonging to domain&#x000a0;3 showed no gross changes in SHAPE reactivity with the exception of positions 179&#x02013;180, while nucleotides 53&#x02013;66 within domain&#x000a0;2 were protected. These results show that eIF4B specifically induces protection of residues belonging to domains 2 and 5.</p><p>It is worth mentioning that specific residues were differentially protected upon incubation of the IRES with eIF4G or eIF4B at low Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0008" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). For instance, while eIF4G&#x02013;IRES complexes protect residues within domain&#x000a0;4 (blue&#x02010;shaded nucleotides in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0008" ref-type="fig">8</xref>A), complexes assembled with eIF4B preferentially protect the hairpin of domain&#x000a0;5 (blue&#x02010;shaded nucleotides in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0008" ref-type="fig">8</xref>B). However, in both cases, a reorganization of flanking sequences within the pyrimidine&#x02010;rich region of domain&#x000a0;5 and the basal region of domain&#x000a0;3 (red&#x02010;shaded nucleotides in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0008" ref-type="fig">8</xref>A,B) was observed, suggesting that these residues are in close proximity in the three&#x02010;dimensional structure of the IRES.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="febs12890-fig-0008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Summary of changes in <styled-content style="fixed-case">NMIA</styled-content> attack upon incubation of the IRES with eIF4G (A) or eIF4B (B) at 0.5 mM Mg<sup>2+</sup>. Blue&#x02010;shaded nucleotides represent protected positions within domains 4 and 5, and red&#x02010;shaded nucleotides are those with higher reactivity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="febs-281-3685-g08"><alt-text>image</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="febs12890-sec-0006"><title>Hydroxyl radical cleavage reveals a compact IRES structure at high concentrations of the divalent cation</title><p>The different patterns of reactivity observed in IRES complexes assembled with eIF4B or eIF4G proteins prompted us to assess the solvent accessibility of the IRES under low and high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentrations by hydroxyl radical cleavage footprinting, a methodology that reveals nucleotides buried within the folded RNA structure. In this assay, <italic>in&#x000a0;situ</italic>&#x02010;generated hydroxyl radicals cleave locations on the RNA backbone in proportion to their solvent exposure <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">40</xref>. The solvent accessibility of the IRES was probed using Fe(II)&#x02013;EDTA and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in a solution of RNA renatured in the presence or absence of Mg<sup>2+</sup>, followed by primer extension analysis with fluorescently labeled primers, and capillary electrophoresis was used to resolve the reaction products. The results yielded cleavage information at single&#x02010;nucleotide resolution, indicating solvent exposure of the 3&#x02032; end region of the IRES (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>A).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="febs12890-fig-0009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Hydroxyl radical probing of <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> domains 4 and 5. (A) Histograms of cleavage intensity versus nucleotide position in the absence or presence of Mg<sup>2+</sup> determined using <italic>in&#x000a0;situ</italic>&#x02010;generated hydroxyl radicals. Cleavages were determined by primer extension using fluorescent&#x02010;labeled primers and capillary electrophoresis. Gray bars indicate solvent&#x02010;inaccessible nucleotides in the folded <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> (intensities&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;half the mean), and solvent&#x02010;accessible residues are shown in purple. Black arrows at the top indicate positions whose accessibility decreases upon increasing concentration of Mg<sup>2+</sup> in the folding buffer. (B) Predicted secondary <styled-content style="fixed-case">RNA</styled-content> structure of domains 4 and 5 of the <styled-content style="fixed-case">IRES</styled-content> imposing <styled-content style="fixed-case">SHAPE</styled-content> constraints. Solvent&#x02010;inaccessible nucleotides are shown in gray; solvent&#x02010;accessible nucleotides are shown in purple.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="febs-281-3685-g09"><alt-text>image</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>Upon folding of the RNA in the presence of high concentrations of Mg<sup>2+</sup>, the hairpin of domain&#x000a0;5 became solvent&#x02010;inaccessible (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>B, gray nucleotides) indicating burial of this region due to structural compaction. Concomitantly, a change in accessibility to the solvent for residues within the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4 was observed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>B, compare gray and purple nucleotides in left and right panels). Thus, the basal region of domain&#x000a0;4 and most of domain&#x000a0;5 remain solvent&#x02010;inaccessible at high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration. These results, together with those shown in Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="febs12890-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, <xref rid="febs12890-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <xref rid="febs12890-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, suggest that eIF4B interaction with the IRES is independent of the compactness of the IRES structure, while binding of eIF4G is favored by RNA flexibility in this region, probably provided by a solvent&#x02010;accessible hairpin of domain&#x000a0;5.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="febs12890-sec-0007"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we show that the FMDV IRES structure is modulated by the concentration of Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions. Using SHAPE methodology, we identified three discrete regions where the RNA structure is dependent on the cation concentration. Furthermore, the conformational changes induced by Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration differentially affected the binding of two host factors: eIF4G and eIF4B. Interestingly, the IRES&#x02013;eIF4G complex was sensitive to the conformational changes induced by Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions. Indeed, at high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentrations of the ion, no footprinting was observed on the IRES RNA, but it was readily observed at low Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration. Conversely, interaction of eIF4B with the IRES was detected at both low and high concentrations of the ion, leading to a similar pattern of reactivity irrespective of the concentration of Mg<sup>2+</sup>. The analysis of IRES&#x02013;protein complexes revealed an increased reactivity in regions flanking eIF4G and eIF4B binding sites, indicating that assembly of these complexes generates secondary structure rearrangements in regions adjacent to the protein&#x02010;binding site.</p><p>In recent years, RNA has received much attention, and has been shown to be a major player in many cellular processes. Many of the novel biological functions identified depend on RNA structure. However, obtaining accurate three&#x02010;dimensional models of RNA molecules is hampered by the flexibility of RNA in solution and the relative low number of RNA three&#x02010;dimensional structures available so far <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">41</xref>. SHAPE probing methodology has the advantage over other high&#x02010;resolution approaches of allowing analysis of long RNA molecules in solution. In this regard, recent SHAPE structural studies have provided information on various RNA conformations, tertiary structures, long&#x02010;distance 3&#x02032;&#x02192;5&#x02032; interactions and ribonucleoprotein complexes of RNA in solution <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0042 febs12890-bib-0043 febs12890-bib-0044 febs12890-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">42</xref>.</p><p>Based on the results shown here by measuring SHAPE reactivity using either radiolabeled primers and conventional denaturing gels or fluorescent primers and capillary electrophoresis, the IRES element adopts a near&#x02010;native conformation in the absence of proteins. In further support of these data, it is worth noting that the organization of the IRES in bulges and stems, as defined by the susceptibility towards NMIA attack under low (0.5&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc>) Mg<sup>2+</sup>, is in agreement with that defined previously on the basis of DMS, and RNases T1 or T2 attack using a buffer containing 1&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup>
<xref rid="febs12890-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref>. Furthermore, all procedures used to probe the RNA structure of this IRES element indicated that the stem holding the apical region of domain&#x000a0;3 remains resistant to NMIA, DMS, and RNases T1 or T2 attack, and mutations that disrupt some of these base pairs led to defective IRES elements <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0046 febs12890-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">46</xref>.</p><p>With regard to the changes induced by different Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentrations on the local RNA flexibility of the apical region of domain&#x000a0;3, it is worth noting that this region harbors three conserved motifs (GNRA, RAAA and the C&#x02010;rich loop). Disruption of these motifs or destabilization of the corresponding stems led to a defective IRES and induced changes in the RNA structure of this region <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0003 febs12890-bib-0017 febs12890-bib-0019 febs12890-bib-0020 febs12890-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">3</xref>. The SHAPE reactivity changes observed upon Mg<sup>2+</sup> increase in the folding buffer are consistent with a strong influence of the divalent cation on the structural organization of this RNA domain.</p><p>As Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions dictate RNA tertiary folding <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">26</xref>, a potential outcome of our work was identification of nucleotides involved in tertiary interactions within the IRES element. Attempts to identify positions involved in distant interactions made use of RNA structure prediction programs that incorporate SHAPE reactivity data <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0049 febs12890-bib-0050 febs12890-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">49</xref>. This was performed as an unbiased method to detect base pairs between nucleotides that resulted in modified reactivity upon Mg<sup>2+</sup> incubation. However, no gross changes in stem&#x02010;loop composition were detected irrespective of whether the full&#x02010;length IRES, individual domains or combinations of its structural domains (4&#x02013;5, 3&#x02013;4&#x02013;5 or 2&#x02013;4&#x02013;5) were used. This result shows that the secondary RNA structure is stable even in the absence of Mg<sup>2+</sup>, which, in turn, appears to indicate that Mg<sup>2+</sup> contributes to tertiary interactions.</p><p>Candidate nucleotides to form base pairs were also manually analyzed by pairwise comparison of the changes in reactivity and solvent accessibility. Attempts to identify candidate base pairs involving residues of the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4 did not detect a second site at which reactivity decreased to the same extent under high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration. Given the difficulties of predicting non&#x02010;canonical base pairs in the RNA structure, it is possible that residues involved in long&#x02010;range interactions were missed if either non&#x02010;canonical base pairs or internal bulges were involved. Although we cannot rule out the possibility that a high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration stabilizes intra&#x02010;loop interactions <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0052 febs12890-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">52</xref>, potential pairing of nucleotides GUAACACGCGAC(337&#x02013;348) with positions CUCGGUUUA(390&#x02013;398) was identified. Interestingly, this is partially coincident with the protection of residues UUUAAAAAAG(397&#x02013;403) by eIF4G at 0.5&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration but not at 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc>. Thus, recognition of the eIF4G&#x02010;binding site at low m<sc>m</sc> Mg<sup>2+</sup> may be at least in part favored by a more flexible RNA structure due to lack of this putative tertiary interaction.</p><p>The contribution of the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4 to IRES activity was analyzed in transfection assays using two mutants, consisting of a full deletion of the loop and a double mutant carrying the substitutions A339C and A340G (designed to base pair with C345 and G346), mimicking the conformation observed at high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration. Both mutants showed a reduction in internal initiation activity of approximately 80% relative to the wild&#x02010;type IRES, suggesting that A339 and A340 perform critical roles in the contribution of this loop to IRES activity. In support of these data, we have found that this particular region is reorganized upon addition of eIF4G, and that the eIF4G&#x02013;IRES interaction is sensitive to the RNA structure reorganization induced by divalent cations. This result has important implications given that the concentration of Mg<sup>2+</sup> in the cellular cytoplasm is approximately 0.5&#x02013;1&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc>
<xref rid="febs12890-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">54</xref>. Interestingly, although K<sup>+</sup> is the predominant monovalent cation in the intracellular environment, we found that Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration determines RNA structure irrespective of which monovalent ion (Na<sup>+</sup> or K<sup>+</sup>) is used, in agreement with previous data <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref>. Furthermore, the low RNA&#x02010;binding affinity of eIF4G <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">55</xref> may explain the moderate protection of eIF4G in the absence of other factors such as eIF4A, PTB and Ebp1 <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref>.</p><p>Because of the relevance of the IRES structural organization for picornavirus protein synthesis, we compared the IRES solvent accessibility measured by hydroxyl cleavage with the inhibitory capacity of 2&#x02032;&#x02010;<italic>O</italic>&#x02010;methyl oligoribonucleotides targeting the entire IRES region in mammalian cells <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">56</xref>. Interestingly, while most oligoribonucleotides complementary to domain&#x000a0;4 were non&#x02010;inhibitory, those complementary to the 10&#x000a0;nt loop of domain&#x000a0;4 and the hairpin of domain&#x000a0;5 were inhibitory. This positive correlation exemplifies the importance of understanding RNA structure for rational development of small molecules with potential antiviral activity.</p><p>Collectively, our results reveal the critical role of divalent cations for IRES structure, that, in turn, affects the interaction of the IRES with eIF4G, an essential factor for translation initiation driven by this IRES element. Future studies are necessary to dissect the implications of divalent cations on assembly of competent IRES&#x02013;protein complexes in living cells. Additionally, as the FMDV IRES is a long, very efficient element that may serve as model for RNA studies of complex IRES elements, understanding the principles controlling its RNA structure has potential implications for other ribonucleoprotein complexes controlling internal initiation of translation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="febs12890-sec-0008"><title>Experimental procedures</title><sec id="febs12890-sec-0009"><title>Constructs and RNA synthesis</title><p>The construct expressing the FMDV IRES has been described previously <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref>. Mutagenesis of the IRES element was performed using the Quikchange mutagenesis procedure (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA), using oligonucleotides 5&#x02032;&#x02010;CAGGTACCCCGAGGCACTCGGGATCTGA&#x02010;3&#x02032; (forward) and 5&#x02032;&#x02010;TCAGATCCCGAGTGCCTCGGGGTACCTG&#x02010;3&#x02032; (reverse) to generate the mutant &#x00394;338&#x02013;347, and 5&#x02032;&#x02010;AGGTACCCCGAGGTCGCACGCGACACTCGG&#x02010;3&#x02032; (forward) and 5&#x02032;&#x02010;CCGAGTGTCGCGTGCGACCTCGGGGTACCT&#x02010;3&#x02032; (reverse) for the mutant A339C/A340G. All plasmids were sequenced to ensure correctness (Macrogen Europe, Amsterdam, The Netherlands).</p><p>Prior to <italic>in&#x000a0;vitro</italic> transcription, plasmids were linearized using <italic>Sph</italic>I. RNA synthesis was performed for 2&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C using T7 RNA polymerase <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref> and the linearized DNA template in 40&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Tris/HCl, 50&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> dithiothreitol, 0.5&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> rNTPs, as described previously <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="febs12890-sec-0010"><title>SHAPE analysis</title><p>RNAs (2&#x000a0;pmol) were treated with NMIA (Invitrogen, Eugene, OR, USA) <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">29</xref> using a range of MgCl<sub>2</sub> concentrations (0&#x02013;6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc>) in the folding buffer. Prior to primer extension, 0.5&#x000a0;pmol of treated and untreated RNAs were incubated with 2&#x000a0;pmol of the antisense 5&#x02032;&#x000a0;end fluorescently&#x02010;labeled primer 5&#x02032;&#x02010;TAGCCTTATGCAGTTGCTCTCC&#x02010;3&#x02032; at 65&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min and 35&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min, and then chilled on ice for 2&#x000a0;min <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">57</xref>. Primer extension reactions were performed in a final volume of 16&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L containing reverse transcriptase buffer (50&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Tris/HCl pH 8.3, 3&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 75&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 8&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> dithiothreitol) and 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;<sc>m</sc> of each dNTP. The mixture was heated at 52&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min prior to addition of 100&#x000a0;units of SuperScript III reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA), and incubated at 52&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;min. A sequencing ladder was generated using untreated RNA in the presence of 0.1&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> ddCTP. NED fluorophore (Applied Biosystems, Warrington, UK) was used for both NMIA&#x02010;treated and untreated samples, while VIC fluorophore (Applied Biosystems, Warrington, UK) was used for the sequencing ladder. cDNA products were resolved by capillary electrophoresis.</p><p>For primer extension using radiolabeled primers, equal amounts of NMIA&#x02010;treated and untreated RNAs (0.5&#x000a0;pmol) were incubated with 2&#x000a0;pmol each of the antisense 5&#x02032;&#x000a0;end <sup>32</sup>P&#x02010;labeled primers 5&#x02032;&#x02010;CTACGAAGCAACAGTG&#x02010;3&#x02032;, 5&#x02032;&#x02010;CCCGGGTGTGGGTACC&#x02010;3&#x02032;, 5&#x02032;&#x02010;GGAATGGGATCCTCGAGCTCAGGGTC&#x02010;3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;&#x02010;GGCCTTTCTTTATGTTTTTGGCG&#x02010;3&#x02032; in separate reactions, as described previously <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>. Primer extension was performed as above. After alkaline hydrolysis of the RNA template <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>, cDNAs were precipitated and fractionated in 6% acrylamide/7&#x000a0;<sc>m</sc> urea gels in parallel to a sequence ladder obtained using the same primer as in the primer extension reaction.</p></sec><sec id="febs12890-sec-0011"><title>SHAPE RNA probing in the presence of IRES&#x02010;binding factors</title><p>RNA&#x02013;protein complexes were assembled in folding buffer containing a high Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration (100&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> HEPES pH 8.0, 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 100&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> NaCl) or folding buffer containing a low Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration (100&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> HEPES pH 8.0, 0.5&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 100&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> NaCl) in the presence of increasing concentration of His&#x02010;tagged eIF4B (60, 300 and 500&#x000a0;n<sc>m</sc>) or His&#x02010;tagged eIF4G (40 and 80&#x000a0;n<sc>m</sc>) for 10&#x000a0;min at room temperature. Then, RNA alone or RNA pre&#x02010;incubated with the protein of interest was treated with NMIA and analyzed by primer extension analysis using radiolabeled primers as described in the previous paragraph.</p></sec><sec id="febs12890-sec-0012"><title>Hydroxyl radical footprinting</title><p>RNA (2&#x000a0;pmol) was denatured, chilled on ice and folded in folding buffer (40&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> MOPS pH 8.0, 80&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> KOAc, and 0, 0.5 or 6&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>). Fe(II)&#x02013;EDTA (7.5&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> Fe(SO<sub>4</sub>)2(NH<sub>4</sub>)2&#x000b7;6H<sub>2</sub>O and 11.25&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, pH 8.0), 0.3% hydrogen peroxide and 150&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> sodium ascorbate solutions were freshly prepared before each experiment <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">58</xref>. Hydroxyl radical cleavage was initiated by adding 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of the Fe(II)&#x02013;EDTA complex, 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of sodium ascorbate and 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of hydrogen peroxide solution to the reaction. A control reaction lacking Fe(II)&#x02013;EDTA was performed in parallel. After incubation at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s, reactions were quenched and precipitated by addition of 75% glycerol (one&#x02010;third volume), 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of 20&#x000a0;mg&#x000b7;mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> glycogen, 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of 3&#x000a0;<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of 0.5&#x000a0;<sc>m</sc> EDTA and 2.5&#x000a0;volumes of ice&#x02010;cold ethanol. RNAs were re&#x02010;suspended and reverse&#x02010;transcribed. Primer extension reactions were performed using fluorescent primers as described above for SHAPE reactivity. The NED fluorophore was used for both treated and untreated samples, while the VIC fluorophore was used for the sequencing ladder. cDNA products were resolved by capillary electrophoresis.</p></sec><sec id="febs12890-sec-0013"><title>SHAPE reactivity and hydroxyl radical cleavage data analysis</title><p>Quantitative SHAPE reactivity for individual datasets obtained with radiolabeled primers was normalized to a scale spanning 0&#x02013;1.5, in which 0 indicates unreactive nucleotides and the mean intensity at highly reactive nucleotides is set to 1.0 <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref>. For each dataset, the intensity of the untreated RNA was subtracted from that of the treated RNA to obtain the net reactivity. Then, a normalization factor was determined by excluding the 2% most&#x02010;reactive peak intensities, followed by calculating the mean for the next 8% of peak intensities. Reactivity values were then divided by this mean <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">58</xref>. Data from at least three independent assays were used to calculate the SHAPE reactivity (mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SD).</p><p>SHAPE electropherograms were analyzed using <sc>qushape</sc> software <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">59</xref>. Quantitative SHAPE reactivities for individual datasets were normalized to a scale spanning 0&#x02013;1.5, in which 0 indicates an unreactive nucleotide, and the mean intensity at highly reactive nucleotides is set to 1.0.</p><p>Hydroxyl radical cleavage intensities were normalized to a scale from 0 to 1.5, where 1.0 is defined as the mean intensity of highly reactive residues. Nucleotides with reactivity values lower than half the mean reactivity are defined as solvent&#x02010;inaccessible <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">60</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="febs12890-sec-0014"><title>RNA structure analysis</title><p>The secondary RNA structure was visualized using VARNA <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">61</xref>. RNAsc, RNAstructure and <sc>shapeknots</sc> software <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0049 febs12890-bib-0050 febs12890-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">49</xref> were used to predict the secondary RNA structure including SHAPE reactivity values.</p></sec><sec id="febs12890-sec-0015"><title>Nucleotide sequence analysis</title><p>Alignment of 180 FMDV IRES nucleotide sequences available in GenBank was performed using <sc>clustalx</sc> with default parameters (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clustal.org">http://www.clustal.org</ext-link>). Polymorphic positions in the region 306&#x02013;380 were determined relative to the FMDV C&#x02010;S8 isolate (GenBank accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/AF274010.1">AF274010.1</ext-link>). The sequence logo (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://weblogo.berkeley.edu">http://weblogo.berkeley.edu</ext-link>) was generated from alignment of the 180 IRES sequences. The overall height of each stack indicates the sequence conservation at that position (measured in bits), and the height of symbols within the stack reflects the relative frequency of the corresponding nucleic acid at that position.</p></sec><sec id="febs12890-sec-0016"><title>Expression and purification of proteins</title><p><italic>Escherichia&#x000a0;coli</italic> BL21 was transformed with plasmids expressing His&#x02010;tagged eIF4G <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">62</xref> and His&#x02010;tagged eIF4B <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">63</xref>, and grown in Luria&#x02013;Bertani medium at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Protein expression was induced using isopropyl&#x02010;&#x003b2;&#x02010;<sc>d</sc>&#x02010;thiogalactopyranoside for 2&#x000a0;h. Bacterial cell lysates were prepared in binding buffer (20&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 500&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 20&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> imidazole), and cell debris was eliminated by centrifugation twice at 16&#x000a0;000&#x000a0;<italic><bold>g</bold></italic> for 30&#x000a0;min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The lysate was loaded into His&#x02010;GraviTrap columns (GE HealthCare, Little Chalfont, UK), and the recombinant protein was eluted using 500&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> imidazole. Proteins were dialyzed against phosphate buffer, pH 6.8, containing 1&#x000a0;m<sc>m</sc> dithiothreitol, and stored at &#x02212;20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in 50% glycerol.</p></sec><sec id="febs12890-sec-0017"><title>IRES activity assays</title><p>Relative IRES activity was quantified as the expression in transfected BHK&#x02010;21 cell monolayers of luciferase normalized to that of chloramphenicol acetyltransferase from bi&#x02010;cistronic mRNAs as described previously <xref rid="febs12890-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">47</xref>. Experiments were performed in triplicate wells, and each experiment was repeated at least three times.</p></sec></sec><sec id="febs12890-sec-0019"><title>Author contributions</title><p>GL, NF, EMS Planned experiments; GL, NF Performed experiments; GL, EMS Analyzed data; EMS Wrote the paper.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="febs12890-sec-0018"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to I.N. Shatsky [Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry of Nucleoproteins, Belozersky Institute of Physico&#x02010;Chemical Biology, Lomonosov Moscow State University, Moscow, Russia)] and A. Nieto [Department of Molecular and Cellular Biology, Centro Nacional de Biotecnolog&#x000ed;a, Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas (C.S.I.C.), Madrid (Spain)] for provision of His&#x02010;tagged eIF4B and His&#x02010;tagged eIF4G expression vectors, respectively, J. Ramajo [Department of Genome Dynamics and Function, Centro de Biolog&#x000ed;a Molecular Severo Ochoa, CSIC&#x02010;Universidad Aut&#x000f3;noma de Madrid, Madrid (Spain)] for excellent technical assistance, and C. Gutierrez [Department of Genome Dynamics and Function, Centro de Biolog&#x000ed;a Molecular Severo Ochoa, CSIC&#x02010;Universidad Aut&#x000f3;noma de Madrid, Madrid (Spain)], I. Dotu [Biology Department, Boston College, Massachusetts (USA)], C. Briones [Department of Molecular Evolution, Centro de Astrobiolog&#x000ed;a (INTA&#x02010;CSIC), Torrej&#x000f3;n de Ardoz, Madrid (Spain)] and R. Diaz&#x02010;Toledano[Department of Genome Dynamics and Function, Centro de Biolog&#x000ed;a Molecular Severo Ochoa, CSIC&#x02010;Universidad Aut&#x000f3;noma de Madrid, Madrid (Spain)] for helpful comments on the manuscript. This work was supported by grants BFU2011&#x02010;25437, CSD2009&#x02010;00080 (Ministerio de Econom&#x000ed;a y Competitividad) and an institutional grant from Fundaci&#x000f3;n Ram&#x000f3;n Areces.</p></ack><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="febs12890-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="febs12890-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McPheeters</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cremona</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sunder</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Averbeck</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leatherwood</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Wise</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A complex gene regulatory mechanism that operates at the nexus of multiple RNA processing decisions</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source><volume>16</volume>, <fpage>255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19198588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Anokhina</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bessonov</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miao</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Westhof</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hartmuth</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Luhrmann</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>RNA structure analysis of human spliceosomes reveals a compact 3D arrangement of snRNAs at the catalytic core</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source><volume>32</volume>, <fpage>2804</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24002212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernandez</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernandez&#x02010;Miragall</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramajo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia&#x02010;Sacristan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bellora</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eyras</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Briones</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Structural basis for the biological relevance of the invariant apical stem in IRES&#x02010;mediated translation</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>39</volume>, <fpage>8572</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21742761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Perard</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leyrat</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baudin</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drouet</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Jamin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Structure of the full&#x02010;length HCV IRES in solution</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source><volume>4</volume>, <fpage>1612</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23511476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jan</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Sarnow</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Factorless ribosome assembly on the internal ribosome entry site of cricket paralysis virus</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>324</volume>, <fpage>889</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12470947</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pacheco</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Serrano</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Fernandez</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>New insights into internal ribosome entry site elements relevant for viral gene expression</article-title>. <source>J Gen Virol</source><volume>89</volume>, <fpage>611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>626</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18272751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Filbin</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Kieft</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Toward a structural understanding of IRES RNA function</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source><volume>19</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19362464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Spriggs</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bushell</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Willis</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Translational regulation of gene expression during conditions of cell stress</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source><volume>40</volume>, <fpage>228</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20965418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sonenberg</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Hinnebusch</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names></string-name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Regulation of translation initiation in eukaryotes: mechanisms and biological targets</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>136</volume>, <fpage>731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>745</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19239892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The impact of RNA structure on picornavirus IRES activity</article-title>. <source>Trends Microbiol</source><volume>16</volume>, <fpage>230</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18420413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernandez&#x02010;Miragall</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lopez de Quinto</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Relevance of RNA structure for the activity of picornavirus IRES elements</article-title>. <source>Virus Res</source><volume>139</volume>, <fpage>172</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18692097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lopez de Quinto</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lafuente</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>IRES interaction with translation initiation factors: functional characterization of novel RNA contacts with eIF3, eIF4B, and eIF4GII</article-title>. <source>RNA</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>1213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11565745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pacheco</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lopez de Quinto</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramajo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernandez</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A novel role for Gemin5 in mRNA translation</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>37</volume>, <fpage>582</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19066202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stassinopoulos</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Belsham</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A novel protein&#x02013;RNA binding assay: functional interactions of the foot&#x02010;and&#x02010;mouth disease virus internal ribosome entry site with cellular proteins</article-title>. <source>RNA</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11214173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pilipenko</surname>
<given-names>EV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pestova</surname>
<given-names>TV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kolupaeva</surname>
<given-names>VG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khitrina</surname>
<given-names>EV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poperechnaya</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Agol</surname>
<given-names>VI</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Hellen</surname>
<given-names>CU</given-names></string-name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A cell cycle&#x02010;dependent protein serves as a template&#x02010;specific translation initiation factor</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>2028</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2045</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10950867</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abaeva</surname>
<given-names>IS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marintchev</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pestova</surname>
<given-names>TV</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Hellen</surname>
<given-names>CU</given-names></string-name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Common conformational changes induced in type&#x000a0;2 picornavirus IRESs by cognate <italic>trans</italic>&#x02010;acting factors</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>39</volume>, <fpage>4851</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21306989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernandez</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia&#x02010;Sacristan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramajo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Briones</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Structural analysis provides insights into the modular organization of picornavirus IRES</article-title>. <source>Virology</source><volume>409</volume>, <fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21056890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Duncan</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Weeks</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Nonhierarchical ribonucleoprotein assembly suggests a strain&#x02010;propagation model for protein&#x02010;facilitated RNA folding</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source><volume>49</volume>, <fpage>5418</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20533823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernandez&#x02010;Miragall</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Structural organization of a viral IRES depends on the integrity of the GNRA motif</article-title>. <source>RNA</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14561883</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernandez&#x02010;Miragall</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramos</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramajo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Evidence of reciprocal tertiary interactions between conserved motifs involved in organizing RNA structure essential for internal initiation of translation</article-title>. <source>RNA</source><volume>12</volume>, <fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16373480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Schlick</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Candidate RNA structures for domain&#x000a0;3 of the foot&#x02010;and&#x02010;mouth&#x02010;disease virus internal ribosome entry site</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>41</volume>, <fpage>1483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23275533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shenvi</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friedman</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanson</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Cate</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Accessibility of 18S rRNA in human 40S subunits and 80S ribosomes at physiological magnesium ion concentrations &#x02013; implications for the study of ribosome dynamics</article-title>. <source>RNA</source><volume>11</volume>, <fpage>1898</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16314459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>ZJ</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Importance of diffuse metal ion binding to RNA</article-title>. <source>Met Ions Life Sci</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22010269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Draper</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names></string-name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A guide to ions and RNA structure</article-title>. <source>RNA</source><volume>10</volume>, <fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14970378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ramos</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Long&#x02010;range RNA interactions between structural domains of the aphthovirus internal ribosome entry site (IRES)</article-title>. <source>RNA</source><volume>5</volume>, <fpage>1374</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10573128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bowman</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lenz</surname>
<given-names>TK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hud</surname>
<given-names>NV</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names></string-name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Cations in charge: magnesium ions in RNA folding and catalysis</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source><volume>22</volume>, <fpage>262</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22595008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Behrouzi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roh</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kilburn</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Briber</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Woodson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Cooperative tertiary interaction network guides RNA folding</article-title>. <source>Cell</source><volume>149</volume>, <fpage>348</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22500801</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petersen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Niepmann</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Interaction of eukaryotic initiation factor eIF&#x02013;4B with a picornavirus internal translation initiation site</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source><volume>69</volume>, <fpage>2819</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7707504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wilkinson</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Merino</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Weeks</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Selective 2&#x02032;&#x02013;hydroxyl acylation analyzed by primer extension (SHAPE): quantitative RNA structure analysis at single nucleotide resolution</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source><volume>1</volume>, <fpage>1610</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17406453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Weeks</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Mauger</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Exploring RNA structural codes with SHAPE chemistry</article-title>. <source>Acc Chem Res</source><volume>44</volume>, <fpage>1280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21615079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mortimer</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Weeks</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>C2&#x02032;&#x02010;endo nucleotides as molecular timers suggested by the folding of an RNA domain</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>106</volume>, <fpage>15622</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15627</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19717440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mortimer</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Weeks</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Time&#x02010;resolved RNA SHAPE chemistry: quantitative RNA structure analysis in one&#x02010;second snapshots and at single&#x02010;nucleotide resolution</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source><volume>4</volume>, <fpage>1413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19745823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lopez de Quinto</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Conserved structural motifs located in distal loops of aphthovirus internal ribosome entry site domain&#x000a0;3 are required for internal initiation of translation</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source><volume>71</volume>, <fpage>4171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9094703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pineiro</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernandez</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramajo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Gemin5 promotes IRES interaction and translation control through its C&#x02013;terminal region</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>41</volume>, <fpage>1017</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23221641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lopez de Quinto</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Interaction of the eIF4G initiation factor with the aphthovirus IRES is essential for internal translation initiation <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title>. <source>RNA</source><volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1380</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11073214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kolupaeva</surname>
<given-names>VG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pestova</surname>
<given-names>TV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hellen</surname>
<given-names>CU</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Shatsky</surname>
<given-names>IN</given-names></string-name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Translation eukaryotic initiation factor 4G recognizes a specific structural element within the internal ribosome entry site of encephalomyocarditis virus RNA</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>273</volume>, <fpage>18599</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9660832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Clark</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Robertson</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conn</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Belsham</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Conserved nucleotides within the J&#x000a0;domain of the encephalomyocarditis virus internal ribosome entry site are required for activity and for interaction with eIF4G</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source><volume>77</volume>, <fpage>12441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14610168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bassili</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tzima</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saleh</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ochs</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Niepmann</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Sequence and secondary structure requirements in a highly conserved element for foot&#x02010;and&#x02010;mouth disease virus internal ribosome entry site activity and eIF4G binding</article-title>. <source>J Gen Virol</source><volume>85</volume>, <fpage>2555</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15302949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pestova</surname>
<given-names>TV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hellen</surname>
<given-names>CU</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Shatsky</surname>
<given-names>IN</given-names></string-name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Canonical eukaryotic initiation factors determine initiation of translation by internal ribosomal entry</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>16</volume>, <fpage>6859</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8943341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rangan</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Masquida</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Westhof</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Woodson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Assembly of core helices and rapid tertiary folding of a small bacterial group&#x000a0;I ribozyme</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>100</volume>, <fpage>1574</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12574513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cruz</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blanchet</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boniecki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bujnicki</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Das</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dokholyan</surname>
<given-names>NV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flores</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name><italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>RNA&#x02010;Puzzles: a CASP&#x02010;like evaluation of RNA three&#x02010;dimensional structure prediction</article-title>. <source>RNA</source><volume>18</volume>, <fpage>610</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22361291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gulay</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kasprzak</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dinman</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shapiro</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Simon</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The kissing&#x02010;loop T&#x02013;shaped structure translational enhancer of pea enation mosaic virus can bind simultaneously to ribosomes and a 5&#x02032; proximal hairpin</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source><volume>87</volume>, <fpage>11987</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12002</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23986599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grigull</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ore</surname>
<given-names>MO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>White</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Global organization of a positive&#x02010;strand RNA virus genome</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e1003363</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23717202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lusvarghi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sztuba&#x02010;Solinska</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Purzycka</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pauly</surname>
<given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rausch</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Grice</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The HIV&#x02013;2 Rev&#x02010;response element: determining secondary structure and defining folding intermediates</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>41</volume>, <fpage>6637</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23640333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Romero&#x02010;Lopez</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barroso&#x02010;Deljesus</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia&#x02010;Sacristan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Briones</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Berzal&#x02010;Herranz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>End&#x02010;to&#x02010;end crosstalk within the hepatitis&#x000a0;C virus genome mediates the conformational switch of the 3&#x02032;X&#x02010;tail region</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>42</volume>, <fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24049069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Serrano</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramajo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Rescue of internal initiation of translation by RNA complementation provides evidence for a distribution of functions between individual IRES domains</article-title>. <source>Virology</source><volume>388</volume>, <fpage>221</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19383564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Regalado</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Domingo</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Identification of an essential region for internal initiation of translation in the aphthovirus internal ribosome entry site and implications for viral evolution</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source><volume>70</volume>, <fpage>992</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>998</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8551640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernandez</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buddrus</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pineiro</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Evolutionary conserved motifs constrain the RNA structure organization of picornavirus IRES</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>587</volume>, <fpage>1353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23507141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zarringhalam</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dotu</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chuang</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Clote</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Integrating chemical footprinting data into RNA secondary structure prediction</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e45160</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23091593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reuter</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Mathews</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>RNAstructure: software for RNA secondary structure prediction and analysis</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><volume>11</volume>, <fpage>129</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20230624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hajdin</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bellaousov</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huggins</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leonard</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mathews</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Weeks</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Accurate SHAPE&#x02010;directed RNA secondary structure modeling, including pseudoknots</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>110</volume>, <fpage>5498</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23503844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chauhan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Woodson</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Tertiary interactions determine the accuracy of RNA folding</article-title>. <source>J Am Chem Soc</source><volume>130</volume>, <fpage>1296</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18179212</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bindewald</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wendeler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Legiewicz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bona</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pritt</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Le Grice</surname>
<given-names>SF</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Shapiro</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Correlating SHAPE signatures with three&#x02010;dimensional RNA structures</article-title>. <source>RNA</source><volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1688</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21752927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gunther</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Concentration, compartmentation and metabolic function of intracellular free Mg<sup>2+</sup></article-title>. <source>Magnes Res</source><volume>19</volume>, <fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17402290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lomakin</surname>
<given-names>IB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hellen</surname>
<given-names>CU</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Pestova</surname>
<given-names>TV</given-names></string-name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Physical association of eukaryotic initiation factor 4G (eIF4G) with eIF4A strongly enhances binding of eIF4G to the internal ribosomal entry site of encephalomyocarditis virus and is required for internal initiation of translation</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>20</volume>, <fpage>6019</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6029</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10913184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fajardo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosas</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sobrino</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Exploring IRES region accessibility by interference of foot&#x02010;and&#x02010;mouth disease virus infectivity</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e41382</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22815996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dotu</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lozano</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clote</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Martinez&#x02010;Salas</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Using RNA inverse folding to identify IRES&#x02010;like structural subdomains</article-title>. <source>RNA Biol</source><volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1842</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24253111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McGinnis</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duncan</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Weeks</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>High&#x02010;throughput SHAPE and hydroxyl radical analysis of RNA structure and ribonucleoprotein assembly</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol</source><volume>468</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20946765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Karabiber</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McGinnis</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Favorov</surname>
<given-names>OV</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Weeks</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>QuShape: rapid, accurate, and best&#x02010;practices quantification of nucleic acid probing information, resolved by capillary electrophoresis</article-title>. <source>RNA</source><volume>19</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23188808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chakraborty</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mehtab</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patwardhan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Krishnan</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Pri&#x02010;miR&#x02013;17&#x02013;92a transcript folds into a tertiary structure and autoregulates its processing</article-title>. <source>RNA</source><volume>18</volume>, <fpage>1014</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22450760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Darty</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Denise</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Ponty</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>VARNA: interactive drawing and editing of the RNA secondary structure</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1974</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1975</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19398448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aragon</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>de la Luna</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Novoa</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carrasco</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ortin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Nieto</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Eukaryotic translation initiation factor 4GI is a cellular target for NS1 protein, a translational activator of influenza virus</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>20</volume>, <fpage>6259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10938102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="febs12890-bib-0063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dmitriev</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Terenin</surname>
<given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dunaevsky</surname>
<given-names>YE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Merrick</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name> &#x00026; <string-name><surname>Shatsky</surname>
<given-names>IN</given-names></string-name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Assembly of 48S translation initiation complexes from purified components with mRNAs that have some base pairing within their 5&#x02032; untranslated regions</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>23</volume>, <fpage>8925</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8933</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14645505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>