<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rimtsp</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Revista do Instituto de Medicina Tropical de S&#x000e3;o Paulo</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0036-4665</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1678-9946</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Instituto de Medicina Tropical</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26603237</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4660459</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0036-46652015000500016</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>FIRST REPORT OF CUTANEOUS LEISHMANIASIS CAUSED BY<italic>Leishmania</italic> (<italic>Leishmania</italic>) <italic>infantum chagasi</italic> IN AN URBAN AREA OF RIO DE JANEIRO, BRAZIL</article-title><trans-title-group xml:lang="pt"><trans-title>Primeiro relato da leishmaniose cut&#x000e2;nea causada por<italic>Leishmania (Leishmania) infantum chagasi </italic>em uma &#x000e1;rea urbana do Rio de Janeiro, Brasil</trans-title></trans-title-group></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>LYRA</surname><given-names>Marcelo Rosandiski</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>PIMENTEL</surname><given-names>Maria In&#x000ea;s Fernandes</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>MADEIRA</surname><given-names>Maria de F&#x000e1;tima</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>ANTONIO</surname><given-names>Liliane de F&#x000e1;tima</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>LYRA</surname><given-names>Janine Pontes de Miranda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>FAGUNDES</surname><given-names>Aline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>SCHUBACH</surname><given-names>Armando de Oliveira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>(1)</label>Laborat&#x000f3;rio de Pesquisa Cl&#x000ed;nica e Vigil&#x000e2;ncia em Leishmanioses (LapClin VigiLeish), Instituto Nacional de Infectologia Evandro Chagas (INI)/ Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Oswaldo Cruz (FIOCRUZ), Rio de Janeiro, Brasil</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>(2)</label>Pesquisador N&#x000ed;vel 1D do Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico (CNPq)</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c01"><bold>Correspondence to</bold>: Liliane de F&#x000e1;tima Antonio. Laborat&#x000f3;rio de Pesquisa Cl&#x000ed;nica e Vigil&#x000e2;ncia em Leishmanioses (LapClin VigiLeish), Instituto Nacional de Infectologia Evandro Chagas (INI)/FIOCRUZ, Av. Brasil 4365, Manguinhos, 21040-360 Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brasil. Tel.: +55.21.80228384; +55.21.38659541. E-mail: <email>lilianedefatima@gmail.com, liliane.fatima@ini.fiocruz.br</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><season>Sep-Oct</season><year>2015</year></pub-date><!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' --><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Sep-Oct</season><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>57</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>454</lpage><permissions><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><title>SUMMARY</title><p>American tegumentary leishmaniasis (ATL) is an infectious disease caused by protozoa of the genus <italic>Leishmania</italic>, and transmitted by sandflies. In the state of Rio de Janeiro, almost all of the cases of American tegumentary leishmaniasis (ATL) are caused by <italic>Leishmania (Viannia) braziliensis</italic>, while cases of visceral leishmaniasis (VL) are caused by <italic>Leishmania (Leishmania) infantum chagasi</italic>. The resurgence of autochthonous VL cases in Rio de Janeiro is related to the geographic expansion of the vector <italic>Lutzomyia longipalpis</italic> and its ability to adapt to urban areas. We report the first case of leishmaniasis with exclusively cutaneous manifestations caused by <italic>L. (L.) infantum chagasi</italic> in an urban area of Rio de Janeiro. An eighty-one-year-old woman presented three pleomorphic skin lesions that were not associated with systemic symptoms or visceromegalies. Multilocus enzyme electrophoresis identified <italic>L. (L.) infantum chagasi</italic>, but direct smear and PCR of bone narrow were negative for <italic>Leishmania sp</italic>. (suggesting exclusively cutaneous involvement). We discuss the different dermatological presentations of viscerotropic leishmaniasis of the New and Old World, and the clinical and epidemiological importance of the case. Etiologic diagnosis of ATL based upon exclusive clinical criteria may lead to incorrect conclusions. We should be aware of the constant changes in epidemiological patterns related to leishmaniases. </p></abstract><trans-abstract xml:lang="pt"><title>RESUMO</title><p>A leishmaniose tegumentar americana (LTA) &#x000e9; uma doen&#x000e7;a infecciosa causada por protozo&#x000e1;rios do g&#x000ea;nero <italic>Leishmania</italic>, transmitida por flebotom&#x000ed;neos. No estado do Rio de Janeiro, quase todos os casos de LTA s&#x000e3;o causados por <italic>Leishmania (Viannia) braziliensis</italic>, enquanto a leishmaniose visceral (LV) &#x000e9; causada por <italic>Leishmania (Leishmania) infantum chagasi</italic>. O ressurgimento de casos aut&#x000f3;ctones de LV no Rio de Janeiro est&#x000e1; relacionado com a expans&#x000e3;o geogr&#x000e1;fica dos vetores<italic>Lutzomyia longipalpis</italic> e &#x000e0; sua capacidade de se adaptar &#x000e0;s &#x000e1;reas urbanas. Relatamos o primeiro caso de leishmaniose com manifesta&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es exclusivamente cut&#x000e2;neas causadas por <italic>L. (L.) infantum chagasi</italic>em uma &#x000e1;rea urbana do Rio de Janeiro. Mulher de 81 anos apresentou tr&#x000ea;s les&#x000f5;es cut&#x000e2;neas pleom&#x000f3;rficas n&#x000e3;o associadas a sintomas sist&#x000ea;micos ou visceromegalias. A eletroforese de enzimas multilocus obtida a partir da les&#x000e3;o cut&#x000e2;nea identificou <italic>L. (L.) infantum chagasi, </italic>por outro lado o exame direto e o PCR da medula &#x000f3;ssea foram negativos para <italic>Leishmania</italic>sp. (sugerindo acometimento exclusivamente cut&#x000e2;neo). Discutimos as diferentes apresenta&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es dermatol&#x000f3;gicos da leishmaniose visceral do Novo e Velho Mundo, assim como a import&#x000e2;ncia cl&#x000ed;nica e epidemiol&#x000f3;gica deste caso. O diagn&#x000f3;stico etiol&#x000f3;gico da LTA com base apenas em crit&#x000e9;rios cl&#x000ed;nicos pode levar a conclus&#x000f5;es incorretas. Devemos estar conscientes das constantes mudan&#x000e7;as nos padr&#x000f5;es epidemiol&#x000f3;gicos relacionados &#x000e0; leishmaniose.</p></trans-abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Cutaneous leishmaniasis</kwd><kwd>Leishmania (Leishmania) infantum chagasi</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="21"/><page-count count="4"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Leishmaniases are antropozoonoses caused by protozoa of the genus<italic>Leishmania</italic> and comprise a complex of diseases with varied clinical spectrum and epidemiological diversity, whose transmission occurs during blood feeding of infected female sandflies<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>. In the state of Rio de Janeiro, almost all of the cases of American tegumentary leishmaniasis (ATL) are caused by <italic>Leishmania (Viannia) braziliensis</italic>
<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, while visceral leishmaniasis (VL) is caused by <italic>Leishmania (L.) infantum chagasi</italic>. The resurgence of autochthonous VL cases in the state of Rio de Janeiro since 2010 is related to the geographic expansion of the vector <italic>Lutzomyia longipalpis</italic> and to its ability to adapt to urban areas<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>. In the city of Rio de Janeiro, dogs are the main reservoir of <italic>L. (L.) infantum chagasi</italic>. Canine enzooties have preceded the occurrence of human cases, and infection in dogs has been more prevalent than in humans<xref rid="B08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>. The patient we describe lived in Caju neighborhood, located near downtown, in an area without forest remnants. The emergence of VL in the urban area of Rio de Janeiro is highly relevant, since it represents an important public health problem. While in Central America cutaneous manifestations of <italic>L. (L) infantum chagasi</italic> are quite common, in Brazil they are extremely rare. We report the first case of leishmaniasis with exclusively cutaneous manifestations caused by <italic>L. (L.) infantum chagasi</italic> in an urban area of Rio de Janeiro, discussing its clinical importance and possible epidemiological consequences.</p></sec><sec><title>CASE REPORT</title><p>An eighty-one-year-old woman, from Rio de Janeiro, residing for the previous two years in a nursing home in Caju neighborhood, reported the appearance of skin lesions about seven months earlier. She had cardiac disease and chronic renal failure (CRF) and was referred to the Laboratory of Leishmaniases Surveillance of the Evandro Chagas National Institute of Infectious Diseases, of the Oswaldo Cruz Foundation. Dermatological examination revealed the presence of three pleomorphic lesions that measured between 3 and 4 cm in diameter and were located in the frontal and left malar regions of the face, and in the right elbow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref>). The lesions were not associated with systemic symptoms such as fever, weight loss or poor general condition. The patient had no lymphadenopathy or visceromegalies. Laboratory tests were within normal range, except for increased urea (135 mg/dL) and creatinine (2.65 mg/dL) due to pre-existing CRF. Electrocardiogram showed cardiac arrhythmia and enlargement of the corrected QT space (QTc) (0.50 seconds). Abdominal ultrasound did not reveal the presence of hepatomegaly or splenomegaly. Histopathology, direct smear, culture in McNeal, Novy, Nicolle (NNN) medium, and polymerase chain reaction (PCR) performed on cutaneous lesions fragments confirmed the clinical diagnosis of ATL. Montenegro skin test and enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) serology for leishmaniasis resulted positive. Since no previous cases of ATL were known in this neighborhood, and a recent case of VL had been described in this location<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, we performed the multilocus enzyme electrophoresis assay as previously described<xref rid="B05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, and the identification of <italic>L. (L.) infantum chagasi</italic> was confirmed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Fig. 3</xref>). Culture and PCR of a bone marrow sample were negative for parasite isolation or<italic>Leishmania</italic> DNA detection. Since the patient presented a history of heart disease and chronic renal failure, we discarded the use of meglumine antimoniate. The patient received liposomal amphotericin B 4 mg/kg/day with a cumulative dose of 1.25 g. During hospitalization, the patient did not present any systemic manifestations compatible to VL. Two months post-treatment, the facial lesions had healed and the lesion of the arm was partially epithelialized. </p><p>
<fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>
<bold>-</bold>
<bold>A)</bold> Ulcerative and vegetating lesion in the left infra-orbital region. <bold>B)</bold> Infiltrative exulcerated plaque in the frontal region.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0036-4665-rimtsp-57-05-00451-gf01"/></fig>
</p><p>
<fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>
<bold>-</bold> Round ulcer with infiltrated borders in the right elbow.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0036-4665-rimtsp-57-05-00451-gf02"/></fig>
</p><p>
<fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>
<bold>-</bold> Multilocus enzyme electrophoresis representative gel showing the patterns observed for the nucleoside hydrolase (NH) system. Lane 1: <italic>Leishmania</italic> (<italic>Leishmania</italic>)<italic>amazonensis</italic> reference strain (IFLA/BR/1967/PH8); Lane 2: <italic>Leishmania</italic> (<italic>Viannia</italic>)<italic>guyanensis</italic> reference strain (MHOM/BR/1975/M4147); Lane 3: <italic>Leishmania </italic>(<italic>Viannia</italic>)<italic>braziliensis</italic> reference strain (MHOM/BR/1975/M2903); Lanes 4 and 6: <italic>Leishmania</italic> (<italic>Leishmania</italic>)<italic>infantum chagasi </italic>reference strain (MHOM/BR/1974/PP75); Lanes 5 and 7: sample isolated from patient's cutaneous lesion that showed similar profiles with<italic>Leishmania</italic> (<italic>Leishmania</italic>)<italic>infantum chagasi </italic>reference strain.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0036-4665-rimtsp-57-05-00451-gf03"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Only two cases of ATL caused by species other than <italic>L. (V.) braziliensis</italic> were previously described in the state of Rio de Janeiro: one in the city of Paraty, in 2007, caused by <italic>Leishmania (L.). amazonensis</italic>
<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>; and another caused by <italic>L. donovani</italic>
<italic>chagasi</italic> (now known as <italic>Leishmania (L.) infantum chagasi</italic>) in a rural area of the city of Rio de Janeiro in 1986<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>. In addition, a case of co-infection in which the patient showed VL caused by <italic>L. donovani</italic> and ATL caused by<italic>L. braziliensis braziliensis</italic> (now known as <italic>L. (V.) braziliensis</italic>) was described<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>.</p><p>In the case reported here, the identification of the parasite isolated through culture of a cutaneous fragment was performed by multilocus enzyme electrophoresis, considered the gold standard method for the characterization of<italic>Leishmania</italic> species. Moreover, the failure to detect parasite or<italic>Leishmania</italic> DNA in a bone narrow sample suggests exclusive cutaneous involvement. </p><p>In a series of 18 patients with VL in northeastern Brazil, 40% were positive for<italic>L. (L) infantum chagasi</italic> in the culture of fragments of skin lesions or unimpaired skin<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>. Cases related to <italic>L. (L.) donovani</italic> with dermatological compromise in Africa and in the Indian subcontinent are generally associated with post kala-azar dermal leishmaniasis. In these cases, cutaneous lesions (macules, papules, nodules, or plaques), without a tendency to ulcerate, arise on the skin after the end of the treatment for VL<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>. In Brazil, this presentation is rare and is usually related to HIV-coinfection<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>. In Europe, rare cases of cutaneous<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> or mucocutaneous<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>leishmaniasis caused by <italic>L. (L.) infantum </italic>have been reported, and these cases seem to be related to specific zymodemes<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>. Alternatively, the exclusively cutaneous involvement by <italic>L. donovani chagasi </italic>is described in Central America. However, no genetic differences between <italic>Leishmania (L.) chagasi</italic> strains causing VL and CL were observed in Honduras<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> and Nicaragua<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>. Cutaneous leishmaniasis caused by <italic>Leishmania (L.) chagasi</italic> in patients from Central America tends to have an atypical presentation: the lesions are papulonodular, surrounded by areas of hypochromia; they predominate in the cephalic segment and do not ulcerate<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>. In these countries, children under five years of age present visceral forms mostly, while the cutaneous forms prevail in older children and young adults. </p><p>In Venezuela, patients affected by <italic>L. colombiensis</italic> present VL as much as CL<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>. The clinical presentation results from a complex interaction among the <italic>Leishmania</italic> species with host immunity.</p><p>In Brazil, cases of CL caused by <italic>L. (L) infantum chagasi</italic> are so rare that it is not possible to certify the age range that can influence the clinical expression of the disease. In this report, the benign manifestation of the disease suggests a partially effective immunity that is not related to previous infection with <italic>L. (L) infantum chagasi</italic> in childhood, since our patient was not coming from an LV endemic area and only resided in Caju neighborhood for two years. </p><p>The case reported that exclusive cutaneous form caused by <italic>L. (L) infantum chagasi</italic> may not represent an isolated case. Recently, two cases of ATL with cutaneous manifestations arising from a community located in the same region were taken into account by the Brazilian system for notifiable diseases, SINANNET<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>. Although the characterization of the involved <italic>Leishmania</italic> species was not possible in those cases, dermotropic strains of <italic>L. (L) infantum chagasi </italic>could be involved. In this area, no previous ATL cases have been reported, and neither the presence of<italic>Lutzomyia intermedia</italic>, the main vector of <italic>Leishmania (V.) braziliensis</italic> in the state of Rio de Janeiro, was observed. On the other hand, the presence of <italic>Lutzomyia longipalpis, </italic>the principal vector of <italic>L. (L) chagasi infantum</italic> in Brazil, has been demonstrated. Etiologic diagnosis of ATL based upon exclusive clinical criteria may lead to incorrect conclusions. We should be aware of the constant changes in epidemiological patterns related to the leishmaniases. We therefore suggest that multilocus enzyme electrophoresis of isolated parasites and/or PCR of tissue fragments should be performed in order to identify the involved species in futures suspected cases of ATL in the Caju neighborhood.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>This work received support from INI/FIOCRUZ and the National Council of Scientific and Technicological Development Brazil (CNPq).</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B01"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azeredo-Coutinho</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Concei&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o-Silva</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cupolillo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Quintella</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Madeira</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First report of diffuse cutaneous leishmaniasis and Leishmania amazonensis infection in Rio de Janeiro State, Brazil</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><year>2007</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>735</fpage><lpage>737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17368698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B02"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Videa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Widespread atypical cutaneous Leishmaniasis caused by Leishmania (L.) chagasi in Nicaragua</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><year>1999</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10497975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B03"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Brasil. Minist&#x000e9;rio da Sa&#x000fa;de</collab></person-group><source>Manual de vigil&#x000e2;ncia da leishmaniose tegumentar cut&#x000e2;nea</source><sup>a</sup><publisher-loc>Bras&#x000ed;lia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Minist&#x000e9;rio da Sa&#x000fa;de</publisher-name><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B04"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carna&#x000fa;ba D</surname><given-names>Jr</given-names></name><name><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Petri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira-Chioccola</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atypical disseminated leishmaniasis similar to post-kala-azar dermal leishmaniasis in a Brazilian AIDS patient infected with Leishmania (Leishmania) infantum chagasi: a case report</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e504</fpage><lpage>e507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19447660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B05"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cupolillo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gimaldi G</surname><given-names>Jr</given-names></name><name><surname>Momen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A general classification of New World Leishmania using numerical zymotaxonomy</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><year>1994</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8147488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B06"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>DATASUS</collab></person-group><source>Leishmaniose tegumentar americana: casos confirmados notificados no sistema de informa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de agravos de notifica&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o</source><publisher-loc>Bras&#x000ed;lia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Minist&#x000e9;rio da Sa&#x000fa;de/SINAN</publisher-name><year>2014</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dtr2004.saude.gov.br/sinanweb/tabnet/tabnet?sinannet/lta/bases/ltabrnet.def">http://dtr2004.saude.gov.br/sinanweb/tabnet/tabnet?sinannet/lta/bases/ltabrnet.def</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="B07"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Andrade</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cristaldo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>de Andrade</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>C</surname><given-names>A</given-names><suffix>Filho</suffix></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial distribution and environmental factors associated to phlebotomine fauna in a border area of transmission of visceral leishmaniasis in Mato Grosso do Sul, Brazil</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24898032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B08"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names><suffix>Filho</suffix></name><name><surname>Schubach</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Madeira M de</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relato de caso aut&#x000f3;ctone de leishmaniose visceral canina na zona sul do munic&#x000ed;pio do Rio de Janeiro</article-title><source>Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</source><year>2010</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20305979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B09"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gradoni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gramiccia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leishmania infantum tropism: strain genotype or host immune status?</article-title><source>Parasitol Today</source><year>1994</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15275441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenvers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Peyron</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ulc&#x000e9;ration chron&#x000ed;que du visage: penser &#x000e0; une leishmaniose cutan&#x000e9;e m&#x000e9;tropolitaine due &#x000e0; Leishmania infantum</article-title><source>Ann Dermatol Venerol</source><year>2013</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>704</fpage><lpage>707</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges-Costa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares-Almeida</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Campino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An atypical case of cutaneous leishmaniasis caused by Leishmania infantum in Portugal</article-title><source>Dermatol Online J</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>20407</fpage><lpage>20407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24314782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martins-Melo</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima M da</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos AN</surname><given-names>Jr</given-names></name><name><surname>Alencar</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Heukelbach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mortality and case fatality due to visceral leishmaniasis in Brazil: a nationwide analysis of epidemiology, trendsand spatial patterns</article-title><source>Plos One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id/></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marzochi</surname><given-names>MCA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagundes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Madeira M de</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mouta-Confort</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visceral leishmaniasis in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil: eco-epidemiological aspects and control</article-title><source>Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</source><year>2009</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>570</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19967242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noyes</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chance</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponce</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponce</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Maingon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leishmania chagasi: genotypically similar parasites from Honduras cause both visceral and cutaneous leishmaniasis in humans</article-title><source>Exp Parasitol</source><year>1997</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9085923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira-Neto</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimaldi G</surname><given-names>Jr</given-names></name><name><surname>Momen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pacheco</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Marzochi</surname><given-names>MCA</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon Pratt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Active cutaneous leishmaniasis in Brazil, induced by Leishmania donovani chagasi</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><year>1986</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3574128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>MP</given-names><suffix>Neto</suffix></name><name><surname>Marzochi</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimaldi G</surname><given-names>Jr</given-names></name><name><surname>Pacheco</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Toledo</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Momen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Concurrent human infection with Leishmania donovani and Leishmania braziliensis braziliensis</article-title><source>Ann Trop Med Parasitol</source><year>1986</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3675032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez-Bonfante</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonfante-Garrido</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimaldi G</surname><given-names>Jr</given-names></name><name><surname>Momen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cupolillo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genotypically distinct Leishmania colombiensis isolates from Venezuela cause both cutaneous and visceral leishmaniasis in humans</article-title><source>Infect Genet Evol</source><year>2003</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12809806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bocheat</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferry</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho R de</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First case of autochthonous human visceral leishmaniasis in the urban Center of Rio de Janeiro: case report</article-title><source>Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</source><year>2014</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24553614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-kala-azar dermal leishmaniasis: recent developments</article-title><source>Int J Dermatol</source><year>2011</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1099</fpage><lpage>1108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22126871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasconcelos I de</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousa A de</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Di&#x000f3;genes</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Momen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimaldi G</surname><given-names>Jr</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parisitisme cutan par Leishmania (Leishmania) chagasi au cours de la leishmaniose viscerale Sud-Am&#x000e9;ricaine</article-title><source>Bull Soc Pathol Exot</source><year>1993</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8353466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group><source>Leishmaniasis</source><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name><year>2013</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/leishmaniasis/en/">http://www.who.int/leishmaniasis/en/</ext-link></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>