<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Respir Med Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Respir Med Case Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Respiratory Medicine Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2213-0071</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27358764</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4915958</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2213-0071(16)30047-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rmcr.2016.06.003</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fatal hemorrhagic pneumonia: Don&#x02019;t forget <italic>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name><email>CGutierrez4@mdanderson.org</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pravinkumar</surname><given-names>Egbert</given-names></name><email>EPravink@mdanderson.org</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balachandran</surname><given-names>Dave</given-names></name><email>DBalachandran@mdanderson.org</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>Virginia</given-names></name><email>vfschnei@mdanderson.org</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Critical Care, Division of Anesthesiology and Critical Care, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX, USA</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Pulmonary Medicine, Division of Internal Medicine, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. Department of Critical Care, Division of Anesthesiology and Critical Care, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, 1515 Holcombe Blvd, Unit 0112, Houston, TX, 77030, USA.Department of Critical CareDivision of Anesthesiology and Critical CareThe University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center1515 Holcombe BlvdUnit 0112HoustonTX77030USA <email>CGutierrez4@mdanderson.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2016 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>We present a case of fatal hemorrhagic pneumonia secondary to <italic>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic> in a patient with acute myeloid leukemia. <italic>S.&#x000a0;maltophilia</italic> is commonly a non-virulent pathogen. However, in the immunocompromised, it is generally associated with bacteremia after central venous catheter placement or pneumonia. Hemorrhagic pneumonia is a rare presentation of this bacteria, with only 31 cases reported in the literature, and has 100% mortality within 72 hours. Rapid recognition and early suspicion should be key in the treatment of these patients.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic></kwd><kwd>Hemorrhagic pneumonia</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Case report</title><p>A 59 year old man with history of acute myeloid leukemia in remission and undergoing chemotherapy treatment in preparation for stem cell transplant, presented to the emergency department with fever. At the time he was found to be febrile, tachypneic and hypoxic on room air. Laboratory work up was significant for neutropenia which was present for at least 23 days, a normal coagulation profile and mild thrombocytopenia (56.000&#x000a0;&#x00198;/&#x003bc;L). A chest-X ray showed a left lung base infiltrate suggestive of pneumonia (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>a). He was admitted to the hospital and started on antibiotics for health care associated bacterial pneumonia and fluconazole for possible fungal infection. Within 36 hours of admission he was transferred to the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) with frank hemoptysis, respiratory failure and refractory shock. Chest X-ray at the time showed progression of the pulmonary infiltrates on the left upper and middle lobes (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>b). A bronchoscopy performed to further asses the source of bleeding revealed no endobronchial lesions, but there was evidence of profuse hemorrhage from the posterior basal segment of the left lower lobe (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). Bronchoscopic interventions such as instillation of epinephrine, cold saline and thrombin solution, were unsuccessful to stop the bleeding. The patient&#x02019;s respiratory status continued to deteriorate requiring PEEP of 15 and 100% FiO2 and later on was initiated on APRV mode, but still unable to tolerate FiO2 less than 100%. ABGs at the time continued to show severe hypoxemia and respiratory acidosis (7.27/42/63/89%). Admission blood cultures and bronchial washing revealed gram-negative rods that were later identified as <italic>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic>. Upon recognition of the bacteria trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole (TMP-SMX) was initiated. Despite aggressive support, the patient continued to deteriorate and died within 24&#x000a0;h of ICU admission (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>c).</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Discussion</title><p>The differential diagnosis of pathogens causing pneumonia in the immunocompromised host are extensive. The predominant organisms in the non-neutropenic phase of patients with hematological malignancies include <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic>, and community-acquired respiratory viruses such as <italic>influenza, parainfluenza, respiratory syncytial virus,</italic> and <italic>adenovirus</italic>
<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Common gram negative organisms include <italic>Serratia, Pseudomonas</italic>, <italic>Acinetobacter, Citrobacter and enterobacter(1)</italic>. When neutropenia has less than 1 week of onset common pathogens for pneumonia are <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, <italic>Enterobacteraceae</italic>, <italic>S.&#x000a0;pneumonia</italic>, Influenza virus and RSV infections. After the second week of neutropenia organisms such as <italic>Serratia, Pseudomonas, Acinetobacter, Citrobacter, Enterobacter and mold</italic> are more common (1). In prolonged neutropenia the organisms are similar to those in the second week but are mainly multi drug resistant organisms.</p><p><italic>S.&#x000a0;maltophilia</italic> is usually a non-virulent, gram-negative bacillus found as an airway colonizer in the immunocompetent host <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Since the 1990s however, this bacteria has emerged as an important nosocomial pathogen <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. In immunocompromised patients, <italic>S.&#x000a0;maltophilia</italic> commonly causes pneumonia and bacteremia associated with central venous catheter infections <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Other sites of infection include the eye, soft tissues, joints, meninges, endocardium and urinary tract <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. In immunocompromised patients, and specifically cancer patients, risk factors for infection include neutropenia, prolonged ICU stay, prior use of broad spectrum antibiotics and mechanical ventilation <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. If a patient has any of these risk factors mortality ranges between 14 and 77%; moreover, mortality is higher when bacteremia is secondary to central venous catheter placement and when the patient has required mechanical ventilation <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. When <italic>S.&#x000a0;maltophilia</italic> pneumonia develops in a patient without risk factors, it is usually a mild lobar pneumonia and can be treated as an outpatient <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. On the contrary, in the presence of any risk factors, patients can develop a disease severe enough to require ICU admission, and carries a mortality as high as 50% <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p><p>Hemorrhagic pneumonia is a rare presentation of <italic>S.&#x000a0;maltophilia.</italic> To our knowledge, only 31 cases are reported in the literature and they are all in patients with hematological malignancies <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. The exact mechanism by which <italic>S.&#x000a0;maltophilia</italic> causes hemorrhage is unknown. A study by Windhorst et&#x000a0;al., suggests that StmPr1, a protease of the subtilase family, is secreted by the bacteria leading to tissue invasion, destruction and hemorrhage <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Hemorrhagic pneumonia by <italic>S.&#x000a0;maltophilia</italic> develops in patients who have recently received chemotherapy or a hematopoietic stem cell transplant <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Eighty-four percent of these patients have bacteremia, and their clinical presentation is severe with 100% mortality within 72 hours of diagnosis <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Due to its severity and rapid progression, early suspicion is important; however, efforts for surveillance and prophylaxis are so far limited. In a systematic review of the literature surveillance sputum cultures were positive in only 30% of patients who developed hemorrhagic pneumonia <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Also, despite prophylaxis with quinolones or co-trimoxazole, mortality was unchanged for patients who developed hemorrhagic pneumonia <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. While immunosuppression is a significant risk factor for <italic>S.&#x000a0;maltophilia</italic> infection, it is important to recognize that other infectious causes for hemoptysis such as aspergillomas and tuberculosis should be considered in this population <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p><p><italic>S.&#x000a0;maltophilia</italic> is resistant to third generation cephalosporins, &#x003b2;-lactams, carbapenems and aminoglycosides, all of which are commonly used as initial therapy for pneumonia in the immunocompromised <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. While the mechanism of resistance is not completely understood, it is believed that low membrane permeability and chromosomally encoded efflux pumps cause resistance to beta-lactamases, aminoglycosides and quinolones <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Another limitation to adequate treatment of this pathogen is that <italic>in-vitro</italic> results of susceptibility for <italic>S.&#x000a0;maltophilia</italic> are not standardized; this leads to discrepancy when reporting results and can impact treatment efficacy <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. TMP-SMX is considered the drug of choice. Dosing, while not clinically studied, should be similar as in pneumocystis treatment <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Increasing resistance to TMP-SMX is reported, and it is now debated whether synergistic double coverage therapy should be recommended for initial treatment. Combination therapy should include TMP-SMX and addition of quinolones, colistin, ticarcillin-clavulanate, ceftazidime or aztreonam <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. When considering quinolones, moxifloxacin has shown to have better <italic>in-vitro</italic> activity against <italic>S.&#x000a0;maltophilia</italic> when compared to ciprofloxacin <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Data on the efficiency and clinical response of combination therapy is scarce and no clinical studies are available <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>Commonly, invasive fungal pneumonia is suspected in immunocompromised patients with hemorrhagic pneumonia; however, <italic>S.&#x000a0;maltophilia</italic> should be considered in the differential diagnosis in patients with risk factors. Heightened clinical suspicion and early treatment may lead to increased survival.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Funding and conflict of interest</title><p>No financial or other potential conflicts of interest exist for either author.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>V.R.E.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morice</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Travis</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bashoura</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Safdar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faiz</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balachandran</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nates</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pravinkumar</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickey</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Respiratory complications</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>W.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>American Association for Cancer Research</surname></name></person-group><source>Holland Frei Cancer Medicine 8</source><edition>eighth ed.</edition><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Shelton, Conn.: People&#x02019;s Medical Pub. House</publisher-name><fpage>xxv</fpage><comment>2021 p</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Anazi</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Jasser</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infections caused by Stenotrophomonas maltophilia in recipients of hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</article-title><source>Front. Oncol.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>232</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25202682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Araoka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Izutsu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishiwata</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asano-Mori</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wake</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoneyama</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapidly progressive fatal hemorrhagic pneumonia caused by Stenotrophomonas maltophilia in hematologic malignancy</article-title><source>Transpl. Infect. Dis.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22283869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooke</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia: an emerging global opportunistic pathogen</article-title><source>Clin. Microbiol. Rev.</source><volume>25</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22232370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsunemine</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Imada</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Life-threatening hemorrhagic pneumonia caused by Stenotrophomonas maltophilia in the treatment of hematologic diseases</article-title><source>Ann. Hematol.</source><volume>93</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>901</fpage><lpage>911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24535696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Safdar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolston</surname><given-names>K.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia: changing spectrum of a serious bacterial pathogen in patients with cancer</article-title><source>Clin. Infect. Dis.</source><volume>45</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>1602</fpage><lpage>1609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18190323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aisenberg</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolston</surname><given-names>K.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickey</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kontoyiannis</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raad</surname><given-names>I.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Safdar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia pneumonia in cancer patients without traditional risk factors for infection, 1997&#x02013;2004</article-title><source>Eur. J. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. Dis.</source><volume>26</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17200840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Windhorst</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgieva</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Genov</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borowski</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The major extracellular protease of the nosocomial pathogen Stenotrophomonas maltophilia: characterization of the protein and molecular cloning of the gene</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Biol. Chem.</source><volume>277</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>11042</fpage><lpage>11049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11796713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guzoglu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Demirkol</surname><given-names>F.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aliefendioglu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haemorrhagic pneumonia caused by Stenotrophomonas maltophilia in two newborns</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Infect. Dev. Ctries.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25989175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>C.P.S.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Oncologic Emergencies-principles of Critical Care</source><edition>fourth ed.</edition><year>2015</year><publisher-name>McGraw-Hill Education LLC</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York, N.Y.</publisher-loc><fpage>1</fpage><comment>online resource</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venditti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Micozzi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarasi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martino</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In&#x000a0;vitro activity of moxifloxacin against Stenotrophomonas maltophilia blood isolates from patients with hematologic malignancies</article-title><source>Clin. Microbiol. Infect.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11284945</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Progression of chest X-ray in a patient with <italic>S.&#x000a0;maltophilia</italic> hemorrhagic pneumonia. <bold>a</bold>. Portable chest X-ray on admission. <bold>b</bold>. Post-intubation portable chest X-ray, 36 hours after admission to the hospital <bold>c</bold>. Portable chest X-ray 72 hours after hospital admission.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Evidence of active bleeding during bronchoscopy from posterior basal segment of the left lower lobe.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></floats-group></article>