<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Pediatr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Korean J Pediatr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Korean Journal of Pediatrics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1738-1061</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2092-7258</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Korean Pediatric Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27186231</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4865644</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3345/kjp.2016.59.4.196</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Concomitant use of corticosteroid and antimicrobials for liver abscesses in patients with chronic granulomatous disease</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>Kyung-Sue</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Mu Suk</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Pediatrics, Gyeongsang National University Changwon Hospital, Changwon, Korea.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Diagnostic Radiology, Jeju National University School of Medicine, Jeju, Korea.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding author: Kyung-Sue Shin, MD, Department of Pediatrics, Gyeongsang National University Changwon Hospital, 11, Samjeongja-ro, Seongsan-gu, Changwon 51472, Korea. Tel: +82-55-214-3792, Fax: +82-55-214-1031, <email>kyungsue@gnuh.co.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>59</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>02</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 by The Korean Pediatric Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Chronic granulomatous disease (CGD) is a rare inherited disorder caused by defective nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate oxidase enzyme and characterized by recurrent bacterial and fungal infections. Although liver abscess is a common manifestation of CGD, its management in CGD patients is not well-defined. In addition, the generalized guidelines for treating liver abscesses do not necessarily apply to CGD patients. Corticosteroids are commonly used to control granulomatous complications, such as inflammatory gastrointestinal and genitourinary lesions, in patients with CGD, Corticosteroids have also been used in combination with antimicrobials to treat refractory infections in patients with CGD. Because corticosteroids are capable of suppressing symptomatic inflammation, all potential infections must be adequately controlled prior to corticosteroid initiation. We report 3 typical CGD cases with liver abscesses refractory to conventional treatments that were successfully treated with the concomitant use of corticosteroid and antimicrobials. It remains unclear whether corticosteroid therapy is required for liver abscesses in CGD refractory to conventional treatments. However, based on our observations, use of corticosteroids in combination with optimal antimicrobials should be considered for refractory liver abscesses in CGD.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Chronic granulomatous disease</kwd><kwd>Liver abscess</kwd><kwd>Corticosteroid</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source country="KR"><institution-wrap><institution>Jeju National University</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="CrossRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100002449</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Chronic granulomatous disease (CGD) is a rare primary immunodeficiency caused by mutations in any one of 5 genes encoding subunits of the phagocyte nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate (NADPH) oxidase. The functional activity of NADPH oxidase is significantly diminished or completely absent in patients with CGD, resulting in very low or no production of superoxide derivatives, which are important for killing invading microorganisms<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2)</xref>.</p><p>Infections in patients with CGD are typically caused by a narrow spectrum of bacteria and fungi, such as <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>Serratia marcescens</italic>, <italic>Burkholderia cepacia</italic>, <italic>Aspergillus</italic> species, and <italic>Candida</italic> species<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4)</xref>. Recurrent infections occur primarily in the lung, skin, lymph nodes, and liver. Although liver abscesses are observed in about 30%-35% of CGD patients<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, the management of liver abscesses in CGD patients is not well-defined. At this time, the generalized guidelines for treating liver abscesses do not necessarily apply to CGD patients. Recently, some studies have reported that concurrent therapy with corticosteroids and antimicrobials is highly effective in CGD patients with liver abscesses<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>.</p><p>We report three typical CGD cases with liver abscesses refractory to conventional treatments that were successfully treated with the concomitant use of corticosteroid and antimicrobials.</p></sec><sec><title>Case reports</title><sec><title>1. Case 1</title><p>A 23-year-old female with CGD was referred for a persistent fever. She was diagnosed with p22<sup><italic>phox</italic></sup>-deficient (phox, phagocytic oxidase) CGD at 7 years of age. She had multiple pneumonias, lymphadenitis, cellulitis, osteomyelitis, and liver abscess. She had been undergoing prophylactic therapy with interferon-gamma (IFN-&#x003b3;). Her younger sister was also diagnosed with CGD at 5 years of age (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). One month prior to the current presentation, she was admitted to another hospital with fever, malaise, and chest pain during breathing. Abdominal ultrasound and computed tomography showed a 2 cm-sized abscess in the right hepatic lobe. Treatment with vancomycin, imipenem, and metronidazole reduced the fever after 10 days, but the fever recurred after 3 days. Although amphotericin B was administered, fever continued intermittently for a further 2 weeks.</p><p>On transfer to Jeju National University Hospital, she had abdominal pain and fever. Laboratory data showed elevated white blood cell (WBC) count (15,300/mm<sup>3</sup>), liver enzyme alanine aminotransferase 96 IU/L, and aspartate aminotransferase 113 IU/L, and inflammatory markers erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) &#x0003e;120 mm/hr and C-reactive protein (CRP) 232.7 mg/L. Computed tomography of the abdomen showed multiple abscesses in the right lobe of the liver (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2A, B</xref>). Two large abscesses in the dome (5 cm&#x000d7;4.5 cm) and inferior portion (4 cm&#x000d7;2.5 cm) of the liver were aspirated and percutaneously drained. Antibiotic treatment was initiated with vancomycin, clindamycin and meropenem. She remained febrile for the first 2 weeks of hospitalization, but cultures of the blood and aspirate were negative. Due to persistence of the fever and abscess despite antibiotic treatment, the drains were removed and intravenous methylprednisolone (1.0 mg/kg/day) was administered. She showed rapid clinical improvement within 1 week with significant decreases in the size of the abscesses, and inflammatory markers also decreased (ESR, 71 mm/hr; CRP, 22.5 mg/L). After weaning of intravenous methylprednisolone over 4 weeks to 0.25 mg/kg/day, followed by transition to trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole (TMP/SMX), cefdinir, and oral prednisone (0.25 mg/kg/day), she was discharged. Abdominal ultrasound 1 month after discharge showed only a residual 3.5 cm lesion in the liver dome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>). Oral prednisone was tapered and stopped over 3 months.</p></sec><sec><title>2. Case 2</title><p>A 21-year-old male was admitted after 1 week of fever while on prophylactic TMP/SMX and IFN-&#x003b3; therapy. He was diagnosed with p22<sup><italic>phox</italic></sup>-deficient CGD at 14 years old, based on multifocal liver abscesses. While he had experienced pneumonias, lymphadenitis, cellulitis, and osteomyelitis, he was not diagnosed with CGD until this time. Abdominal ultrasound on admission showed a 4&#x000d7;2 cm-sized abscess in the left hepatic lobe. Laboratory data showed an elevated WBC count (20,500/mm<sup>3</sup>) and inflammatory markers (ESR, 75 mm/hr; CRP, 114.6 mg/L). Antibiotic treatment was initiated with vancomycin, cefotaxime, and metronidazole. He remained febrile for a further 2 weeks and blood cultures were negative. The abscess was aspirated using ultrasound guidance. The antibiotic regimen was changed to vancomycin, clindamycin and meropenem, and intravenous methylprednisolone (0.5 mg/kg/day) was initiated. The fever gradually subsided during the following 2 weeks and follow-up imaging of the abdomen showed significant decreases in the size of the abscesses. Intravenous methylprednisolone was tapered over 2 weeks to 0.15 mg/kg/day, followed by transition to oral prednisone (0.1 mg/kg/day). Over the next 3 months, liver lesions completely resolved despite the discontinuation of oral prednisone and antibiotics.</p></sec><sec><title>3. Case 3</title><p>A 14<sup>+6</sup>-year-old female with p22<sup><italic>phox</italic></sup>-deficient CGD was admitted with 4 days of fever, cough, nausea, chills and myalgias. She was diagnosed with CGD at 12 months of age and had experienced pneumonia, lymphadenitis, cellulitis, and osteomyelitis on several occasions. Her younger brother was also diagnosed with CGD shortly after the birth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Prophylactic TMP/SMX and IFN-&#x003b3; therapy had been voluntarily discontinued for more than 1 year before admission. Chest radiographs on admission showed pneumonic consolidation of the right upper lung field (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>), and inflammatory markers (ESR, 116 mm/hr; CRP, 159.7 mg/L) were elevated. She was initially treated with ampicillin/sulbactam and cefotaxime for pneumonia. Fever continued intermittently for 2 weeks. Ampicillin/sulbactam was stopped and vancomycin and amphotericin B were added to the treatment. However, after the new regimen was initiated, she was febrile for a further 1 week. Surveillance abdominal ultrasound identified three large lobulated cystic lesions in the right liver dome (7.7 cm) and left lateral (5.0 cm) and medial segment (2.8 cm) of the liver (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B, C</xref>). Inflammatory markers (ESR&#x0003e;120 mm/hr; CRP, 220.3 mg/L) were elevated. Two large abscesses in the dome and lateral segment of the liver were percutaneously drained, and intravenous methylprednisolone (1.0 mg/kg/day) was started. She gradually improved during the following 10 days. After 2 weeks of intravenous methylprednisolone, methylprednisolone was weaned over 2 weeks. However, at a dose of 0.25 mg/kg of methylprednisolone, fever recurred with increased inflammatory markers. Intravenous methylprednisolone (0.75 mg/kg/day) was restarted and more slowly weaned over 3 weeks to 0.25 mg/kg/day. Intravenous methylprednisolone were transitioned to oral prednisone (0.25 mg/kg/day) and she was discharged. Oral prednisone was tapered and stopped with the antibiotics over 3 months. Subsequent abdominal ultrasound performed 13 months after initial presentation showed complete resolution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>CGD is an inherited primary immunodeficiency resulting from defects in any one of the subunits of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2)</xref>. The NADPH oxidase complex is composed of 5 major subunits. Two of these, gp91<sup><italic>phox</italic></sup> and p22<sup><italic>phox</italic></sup>, are membrane-bound components encoded by the <italic>CYBB</italic> and <italic>CYBA</italic> genes, respectively. The remaining 3 components include p47phox, p67<sup><italic>phox</italic></sup>, and p40<sup><italic>phox</italic></sup>, encoded by the corresponding genes, <italic>NCF1</italic>, <italic>NCF2</italic>, and <italic>NCF4</italic><xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2)</xref>. The X-linked form of CGD is caused by mutations in CYBB, and accounts for approximately 70% of cases. The autosomal recessive forms are caused by mutations in <italic>CYBA</italic>, <italic>NCF1</italic>, and <italic>NCF2</italic>, accounting for approximately 5%, 20%, and 5% of cases, respectively<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9)</xref>. Only one case with a mutation in <italic>NCF4</italic> has been reported to date<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10)</xref>. The incidence of CGD is 3-4 per 1,000,000 individuals<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4)</xref>, and the prevalence of CGD in Korea is similar to that in other regions<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11)</xref>. On the other hand, the prevalence of CGD on Jeju Island is 20.7 per 1,000,000 individuals, which is 10&#x000d7;50 folds higher than in other regions of Korea<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12)</xref>. We hypothesized that the high prevalence of CGD on Jeju Island was associated with the same mutation inherited from a common proband, and we demonstrated that all the CGD patients on Jeju Island had an identical and homozygous mutation in the CYBA gene; c.7C&#x0003e;T in CYBA exon 1, and p.Q3X in p22<sup><italic>phox</italic></sup>.<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12)</xref> All patients with CGD on Jeju Island were presumed to be the A22<sup>0</sup> phenotype (where A indicates autosomal recessive, and the superscript 0 indicates a complete absence of the affected subunit)<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12)</xref>.</p><p>The majority of CGD patients with liver abscesses have prior histories, such as cases 1 and 2. With or without surgery, liver abscesses are relatively easily controlled, but commonly recur with a different organism<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13)</xref>. It is known from previous reports that a prior liver abscess is an important risk factor for recurrence<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref>. This may be because hepatic dysfunction with portal venopathy and nodular regenerative hyperplasia is strongly associated with liver abscesses in CGD patients<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14)</xref>. It is thought that liver regeneration or microvascular insults after repeated abscesses cause nodular regenerative hyperplasia and portal venopathy, and the altered hepatic architecture or blood flow results in subsequent infection<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13)</xref>. However, whether there is a cause-and-effect relationship between repeated abscesses and altered hepatic architecture or blood flow remains unclear.</p><p>Although liver abscess is a common manifestation of CGD, few reports describe the management of liver abscesses in patients with CGD. In the past, hepatic resection, evacuation of the exudate, external drainage, and long-term continuous antibiotic therapy has been recommended<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5)</xref>. The majority of cases used percutaneous aspiration of hepatic abscesses for isolation of the organism before use of antibiotics and surgical management. Since liver abscesses in patients with CGD are septated masses with a fibrous pseudo-capsule and thick condense fluid, most attempts at aspiration and drainage of hepatic abscesses are unsuccessful<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5)</xref>. In our cases, liver abscesses were aspirated and drains were placed percutaneously, but the amount of aspirate was minimal and drainage was unsuccessful. Rather, the percutaneous drain seemed to be a focus of the secondary liver infection. Lublin et al.<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5)</xref> recommended the administration of ceftriaxone and vancomycin with or without rifampin because <italic>S. aureus</italic> was the most common isolate from liver abscesses.</p><p>antimicrobial therapy, but it is difficult to identify the causative pathogen in the majority of clinical CGD cases. In our case, cultures from blood and aspirates of liver abscess were all negative. While treating liver abscesses refractory to proper antimicrobial coverage against potential pathogens, we used corticosteroids to improve symptoms and ameliorate aberrant inflammation. It has been shown that liver abscesses in patients with CGD can be treated with systemic corticosteroids in addition to antimicrobials<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref>.</p><p>Corticosteroids are commonly used to control granulomatous complications in patients with CGD, such as inflammatory gastrointestinal and genitourinary lesions<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3)</xref>. Corticosteroids have also been used in combination with antimicrobials to treat refractory infections in patients with CGD<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref>. Patients with CGD display signs of dysregulated inflammation, which is not only associated with deficient superoxide and related reactive oxygen intermediates. Although several mechanisms of chronic and hyperinflammation in CGD had been proposed, it cannot be fully explained at present. However, the hyperinflammation in CGD may be associated with the intracellular persistence of microorganisms and could inhibit the delivery of antimicrobials to the cells<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6)</xref>. Corticosteroids decrease the activation, proliferation, and differentiation of many cells involved in inflammation<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref>. In the case of refractory infections in patients with CGD, concomitant administration of corticosteroids with antimicrobials decreases the severe inflammatory response and thus seems to effectively manage the refractory infections.</p><p>Case 1 in this report showed multiple abscesses and progressive liver abscesses despite optimal antimicrobial coverage. Corticosteroids were started at a dose of 1 mg/kg daily and continued for 2 weeks before tapering off over several months. Although there was no uniform dose of corticosteroid, low or moderate anti-inflammatory doses (about 1 mg/kg per day of prednisone) are recommended<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref>. Because corticosteroids are capable of suppressing symptomatic inflammation, all potential infections must be adequately covered prior to corticosteroid initiation. Use of corticosteroid without optimal antimicrobial coverage can have negative consequences in CGD<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15)</xref>.</p><p>As seen in case 3, rapid tapering of corticosteroid may be associated with exacerbation of inflammation and liver abscesses. Because long-term use of corticosteroids may cause opportunistic infections and have metabolic effects, the appropriate duration of tapering from our experience was not more than 3 months. The necessity of intravenous antimicrobials is also unclear, but the concomitant use of corticosteroid with antimicrobials is reasonable and safe for unexpected infections.</p><p>It remains unclear whether the corticosteroid therapy is helpful or required for liver abscesses refractory to conventional treatments. Moreover, there was no uniform regimen for corticosteroids therapy, such as dosage, duration, duration of tapering, the necessity for coadministration of antimicrobials, and the comparative advantages over surgical treatment. Controlled prospective studies are needed to determine the safety and proper regimen for corticosteroid therapy in CGD.</p><p>In conclusion, we report three typical cases of CGD with liver abscesses refractory to conventional treatments that were successfully treated with the concomitant use of corticosteroids and antimicrobials. Based on our observations, concomitant use of corticosteroids in combination with optimal antimicrobials should be considered for refractory liver abscesses in CGD.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>This research was supported by the 2014 scientific promotion program funded by Jeju National University.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Veys</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Malech</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic granulomatous disease: lessons from a rare disorder</article-title><source>Biol Blood Marrow Transplant</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>s123</fpage><lpage>s131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21195301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heyworth</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Curnutte</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic granulomatous disease</article-title><source>Curr Opin Immunol</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14499268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winkelstein</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>RB</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Curnutte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallin</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chronic granulomatous disease. Report on a national registry of 368 patients</article-title><source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source><year>2000</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10844935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van den Berg</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>van Koppen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahlin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Belohradsky</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernatowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbeel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chronic granulomatous disease: the European experience</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e5234</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19381301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lublin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Danforth</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kauffman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallin</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Malech</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatic abscess in patients with chronic granulomatous disease</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source><year>2002</year><volume>235</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11882760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamazaki-Nakashimada</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiehm</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietropaolo-Cienfuegos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez-Bautista</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Espinosa-Rosales</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corticosteroid therapy for refractory infections in chronic granulomatous disease: case reports and review of the literature</article-title><source>Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol</source><year>2006</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16937761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leiding</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Marciano</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Uzel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Malech</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Corticosteroid therapy for liver abscess in chronic granulomatous disease</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>694</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22157170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhns</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Maddalena</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roesler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ariga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hematologically important mutations: X-linked chronic granulomatous disease (third update)</article-title><source>Blood Cells Mol Dis</source><year>2010</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20729109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhns</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Maddalena</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kannengiesser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hematologically important mutations: the autosomal recessive forms of chronic granulomatous disease (second update)</article-title><source>Blood Cells Mol Dis</source><year>2010</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20167518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matute</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Arias</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wrobel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A new genetic subgroup of chronic granulomatous disease with autosomal recessive mutations in p40 phox and selective defects in neutrophil NADPH oxidase activity</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2009</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>3309</fpage><lpage>3315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19692703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhim</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of primary immunodeficiency in Korea</article-title><source>J Korean Med Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>788</fpage><lpage>793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22787376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of 10 unrelated Korean families with p22-phox-deficient chronic granulomatous disease: an unusually identical mutation of the CYBA gene on Jeju Island, Korea</article-title><source>J Korean Med Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1045</fpage><lpage>1050</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19949658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic granulomatous disease</article-title><source>Hematol Oncol Clin North Am</source><year>2013</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23351990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Feld</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleiner</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoofnagle</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Eulate</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahlawat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatic abnormalities in patients with chronic granulomatous disease</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17326162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Marciano</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Uzel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Costas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corticosteroids in the treatment of severe nocardia pneumonia in chronic granulomatous disease</article-title><source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source><year>2011</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>806</fpage><lpage>808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21412179</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Case pedigrees: (A) pedigree of case 1, (B) pedigree of case 2, and (C) pedigree of case 3. <sup>*</sup>Not analyzed.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjped-59-196-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Computed tomography (CT) and abdominal ultrasound for case 1. The coronal view on enhanced CT shows multiple abscesses in the right lobe of the liver, with 2 large abscesses in the dome (5 cm&#x000d7;4.5 cm, black arrowheads, (A) and inferior portion (4 cm&#x000d7;2.5 cm, black arrowheads, (B) of the liver. (C) The abdominal ultrasound image obtained 5 months after initial presentation shows a reduction in size (3.5 cm) of the liver dome.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjped-59-196-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Chest radiography and abdominal ultrasound for case 3. (A) Chest radiograph on admission shows a pneumonic consolidation (white arrowheads) in the right upper lung field black. (B, C) Abdominal ultrasound shows 3 large lobulated cystic lesions in the right liver dome and left lateral and medial segments of liver. (D) Abdominal ultrasound obtained 13 months after initial presentation shows complete resolution.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="kjped-59-196-g003"/></fig></floats-group></article>