<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Gastroenterol Hepatol Bed Bench</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Gastroenterol Hepatol Bed Bench</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GHFBB</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Gastroenterology and Hepatology From Bed to Bench</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2008-2258</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2008-4234</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Research Institute for Gastroenterology and Liver Diseases</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24834283</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4017532</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">GHFBB-6-S019</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Metabonomics exposes metabolic biomarkers of Crohn's disease by <sup>1</sup>HNMR</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fathi</surname><given-names>Fariba</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ektefa</surname><given-names>Fatemeh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hagh-Azali</surname><given-names>Mehrdad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Aghdaie</surname><given-names>Hamid Asadzadeh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Department of Chemistry, Sharif University of Technology, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>Department of Chemistry, Tarbiat Modares University, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>Gastroenterology and Liver Diseases Research Center, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="AF0004"><label>4</label>Basic and Molecular Epidemiology of Gastroenterology Disorder Research Center, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Reprint or Correspondence:</bold> Hamid Asadzadeh Aghdaie MD., Basic and Molecular Epidemiology of Gastroenterology Disorder Research Center, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran. <bold>E-mail:</bold><email xlink:href="hamid.asadzadeh@gmail.com">hamid.asadzadeh@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>S19</fpage><lpage>S22</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2013 Research Institute for Gastroenterology and Liver Diseases</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License which allows users to read, copy, distribute and make derivative works for non-commercial purposes from the material, as long as the author of the original work is cited properly.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Metabonomics and other &#x0201c;omics&#x0201d; fields are essential science in analytical chemistry. Modern analytical instruments such as proton nuclear magnetic resonance (<sup>1</sup>H NMR) can be provided the great quantity of analytical information. In order to assign unknown samples, chemometrics methods recognition build classification model based on experimental data. Firstly some current strategies for regarding disease diagnosis are exhibited in metabonomics studies. Some disease such as crohn's disease can be difficult to diagnosis since its signs and symptoms may be similar to other medical problems or often mimic other symptoms. Applications of NMR and supervised pattern recognition in the field of metabonomics are also reviewed in recent years. The aim of present study was to review the assessment of <sup>1</sup>HNMR to investigate a metabolic profile of crohn's disease.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Metabonomics</kwd><kwd><sup>1</sup>HNMR</kwd><kwd>Crohn disease</kwd><kwd>Chemometrics</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><p><bold>(</bold>Please cite as: <bold>Fathi F, Ektefa F, Hagh-Azali M, Asadzadeh Aghdaie H. Metabonomics exposes metabolic biomarkers of Crohn&#x02019;s disease by <sup>1</sup>HNMR. Gastroenterol Hepatol Bed Bench 2013;6(Suppl.1):S19-S22).</bold></p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>A revolution has created in the practice of biological research in the last decade (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). These changes can develop of techniques that are valuable to profile levels of molecular organization at body. &#x02018;Omics&#x02019; informally refers to this wide coverage of techniques that can perform metabolic profiling studies such as metabonomics or metabolomics (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). In this viewpoint, there is a particular emphasis on how the levels of metabolites change in response to pathophysiological stimuli or genetic modification in living systems because of many molecules with small molecular weight involved in metabolism (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis are the two main types of chronic inflammatory bowel disease. Crohn's disease is called regional enteritis that affects the gastrointestinal tract. The disorder usually affects the colon and rectum, however, may influence in each area of the mouth to the anus. In some cases the correct diagnosis of crohn's disease may be difficult because this disease often imitates other symptoms. To make correct diagnosis in many areas, metabonomics field is to achieve improvements in understanding of metabolic processes that occur while a person is suffering from a disease (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). There are several available methods for metabolite profiling. One of them is proton nuclear magnetic resonance (<sup>1</sup>H-NMR) that has been utilized as an analytical tool in studies of metabolism for many years (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). NMR spectroscopy technique is non-selective in the analytical studied and obtained vital information in a short time. Also it is non-destructive and highly reproducible with minimal sample preparation.</p><p>Statistical modeling in metabolic profiling has goals; one of them is to visualize the overall similarities and differences between samples and variables. The main focus in this review is to provide general knowledge of data preprocessing in <sup>1</sup>HNMR approach and the use of chemometrics techniques. For reach to this purpose, we have focused on studies on crohn's disease using a metabonomics.</p></sec><sec id="S0002"><title>Sample and data preprocessing</title><p>To convert the NMR data into a form that can be useable in statistical procedures firstly the FIDs -already have been fourier transformed to the frequency domain- manually phased and baseline-corrected applying XWINNMR or other software(<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Then the NMR data are usually transformed into a matrix in which a sample and a metabolic signal pertain to a row and a column, respectively. The spectral intensity at a particular chemical shift corresponds to the estimated level of a particular metabolite. The Carr&#x02013;Pucell&#x02013;Meiboom&#x02013;Gill (CPMG) spin-echo pulse sequence, &#x003c0;/2-t<sub>D</sub>-&#x003c0;-t<sub>D</sub>, was used for serum samples (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). CPMG experiment can enhances visualization of the low molecular weight metabolites and to suppress the broad signal from the protein (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Spectral regions within the range of 0.2 to 10 ppm were used after deleting the region containing residual water and urea signals (4.5 to 6.0 ppm) (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Biological fluids such as serum, plasma and urine have been used for studies of crohn's disease. Serum and plasma are the most common fluids in metabonomics surveys. These samples are also relatively easy to obtain.</p><p>The human metabolome database (HMDB) is a freely available electronic database containing detailed information about metabolites found in the body. Urine is one of the simplest fluids physical that frequently used as a bio-fluid for human and animal metabolic studies. Schicho and co-authors performed quantitative metabolomic profiling of serum, plasma and urine by <sup>1</sup>HNMR spectroscopy on patients with inflammatory bowel disease (crohn's disease and active ulcerative colitis) (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). In other survey, Stephens et al. highlighted the potential for metabolomics to distinguish inflammatory bowel disease from the healthy state in urine sample (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). They build a metabolic profile applying NMR spectroscopy to distinguish patients with inflammatory bowel disease from healthy individuals (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Fathi and colleagues reveal new differentiating metabolites for crohn's disease by examining on serum of Iranian samples (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Murdoch and colleagues correlated the progress of inflammatory bowel disease with specific changes in a mouse urinary metabolic fingerprint applying metabolomics (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Marchesi and colleagues displayed the first classification of fecal extracts acquired from patients with ulcerative colitis and crohn's disease using a metabonomics technique. This approach combines multivariate pattern recognition analysis and high resolution <sup>1</sup>HNMR spectroscopy (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S0003"><title>Scaling in metabonomics</title><p>In some researches, for each samples 4,4-dimethyl-4-silapentane-1-sulfonic acid (DSS) was added as internal reference substance (<italic>&#x003b4; = 0 ppm</italic>). Also peak of the lactate methyl doublet (&#x003b4; = 1.33 ppm) or other metabolites are referenced within XWINNMR for spectra (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Scaling is a column- each spectral intensity across all samples- operation that including mean center, auto scaling, pareto scaling etc. Mean centering includes subtracting the column mean from each value in the column and given a mean of zero. Second scaling is auto scaling also called unit or unit variance scaling; in which each value in the column is divided by the standard deviation of the column (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Pareto scaling is other forms of scaling that is very similar to auto scaling. Here, each variable is divided by the square root of the standard deviation of the column (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p><p>Rezaei-Tavirani et al. stated that preprocessing the spectroscopic data is essential (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). They showed scaling effects in metabonomics investigation of patients diagnosed with crohn's disease by applying two techniques of scaling including: mean centering and auto scaling (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Results of recent study reveal that the mean centering is more useful to segregate patients from healthy subjects in the data set of crohn's disease. They showed that the mean centering option is more effective at eliminating correlation from the principal component analysis (PCA) residuals than the auto scaling in this situation. In survey of Fathi et al. the data were scaled to pareto scaling preceding multivariate analysis (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>).</p><p>Regarding the published studies in this field, it can be suggested that the goal of scaling is to regulate for the distinctions in fold differences between the different metabolites and improving their biological interpretability.</p></sec><sec id="S0004"><title>Classification methods</title><p>Classification methods are widely used in order to diagnosis crohn's disease from healthy subjects and to seek the metabolic biomarkers causes of crohn's disease compare to control group. Methods applied in crohn's literatures include the following: classification and regression tree (CART) and orthogonal projections to latent structures discriminated analysis (OPLS-DA).</p><p>Breiman et al. in 1984 develop CART as non-parametric statistical technique (<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). This method is able both classification and regression. A decision tree is built in both cases and describes a response <italic>Y</italic> by selecting some independent variables <italic>X</italic> from a larger set of <italic>X</italic> values. Fathi and colleagues utilized CART in order to classification of crohn's disease and healthy subjects (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). They obtained classification model showed 89% correct classification of crohn's disease and healthy subject for the external test set. According to CART diagram, they concluded that just using one descriptor (lipid) crohn's disease and control group could be classified separately. Based on CART diagram, lipid level reduces in blood serum of patients compared to healthy individuals. The parameters of classification in last research showed that CART classification model has great chance in diagnosis of crohn's disease.</p><p>OPLS-DA as regression technique is frequently used for classification method (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Using this method, those metabolites which show a discrepancy between diagnostic groups can be identified. In order to divide the systematic variation into two model parts in the metabolite levels, OPLS-DA is used (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). These two parts are including co-variation between metabolite levels and the class of each sample and captures systematic variation in metabolite levels orthogonal to the class of each sample (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>).</p><p>Schicho et al. used hierarchical OPLS-DA for comparing several blocks derived from the same subject to examine differences in metabolites. Based on recent research, methanol, mannose, formate, 3-methyl-2-oxovalerate, and amino acids increased in serum and plasma and mannitol, allantoin, xylose, and carnitine increase in urine of IBD patients (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Quantitative metabolomic profiling of serum, plasma and urine discriminated healthy subjects and IBD patients. However, they showed that the metabolic differences between the ulcerative colitis and crohn's disease cohorts are less pronounced (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Stephens et al. performed OPLS-DA in order to examine which metabolites were contributing to the separation crohn's disease and healthy cohorts (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). In this study IBD patients could be differentiated from healthy according to urinary metabolomics. TCA cycle intermediates, amino acids and gut microflora metabolites have main differences between inflammatory bowel disease patients and healthy cohorts. (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S0005"><title>Conclusions and future prospects</title><p>In this review, we evaluated the use of classification method to build an easily interpretable predictive model to distinguish between crohn's disease and healthy controls. It is clear that statistical model and bioinformatics methods are valuable in metabonomics investigation. The aim of these &#x0201c;omics&#x0201d; science is to enable the maximum useful information to be gleaned from this rich and complex data. We suggest using metabonomics to identify other patients in the future.</p><p>References</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebbels</surname><given-names>TMD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioinformatic methods in NMR-based metabolic profiling</article-title><source>Prog Nucl Magn Reson Spectrosc</source><year>2009</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>74</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbruzzesse</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs in plasma of pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma patients as novel blood-based biomarkers of disease</article-title><source>Cancer Prev Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fathi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tafazzoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehrpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahidi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study of metabolic profiling Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>HealthMED</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes.</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabonomics&#x02019;: understanding the metabolic responses of living systems to pathophysiological stimuli via multivariate statistical analysis of biological NMR spectroscopic data</article-title><source>Xenobiotica</source><year>1999</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1181</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10598751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>German</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammock</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolomics: Building on a century of biochemistry to guide human health</article-title><source>Metabolomics</source><year>2005</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16680201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>M-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>Y-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>C-S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Metabonomic Understanding of Probiotic Effects in Humans With Irritable Bowel Syndrome</article-title><source>J Clin Gastroenterol</source><year>2011</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21494186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bezabeh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Somorjai</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>ICP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MR metabolomics of fecal extracts:applications in the study of bowel diseases</article-title><source>Magn Reson Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>61</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gall</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Noor</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ridgway</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Scovell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Metabolomics of Fecal Extracts Detects Altered Metabolic Activity of Gut Microbiota in Ulcerative Colitis and Irritable Bowel Syndrome</article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>4208</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21761941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Claridge TDW</collab><source>High-resolution NMR techniques in organic chemistry</source><year>1999</year><publisher-name>Elsevier Sciences Ltd</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehrpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tafazzoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fathi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Joghataie</surname><given-names>M-T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A metabonomics investigation of multiple sclerosis by nuclear magnetic resonance</article-title><source>Magn Reson Chem</source><year>2013</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23255426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schicho</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaykhutdinov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazyrova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Panaccione</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantitative Metabolomic Profiling of Serum, Plasma, and Urine by 1H NMR Spectroscopy Discriminates between Patients with Inflammatory Bowel Disease and Healthy Individuals</article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>3344</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22574726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Siffledeen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Murdoch</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedorak</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Slupsky</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Urinary NMR metabolomic profiles discriminate inflammatory bowel disease from healthy</article-title><source>J Crohns Colitis</source><year>2012</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fathi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nejad</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezaye-Tavirani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Naderi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zali</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A metabonomics study on Crohn's Disease using Nuclear Magnetic Resonance spectroscopy</article-title><source>HealthMED</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>3577</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murdoch</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>MacFarlane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sydora</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedorak</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Slupsky</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Urinary metabolic profiles of inflammatory bowel disease in interleukin-10 gene-deficient mice</article-title><source>Anal Chem.</source><year>2008</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>5524</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18558774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchesi</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kochhar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scanlan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanahan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rapid and Noninvasive Metabonomic Characterization of Inflammatory Bowel Disease</article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>546</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17269711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fathi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Darvizeh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehrpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tafazzoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahidi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship Between Serum Level of Selenium and Metabolites Using 1 HNMR-Based Metabonomics in Parkinson's Disease</article-title><source>Appl Magn Reson</source><year>2013</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cloarec</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindon</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scaling and Normalization Effects in NMR Spectroscopic Metabonomic Data Sets</article-title><source>Anal Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>2262</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16579606</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kettaneh-Wold</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scaling</article-title><source>Introduction to multi- and megavariate data analysis using projection methods (PCA &#x00026; PLS) Umetrics</source><year>1999</year><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rezaei-Tavirani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fathi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Darvizeh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zali</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rostami Nejad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rostami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Advantage of Applying OSC to 1H NMR-Based Metabonomic Data of Celiac Disease</article-title><source>Int J Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2012</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23843818</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breiman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Olshen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification and Regression Trees</article-title><year>1984</year><publisher-name>Chapman &#x00026;Hall</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trygg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundstedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemometrics in metabolomics</article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17269704</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>