<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Caring Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Caring Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">J Caring Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">JCS</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TBZMED</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Caring Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2251-9920</issn><issn-l>2251-9920</issn-l><publisher><publisher-name>Tabriz University of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27354976</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4923836</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15171/jcs.2016.013</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Is Nurses' Professional Competence Related to Their Personality and Emotional
Intelligence? A Cross-Sectional Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heydari</surname><given-names>Abbas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A01">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kareshki</surname><given-names>Hossein</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A02">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Armat</surname><given-names>Mohammad Reza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A03">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="COR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A01"><sup>1</sup> Evidence-Based Caring Research Center, Department of Medical-Surgical Nursing,
School of Nursing and Midwifery, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran</aff><aff id="A02"><sup>2</sup>Department of Educational Psychology, Ferdowsi University of Mashhad, Iran</aff><aff id="A03"><sup>3</sup>Department of Medical- Surgical Nursing, School of Nursing and Midwifery,
Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>Corresponding Author: Mohammad Reza Armat (PhD),
email:<email>rezaarmat@yahoo.com</email>. This study was approved and funded by the
deputy of research of Mashhad University of Medical Sciences (Project number: 930631).
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 by The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" license-type="open-access"><license-p>This work is published by Journal of Caring Sciences as an open access article
distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License
(<uri xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</uri>). Non-commercial uses of
the work are permitted, provided the original work is properly cited. </license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://journals.tbzmed.ac.ir/JCS">http:// journals.tbzmed.ac.ir/
JCS</self-uri><abstract><p>
<bold><italic>Introduction:</italic></bold> Nurses' professional competence is a crucial
factor in clinical practice. Systematic evaluation of nurses&#x02019; competence and its related
factors are essential for enhancing the quality of nursing care. This study aimed to
assess the nurses&#x02019; competence level and its possible relationship with their personality
and emotional intelligence. </p><p><bold><italic>Methods:</italic></bold> Using a cross-sectional survey design, three
instruments including Nurse Competence Scale, short form of Schutte Self Report Emotional
Intelligence Test, and the short 10-item version of Big Five Factor Inventory, were
administered simultaneously to a randomized stratified sample of 220 nurses working in
hospitals affiliated to Mashhad University of Medical Sciences. Data analysis was
performed using SPSS 11.5.</p><p><bold><italic>Results:</italic></bold> Majority of nurses rated themselves as "good" and
"very good", with the highest scores in "managing situations" and "work role" dimensions
of nurse competence. A relatively similar pattern of scores was seen in competence
dimensions, personality and emotional intelligence, among male and female nurses.
Emotional intelligence and personality scores showed a significant relationship with
nurses&#x02019; competence, explaining almost 20% of variations in nurse competence scores.</p><p><bold><italic>Conclusion:</italic></bold> Iranian nurses evaluated their overall
professional competence at similar level of the nurses in other countries. Knowledge about
the nurses&#x02019; competence level and its related factors, including personality and emotional
intelligence, may help nurse managers in enhancing nurses' professional competence through
appropriate task assignments and conducting in-service educational programs, thus
improving the health status of patients.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Competence</kwd><kwd>Personality</kwd><kwd>Emotional intelligence</kwd><kwd>Nurse</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="3"/><ref-count count="42"/><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta><notes><p> Please cite this paper as: Heydari A, Kareshki H, Armat MR. Is nurses' professional
competence related to their personality and emotional intelligence? a cross-sectional study.
J Caring Sci 2016; 5 (2): 121-31. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.15171/jcs.2016.013">
10.15171/jcs.2016.013</ext-link>.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p> Nursing competency has been extensively addressed in literature in terms of safety and
quality of nursing care, though still lacks worldwide consensus in definition.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> WHO has described it as a framework of skills
portraying knowledge, attitudes and psychosocial and psychomotor components.<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> It is more comprehensively defined as the
capability of nurse in demonstrating a set of attributes including personal characteristics,
knowledge, attitudes, values, and skills needed to accomplish nursing professional
responsibilities.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p><p> Acquiring essential competencies by nurses is believed to be crucial for the quality of
nursing practice.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> The competence level of
nurses directly influences the patients' safety, health status, morbidity and
mortality,<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> as well as satisfaction
with nursing care and conflict managements.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Nurses' poor competency may lead
to some undesirable consequences including nurses' frustration, job
dissatisfaction,<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> and their
attrition.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Therefore, systematically
measuring of nurses&#x02019; competence is essential for management and education in nursing
profession, giving a better insight to nurse educators and managers, and helpin them to
enhance the nursing care quality.<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p><p> Nurse competence may be associated with some personal attributes, such as emotional
intelligence (EI) and personality traits.<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Recently, the EI and
personality characteristics have received considerable attention in health care
professions.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Some authors argue that emotional intelligence is even more
important than intelligence quotient (IQ) in achieving positive outcomes regarding patients
and nurses.<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup></p><p> Salovey and Mayer defined EI as the &#x0201c;ability to monitor one&#x02019;s own and others feelings and
emotions, to discriminate among them and using this information to guide one&#x02019;s thinking and
actions&#x0201d;.<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Emotions, according to
Salovey and Grewal, are &#x0201c;useful sources of information that help individuals to make sense
of and navigate the social environment&#x0201d;.<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>
Nurses need the ability to make good rapport with their clients, show empathy with patients,
and manage their own emotions in order to provide quality care.</p><p> Thus skills in emotional intelligence may help them to better understand the emotional
ambience of the healthcare environments. During work, nurses are expected to make critical
decisions in life-and-death situations based on all available data, including data achieved
from emotions. Therefore, improved decision making and problem solving linked to the
emotional intelligence, makes it as a characteristic of effective nursing performance and
outcomes.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Although, emotions are
fundamental to nursing practice and potentially affects all aspects of working situation in
commonly stressful and emotionally charged health care settings,<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> still there is a
limited or contradictory evidence in this area.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup></p><p> Personality is shaped through the interaction with the environment, and its determinants
are related to genetic-physiological, as well as socio-cultural factors.<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> As an influential factor, personality is
suggested to be considered in nursing profession.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> However, there is a controversial evidence about the relationship of
personality and job performance.<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>-<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> For example, Chang et al., showed that the
personality can predict nurses&#x02019; job satisfaction, and enhances the positive career outcome.
They suggest that it has significant implications for nurses and healthcare
managers.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Also, Shimizutan et al.,
suggested a relationship between personality type and burnout.<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> However, Whitworth<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> reported no significant correlation between female registered nurses&#x02019;
personality factors and their methods of conflict management.</p><p> Despite the important role of nurse competence in clinical practice, and its related
factors, few studies have been conducted to investigate it&#x02019;s the relationship of nurses'
competence with their personality and emotional intelligence.<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>-<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Understanding of
this relationships may help nurse managers to adopt appropriate strategies to achieve very
important outcomes such as nurses&#x02019; better performance, job satisfaction, and conflict
managements.&#x0200f;</p><p> This study aimed to examine the competence level of clinical practicing nurses and its
possible relationship with their personality traits and emotional intelligence.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><p> A cross-sectional survey design was adopted to study the population of nurses working in
clinical wards of teaching hospitals, affiliated to Mashhad University of Medical Sciences,
Mashhad, Iran. The target population was nurses with baccalaureate degree in nursing
(N&#x02248;3000). Because of possible heterogeneity of work places, a randomized stratified
sample of nurses was selected from 11 teaching hospitals comprising 140 clinical wards. The
sample size was estimated using the Cochran's sample size formula
(n=&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>*&#x00396;<sup>2</sup>/e<sup>2</sup>). We used an average standard
deviation (SD=11.01) for nurse competence scores estimated from a pilot study, and the
values reported in previous studies conducted in Iran.<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>-<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> The confidence level was set
to 95% (a &#x0003c;0.05, Z=1.96), and error of estimation (e) to 1.5. The calculated sample size
was 207 nurses, but we selected 220 nurses because of possible attrition. Inclusion criteria
was having at least one year clinical work experience, and working as a clinical nurse in
one of university affiliated hospitals.</p><p> We used self-report questionnaires in paper and pencil form, including the Persian
translated versions of Meretoja's Nurse Competence Scale (NCS);<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> the short form of
Schutte Self Report Emotional Intelligence Test (SSEIT),<sup><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> the abbreviated 10-item version of Big Five Factor Inventory
(BFI-10),<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>-<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> as well as a questionnaire for demographic and background variables. To
reduce the risk of fatigue, boredom and burden, thus increasing the quality of the data, we
used short forms of instruments to measure EI and personality. The instruments underwent the
processes of translation from English to Persian and back-translation. We consulted with the
experts regarding the face and content validity of the Persian versions of the instruments.
Also, we tested the instruments using a sample of 30 nurses in a pilot study. Few minor
changes were made in wording of some items according to the feedback received from experts
and nurses.</p><p> Demographic data included participants' gender, age, educational level, and number of
years working as a nurse.</p><p> This scale was originally developed for practicing nurses based on Benner's competency
framework,<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> but it also showed
validity in measuring nurses' as well as nurse students&#x02019; competencies.<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> The
Persian version of this scale has also been adapted and used within the context of Iranian
hospitals.<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>-<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup></p><p> NCS has 73 items, and seven dimensions: helping role (7 items), teaching-coaching (16
items), diagnostic functions (7 items), managing situations (8 items), therapeutic
interventions (10 items), ensuring quality (6 items), and work role (19 items). Nurses rated
their competence level on each item, using a visual analogue scale (VAS), from 0 (very low),
to 100 (very high). The total competence score was calculated by adding up the whole item
scores and dividing the sum by 73. Subscale scores were calculated by dividing the sum of
item scores in each dimension by the number of items within that dimension. Finally, the
scores were categorized into four levels, as low (0&#x02013;25), quite good (25&#x02013;50), good (50&#x02013;75)
and very good (75&#x02013;100).</p><p> The frequency of using each skill by nurses during their clinical practice, were also
measured on a four point scale (0, not applicable in my work; 1, used very seldom; 2, used
occasionally; and 3, used very often in my work).</p><p> The Cronbach alpha in the present study was 0.987 for the whole NCS, and ranged from 0.897
to 0.962 for its subscales. Split-half reliability for equal forms was estimated as 0.935,
using Spearman-Brown Coefficient.</p><sec id="s2-1"><title> The abbreviated 10-item version of Big Five Factor Inventory (BFI-10)</title><p> This scale includes 10 items for personality traits assessment based on Big Five Factor
Model<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> with adequate psychometric
properties, introduced and cross-culturally tested by Rammstedt<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> Original BFI-10 showed acceptable discriminant, convergent,
and external validity, as well as test-retest reliability.<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> The Persian translated version of this scale has been used
by two studies in Iran, reporting acceptable validity (convergent validity for the whole
scale .67) and reliability (test-retest reliability .68 to .84),<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> confirming the existence of Five Factors<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> in the original version.</p><p> The core aspects of a Big Five dimensions were assessed by a pair of short items
(Extraversion 1 and 6; Agreeableness 2 and 7; Conscientiousness 3 and 8; Neuroticism 4 and
9; and Openness 5 and 10), while one item indicated the positive pole in the dimension,
and the other denoted the negative pole. Items were rated from 1 for "strongly disagree"
to 5 for "strongly agree". A common stem, "I see myself as someone who:" was used for all
items. Item 1 in Extraversion; 7 in Agreeableness; 3 in Conscientiousness; 4 in
Neuroticism; and 5 in Openness was scored in reverse.<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> After reversing the &#x0201c;Neuroticism&#x0201d; scores, we added up the scores of
all items, and subscale items, to calculate the total scale score and subscale scores,
respectively. The total score could range from 10 to 50.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title> Schutte Self Report Emotional Intelligence Test (SSEIT-33) </title><p> The scale has been originally developed by Schutte et al.,<sup><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> based on the trait model of emotional intelligence
introduced by Salovey and Mayer<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>. A few
studies have examined the factor structure of SSEIT-33. We considered the Kun et al.,
study because we found it more clear and conclusive than others. She suggested three
factors for the scale, including: &#x0201c;Appraisal of Emotions&#x0201d; (10 items), &#x0201c;Optimism and
Regulation of Emotions&#x0201d; (7 items), and &#x0201c;Intrapersonal and Interpersonal Utilization of
Emotions&#x0201d; (7 items). Nine items has been left uncategorized.<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> The original scale shows good internal consistency (alpha =
0.87) and test-retest reliability (r = 0.78). The correlation of the scale with the
related constructs (regulation of emotions, impulsivity, and awareness of emotion,
depressed mood, and outlook on life) supports its validity. The Persian version of the
scale has been evaluated and used in Iran, showing to be valid and reliable.<sup><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup></p><p> Participants answered the items on a 5-point Likert scale, which 1 denoted &#x0201c;strongly
disagree&#x0201d; and 5 implied &#x0201c;strongly agree&#x0201d;; to describe themselves. The items 5, 28 and 33
were reversely scored. The total score was calculated by summing up all item scores, that
could range from 33 to 165, with the higher scores indicate to greater ability in
emotional intelligence, and vice versa. Also, subscale scores were calculated by adding up
item scores within each dimension. In this study, the Cronbach alpha for the whole scale
was 0.911. Using Spearman-Brown coefficient, the equal length split-half reliability was
estimated as 0.879.</p><p> Data were collected during September and October 2014. The researcher visited the
selected nurses at their work place. After introducing the purpose of the research,
receiving consent, and giving necessary instruction, nurses participated in the study and
filled the questionnaires.</p><p> Data analysis was performed using SPSS 11.5 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, USA) software. To
summarize the data, we used frequency distribution, mean, range and standard deviation. In
all statistical tests, the significance level was set to 0.05 (two tailed).</p><p> To examine the relationship between nurses' competence levels, as dependent variable,
and other factors such as background variables, SSEIT-33 and BFI-10 scores, as independent
variables, Spearman's rank correlation coefficient and multiple linear regression analyses
were used. We excluded participants who left more than 50% of subscale items with no
answer.</p><p> This study was approved by Ethical Committee of Mashhad University of Medical Sciences,
Iran (ethical code: 243451-2014/8/20). We obtained written approval from authors of the
original instruments used in this study. All the participants were given written and
verbal description of study, and their anonymity and confidentiality throughout the study
were guaranteed. Participation in the study was voluntary, and returning the
questionnaires was considered as informed consent.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p> A total of 204 questionnaires (response rate: 92.7%) were returned. Of them, 173
questionnaires without missing responses in the NCS and its sub-scales were used in the
analyses. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref> represent nurses&#x02019; descriptive variables. </p><sec id="s3-1"><title>Nurses' self-assessed competence level</title><p> The total score of clinical competence of nurses&#x02019; ranged from 35 to 100 (n=173). The
mean of nurses&#x02019; competence scores was 75.16 (SD=13.15; SE=1.00). Majority of nurses rated
themselves as &#x0201c;good&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;very good&#x0201d;. As seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure
1</xref>, score variations in dimensions of nursing skills represent a similar pattern
among male and female nurses.</p><p> Highest scores belong to &#x0201c;managing situation&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;work role&#x0201d; both in male and female
nurses, while lowest scores in male nurses pertain to &#x0201c;ensuring quality&#x0201d; and
&#x0201c;teaching-coaching&#x0201d; skills, and in female nurses to &#x0201c;ensuring quality&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;therapeutic
interventions&#x0201d;. The overall frequencies of the skills "used occasionally" and "used often"
by nurses, were 74.0% for helping roles, 70.3% for teaching-coaching, 71.0% for diagnostic
functions, 88.7% for managing situations, 68.4% for therapeutic interventions, 60.2% for
ensuring quality, and 74.9% for work role. Mean reported score for frequency of using the
skills, ranged from 2.99 for "ensuring quality", to 3.46 for "managing situations"
categories.</p><p> A linear positive correlations were observed between the frequencies with which the
skills used by nurses and their competence scores in all categories. The Pearson
correlation coefficient between these variables showed a moderate to strong values of
0.714 (helping role), 0.696 (teaching-coaching), 0.671 (diagnostic functions), 0.678
(managing situations), 0.654 (therapeutic interventions), 0.659 (ensuring quality), and
0.646 (work role), all were statistically significance at 95% confidence level
(P&#x0003c;0.001).</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Background factors in relation to the nurse competence levels</title><p> No statistically significant correlation was found between age and the NCS overall
scores as well as its sub-scores (r=0.140, P=0.073). NCS overall scores were not
significantly different between male and female (t=1.223, P=0.223), as well as single and
married nurses (t=0.840, P=0.076). Also, variables including years of working experience,
residence place (city, countryside), type of university (public, private), high school and
university GPAs, showed no significant association with NCS scores and its sub-scores
(P&#x0003c;0.05).</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Personality and Emotional Intelligence</title><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>
show a similar pattern in scores of personality and EI dimensions between male and female
nurses. The overall mean for total personality scores was 35.82 (4.167). Maximum and
minimum scores belonged to the dimensions of conscientiousness and neuroticism,
respectively. Female nurses rated their personality slightly higher than their male
counterparts in all dimensions, except &#x0201c;openness to experiences&#x0201d;, though this difference
was not statistically significant, neither in total scores (P=0.471), nor in sub-scores
(P=0.527).</p><p> The overall mean for total EI scores was 98.18 (9.277). The highest and lowest scores
belonged to the dimensions of &#x0201c;appraisal of emotions&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;intrapersonal and
interpersonal utilization of emotions&#x0201d;, respectively both in male and female nurses.
Again, female nurses retained their slight dominance in terms of their EI scores as
compared to male nurses; but here, this dominancy were statistically significant in the
total EI score (P=0.032) and sub-score of &#x0201c;intrapersonal and interpersonal utilization of
emotions&#x0201d; (P=0.010), according to Mann-Whitney U test.</p><p> Using Spearman's rank correlation coefficient, NCP overall scores showed modest to
moderate positive correlations with both the total personality scores (r=0.297,
P&#x0003c;0.001), and total EI scores (r=0.488, P&#x0003c;0.001). Accordingly, multiple linear
regression analyses were adopted to examine the association of EI and personality traits
as independent variables, with NCS overall scores, as dependent variables. Using the Enter
method, we included the total personality and EI scores in the model, and set the
probability of F value to 0.05 and 0.1 for entry and removal of variables in the model,
respectively. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref> shows a regression model in
which the nurses&#x02019; total personality and EI scores can significantly predict their NCS
overall scores (P&#x0003c;0.001). The model produced an R<sup>2</sup> value of 0.215
(SE=11.700), explaining almost 20% of total variance in NCS overall scores. According to
standardized Beta values, EI showed a stronger correlation with nurse competence and had
more weight in predicting NCS overall scores, as compared to personality scores.
Standardized Beta coefficients indicate that an increase of one standard deviation in
personality scores, holding the EI scores constant, results in an increase of NCS total
scores by almost 21% of its standard deviation. Similarly, an increment of EI score by one
standard deviation, holding the personality scores constant, results in an increase of NCS
total scores by almost 40% of its standard deviation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Demographic data of participants</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td style="border-style: solid none solid none; border-width: 1px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variables</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center; border-style: solid none solid none; border-width: 1px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>N (%)</bold>
</td><td style="border-style: solid none solid none; border-width: 1px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variables</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center; border-style: solid none solid none; border-width: 1px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>N (%)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Gender</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Place of residence</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 30px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (23)</td><td style="padding-left: 30px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">City</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190 (93.1)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 30px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157 (77)</td><td style="padding-left: 30px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Countryside</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (3.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Marital status</bold>
<sup>*</sup>
</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td style="padding-left: 30px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (2.9)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 30px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (23)</td><td style="padding-left: 30px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>University type</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 30px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154 (76)</td><td style="padding-left: 30px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (57.4)</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left: 30px; border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Widow</td><td style="text-align: center; border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1)</td><td style="padding-left: 30px; border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Private</td><td style="text-align: center; border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (42.6)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>
<sup>*</sup>Mised=1</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Descriptive statistics of participant nurses (continuous variables)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td style="border-style: solid none solid none; border-width: 1px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variable</bold>
</td><td style="border-style: solid none solid none; border-width: 1px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>N</bold>
</td><td style="border-style: solid none solid none; border-width: 1px" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean (SD)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Age</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">193</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.96 (6.738)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Years of working as a nurse</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.27 (6.074)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>High school GPA (0-20)</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.81 (1.451)</td></tr><tr><td style="border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Nursing school GPA (0-20)</bold>
</td><td style="border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162</td><td style="border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.18
(1.207)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><graphic xlink:href="jcs-5-121-g001"/><statement><p>Self-reported nurses&#x02019; competence scores by gender</p></statement></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><graphic xlink:href="jcs-5-121-g002"/><statement><p>Self-reported nurses&#x02019; personality scores by gender</p></statement></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><graphic xlink:href="jcs-5-121-g003"/><statement><p> Self-reported nurses&#x02019; emotional intelligence scores by gender Regression model</p></statement></fig><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Multiple regression results (Method: Enter; n=167; Dependent Variable: NCS total
scores)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" style="text-align: center; border-style: solid none none none; border-width: 1px" rowspan="1">
</td><td colspan="2" style="text-align: center; border-style: solid none none none; border-width: 1px" rowspan="1">
<bold>95% Confidence Interval for B</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td style="border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Predictors</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center; border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center; border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Std. Error</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center; border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Beta</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center; border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>t</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center; border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sig.</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center; border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Lower</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center; border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Upper</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Constant</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.513</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.744</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.214</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.831</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-25.702</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.675</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Personality Total Score</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.645</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.216</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.208</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.992</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.219</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.071</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>EI total Score</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.556</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.391</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.636</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.361</td><td style="text-align: center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.750</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8" style="text-align: right; border-style: none none solid none; border-width: 1px;" rowspan="1">
Adjusted R Square= 0.205</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p> In this study, the majority of nurses assessed their overall nursing competencies as good
and very good. This is in line with the result of other studies conducted in Iran and other
countries.<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> This may indicate that Iranian
nurses are as competent as nurses in other countries, despite their different educational
and cultural context. Undoubtedly, more detailed, cross-cultural studies seem to be required
to determine the roots of this similarity.</p><p> The male and female nurses similarly rated themselves in &#x0201c;managing situation&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;work
role&#x0201d; with the highest scores; while they did it in the &#x0201c;ensuring quality&#x0201d; and
&#x0201c;teaching-coaching&#x0201d; dimensions, with the lowest scores. Exactly similar pattern was reported
in Istomnia et al., study in which the Lithuanian surgical nurses assessed their
professional competence; however, the results were not reported separately for male and
female nurses.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p><p> A positive correlation existed between the frequencies of using the nurse skills and the
competence level of those skills. This is consistent with previous studies.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> As
expected, the higher the frequency of using a skill, the higher the competence level in that
skill.<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Poor overall mean score in
ensuring quality dimension signifies the vigorous need of managers&#x02019; more attention to this
dimension.</p><p> Our results showed that the nurses&#x02019; personality and EI are significantly correlated with
their competence level. The association of nurses' performance and their personality
traits,<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> as well as their EI<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> has
been discussed in the literature. Pitt et al., demonstrated that personal qualities affect
academic and clinical performance of preregistration nurse students as well as their ability
to complete a pre-registration program in three years. They reported that better academic
performance was correlated with lower aloofness, higher self-control (conscientiousness),
and higher resilience (emotional stability). Also they found that students with higher
confidence had been more competent in their final clinical assessment. <sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup></p><p> In the study of Chang et al., nurses who had positive evaluation and expectation towards
themselves and others, expressed higher job satisfaction. They advocated that training
workshops can enhance nurses&#x02019; self-care awareness, helping them to become more proactive in
their work.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup></p><p> In another study, Whitworth reported a relationship between female nurses&#x02019; personality
type and their preferred conflict management styles. She suggested that nurse managers
should consider the relationship between personality characteristics and methods of dealing
with conflicts, as a component of nurse competence, for facilitating constructive changes in
organizational culture.<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> In line with
this, Shimizutani et al., showed an association between nurses&#x02019; personality characteristics
and their coping styles, as well as personal, work-relates, and client-related
burnout.<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup></p><p> Above findings suggest that as the desired changes in personality is not easy, the nurse
managers are expected to appoint their nurse staff to those tasks that well-match with their
personality attributes. This may help to prevent conflicts and nurse burnout, and ultimately
improves patient outcomes.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p><p> O'Boyle et al., in their meta-analysis addressed the emotional intelligence as an
important predictor of job performance and work-related outcomes.<sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> Also, the impact of emotional intelligence on nursing team
performance and cohesiveness has been studied. It is believed that emotional regulation may
enhance patient outcomes, thus training professionals to this ability could be
productive.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> Moreover, the
relationships of EI and nursing performance, stress, coping, and well-being among nurses
have been supported in other studies.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Bulmer-Smith et al., concluded that
emotionally intelligent leaders may positively affect the employee retention, nursing care
quality, and patient outcomes.<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p><p> Moreover, Kooker et al., highlighted the importance of EI competencies in both practice
and educational settings.<sup><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup></p><p> The relationship of personality and EI has been addressed in the literature.<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> Whether the personality is associated with EI
or not, the relationship of performance with both personality and EI has been established
separately in the literature.</p><p> Likewise, the relationship of these two factors with nurse competence was demonstrated in
the present study. We believe that, nurses&#x02019; competence acts as a mediator between the
variables of nurses&#x02019; personality and EI in one side, and the variable of nurses&#x02019; performance
on the other side. Obviously, more detailed structural modeling studies are required to
confirm such relationships.</p><p> The randomized cluster sampling in this study may increase the representativeness of the
sample, thus increasing the generalizability of the findings. Also, we achieved a high
response rate by providing the participants with face to face explanation of the study
details and instruction to complete the questionnaires, ensuring them about the anonymity.
Also, simultaneous inclusion of personality and EI to assess their relationship with nurse
competence may be considered as strength of present study; though no causality inferences
can be made because of cross-sectional design adoption.</p><p> The sample size of this study was not large. Also, to achieve measures of nurse competence
levels, we merely used a self-report approach. Adoption of multi-method approach to nurse
competence evaluation may increase the validity of results.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p> Overall, Iranian clinical nurses evaluated their professional competencies as &#x0201c;good&#x0201d; and
&#x0201c;very good&#x0201d;. The nurses&#x02019; competence level was associated with their personality traits and
EI. Nursing leaders, who can address the personality types and emotional side of their
staff, patients, and families, may develop highly energized and synergized teams, necessary
for survival during this ever-changing landscape of healthcare. More longitudinal and
interventional studies are needed to give clearer picture of factors shaping and influencing
the nurses&#x02019; competence. Also, systematic and regular evaluation of nurses&#x02019; competence level
is of paramount.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p> Authors appreciate hospital nurses&#x02019; participation. Also the research team would like to
thank the authorities of Mashhad University of Medical Sciences and affiliated hospitals for
their permission and support of the study project.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethical issues</title><p> None to be declared.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p> The authors declare no conflict of interest in this study&#x0200f;.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Egmar</surname><given-names>A-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Florin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leksell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Development and validation of a new tool measuring nurses self-reported
professional competence-The nurse professional competence (NPC) Scale</article-title><source>Nurse Educ Today</source><year>2014</year><volume>34</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>574</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nedt.2013.07.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23938092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"> Girardet E.
Global standards for the initial education of professional nurses and midwives. Geneva:
Department of Human Resources for Health, World Health Organization. 2009. Available from:
http://www.who.int/hrh/ nursing_ midwifery/hrh_global_standards_education.pdf.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takase</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Teraoka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Development of the holistic nursing competence scale</article-title><source>Nurs Health Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1442-2018.2011.00631.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21883769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kendall-Gallagher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Blegen</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>Competence and certification of registered nurses and safety of patients in
intensive care units</article-title><source>Am J Crit Care</source><year>2009</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4037/ajcc2009487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19255100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ahanchian</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Emami Zeydi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Armat</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><article-title>Conflict management styles among iranian critical care nursing staff: a
cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Dimens Crit&#x000a0;Care&#x000a0;Nurs</source><year>2015</year><volume>34</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/DCC.0000000000000106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25840129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>JCY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sit</surname><given-names>ENM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><article-title>Conflict management styles, emotional intelligence and implicit theories of
personality of nursing students: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Nurse Educ Today</source><year>2014</year><volume>34</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>934</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nedt.2013.10.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24225346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kovner</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairchild</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Poornima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Djukic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Newly licensed RNs' characteristics, work attitudes, and intentions to
work</article-title><source>Am J Nurs</source><year>2007</year><volume>107</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17721152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kajander-Unkuri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meretoja</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Katajisto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Saarikoski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salminen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Suhonen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Self-assessed level of competence of graduating nursing students and
factors related to it</article-title><source>Nurse Educ Today</source><year>2014</year><volume>34</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>795</fpage><lpage>801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nedt.2013.08.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24018358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Istomina</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Suominen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Razbadauskas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinkenas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meretoja</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leino-Kilpi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Competence of nurses and factors associated with it</article-title><source>Medicina (Kaunas)</source><year>2011</year><volume>47</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21829056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bulmer-Smith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Profetto-McGrath</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><article-title>Emotional intelligence and nursing: an integrative literature
review</article-title><source>Int J Nurs Stud</source><year>2009</year><volume>46</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1624</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2009.05.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19596323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beauvais</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Shea</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>MTQ</given-names></name><article-title>Emotional intelligence and nursing performance among nursing
students</article-title><source>Nurse Educ Today</source><year>2011</year><volume>31</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nedt.2010.07.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20739106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><article-title>The influence of personality traits on nurses' job satisfaction in
Taiwan</article-title><source>Int Nurs Rev</source><year>2010</year><volume>57</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1466-7657.2010.00825.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21050200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cadman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Emotional intelligence: a vital prerequisite for recruitment in
nursing</article-title><source>Journal of Nursing Management</source><year>2001</year><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.0966-0429.2001.00261.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11879479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Salovey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><article-title>Emotional Intelligence</article-title><source>Imagination, Cognition, and Personality</source><year>1990</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2190/DUGG-P24E-52WK-6CDG</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Salovey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>The science of emotional intelligence</article-title><source>Curr Dir Psychol Sci</source><year>2005</year><volume>14</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0963-7214.2005.00381.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Por</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barriball</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Emotional intelligence: Its relationship to stress, coping, well-being and
professional performance in nursing students</article-title><source>Nurse Educ Today</source><year>2011</year><volume>31</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>855</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nedt.2010.12.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21292360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Quoidbach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansenne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>The Impact of Trait Emotional Intelligence on Nursing Team Performance and
Cohesiveness</article-title><source>J Prof Nurs</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.profnurs.2007.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19161959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><article-title>Personality measurement among nurses: a review</article-title><source>Int J Nurs Stud</source><year>1976</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0020-7489(76)90003-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">795775</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Naami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Behzadi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Parisa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Charkhabi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>A study on the personality aspects of adaptive performance among
governmental hospitals nurses: a conceptual model</article-title><source>Procedia&#x000a0;Soc Behav Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>159</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sbspro.2014.12.388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Riggio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Personality and Communication Skills as Predictors of Hospice Nurse
Performance</article-title><source>J Bus Psychol</source><year>2000</year><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1007832320795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shimizutani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Odagiri</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimomitsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Relationship of nurse burnout with personality characteristics and coping
behaviors</article-title><source>Industrial Health</source><year>2008</year><volume>46</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2486/indhealth.46.326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18716380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Whitworth</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><article-title>Is there a relationship between personality type and preferred
conflict-handling styles? An exploratory study of registered nurses in southern
Mississippi</article-title><source>Journal of Nursing Management</source><year>2008</year><volume>16</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>921</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2834.2008.00918.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19094104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bahreini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moattari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahamat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobaradaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravanipour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Improvement of Iranian nurses' competence through professional portfolio: a
quasi-experimental study</article-title><source>Nursing &#x00026; Health Sciences</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1442-2018.2012.00733.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22934971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bahreini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moattari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaveh</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayatdavoudy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirzaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Comparison of head nurses and practicing nurses in nurse competence
assessment</article-title><source>Iran J Nurs Midwifery Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22224112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bahreini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moatary</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaveh</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Self-assessment of the clinical competence of nurses in major educational
hospital of Shiraz University of Medical Sciences</article-title><source>Pars Journal of Medical Sciences , Journal of Jahrom University of Medical
Sciences</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><comment>(Persian)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Meretoja</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Isoaho</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leino&#x02010;Kilpi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Nurse Competence scale: development and psychometric
testing</article-title><source>Journal of Advanced Nursing</source><year>2004</year><volume>47</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2648.2004.03071.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15196186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Numminen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Meretoja</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Isoaho</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leino&#x02010;Kilpi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Professional competence of practising nurses</article-title><source>Journal of Clinical Nursing</source><year>2013</year><volume>22</volume><issue>9-10</issue><fpage>1411</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2702.2012.04334.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23574296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schutte</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Malouff</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Haggerty</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Development and validation of a measure of emotional
intelligence</article-title><source>Personality and Individual Differences</source><year>1998</year><volume>25</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0191-8869(98)00001-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McCrae</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jr</surname><given-names>Jr</given-names></name><article-title>Personality trait structure as a human universal</article-title><source>American Psychologist</source><year>1997</year><volume>52</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9145021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rammstedt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>The 10-item Big Five Inventory: Norm values and investigation of
sociodemographic effects based on a German population representative
sample</article-title><source>Eur J Psychol Assess</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>193</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1027/1015-5759.23.3.193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rammstedt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><article-title>Measuring personality in one minute or less: a 10-item short version of the
Big Five Inventory in English and German</article-title><source>Journal of Research in Personality</source><year>2007</year><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jrp.2006.02.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O'Leary</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Comparison of self-assessed competence and experience among critical care
nurses</article-title><source>Journal of nursing management</source><year>2012</year><volume>20</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2834.2012.01394.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22823216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bahreini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moattari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaveh</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>A comparison of nurses' clinical competences in two hospitals affiliated to
Shiraz and Boushehr Universities of medical sciences: a self-assessment</article-title><source>Iranian Journal of Medical Education</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><comment>(Persian)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tahmasb</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghorbani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><article-title>relationships between self- and peer-reported integrative self-knowledge
and the big five factors in Iran</article-title><source>Current Psychology</source><year>2008</year><volume>27</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12144-008-9030-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kakabaraee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moradi</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Arjmandnia</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Afrooz</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooman</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><article-title>Short Version of the big five inventory: testing for the factorial
invariance across parents with normal and exceptional children</article-title><source>International Journal of Psychology</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>99</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Salovey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>The intelligence of emotional intelligence</article-title><source>Intelligence</source><year>1993</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Balazs</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapitany</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Demetrovics</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><article-title>Confirmation of the three-factor model of the Assessing Emotions Scale
(AES): verification of the theoretical starting point</article-title><source>Behavior Research Methods</source><year>2010</year><volume>42</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>596</fpage><lpage>606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/brm.42.2.596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20479191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Besharat</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>Psychometric properties of Farsi version of the Emotional Intelligence
Scale-41 (FEIS-41)</article-title><source>Pers Individ Dif</source><year>2007</year><volume>43</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>991</fpage><lpage>1000</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.paid.2007.02.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hengstberger-Sims</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eagar</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrew</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Relating new graduate nurse competence to frequency of use</article-title><source>Collegian</source><year>2008</year><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.colegn.2008.02.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18567478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Powis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Levett-Jones</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>The influence of personal qualities on performance and progression in a
pre-registration nursing programme</article-title><source>Nurse Educ Today</source><year>2014</year><volume>34</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>866</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nedt.2013.10.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24231636</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O'Boyle</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawver</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Story</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><article-title>The relation between emotional intelligence and job performance: a
meta-analysis.</article-title><source>Journal of Organizational Behavior</source><year>2011</year><volume>32</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>788</fpage><lpage>818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/job.714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kooker</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoultz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Codier</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><article-title>Identifying Emotional Intelligence in Professional Nursing
Practice</article-title><source>J Prof Nurs</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17292131</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>