<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Rural Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Rural Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JRM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Rural Medicine : JRM</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1880-487X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1880-4888</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Japanese Association of Rural Medicine</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25648424</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4309330</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2852</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2185/jrm.7.6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Effect of Utilization of In-home Services and the Changes in Levels of
Care Needs of Frail Persons (2002&#x02013;2004): Results of a Two-year Follow-up
Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Jung-Nim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shiwaku</surname><given-names>Kuninori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> Tokyo University and Graduate School of Social Welfare,
Japan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> Shimane University School of Medicine, Japan</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Jung-Nim Kim, Tokyo University and
Graduate School of Social Welfare, 2020-1 Sano-cho, Isesaki City, Gunma 372-0831, Japan.
e-mail: <email xlink:href="daab2000@gmail.com">daab2000@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2012 The Japanese Association of Rural Medicine</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. </license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><bold>Objectives</bold>: Despite the increasing utilization of in-home services, the
assessment of in-home services used by those that have certified levels of care needs has
been limited to the actual changes in individual outcomes. The purpose of the present
study was to determine factors affecting how the utilization of in-home services could
have sustained and/or improved or deteriorated the care needs levels of frail persons. We
also examined the effect of in-home services used in the lower level of care needs
subgroup and the higher level of care needs subgroup during a two-year period.</p><p><bold>Subjects and Methods:</bold> We used longitudinal data from Izumo City of those
individuals with certified levels of care needs to analyze the changes in care need levels
in Izumo City between 2002 to 2004. In 2002, 2,651 persons had certified levels of care
needs. All permanent residents of care facilities, at care needs level 5 in 2002, those
who died since 2002 and people who could not be traced during the two-year follow-up
period were excluded. The remaining data from 1,788 frail persons were ultimately
analyzed. We arbitrarily divided the changes in care needs levels into two categories:
sustained/improved and deteriorated. The care needs levels were also stratified into a
lower level of care needs subgroup and a higher level of care needs subgroup at the
baseline. Simple statistical analysis and binary logistic regression analysis were used to
analyze factors that were thought to be related to in-home service utilization data to
predict changes in care needs levels.</p><p><bold>Results:</bold> Approximately 63.3% of the respondents had a sustained or improved
care needs level, and 36.7% of the respondents showed deteriorated of care needs levels.
In the lower level of care needs subgroup, utilization of home help/bathing (OR=2.59) was
associated with significant sustained/improved care needs levels. In the higher level of
care needs subgroup, day care service (OR=0.90) and short stay services (OR=0.87) were
significantly related to deteriorated care needs levels, respectively.</p><p><bold>Conclusions:</bold> This study shows that home help/bathing care in the lower level
of care needs subgroup was a significant predictor of sustained/improved levels of care
needs for frail persons but that short stay services and day care services in the higher
level of care needs subgroup have a negative impact on sustained/improved levels of care
needs. Our results suggest that utilization of home help services can prevent
deterioration of these levels of care needs in frail persons.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>follow-up study</kwd><kwd>utilization of in-home services</kwd><kwd>changes in levels of care needs</kwd><kwd>frail persons</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The family's capacity to care for the elderly is weakening because of a changing household
structure, an increasing number of working women and an enhanced social security system in
Japan. There are 4.884 million people in Japan certified as eligible for the long-term care
insurance system. The ratio of those aged 65 and over was 16.9%, and the number of home
services users was 2.924 million people in May 2010<sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>. Disabilities are associated with a loss of independence, an
increased need for health care services and subsequently higher health care costs<sup><xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>. In response to these problems, the public long-term care
insurance system (LTCIS) was introduced in 2000 by the Ministry of Health, Labour and
Welfare, which focuses on providing both in-home services (home care) and also services at
facilities (institutional care). All persons aged 65 and over are eligible, along with
people aged 40 to 64 who have a health-related disability. In-home services have become the
fastest growing segment of the Japan LTCIS. They are expected to play a significant role as
an effective tool for not only preventing deterioration and improving the disability status
for frail persons but also decreasing the burden for family caregivers and improving the
lives of those living in the community with certified care needs levels.</p><p>There is an ongoing debate over the effectiveness of in-home services for the various
levels of care needs of frail persons. Despite a considerable number of meta-analyses and
reviews synthesizing the home-visit nursing literature<sup><xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>, there have been few reviews examining in-home services for
those with certified levels of care needs or support needs, and the available literature
does little to inform us about whether the association of in-home services with levels of
care needs of frail persons has been maintained/improved or deteriorated in Japan since the
implementation of the national long-term care insurance system (LTCIS).</p><p>The main objective of the present study was to determine how the utilization of in-home
services could have sustained/improved or deteriorated the levels of care needs of frail
persons. We also examined the effect of in-home services used in the lower level of care
needs subgroup and the higher level of care needs subgroup during a two-year period. Studies
have been limited by the lack of evidence for the effectiveness of in-home services for
frail elderly on changes in levels of care needs such as lower level of care needs and
higher level of care needs<sup><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>.
Some studies have indicated that in-home services had positive or negative effects on
reductions in functional levels. Kato <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup><sup>)</sup> found that use of respite stays in a nursing home,
and use of medical management by a physician were significantly related to a deterioration
of the user's levels of care needs. On the other hand, Ishibashi <italic>et
al</italic>.<sup><xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup><sup>)</sup> demonstrated
that the risk of decline in functional status was lower for users of home help services.
Moreover, Fukuma and Shiwaku<sup><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>
indicated that at the end of tracking of two years, improvement in the care level was
related to either levels of care needs or utilization of short stays. A study by Tomita
<italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>
reported that among the types of services, users of respite care and rental services for
assistive devices were less likely to be hospitalized or institutionalized than nonusers.
Concerning those with relatively light needs, users of day care services were also less
likely to be hospitalized or institutionalized than nonusers. Markle-Reid <italic>et
al</italic>.<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup><sup>)</sup> found that a
variety of home visiting interventions carried out by nurses can favorably affect health and
functional status and mortality rates. However, Stuck <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup><sup>)</sup> used subgroup analysis to reveal
that public home-visit nursing can reduce disabilities among elderly people at low risk but
not among those at high risk for functional impairment after three years. Other studies,
however, indicated that the use of home help services had no effect on reducing functional
decline<sup><xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Although multidimensional services and levels of care needs have been studied, these
previous reviews have had significant limitations. There is still insufficient evidence not
only regarding the effectiveness of in-home based services<sup><xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup><sup>)</sup> but also what kinds of in-home services have a
significant predictor of sustained/improved level of care needs for frail persons in the
lower level of care needs subgroup and the higher level of care needs subgroup in panel
study. Given the shortcomings of previous reviews and the lack of consistency among their
findings, we thought it important to undertake a panel analysis to clarify the benefits of
in-home based services. The results of this study will contribute to the discussion
concering effective in-home service strategies for frail persons.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Subjects and Methods</title><sec><title>Subjects</title><p>All subjects were selected from those who had applied for LTCI for the first time
beginning in April 2002 and had been newly certified as community-dwelling frail persons
in Izumo City, Shimane Prefecture, Japan. The subjects in the first wave were 2,625
residents in 2000, those in the second wave were 3,435 residents in 2002 and those in the
third wave were 4,206 residents in 2004. The population in the third wave was comprised of
residents who were observed by a survey that was subsequently performed every two years by
the Izumo long-term care insurance union in Izumo City. We used second wave and third wave
data (2002&#x02013;2004) from those who were certified for long-term care insurance by the Izumo
LTCI union. Because the care insurance system started in 2000 in Japan, the second wave
data was more stable than the first wave data.</p><p>Of the 2,651 subjects who were certified as &#x0201c;support level of care needs&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;care needs
levels 1 to 5&#x0201d; in Izumo City in 2002, 1,788 completed the entire survey in 2004. The
subjects of the analysis were calculated by limiting the numerator to those who were
certified as &#x0201c;support need&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;levels of care needs&#x0201d;. First, all permanent residents of
care facilities were excluded from the analysis. Second, 435 people who died and 99 people
who could not be traced during the two-year follow-up period in 2002 were also excluded.
Third, 329 people at care needs level 5 in 2002 were excluded. Because the subjects were
limited to those capable of living at home in 2004 and the dependent variables include the
change in the care needs levels, care needs level 5 could be identified as sustained or
improved but could not be classified as deteriorated.</p></sec><sec><title>Dependent variables</title><p>The levels of care needs were determined by Izumo City through a predetermined process. A
trained local government official visits the home to evaluate nursing care needs using a
questionnaire on current physical and mental status (73 items) and use of medical
procedures (12 items). A computer program classifies each applicant into one of six levels
of dependency care after the evaluation. The Nursing Care Needs Certification Board,
consisting of social and health services experts appointed by the mayor, determines
whether the initial levels of care needs are appropriate<sup><xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>. Care needs level 0 (assistance required) is
intended for preventive services. The other five levels of care needs (care required)
range from the lowest (level 1 of care need) to highest (care needs level 5) levels of
care needs<sup><xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>. We arbitrarily
set the changes in levels of care needs into two categories: sustained or improved and
deteriorated. The changes in the levels of care needs were calculated by subtracting the
baseline levels of care needs from the levels of care needs in 2004. If a subject&#x02019;s change
in level of care needs was calculated to be 0 or &#x02013;1&#x0003e;, the change in the level of care
needs was defined as a &#x0201c;sustained&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;improved.&#x0201d; If the subject's change in level of care
needs was calculated to be &#x0003c;1, the change in level of care needs was defined as
"deteriorated.&#x0201d;</p></sec><sec><title>Independent variables and controlled variables</title><p>In-home services can be provided by nonprofit and for-profit firms. An eligible person
must pay a 10% co-payment for each insured service and the municipality pays the rest. The
independent variables included in-home services of 8 kinds: home help service, home-visit
bathing, home-visit nursing, home-visit rehabilitation, day care service, day
rehabilitation service, rental service for equipment, and short stay service. The response
categories for this question were dichotomized (used service or did not used service).
There were significantly fewer users of home help service and home-visit bathing,
respectively, so these services were calculated as sum categories 1 and 2 concerning use
of home help service and home-visit bathing, with category 1 indicating that the home
help/bathing was not used.</p><p>The controlled variables included age, gender, and household structure.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Descriptive analysis of the following statistical results characterize the face sheets of
the subjects, levels of care needs and in-home service. First, differences in the changes
in levels of care needs and baseline characteristics were examined with simple statistical
analysis and cross tabulation. Second, cross tabulation is the process of creating a
contingency table from the multivariate frequency distribution of statistical variables,
and we tested for the statistical significance of values. Third, binary logistic
regression analysis was used to build a final model for utilization of in-home service
with the dependent variable divided into two categories, sustained/improved and
deteriorated.</p><p>The changes in levels of care needs were stratified into a lower level of care needs
subgroup and a higher level of care needs subgroup based on the baseline levels of care
needs. The lower level of care needs subgroup included the support level and care needs
level 1. The higher level of care needs subgroup included care needs level 2, 3 and 4.
Because the LTCI system was amended in April 2006 to include 7 levels instead of 6, with
eligibility determined through a process of care needs certification by the municipality,
those eligible were 1) persons certified before the revision as &#x0201c;support level&#x0201d; (support
level 1 in the new classification) and 2) persons with a higher possibility of maintaining
or improving their condition among those certified before the revision as care needs level
1 (support level 2 in the new classification)<sup><xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>.</p><p>SPSS 18.0J Windows was used for the statistical analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Characteristics of the study population</title><p><xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref><table-wrap id="tbl_001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characteristics of the frail persons of the Izumo in-home cohort study</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Response category</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% (N=3,435)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% (N=2,322)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% (N=2,651)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% (N=1,788)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="7" colspan="1"> Stay in place</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In-home</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.2 (2,651)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group home</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8 (27)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Special nursing home</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 (412)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health service facility</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1 (243)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sanatorium type mecical care facility</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3 (115)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Death</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7 (435)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Could not track</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3 ( 99)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.2 (934)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.7 (566)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.8 (1,717)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.3 (1,222)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;64 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3 (114)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 (57)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65&#x02013;74 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5 (463)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0 (251)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75&#x02013;84 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5 (1,073)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.1 (699)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 years and over</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.8 (1,001)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.7 (781)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean&#x000b1;standard deviation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.1 &#x000b1; 8.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.4 &#x000b1; 8.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Household</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living alone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6 (349)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4 (310)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living with spouse</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.3 (401)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9 (320)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lining with 2-generations or more</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.1 (1,749)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.7 (1,119)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Care needs levels</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Support level</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6 (280)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2 (183)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care level 1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3 (618)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.9 (535)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care level 2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.6 (547)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7 (334)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care level 3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9 (421)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.0 (340)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care level 4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0 (292)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4 (222)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care level 5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4 (329)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7 (174)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="7" colspan="1">In-home services used</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Home help/bathing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3 (671)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4 (437)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Home-visit nursing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5 ( 253)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9 ( 141)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day care service</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.0 (770)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0 (572)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day rehabilitation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2 (376)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9 (249)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short stay</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7 (257)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2 (201)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rental service for equipment</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8 (577)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3 (488)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total number of services used in-home (mean&#x000b1;SD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 &#x000b1; 1.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 &#x000b1; 1.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Changesinf levels of care needs</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sustaind or improved</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.3 (1,132)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deteriorated</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.7 (656)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>shows the characteristics of the frail persons at baseline and during the
two-year follow-up period. Overall, the data showed that female subjects were nearly 65%
and 68% in 2002 and 2004, respectively. Those 85 years and over of the subjects were 37.8%
and 43.7% in 2002 and 2004, respectively. In 2002 and 2004, more than 68% and 63% of the
subjects lived in a two-generation household, respectively. In 2002 and 2004, 23% and 30%
of the subjects were care needs level 1 and 12.4% of the subjects and 9.7% were care needs
level 5, respectively. There was a difference in utilization of home help service, with
29% and 32% of the subjects using more day care service in 2002 and 2004, 25.3% and 24.4%
of the subjects used home help service or home-visit bathing in 2002 and 2004,
respectively. More than 63.3% of the subjects had a sustained or improved level of care
needs, nearly 36.7% of the subjects had a deteriorated level of care needs and more than
18.7% of the subjects had died.</p></sec><sec><title>Distribution of care needs levels</title><p><xref rid="tbl_002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
<table-wrap id="tbl_002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Changes in levels of care needs of frail persons with utlizaiton of in-home
services</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Response category</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sustained/Improved<break/>% (N=1,132)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deteriorated<break/>% (N=656)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total<break/>% (N=1,788)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5<sup>**</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">40&#x02013;64 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2<sup>**</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">65&#x02013;74 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">75&#x02013;84 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">85 years and over</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Household</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Living alone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.7<sup>n.s.</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Living with spouse</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Lining with 2-generations or more</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Care needs levels</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Support level</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.9<sup>**</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Care level 1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Care level 2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Care level 3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Care level 4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">In-home services used</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Home help/bathing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.6<sup>**</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Visit nursing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.<sup>7n.s.</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day care service</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.8<sup>**</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day rehabilitation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.5<sup>**</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short stay</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.9<sup>**</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Rental service for equipment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.9<sup>n.s.</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>* and **; * &#x0003c; 0.05 and ** &#x0003c; 0.01, respectively. </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap> shows the changes in care needs levels of frail persons with regard to
utilization of in-home services. For utilization of in-home services, using of home
help/bathing and day care service exhibited statistically significant results and were
related to a sustained/improved level of care needs, respectively. About 78% of the
subjects used home help/bathing, 71% of the subjects used day care service and 58% of the
subjects were using day rehabilitation were associated with significant sustained/improved
care needs levels, respectively. In contrast, about 59% of the subjects using short stays
in a facility were associated with significant deteriorated care needs levels. Whereas,
for 60% of the subjects using home-visit nursing and rental service for equipment was
associated with no significant stained/improved care needs levels, respectively.</p><p>The care needs level 1 to 4 had a sustained/improved care needs level as compare to
support level of care needs group. There was an insignificant difference between men and
women in the change in care needs levels. Those younger than 65 years and over at baseline
had more changes categorized sustained/improved level of care needs. Household size was
almost the same in sustain/improved and deteriorated level of care needs.</p><p>In the present study, we considered all these confounding factors in order to evaluate
the change in the levels of care needs in frail persons, and we compared in-home services
with age and levels of care needs factors. Of the age groups, the 65&#x02013;74-year-old age group
used significantly more home help/bathing (9.7% vs. 7.6%, p &#x0003c; 0.48) and day
rehabilitation (18.9% vs. 8.6%, p = 0.00), than the 85 years and over age group; however,
the 85 years and over age group used significantly more day care service (31.3% vs. 22.5%,
p &#x0003c; 0.00) and short stays (9.8% vs. 3.5%, p = 0.00) than the 65&#x02013;74-year-old age group.
The higher level of care needs subgroup used significantly more home help/bathing (8.5%
vs. 8%, p &#x0003c; 0.00), day rehabilitation (14.2% vs. 9.5%, p = 0.00), and short stays (9.7%
vs. 2.4%, p = 0.00) than the lower level of care needs subgroup, however, the lower level
of care needs subgroup used significantly more day care service (27.9% vs. 27.4%, p &#x0003c;
0.00) than the higher level of care needs subgroup.</p></sec><sec><title>Results of logistic regression analysis for changes in the levels of care
needs</title><p><xref rid="tbl_003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
<table-wrap id="tbl_003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Logisitic regression analysis for changes in levels of care needs</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factor</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sustained/Improved<break/>in the lower level<break/>Odds ratio (95% CI)<break/>Model
1 </th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sustained/Improved<break/>in the higher level<break/>Odds ratio (95% CI)<break/>Model 2 </th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 reference</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 reference</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.166 (0.84&#x02013;1.63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.53&#x02013;1.01)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.93&#x02013;0.97)<sup>**</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.95&#x02013;0.98)<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Household</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living alone</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 reference</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 reference</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living with spouse</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.43&#x02013;1.09)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87 (1.08&#x02013;3.22)<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living with 2 generations or more</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 (0.62&#x02013;1.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 (0.95&#x02013;0.98)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">In-home services used </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonuse of care sevices</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 reference</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 reference</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Home help/bathing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.59 (1.38&#x02013;4.87)<sup>**</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 (0.80&#x02013;2.08)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Home-visit nursing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 (0.46&#x02013;1.02)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 (0.74&#x02013;2.08)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day care service</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (0.87&#x02013;1.08)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.82&#x02013;0.99)<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day rehabilitation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.96&#x02013;1.23)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 (1.00&#x02013;1.19)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short stay</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.74&#x02013;1.02)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.81&#x02013;0.94)<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rental service of equipment</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.95&#x02013;1.15)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.94&#x02013;1.08)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">-2 log Likelihood</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1079.73</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1131.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model Chi-square</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.52<sup>**</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.86<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">N</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">873</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">915</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p> * and **; *&#x0003c; 0.05 and ** &#x0003c; 0.01, respectively. Numbers in parentheses are
95% confidence intervals (CI). Control variables included gender, age and household
in model 1 and model 2.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap> shows the binary logistic regression analysis results. In <xref rid="tbl_003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, the changes to sustained/improved in the
lower level of care needs subgroup are indicated in Model 1, and the changes to
sustained/improved in the higher level of care needs subgroup are indicated in Model
2.</p><p>For the lower level of care needs subgroup in Model 1, utilization of home help/bathing
service (OR= 2.59; CI, 1.38&#x02013;4.87) was significantly higher for the sustained/improved
level of care needs compared with the group that did not use in-home services. For the
following types of service, utilization of day care service (OR=1.08; CI, 0.96&#x02013;1.23),
rental service for equipment (OR=1.04; CI, 0.95&#x02013;1.15), home-visit nursing (OR=0.69; CI,
0.46&#x02013;1.02), day care service (OR=0.97; CI, 0.87&#x02013;1.08), and short stays in a facility
(OR=0.87; CI, 0.74&#x02013;1.02), there was no statistically significant difference in
sustained/improved level of care needs for frail persons, respectively.</p><p>The higher level of care needs subgroup in Model 2 includes care needs levels 2 to level
4. We observed that the utilization of a short stays in a facility (OR=0.87; CI,
0.81&#x02013;0.94) was significantly related to a negatively sustained/improved level of care
needs. That is, that group was more likely to move into a deteriorated level of care
needs. Likewise, using day care service (OR=0.90; CI, 0.82&#x02013;0.99) was significantly related
to deterioration of care needs levels as compared with subjects who did not use in-home
services. In contrast, utilization of home help/bathing service (OR= 1.29; CI, 0.80&#x02013;2.08),
day rehabilitation service (OR= 1.09; CI, 1.00&#x02013;1.19), and rental service for equipment
(OR= 1.01; CI, 0.94&#x02013;1.08) resulted in no statically significant differences in
sustained/improved level of care needs in those groups, respectively.</p><p>We also observed that the higher level of care needs subgroup in Model 2, living with a
spouse (OR= 1.87; CI, 1.08&#x02013;3.22) among subjects was significantly related to
sustained/improved level of care needs. On the other hand, age (OR= 0.95; CI, 0.93&#x02013;0.97;
OR= 0.97; CI, 0.95&#x02013;0.98) of subjects was significantly related to deterioration level of
care needs in the lower and higher care needs level subgruop, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>We studied frail persons based on a cohort study to assess the effects of utilization of
in-home services among lower level and higher level of care needs subgroups of
community-dwelling elderly in Japan.</p><p>Differences in utilization of in-home services occurred between the lower level of care
needs subgroup and higher level of care needs subgroup. The use of home help or home-visit
bathing services was significantly related to a positively sustained/improved level of care
needs in the lower level of care needs subgroup. However, use of short-stay and day care
service were significantly related to a worsening predictor of level of care needs of frail
persons in the higher level of care needs subgroup. In the controlled variables, living with
a spouse was significantly related to a positively sustained/improved level of care needs in
the higher level of care needs subgroup; however, age of the frail persons was significantly
related to worsening level of care needs in both the lower level of care needs and higher
level of care needs subgroups. In our study, we took these factors into consideration by
adjusting for insured persons obtained from records concering certification of needed for
long-term care.</p><p>Our study could not identify causal relationships from empirical analysis. However, we can
explain conjecturally why some use of services showed a significant relationship with
sustain/improved level of care needs or a deteriorating level of care needs.</p><p>Based on our conjecture, the subjects who used home help service or home-visit bathing had
improved or sustained level of care needs in the lower level of care needs subgroup but were
at far higher risk of ADL (Activity of Daily Living) limitations and/ or cognitive
impairments than others. In the lower care needs subgroup, the reason that home helpers are
professionals and provides skilled care works to frail persons who need care continue to
live as independently as possible at home. Frail persons can decide who come to their house
and provides care and thery can set home helpers schedule and determine how and when the
tasks will be done. Thus, the main focus of long-term care services is on primary prevention
of disability for frail persons, and this need has been met especially for those using these
services. Regarding home visiting services, Elkan <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup><sup>)</sup> indicated that regular home visits
for elderly people was associated with a significant reduction in mortality and admission to
long-term institutional care.</p><p>Use of short-term admission to a facility was particularly salient in the higher level of
care needs subgroup. The users of this services were less likely than nonusers of in-home
services to have a sustained or improved level of care needs in the higher level of care
needs subgroup. These users, on average, had more severe ADL or IADL limitations and/or
cognitive impairments than other. This may also be the reason why these services have been
focused on family caregivers for those with greater burden or for working fanilies etc. who
do not provide informal care. This is supported by the fact that numerous publications have
evaluated the effect of short-stay service focusing on outcomes for caregivers, not care
recipients<sup><xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup><sup>, </sup><sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>. Thus, those who used respite care
were less likely than nonusers to be hospitalized or institutionalized<sup><xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>. This service may reduce the care
burden of family caregivers, allowing them to maintain their ability to provide
care<sup><xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup><sup>, </sup><sup><xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>, but so far, most of the users are
at either a sustained or improved level of care needs. Regarding effect of program, Brunette
<italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>
indicated that patients in long-term programs had significantly better outcomes than those
in short-term programs. Quality of care is fundamentally a multidimensional concept, which
in addition to clinical information, includes quality of life and the satisfaction of the
frail persons and the caregiver<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>, that needs to be considered, in association with the
improvement levels of care needs among those who have a higher level of care needs, which
becomes more pronounced as the population continues to age.</p><p>Concerning the impact of day care use on the deterioration level of needs in the high level
of care needs subgroup, we should consider that the service users, on average, had less risk
of ADL limitations and/or cognitive impairments. Thus, many day care service centers have
not employed specialists to perform services, which includes programs for frail persons like
physical therapy, psychological services and special programs of recreation according to the
needs of the frail persons in the high level of care needs subgroup. The day service center
programs provide basic services to frail persons including meals, transportation, bathing
and simple recreation by care workers. We also consider that the number of care workers in
day care services is significantly less than those in facilities providing care to frail
persons. A care worker ratio of 1:15 was maintained for subjects determined to be frail
persons by the LTCS, and sufficient care could not be provided for frail persons to maintain
their physical and mental health, especially in the high level of care needs subgroup. Thus,
users of day care services were more likely than nonusers to be independent and more likely
to be co-performers of activities of daily living with care workers. A sufficient ratio of
care workers to frail persons needs to be established to increase the proportion of frail
persons who improve or sustain their level of care needs, and it is an important public
policy issue.</p><p>Concerning the baseline confounding factors for deteriorated level of care needs, day care
users and short-stay service users were older and had a higher level of care needs in users
with deterioration of physical or mental function. However, regarding a sustained/improved
level of care needs, home help/bathing users were young elderly and had a lower level of
care needs. It has been suggested that the young-old population gains greater benefit from
follow-up home help/bathing services than the old-old population. Therefore, a seemingly
baseline higher level of care needs was related to a deteriorating of level of care needs
even though the subjects were using day care and short stay services.</p><p>However, there was no evidence of an effect of improvement or sustained level of care needs
on users of in-home services, home-visit nursing, day rehabilitation services and welfare
equipment among both the lower level of care needs subgroup and higher level of care needs
subgroup. Concerning in-home services, a previous study reported the effect of improvement
level of care needs on some types of in-home services<sup><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup><sup>, </sup><sup><xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup><sup>,
</sup><sup><xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup><sup>, </sup><sup><xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>. It may be necessary to focus more
investigators on the effect of various types of in-home services on changes in the level of
care needs of frail persons. A study in Saskatchewan, Canada<sup><xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup><sup>)</sup> concluded that persons receiving home care were
more likely to experience improvement of their level of care needs than those not receiving
home care. Therefore, there exists an urgent need to develop and test the effectiveness of
in-home services and strategies designed to improve the level of care needs, or to at least
maintain the level of care needs, among frail persons and to determine how well in-home
services and other strategies work in both the lower level of care needs and higher level of
care needs subgroups.</p><p>Overall, utilization of home help/bathing services in the lower level of care needs
subgroup was a significant predictor of improved/maintained levels of care needs for frail
persons. We consider in-home services to have at least two main purposes. The first is to
provide an alternative to residential support, enabling people to stay in their communities,
families or homes. The second is to provide respite care for family caregivers, often the
children or spouse of the frail persons who are provided home care. Our findings are only
preliminary, but they provide further evidence supporting the importance of the effects of
the levels of care needs for frail persons using in-home services. Given the pressures to
reduce public spending on care of frail persons and a growing desire for in-home services
for the elderly, the emphasis on caring for elderly people in their own homes has gained
momentum across social welfare systems in the developed world<sup><xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup><sup>)</sup>. In-home services for frail persons are intended to improve
the quality of services for improvement or maintenance of the level of care needs, though it
is not yet known whether frail persons and their families are able to be appropriate judges
of which providers and which kind of in-home services will provide the best type of
care.</p><p>Nevertheless, we note several limitations of the present study. First, the data did not
contain any relevant information regarding the socioeconomic situation of frail persons or
family caregivers or the quality of home care service provided. Whether these additional
sources of information affect the levels of care needs for frail persons and the categories
is an issue that requires further investigation. Second, generalization of our findings is
limited because our data were derived from data for individuals who had applied for LTCI and
individuals certified for LTCI among community-dwelling frail persons in a single
prefecture. Future studies are needed from another prefecture to confirm our results. Third,
our analysis did not have informal services data conserning such thing as the private
caregiver situation and support networks because our dataset did not contain these
categories. More detailed data on the private services of subjects would be helpful to
further clarify the changes in the levels of care needs in later life. Fourth, our study
could not identify the effects of using home help service and home visit-bathing had a
improved or sustained level of care needs, respectively. Therefore, in the future, the
effect of use of a home helper service and home-visit bathing should be investigated to
determine whether or not frail persons who are using home help services or visit bathing can
sustain their levels of care needs, respectively. Finally, in-home service programs
targeting frail persons were not included in our study because the goal of our study was to
determine whether or not individuals sustained/maintained their level of care needs, which
kinds of home care services were used and whether the intervention consisted of less than
four visits per year and/or the duration of the intervention program was shorter than 12
months.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The evidence in this investigation points to the importance of the use of home help or
bathing services in maintaining and improving the level of care needs in the lower level of
care needs subgroup. Furthermore, in the higher level of care needs subgroup, the use of a
short stay and day care service was significantly associated with a retrograded level of
care needs. The political and practical problem facing governments is how to achieve
financial savings and increase efficiency without reducing the quality of care. By
identifying potential ways to maintain or improve level of care needs of frail persons and
the utilization of in-home services that are viable from a policy perspective, the present
survey should provide a better sense of which in-home services might result in more positive
changes in levels of care needs for frail persons. This knowledge may suggest that in-home
services contribute to the goal of the long-term care system of preventing deterioration but
also that these services may help make things easier for family caregivers in the community
and help policy-makers reform in-home services.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This study was partly supported by residents certified for long-term care insurance by the
Izumo LTCI union.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ministry of Health, Labour
and Welfare. Kaigohoken Jigyou Joukyou Houkokuno Gaiyo (The outline of report of situation
in long term care insurance) <year>2010</year> [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mhlw.go.jp/topics/kaigo/osirase/jigyo/m10/dl/1001a.pdf">http://www.mhlw.go.jp/topics/kaigo/osirase/jigyo/m10/dl/1001a.pdf</ext-link>]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wissoker</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disabilities and medicare costs of elderly
persons.</article-title><source>The Milbank Quarterly</source><year>1997</year>;
<volume>75</volume>: <fpage>461</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>493</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1468-0009.00066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9415089</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A study of social status and health states. Gender
equality and multicultural conviviality in the age of
globalization.</article-title><source>Tohoku University Global COE
program</source><year>2010</year>; <volume>3</volume>:
<fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage> (In Japanese).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bouman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Rossum</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Evaers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Effects on health care use and associated cost of a home
visiting program for older people with poor health status: randomized clinical trial in
the Netherlands. J Gerontology. Series A</article-title>, <source>Biological Sciences
and Medical Sciences</source><year>2008</year>; <volume>63</volume>:
<fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18375878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Liebel</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Review of nurse home visiting interventions for
community-dwelling older persons with existing
disability.</article-title><source>Medical Care Research and
Review</source><year>2009</year>; <volume>66</volume>:
<fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>146</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1077558708328815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19114607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Fukuma M,
Shiwaku K. Change of care levels of frail elderly individuals after introduction of
long-term nursing care insurance system.</article-title><source>Nihon NouSon
Igaku</source><year>2009</year>; <volume>58</volume>:
<fpage>516</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>525</lpage><comment>(In Japanese)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamiya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashiwagi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Relationship between home care service use and changes in
the care needs level of Japanese elderly.</article-title><source>BMC
Geriatrics</source><year>2009</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>58</fpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2318-9-58</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20025749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Ishibashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikegami</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Should the provision of home help services be contained?:
Validation of the new preventive care policy in Japan.</article-title><source>BMC Health
Services Research</source><year>2010</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>224</fpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6963-10-224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20678189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikegami</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Impact of home and community-based services on
hospitalisation and institutionalisation among individuals eligible for long-term care
insurance in Japan.</article-title><source>BMC Health Service
Research</source><year>2010</year>; <volume>22</volume>: 10: 345.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Markle-Reid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>R,</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The effectiveness and efficiency of home-based nursing
health promotion for older people: A review of the
literature.</article-title><source>Medical Care Research and
Review</source><year>2006</year>; <volume>63</volume>:
<fpage>531</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>569</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1077558706290941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16954307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Stuck</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Minder</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Peter-W&#x000fc;est</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>A randomized trial of in-home visits for disability
prevention in community-dwelling older people at low and high risk for nursing home
admission.</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2000</year>;
<volume>160</volume>: <fpage>977</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>986</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.160.7.977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10761963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiraoka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The effect of changes of health and mental status for
frail elderly at home: panel survey of Tokyo
Metropolitan.</article-title><source>KoseinoSihyou</source><year>2004</year>;
<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage><comment>(In
Japanese)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kikuzawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Effect of service use under long-term care insurance among
those with light disability level: Analyses of change in disability level using panel
data</article-title>. <source>Japanese Journal of Gerontology</source><year>2007</year>;
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>383</lpage> (In
Japanese).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Tsutsui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Muramatsu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Care needs certification in the long-term care insurance
system of Japan.</article-title><source>Journal of the American Geriatrics
Society</source><year>2005</year>; <volume>53</volume>:
<fpage>522</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>527</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2005.53175.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15743300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="eref">Ministry of Health, Labor and
Welfare. Overview of the Revision of the Long-term Care Insurance
System.(6.6.<year>2011</year>) [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ilcjapan.org/linksE/doc/Overview_of_the_Revision_of_LTCI.pdf">http://www.ilcjapan.org/linksE/doc/Overview_of_the_Revision_of_LTCI.pdf</ext-link>]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Elkan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kendrick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of home based support for older people:
systematic review and
meta-analysis.</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2001</year>;
<volume>323</volume>: <fpage>719</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>725</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.323.7315.719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11576978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Respite care for people with dementia and their
carers.</article-title><source>Cochrane database of systematic reviews</source> (Online)
<year>2004</year>; <fpage>CD004396</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15106250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Gaugler</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Early community-based service utilization and its effects on
institutionalization in dementia
caregiving.</article-title><source>Gerontologist</source><year>2005</year>;
<volume>45</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>185</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/geront/45.2.177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15799982</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Brunette</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Comparison of long-term and short-term residential treatment
programs for dual diagnosis patients.</article-title><source>Psychiatr
Serv</source><year>2001</year>; <volume>52</volume>:
<fpage>526</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>528</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.52.4.526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11274501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Nursing home organizational change: The &#x0201c;culture change&#x0201d;
movement as viewed by longterm care specialists.</article-title><source>Medical Care
Research and Review</source><year>2010</year>; <volume>67</volume>:
<fpage>65s</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81s</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1077558710366862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20435790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>van Haastregt</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Diederiks</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>van Rossum</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Effects of preventive home visits to elderly people living
in the community: systematic
review.</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2000</year>; <volume>320</volume>:
<fpage>754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>758</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.320.7237.754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10720360</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottschalk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>A rehabilitation program for physically frail
community-living older persons.</article-title><source>Arch Phys Med
Rehabil</source><year>2003</year>; <volume>84</volume>:
<fpage>394</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>404</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/apmr.2003.50020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12638108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Saskatchewan Health Services
Utilization and Research Commission. The impact of preventive home care and seniors
housing on health outcomes. Saskatoon: <year>2000</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Aronson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Neysmith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>You&#x02019;re not just in there to do the work: Depersonalizing
policies and the exploitation of home care workers labor.</article-title><source>Gender
&#x00026; Society</source><year>1996</year>; <volume>10</volume>:
<fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/089124396010001005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Exploring shared options in funding long-term care for
older people.</article-title><source>Health &#x00026; Social Care in the
Community</source><year>1998</year>; <volume>6</volume>:
<fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>157</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2524.1998.00111.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11560586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Yeoh</surname><given-names>BSA</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Foreign domestic workers and home-based care for the
elderly in Singapore.</article-title><source>Journal of Aging &#x00026; Social
Policy</source>, <year>2010</year>; <volume>22</volume>:
<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08959420903385635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20390713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>