<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Rural Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Rural Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JRM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Rural Medicine : JRM</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1880-487X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1880-4888</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Japanese Association of Rural Medicine</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25648048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4309346</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2845</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2185/jrm.6.32</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Seminomatous Extragonadal Germ Cell Tumor with Complete Obstruction of the
Superior Vena Cava Responding to Intensive Chemotherapy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moritoki</surname><given-names>Yoshinobu</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Toshiki</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nishio</surname><given-names>Hidenori</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kamisawa</surname><given-names>Hideyuki</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>Yasuhiko</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>Ryosuke</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Akita</surname><given-names>Hidetoshi</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Okamura</surname><given-names>Takehiko</given-names></name></contrib><aff>Department of Urology, J.A. Aichi Anjo Kosei Hospital, Japan</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Takehiko Okamura Department of Urology, J.A. Aichi Anjo Kosei Hospital, 28 Higashihirokute, Anjo-cho, Anjo 446-8602, Japan. e-mail: <email xlink:href="hiko2546@sf.commufa.jp">hiko2546@sf.commufa.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2011 The Japanese Association of Rural Medicine</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. </license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>A 20-year-old man was admitted to our hospital with persistent cough and dyspnea. He had
bilateral distention of the jugular veins, and swollen lymph nodes were palpable in the
right subclavicular region. Plain X-ray and computed tomography (CT) of the chest showed a
solid soft tissue mass in the upper mediastinum, with leftward displacement of the trachea
and complete obstruction of the superior vena cava. Mediastinal radiotherapy (1.8 Gy/day)
and methylprednisolone (100 mg/day) were started immediately. Biopsy of the right
subclavicular lymph nodes revealed metastatic seminoma. The patient was referred for
chemotherapy, which was performed with a combination of cisplatin, bleomycin and etoposide
(BEP). A partial response was observed after completion of 3 cycles of chemotherapy, but
there was no further tumor shrinkage after additional salvage chemotherapy. The patient is
being followed up on an outpatient basis and has been free of recurrence for 32 months
after intensive treatment.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Extragonadal germ cell tumor</kwd><kwd>intensive chemotherapy</kwd><kwd>superior vena cava obstruction</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Extragonadal germ cell tumors (EGGCTs) have the same histological components as their
gonadal counterparts, but a gonadal mass is not detectable by palpation or high-resolution
ultrasonography<sup><sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>)</sup>. It has
been estimated that only 2&#x02013;5% of all germs cell tumors are extragonadal. Primary mediastinal
seminomas, in contrast, comprise about 25% of all primary germ cell tumors
(GCTs)<sup><sup><xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>)</sup>. They are
frequently associated with extensive local invasion, and chemotherapy has been reported to
achieve a favorable outcome as initial treatment<sup><sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup><sup>,</sup><sup><xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>)</sup>.
In a minority of patients, the primary tumor is located extragonadally, i.e., in the
retroperitoneum or in the mediastinum. About one-third of these patients will harbor
intratubular germ cell neoplasia (TIN) (synonym: carcinoma in situ, CIS). In another
one-third, ultrasonography of the testes reveals scar tissue indicating burned out
testicular tumors, which also have to be removed. Therefore, only one-third of these
patients have definitive primary EGGCTs<sup><sup><xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>)</sup>. The most common primary sites for EGGCTs are the mediastinum and
the retroperitoneum, while these tumors have also been reported to occur in the
sacrococcygeal and pineal regions<sup><sup><xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>)</sup>. However, management of residual seminomatous GCTs after
chemotherapy remains an issue needing clarification.</p><p>Here, we report a case of primary mediastinal seminoma with complete obstruction of the
superior vena cava and no recurrence of the residual mass after intensive chemotherapy.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Case Report</title><p>A 20-year-old man was admitted to our hospital with persistent cough. His bilateral jugular
veins were distended, and swollen lymph nodes were palpable in the right subclavicular
region. A chest X-ray showed a mediastinal mass. Computed tomography (CT) of the chest
revealed a solid soft tissue mass (95 &#x000d7; 75 &#x000d7; 112 mm) [in diameter] in the upper mediastinum,
as well as a leftward displacement of the trachea and complete obstruction of the superior
vena cava (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Figure 1</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Pretreatment CT shows a solid soft tissue mass (95 &#x000d7; 75 &#x000d7; 112 mm) in the upper
mediastinum, with leftward displacement of the trachea and complete obstruction of the
superior vena cava.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jrm-6-032-g001"/></fig>). Based on the suspicion of a mediastinal tumor with lymph node metastasis,
mediastinal radiotherapy and methylprednisolone were immediately started. Biopsy of the
right subclavicular lymph nodes revealed metastatic seminoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_002">Figure 2</xref>
<fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Biopsy specimen from a right subclavicular lymph node. Well-defined tumor cells with
large nuclei and clear nucleoli and a large clear reticulum are formed as map-like
alveolar tumor cells. Cobblestone growth can be seen with lymph node involvement
surrounding the alveolar tissue.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jrm-6-032-g002"/></fig>), and the patient was referred for chemotherapy.</p><p>Lactate dehydrogenase, &#x003b2;-human chorionic gonadotropin and alpha-fetoprotein were all in the
normal ranges. Ultrasound revealed a uniform, echogenic structure of the bilateral
testicles, without any findings suggestive of malignancy.</p><p>Radiotherapy and methylprednisolone were discontinued, and systemic chemotherapy was
simultaneously started with a combination of cisplatin, bleomycin and etoposide (BEP). Since
lung function test values deteriorated after one cycle of BEP, bleomycin was excluded from
subsequent chemotherapy, and the regimen continued with etoposide plus cisplatin (EP). A
partial response was observed after completing 3 cycles, but no further shrinkage was
observed on subsequent examinations.</p><p>Salvage surgery was then considered for the residual mass because the superior vena cava
was still completely obstructed by the tumor. Although implantation of a prosthetic vessel
was required, the procedure was not performed because it was considered to be a high risk
surgery. Instead, the patient received 2 courses of vinblastine, ifosfamide and cisplatin
(VeIP) as salvage chemotherapy. On completion of the chemotherapy, the evaluable lesions
were considered to represent a "stable disease" (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Figure
3</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Posttreatment CT shows less enhancement of a smaller soft tissue mass (30 &#x000d7; 18 &#x000d7; 36
mm).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jrm-6-032-g003"/></fig>). As of December 2010, there is no evidence of residual tumor growth, new masses or
metastatic foci. The patient is being closely followed up on an outpatient basis and has
been free of recurrence for 32 months after intensive treatment.</p><p>Our patient was first diagnosed as having an EGCT arising from the mediastinum when he
presented with chronic cough and complete obstruction of the superior vena cava.</p><p>Since few patients with early germ cell tumors arising in the mediastinum have any
symptoms, these tumors are often quite large by the time they are diagnosed and the mean
maximum diameter of such tumors is reportedly 4.6 cm<sup><sup><xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>)</sup>. Seminoma accounts for about 25% of EGGCTs<sup><sup><xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>)</sup>. When patients with seminoma or
nonseminomatous tumors are treated with platinum-based chemotherapy (cisplatin or
carboplatin) and radiotherapy, the 5-year progression-free survival rate is 80% for seminoma
versus 35% for nonseminomatous tumors<sup><sup><xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>)</sup>. According to the International Germ Cell Cancer Collaborative
Group (IGCCCG) criteria, primary mediastinal seminoma without any nonpulmonary visceral
metastases is classified as a good risk tumor with favorable sensitivity to chemotherapy and
radiotherapy, and these patients have progression-free survival similar to those with
primary testicular seminoma. However, treatment of the residual mass differs between these
two groups. For primary mediastinal tumors, all residual radiological lesions should be
resected, if possible<sup><sup><xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>)</sup>, and the
presence or absence of viable tumor cells should be determined.</p><p>In 2008, Kesler <italic>et al.</italic> reported that 10 surgical deaths occurred among 158
patients who underwent additional resection of residual primary mediastinal nonseminomatous
tumors<sup><sup><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>)</sup>. Kang <italic>et
al.</italic> also reported in the same year that marked fibrosis and surrounding invasion
of residual tumor cells were detected in the majority of 29 patients who underwent surgery
for residual nonseminomatous tumors<sup><sup><xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>)</sup>. They also reported that it may be very difficult to remove the
tumor completely, particularly if it has invaded the great vessels. In our patient, salvage
surgery was considered for the residual mass after chemotherapy, but the superior vena cava
was completely obstructed by the tumor, suggesting that the operation constituted a high
risk. In addition, residual tumor cells were suspected to have invaded the surrounding
mediastinal tissue, adding further evidence for an unlikely successful operation.</p><p>Like primary testicular seminoma, primary mediastinal seminoma has a good prognosis, and
the rate of necrosis of the residual mass is as high as 92% when partial remission is
obtained after chemotherapy<sup><sup><xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>)</sup>.
When the residual mass is considered inoperable in patients with primary mediastinal
seminoma, additional salvage chemotherapy can be considered for careful follow-up of
patients after initial chemotherapy as described in this report.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bokemeyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Droz</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Extragonadal germ cell tumors
of the mediastinum and retroperitoneum: results from an international
analysis</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2002</year>;
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1864</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1873</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11919246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bokemeyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Droz</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Horwich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Extragonadal seminoma. An
international multicenter analysis of prognostic factors and long-term treatment
outcome</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source><year>2001</year>; <volume>91</volume>:
<fpage>1394</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1401</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283942</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Schmoll</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Souchon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Krege</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group> European
Germ Cell Cancer Consensus Group <article-title>European consensus on
diagnosis and treatment of germ cell cancer: a report of the European Germ Cell Cancer
Consensus Group (EGCCCG)</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2004</year>;
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1399</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15319245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>JD
</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary malignant germinal tumors of the mediastinum. A study
of 24 cases</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source><year>1975</year>;
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1162</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1168</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1237349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">International Germ Cell
Cancer Collaborative Group. <article-title>International germ cell
consensus classification: a prognostic factor-based staging system for metastatic germ
cell cancers</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1997</year>;
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>594</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>603</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9053482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kesler</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieger</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammoud</surname><given-names>ZT</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>A 25-year single institution
experience with surgery for primary mediastinal nonseminomatous germ cell
tumors</article-title>. <source>Ann Thorac Surgery</source><year>2008</year>;
<volume>85</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>378</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jheon</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Surgical treatment of malignant
mediastinal nonseminomatous germ cell tumor</article-title>. <source>Ann Thoracic
Surg</source><year>2008</year>; <volume>85</volume>:
<fpage>379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>384</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2007.09.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>