<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Respirol Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Respirol Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2051-3380</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RCR2</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Respirology Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2051-3380</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26740882</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4694603</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/rcr2.129</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">RCR2129</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Reports</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transbronchial lung biopsy (<styled-content style="fixed-case">TBLB</styled-content>) in diagnosing pulmonary alveolar proteinosis (<styled-content style="fixed-case">PAP</styled-content>): forgotten role in <styled-content style="fixed-case">A</styled-content>ustralia?</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">Transbronchial lung biopsy in PAP</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">A.<styled-content style="fixed-case">H</styled-content>. <styled-content style="fixed-case">T</styled-content>ung <italic>et&#x02009;al</italic>.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="rcr2129-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Tung</surname><given-names>Alvin H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="rcr2129-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="rcr2129-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grace</surname><given-names>Julienne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="rcr2129-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="rcr2129-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>O'Kane</surname><given-names>Gabrielle M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="rcr2129-aff-0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="rcr2129-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Karthik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="rcr2129-aff-0004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="rcr2129-aff-0001"><label><sup>1</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Respiratory Medicine</named-content><institution>Gosford Hospital</institution><named-content content-type="city">Gosford</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">NSW</named-content><country country="AU">Australia</country></aff><aff id="rcr2129-aff-0002"><label><sup>2</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Pathology</named-content><institution>Gosford Hospital</institution><named-content content-type="city">Gosford</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">NSW</named-content><country country="AU">Australia</country></aff><aff id="rcr2129-aff-0003"><label><sup>3</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Microbiology and Infectious Diseases</named-content><institution>Gosford Hospital</institution><named-content content-type="city">Gosford</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">NSW</named-content><country country="AU">Australia</country></aff><aff id="rcr2129-aff-0004"><label><sup>4</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Renal Medicine</named-content><institution>Gosford Hospital</institution><named-content content-type="city">Gosford</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">NSW</named-content><country country="AU">Australia</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold><break/>
Dr Alvin H. Tung, Department of Respiratory Medicine, Gosford Hospital, Holden Street, Gosford, NSW 2250, Australia. E&#x02010;mail: <email>alvin@UNSWalumni.com</email><break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/rcr2.2015.3.issue-4</issue-id><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>8</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> &#x000a9; 2015 The Asian Pacific Society of Respirology <copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2015 The Authors. <italic>Respirology Case Reports</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd on behalf of The Asian Pacific Society of Respirology.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy-nc"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution&#x02010;NonCommercial</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:RCR2-3-145.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="main"><title>Abstract</title><p>Transbronchial lung biopsy (<styled-content style="fixed-case">TBLB</styled-content>) is uncommonly performed in non&#x02010;malignant conditions because of its low sensitivity and small tissue samples. It is not routinely performed in <styled-content style="fixed-case">A</styled-content>ustralia to investigate idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, although it can be a useful adjunct in obtaining tissue diagnosis in selected conditions in interstitial lung disease (<styled-content style="fixed-case">ILD</styled-content>). A 52&#x02010;year&#x02010;old non&#x02010;smoker received a living unrelated renal transplant in <styled-content style="fixed-case">J</styled-content>anuary 2014 but developed insidious onset of dyspnea on exertion 1 year later. Computed tomography of the thorax showed bilateral persistent ground glass opacifications with a characteristic crazy paving pattern, although <styled-content style="fixed-case"><italic>P</italic></styled-content>
<italic>neumocystis jirovecii</italic> pneumonia was more concerning. He was treated as <styled-content style="fixed-case"><italic>P</italic></styled-content>
<italic>neumocystis jirovecii</italic> pneumonia but his initial bronchoscopy failed to confirm either diagnoses. He then went on to <styled-content style="fixed-case">TBLB</styled-content> that showed the presence of periodic acid&#x02013;Schiff staining material. We conclude that <styled-content style="fixed-case">TBLB</styled-content> is a useful adjunct to obtain histological diagnosis of <styled-content style="fixed-case">ILD</styled-content> in carefully selected patients with appropriate radiological indications.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="rcr2129-kwd-0001">Pulmonary alveolar proteinosis (<styled-content style="fixed-case">PAP</styled-content>)</kwd><kwd id="rcr2129-kwd-0002">transbronchial lung biopsy (<styled-content style="fixed-case">TBLB</styled-content>)</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="3"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>component-id</meta-name><meta-value>rcr2129</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>December 2015</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:4.7.2 mode:remove_FC converted:22.12.2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="rcr2129-sec-0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Transbronchial lung biopsy (TBLB) is uncommonly performed in interstitial lung disease (ILD) and various non&#x02010;malignant conditions because of its low tissue yield and small tissue samples in defining histological patterns <xref rid="rcr2129-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">[1]</xref>. In a recent Australian survey <xref rid="rcr2129-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">[2]</xref>, only 1% of respondents in 2012&#x02013;2013 would routinely perform TBLB to investigate idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF). Nonetheless, TBLB is helpful in certain pathological processes involving centrilobular and peribronchial regions <xref rid="rcr2129-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">[3]</xref>. Pulmonary alveolar proteinosis (PAP) is an example of these processes with its typical radiological findings including ground glass opacities, parenchymal consolidation, and reticuloseptal reticulations leading to a non&#x02010;specific but characteristic crazy paving pattern. Open lung biopsy (OLB) is unnecessary to diagnose the condition, and TBLB is a useful adjunct although bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) fluid analysis is often sufficient for its diagnosis <xref rid="rcr2129-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">[4]</xref>. We describe a case of PAP with typical radiological features and failure of an initial BAL to confirm its diagnosis but TBLB did. The case report should remind clinicians that TBLB should be considered as an alternative to OLB in patients with appropriate radiological and clinical indications.</p></sec><sec id="rcr2129-sec-0002"><title>Case Report</title><p>A 52&#x02010;year&#x02010;old non&#x02010;smoker man from New South Wales, Australia, became a recipient of living unrelated renal transplant in January 2014. His initial course was complicated by BK virus infection that resolved 3 months afterward. He had no history of any respiratory illnesses but developed insidious onset of dyspnea on exertion 12 months post&#x02010;transplantation. There were no constitutional symptoms or features to suggest infection, and he had minimal respiratory symptoms otherwise. He continued his work as a tradesperson despite his respiratory symptoms without significant issues. Cardiopulmonary examination remained unremarkable without hypoxia. A computed tomography of the thorax (Fig.&#x02009;<xref rid="rcr2129-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) demonstrated diffuse ground glass opacifications with a perihilar zonal predominance with a crazy paving pattern reported, but <italic>Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> pneumonia (PJP) appeared to be concerning in the context of immunosuppression. He was on appropriate PJP prophylaxis during the post&#x02010;transplant period. His blood tests and connective tissue screening were unremarkable except a creatinine of 128, which is his baseline renal allograft function. Echocardiogram was normal. His lung function test demonstrated mild airflow obstruction and normal lung volumes with mild impairment of gaseous exchange. A 6&#x02010;min walk test documented the absence of post&#x02010;test desaturation. He was initially managed for PJP and given clindamycin and primaquine, but bronchoscopy with BAL fluid analysis failed to establish a diagnosis. Macroscopic appearance of the BAL fluid was also normal. Given the absence of microbiological evidence to suggest infection, TBLB was performed to evaluate the histological pattern of his radiological changes. TBLB showed periodic acid&#x02013;Schiff positive stained, granular eosinophilic material in alveoli consistent with PAP (Fig.&#x02009;<xref rid="rcr2129-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The procedure was well tolerated without any significant complications. An extensive search was in progress to determine the etiology of his PAP, while he opted for a conservative management approach with ongoing clinical monitoring due to the mild degree of symptoms (disease severity score of 1).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="rcr2129-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Computed tomography of the thorax showing ground glass opacifications.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="RCR2-3-145-g001"><alt-text>figure</alt-text><permissions><copyright-holder>2015 The Asian Pacific Society of Respirology</copyright-holder></permissions></graphic></fig><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="rcr2129-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Transbronchial lung biopsy showing periodic acid&#x02013;Schiff (<styled-content style="fixed-case">PAS</styled-content>) positive eosinophilic material in alveoli.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="RCR2-3-145-g003"><alt-text>figure</alt-text><permissions><copyright-holder>2015 The Asian Pacific Society of Respirology</copyright-holder></permissions></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="rcr2129-sec-0003"><title>Discussion</title><p>TBLB was described by Andersen et&#x02009;al. <xref rid="rcr2129-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">[5]</xref> to obtain parenchymal tissue via flexible bronchoscope to investigate diffuse interstitial lung disease. Radiological indications for TBLB included alveolar opacifications, reticulonodular perilymphatic changes, &#x0201c;tree&#x02010;in&#x02010;bud&#x0201d; pattern, and the presence of the &#x0201c;bronchus sign&#x0201d; <xref rid="rcr2129-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">[3]</xref>. It is also useful in conditions where small lung fragments are adequate for tissue diagnosis, such as granulomatous diseases, cryptogenic organizing pneumonia, diffuse alveolar damage but inadequate for IPF, non&#x02010;specific interstitial pneumonitis, and desquamative interstitial pneumonia <xref rid="rcr2129-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">[1]</xref>. The size limitations of its parenchymal tissue obtained subsequently led to the procedure carried out less frequently over time. This was reflected in a recent Australian survey revealing a decrease in the routine use of TBLB to diagnose IPF from 18% of the correspondents in 1999 to 1% in 2012&#x02013;2013, in accordance with changes in international IPF guidelines <xref rid="rcr2129-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">[2]</xref>. More recently, the use of transbronchial lung cryobiopsy (TBLC) generated renewed interest in the technique <xref rid="rcr2129-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">[1]</xref> due to the ability of TBLC to obtain larger lung fragments to assist histological interpretation.</p><p>PAP is characterized by defective surfactant clearance by alveolar macrophages, leading to alveolar accumulation of lipoprotein&#x02010;rich material correlated as ground glass opacity radiology. This is superimposed with reticulations from interstitial disease resulting in a crazy paving pattern. Although this pattern is characteristic of PAP, it is non&#x02010;specific and is found in a wide variety of lesions, including cardiogenic pulmonary edema, alveolar hemorrhage, pulmonary infection, exogenous lipoid pneumonia, or bronchioloalveolar carcinoma <xref rid="rcr2129-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">[4]</xref>. Our case report clearly demonstrated that TBLB could establish a diagnosis when BAL failed to do so. Indeed, in a cohort of 248 patients 34.1% and 58.7% of PAP cases were diagnosed by TBLB and BAL, respectively <xref rid="rcr2129-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">[4]</xref>. Our patient had typical radiological features, but both the macroscopic appearance of his initial BAL and cytology was not suggestive. We postulate that the initial BAL was sampled in a zone without significant lipoprotein&#x02010;rich material, despite the area being abundant of ground glass changes radiologically.</p><p>To conclude, our case report demonstrated that TBLB has its place in the diagnosis of ILD especially when there are non&#x02010;specific, diffuse changes which in turn would allow higher yield of sampled tissue. In carefully selected cases with radiological and clinical indications, we believe that it can be considered as an alternative to OLB despite OLB being readily available in Australia. This is especially important when BAL fails to establish a diagnosis.</p></sec><sec id="rcr2129-sec-0004"><title>Disclosure Statements</title><p>No conflict of interest declared.</p><p>Appropriate written informed consent was obtained for publication of this case report and accompanying images.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="rcr2129-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="rcr2129-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Fruchter</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fridel</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>El Raouf</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names>
</string-name>, et&#x02009;al. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Histological diagnosis of interstitial lung diseases by cryo&#x02010;transbronchial biopsy</article-title>. <source>Respirology</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>683</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>688</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24750376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="rcr2129-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Troy</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chapman</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wilsher</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</string-name>, et&#x02009;al. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Current Australasian practice for diagnosis and management of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: where are we now?</article-title>
<source>Respirology</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>647</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>653</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25808582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="rcr2129-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Poletti</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gasoni</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gurioli</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, et&#x02009;al. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Lung cryobiopsies: a paradigm shift in diagnostic bronchoscopy?</article-title>
<source>Respirology</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>645</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>654</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24862226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="rcr2129-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Borie</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Danel</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Debray</surname>
<given-names>M&#x02010;P</given-names>
</string-name>, et&#x02009;al. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Review: pulmonary alveolar proteinosis</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir Rev</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>98</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>107</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21632797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="rcr2129-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Andersen</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fontana</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Harrison</surname>
<given-names>EG</given-names>
<suffix>Jr.</suffix>
</string-name>, et&#x02009;al. <year>1965</year>
<article-title>Transbronchoscopic lung biopsy in diffuse pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source>Dis. Chest</source>
<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>192</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14333652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>