<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Asian Spine J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Asian Spine J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ASJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Asian Spine Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1976-1902</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1976-7846</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Society of Spine Surgery</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25558315</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4278978</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4184/asj.2014.8.6.735</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>C1-C3 Lateral Mass Screw-Rod Fixation and Fusion for C2 Pathologies and Hangman's Fractures</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>Forhad Hossain</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>Mohammod Raziul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1">Department of Neurosurgery, Dhaka Medical College Hospital, Dhaka, Bangladesh.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding author: Forhad Hossain Chowdhury. Department of Neurosurgery, Dhaka Medical College Hospital, 32 Bokshibazar road, Dhaka, Babgladesh. Tel: +88-01711949570, <email>forhadchowdhury74@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>735</fpage><lpage>746</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>02</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 by Korean Society of Spine Surgery</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Study Design</title><p>Retrospective clinical study.</p></sec><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>We report our experience of eight patients treated with C1-C3 lateral mass rod-screw stabilization and fusion in the treatment of Hangman's fracture and other axis pathologies.</p></sec><sec><title>Overview of Literature</title><p>Different surgical approaches, both anterior and posterior, have been described for treating Hangman's fracture and other pathologies where surgery is indicated.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>All patients who underwent surgical treatment for Hangman's fracture and axial pathology where C1-C3 lateral mass screw-rod stabilization and fusion done, following reduction of the fracture or removal of the pathology were included in this series. The recorded patient management data was retrospectively studied.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>There were 8 cases in total. All were male, with an average age of 40.75 years. Hangman's fracture occurred in 6 cases (75%), one with metastatic squamous cell carcinoma and the remaining with plasmocytoma. Among the Hangman's fractures 4 (66.66%) had no neuro-deficit. Reduction and bilateral C1-C3 lateral mass screw and rod fixation with posterior fusion by bone graft was performed in all cases. In 2 cases, a C2 body tumor was removed transorally. All patients with neuro-deficit fully recovered, except one who expired in the early post-operative period. Rest of all patients were leading a normal life till last follow up.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Although the number of cases was very small with a relatively short follow up period, C1 and C3 lateral mass screw-rod fixation followed by fusion showed promise as an effective and biomechanically sound way for the treatment of properly selected Hangman's fracture cases, and may also be suitable in other axial pathologies.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>C1-C3 lateral mass fixation</kwd><kwd>Hangman's fracture</kwd><kwd>C2 pathology</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Hangman's fractures or traumatic spondylolisthesis of the axis commonly affect young people following trauma [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Nontraumatic pathologies include lymphoma, myeloma, tuberculosis, metastasis and other rare bone tumors [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In Hangman's fracture, surgical reduction and stabilization is usually indicated in cases with neuro-deficit with spinal cord compression, cases with instability, or after failure of conservative treatment. In other pathologies, stabilization and fusion is usually needed along with removal of the C2 pathology. Different surgical approaches, both anterior and posterior, have been described for treating Hangman's fractures and other pathologies [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. We report our experience of eight patients treated with C1-C3 lateral mass rod-screw stabilization and fusion in the treatment of Hangman's fracture and other axis pathologies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>All patients who underwent surgical treatment for Hangman's fracture and axial pathology where C1-C3 lateral mass screw-rod stabilization and fusion were done following reduction of the fracture or removal of the pathology from January 2009 to December 2012 in the department of Neurosurgery, Dhaka Medical College Hospital and a few other private hospitals in Dhaka, Bangladesh were included in this series. Patient management data was recorded prospectively with special attention on stabilization by C1-C3 lateral mass screw-rod. Patient history, clinical features, imaging findings, surgical approaches, preoperative findings, postoperative clinical and imaging follow up (including any complications) were properly recorded. All recorded data were reviewed retrospectively.</p><sec><title>1. Operation</title><p>Operations were performed with the patient kept under skeletal tong traction in the prone position. The head end of operating table was elevated to create a table angle of 35&#x000b0; with the floor. Cervical spine of the patient was kept in a neutral position (not in flexion or extension). Proper alignment was achieved under fluoroscopic control, and the region from C1 to C3 was exposed through posterior midline incision. The C2 root and ganglion were identified and sectioned on both sides, and the C1 lateral mass was exposed with proper hemostasis of venous bleeding. The C3 lateral masses were exposed on either side. 3.5 mm&#x000d7;28 mm polyaxial titanium screws were inserted into the C1 lateral masses on either side followed by insertion of 3.5 mm&#x000d7;14 mm polyaxial screws into the lateral masses of C3. For insertion of the C1 lateral mass screw, the entry point was the middle of the lateral mass with a 10&#x000b0; medial angulation aiming for the anterior tubercle of Atlas. For the C3 lateral mass screw, the entry point was 1mm medial to the center of the lateral mass, with 20&#x000b0; lateral and 15&#x000b0; rostral angulation. The exposed posterior surfaces of C1, C2, and C3 were decorticated, and autologous or heterogenous grafts obtained from the posterior iliac crest or heterogenous bone grafts was applied as an onlay graft, then the wound was closed in layers. Then transoral microsurgical removal of mass lesions causing spinal cord compression was performed in the same sitting, where needed.</p></sec><sec><title>2. Representative cases</title><sec><title>1) Case 2</title><p>A 60-year-old male presented with a history of neck pain, and progressive weakness in all limbs for 5 months. He was a chronic alcoholic, diabetic and hypertensive. Upon examination, he was ill looking, morbidly obese (128 kg at a height of 175 cm), moderately anemic, and had a respiratory rate of 25 breath/min. Neurologically, he was conscious and oriented. His neck was short, neck muscle was taught, and neck movements were restricted and very painful. There was tenderness at the cranio-vertebral junction. His muscle power in all limbs was Medical Research Council grade 0/5 with a sensory level C2, bilaterally. There were signs of upper motor neuron lesions in all limbs. His autonomic functions seemed to be normal, and radiographs showed destruction of the C2 body and dens with atlanto-axial dislocation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A, B</xref>). A computed tomography (CT) scan of the cranio-vertebral junction showed the C2 destruction with dislocation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C, D</xref>), while C1 and C3 seemed to be intact. A magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) showed spinal cord compression at the level of C2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>). Other investigations (complete blood count, chest X-ray, electro cardio gram, abdominal ultrasound, blood film, renal and liver function test) showed no abnormality. After the correction of anemia with proper counseling, we decided to operate using both a posterior and anterior approach in the same sitting. Under general anesthesia with transnasal fiberoptic endotracheal intubation, the C1-C3 lateral mass screw-rod fixation and fusion was performed first through a posterior approach, with a heterologus bone graft. After positional change, the C2 vertebra was approached transoraly. The C2 body and dens were destructed, and there was a vascular, soft, suckable and curatable tumor tissue at the C2 body level compressing the dura. The C1 arch and C3 body were intact. Bone grafting and anterior fixation were not performed at the time of transoral microsurgery, with the hope that a second surgery could be performed after having histopathology and non-surgical treatment, if needed (i.e., chemo or radiotherapy). The dura was decompressed adequately. Postoperatively, the patient was nursed in the intensive care unit. Histopathology reported plasmocytoma. Oncologists advised the bone marrow examination was normal, and local radiotherapy was given for six weeks postoperation. He began to recover neurologically very rapidly from the fourth postoperative day. Early postoperative imaging showed good alignment with the screws and rod in position (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Three weeks later, the patient could sit with a hard cervical collar. By the end of the third month, he became freely ambulant. Though he was counseled for the necessity of another operation, he disappeared from follow up for the next two years, as he was staying abroad. Two years later he returned home, and received follow up. He was doing well. X-rays showed reduced space of the C2 vertebral area with disalignment of the left C1-C3 screw and rod, but there were signs of posterior fusion. He was found to be doing well up to the last follow up (three years postoperation).</p></sec><sec><title>2) Case 4</title><p>A 79-year-old male was involved in an accident while riding a microbus. He briefly lost consciousness, and complained of neck pain after regaining consciousness. He was transferred to a nearby hospital, where radiographs revealed a Hangman's fracture, and the patient was subsequently transferred to our department for surgical management. He had no neurological deficits, but had tenderness over the cervical spine. His cranial CT examination was normal, and CT scan and radiographs of the cervical spine revealed a type III Hangman's fracture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A-C</xref>). MRI of the spine revealed no spinal cord compression or hematoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). In view of the unstable nature of the fracture and the presence of angulation, it was believed that immobilization with external orthosis would not be effective and hence, surgical fixation was opted for. Pre-operative traction was not attempted. CT examination of the spine showed that the fractured fragments were displaced, hence direct fixation of the pars fracture with pars screws was not considered safe or feasible. This led to the decision to use C1-C3 lateral mass screw-rod fixation and fusion. With the patient kept under skeletal traction in the prone position, proper alignment was achieved under peroperative X-ray control, and C1-C3 lateral mass screw-rod fixation and fusion was performed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A, B</xref>). The exposed posterior surfaces of C1, C2, and C3 were decorticated, autologous grafts obtained from the posterior iliac crest were applied as an onlay graft, and the wound was closed in layers. Postoperative radiographs showed good alignment with proper placement of the screws. Postoperatively, the patient developed occipital numbness due to cutting of the C2 ganglion, which was improved by six months postoperation.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>There were 8 cases in total. Details of the cases are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and in Figures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs. 1</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). All were male, with an average age of 40.75 years (range, 16-79 years).</p><p>C2 Pathologies were: six cases of traumatic Hangman's fracture (75%); one metastatic squamous cell carcinoma (12.5%); one plasmocytoma (12.5%). Clinical features included the following: History of road traffic accident in six cases of Hangman's fracture (75%); neck pain and restricted neck movements in seven cases (88.5%); quadriparesis in two cases (25%); quadriplegia in two cases (25%); autonomic dysfunction in one case (12.5%); respiratory difficulty in two cases (25%), one of mild difficultyand one requiring ventilatory support. Among the Hangman's fracture cases, 4 (out of 6) had no neuro deficit.</p><p>Investigations performed on the patients are as follows: plain X-ray with an anterior-posterior and neutral lateral view were done in all cases (100%), while flexion and extension lateral view and open mouth views were performed in 3 cases (37.5%); MRI and CT scans of the cranio-vertebral junction were done in all cases (100%). Operative procedures were performed in the cases as follows: reduction and bilateral C1-C3 Lateral mass screw and rod fixation with posterior fusion by bone graft was performed in all cases (100%); C2 body tumor was removed transorally in 2 cases (25%). During transoral surgery, the soft palate was not cut. In the 2 cases with tumors, radiotheray and chemotherapy were given postoperatively. In the C2 metastetic squamous cell carcinoma (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>; case 1), the primary site was occult.</p><p>All patients with neurodeficit recovered fully except one: an old patient with ankylosing spondylitis accompanying a type-3 Hangman's fracture and a spinal cord injury, with aspiration peumonia, expired on the third postoperative day (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>; case 6). In the case with C2 plasmocytoma (case 2) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>), the patient was unavailable for follow-up and re-surgery as advised, after receiving chemo and radiotherapy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). When the patient returned from abroad two years later, he was doing well without any complaints. X-ray showed reduced space of the C2 vertebral area with disalignment of the left C1-C3 screws and rod, but there were signs of posterior fusion. The patient was found to be doing well up to the last follow up. In the rest of the cases, all patients were leading a normal life without any symptoms at the time of the last follow up.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Traumatic spondylolisthesis of the axis (TSA) has been classified in many ways. The Modified Effendi's [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] classification is as following: type 1, non-displaced fractures with no angulation between C2 and C3, and a fracture dislocation of less than 3 mm; type 2, fractures with significant angulation (&#x0003e;11&#x000b0;) and displacement (&#x0003e;3.5 mm); type 2A, fractures with minimum displacement and significant angulation (&#x0003e;11&#x000b0;); type 3, fractures with severe angulation and displacement associated with unilateral or bilateral C2-3 facet dislocation. Using the aforementioned classifications, many conservative and surgical approaches to TSA have been recommended [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Hangman's fractures constitute 4% of all cervical fractures [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Among the different types of axis fractures, Hangman's fractures constitute 20% [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Among the different types of Hangman's fractures, type I constitutes 65%, type II 28%, and type III 7% [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Most Hangman's fractures can be treated by rigid external immobilization [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Rigid external immobilization for Levine-Edwards type I and type II fractures is recommended, but surgical intervention is favored when there is evidence of instability, as in type IIa and type III fractures; however, the reported failure rates of rigid orthosis eventually requiring surgical fusion varies from 9% to 32% [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Classically, type 1 TSA cases can be treated conservatively, but type 2 and 3 fractures require an anterior or posterior surgical treatment [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. When choosing a surgical procedure, the goals of surgery are to reduce the fracture, maintain alignment of the spine, confer stability, achieve fusion, preserve mobility, and protect the neural structures. It can be quite difficult to balance these factors, equally when determining the most effective operation to perform [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Surgical approaches to TSA include: 1) anterior discectomy and fusion; 2) posterior approaches, which include (a) occipitocervical fusion, (b) C1-C3 fusion, and (c) direct screw fixation of the fractured pars. Each approach has advantages and limitations, and the approach is chosen depending upon the degree of translation, angulation, morphology of the fracture, the patient's anatomy, and the surgeon's experience and skill [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. An anterior approach, transoral or extraoral C2-3 fusion and fixation, addresses C2-3 disc herniation and C2-3 stabilization [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. On the other hand, a posterior approach can fixate posterior and anterior parts of the C2 vertebra, and the addition of posterior C2-C3 fixation can stabilize this segment. A combined approach covers all the elements of the C2-3 segment. An alternative surgical option includes direct screw fixation of the C2 pars or pedicle. The C2 pars and pedicle connect the posterior elements of the C2 vertebra to the C2 body [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>Anterior discectomy and screw plate fixation is an effective, but not very popular technique, due to difficulty in exposing the C2-C3 region, difficulties associated with anterior screw placement in the axis, and the elimination of C2-C3 rotation [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. This approach also puts vital structures, such as the facial and hypoglossal nerves, contents of the carotid sheath and the superior laryngeal nerve, at risk [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Posterior approaches include: 1) occipitocervical fusion, 2) direct fixation of the fracture with pars screw, and 3) C1-C3 lateral mass fusion. Due to elimination of occipitocervical movements, as well as atlantoaxial rotation, occipitocervical fusion should be used only as a last resort, or as a salvage procedure [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>Direct screw fixation of the C2 pars fixes the fracture without compromising movement [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. This technique is only feasible in patients where the fracture is posteriorly located and the screw can be placed safely without risking injury to the vertebral artery [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Another disadvantage of this method is the need for complete manual reduction of the fracture intraoperatively before the placement of lag screws in the fractured pars [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Moreover, the screw passes through the narrowest part of the vertebra, which is bounded medially by the spinal cord and laterally by the vertebral artery. The diameter of the screw is 3.5 mm, while the space available for the screw varies between 5 mm and 7 mm [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The rate of vertebral artery injury for this method varies between 11% and 66% [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Direct pars screw fixation is not suitable for type III Hangman's fractures with associated disruption of the C2-C3 disc [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], because direct pars screw fixation is not effective in limiting flexion and extension if there is disc disruption [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In our patients of Hangman's fracture, we did not consider direct pars screw fixation as an option.</p><p>C1 and C3 lateral mass screw-rod fixation with fusion for Hangman's fractures has the following advantages: 1) risk of vertebral artery injury is minimized; 2) risk of displacement of the fractured fragments into the spinal canal is eliminated; and 3) conventional lateral mass screws can be used, unlike in the direct pars screw fixation technique, which requires the use of appropriate sized lag screws. Biomechanically, fusion of C1 and C3 lateral masses with C2 sparing provides sufficient stability [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]; however, it is not without disadvantages, including elimination of atlantoaxial rotation [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Though few cases of C1 and C3 lateral mass screw-rod fixation with fusion for Hangman's fractures have been reported, the efficacy of the posterior C1-C3 fusion technique was confirmed by a recent biomechanical study by Chittiboina et al. [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], who showed that both anterior C2-C3 discectomy and fusion, as well as posterior C1-C3 fusion, were equally effective biomechanically. The technique of C1-C3 fusion is based on the cervicocranial concept of Hangman's fracture initially elucidated by Effendi et al. [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and later elaborated by Chittiboina et al. [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In this concept, Hangman's fracture consists of two parts, the ventro-cranial part consisting of the atlas, the dens and the body of the axis, and the dorso-caudal part consisting of the posterior elements of the axis and C3 [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Accordingly, fusion of C1 and C3 lateral masses effectively fixes the ventro-cranial and the dorso-caudal components. Moreover, type II and type III fractures with disruption of the C2-C3 disc space and posterior longitudinal ligament are best treated by posterior stabilization, as these injuries are more likely to fail in flexion [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This technique is easy to use, and avoids the above mentioned risks of anterior discectomy and plating, as well as the risks associated with direct pars screws [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>Cranio-spinal junction tumors are rare lesions that have a natural history towards tetraplegia, usually being a serious threat to the life of the patient. The treatment of these upper cervical spine tumors involving C1 and C2 segments has improved considerably in the last few decades. The upper cervical spine tumor pathology C1-C2 imaging investigations that allow the precise definition of the anatomical structures involved in tumor pathology, together with refined surgical techniques including more and more complex fixation instrumentation allows for the complete removal of craniospinal junction tumors with the preservation or the regaining of stability [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Tumors located in the region of the upper cervical spine and the craniocervical junction may be benign or malignant, and are quite rare. The most frequent type is chordoma, which accounts for 1%-4% of all primary bone tumors [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. These tumors are found in the sacrococcygeal region in 45% of cases, on the skull base in 40%, and the remaining 15% relate to the spine (cervical, in particular). Chordoma develops from the persistent portions of the primitive notochord that is an embryological precursor of the axial skeleton [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Most often, it is soft and gelatinous, but it may also be fibrous and rigid, complicating its surgical removal [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Chordoma of the cervical vertebra typically affects the vertebral body and expands into perivertebral soft tissues and the epidural space [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. It grows slowly, and may become quite sizeable prior to the development of symptoms leading to diagnosis. Most frequently, it is diagnosed in the age group of 50-69 years, with men affected twice more often than women [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Excluding chordoma, other tumors that may affect the C2 vertebra and cranio-vertibral junction are osteoid osteomas, osteo-chondromas, plasmocytomas, histiocytoses, fibrous dysplasia, aneurysmatic bone cysts, osteo-blastomas, Ewing sarcoma, and giant-cell tumors of bone and metastases [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Presenting symptoms of such tumors are cervical pain, occipital neuralgia, medullary compression syndrome, and/or cranio-spinal junction instability. The purpose of surgery is to establish a histopathologic diagnosis, and to decompress the neural elements by attempting a total tumor removal, as well as to stabilize the cranio-cervical junction in order to improve the patient's quality of life [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Preoperative work-up included an MRI with a minimum of T1, T2, and T1 with contrast, useful both as a diagnostic tool and for surgical planning. In most situations, plain X-rays and CT scans are required for better visualization of bony structures, but the MRI is by far the most valuable investigation tool in this pathology. CT scanning is impractical for the screening of vertebral tumors, but extremely valuable for preoperative planning. Plain X-rays act as a screening investigation, and dynamic flexion-extension X-rays establish the degree of instability preoperatively and for the postoperative control of stability. Patients with suspected metastatic lesions should receive brain, thoracic and abdominal CT-scans, chest X-ray, bone scan, ultrasonogram, blood film, and bone marrow examination evaluation. Angio CT and spinal angiography are sometimes very helpful in the planning of surgery. Tumor biopsy is reserved for cases which lack neurological signs or spinal instability. A reasonable enough indication for biopsy is the suspicion of a certain histopathological type of tumor that is essentially treatable by non-surgical therapy (radio/chemotherapy or percutaneous vertebroplasty with polyacrilic cement, etc.) [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The surgical treatment for cranio-spinal junctional tumors challenges the neurosurgeon with many difficulties due to the less frequent tumoral pathology at this level, and the unique biomechanical characteristics of the region.</p><p>Surgical success depends on the location, extension, and nature of the tumor, as well as on the neurosurgeon's experience. Difficulties are seen in cases of tumors that involve the bone and ligaments at the C1-C2 level. Decisions over approach and stability methods are essential. The chosen surgical approach should ensure tumor resection, or at least tumor tissue biopsy for histopathological examination. It must also take into account the tumor location and the patient's prognosis. Patient survival is directly related to the extent of the resection and the histopathological type of tumor. If both anterior and posterior approaches are needed, they can be performed in same or different settings. A transoral approach is most commonly used for anterior cervical spinal cord decompression. A submandibular retropharyngian approach may sometimes be useful but it is accompanied by disadvantages in the depth of the operating field, the long dissection time, compression on the nerves IX, XII and on the pharynx, with possible paresis of these nerves and post operatory deglutition impairment (usually transient) [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. A postero-lateral and posterior approach is used more commonly. The advantages of this approach are that it has become familiar to many neurosurgeons as it is frequently used, and allows posterior rahisynthesis with bone grafts or metallic fixation [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. When total tumor resection is planned, total spondylectomy is done through combined anterior and posterior approaches with anterior spinal column reconstruction and posterior stabilization and fusion [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Most tumors that involve the cranio-spinal junction, especially the axis, lead to instability. Fusion techniques have been chosen according to the nature and location of the tumor, the degree of bone involvement, and the patient's prognosis. The most widely used procedure in obtaining cranio-spinal junction stability has been the posterior occipito-cervical fusion. Postoperatively, patients have been immobilized with a halo for 4 to 8 weeks. When C1 and C3 are intact and pathology only involves the axis, then C1-C3 lateral mass screw-rod fixation with fusion can be used; however, to date, report on C1-C3 lateral mass screw-rod fixation with fusion in axial pathology is inadequate. In the case of malignant disease of the axis, postoperatively patients may need radiotherapy or chemotherapy, or both.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Although number of cases was very small and the follow up period was relatively short, C1 and C3 lateral mass screw-rod fixation followed by fusion showed promise as an effective and biomechanically sound way of treatment of properly selected Hangman's fracture cases, and may also be useful in other axial pathologies.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dalbayrak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Firidin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Naderi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traumatic spondylolisthesis of the axis treated with direct C2 pars screw</article-title><source>Turk Neurosurg</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19431128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muthukumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>C1-C3 lateral mass fusion for type IIa and type III Hangman's fracture</article-title><source>J Craniovertebr Junction Spine</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24082686</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serban</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Calina</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The upper cervical spine tumor pathology C1-C2: therapeutic attitude</article-title><source>Romanian Neurosurg</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>263</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stulik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sebesta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyskocil</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kryl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelichovska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Total spondylectomy of C2: a new surgical technique</article-title><source>Acta Chir Orthop Traumatol Cech</source><year>2007</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17493408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The management of traumatic spondylolisthesis of the axis</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>1985</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3968113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Marciano</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Drabier</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadley</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonntag</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute axis fractures. Analysis of management and outcome in 340 consecutive cases</article-title><source>Spine (Phila Pa 1976)</source><year>1997</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1843</fpage><lpage>1852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9280020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadley</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Browner</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonntag</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute axis fractures: a review of 229 cases</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>1989</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>642</fpage><lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2809718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of the management of hangman's fractures</article-title><source>Eur Spine J</source><year>2006</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16235100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Effendi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornish</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dussault</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurin</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fractures of the ring of the axis. A classification based on the analysis of 131 cases</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source><year>1981</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7263741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guiot</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fessler</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complex atlantoaxial fractures</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>1999</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10505495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bristol</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Henn</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pars screw fixation of a hangman's fracture: technical case report</article-title><source>Neurosurgery</source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>E204</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15799815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hakalo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wronski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Operative treatment of hangman's fractures of C2. Posterior direct pars screw repair or anterior plate-cage stabilization?</article-title><source>Neurol Neurochir Pol</source><year>2008</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18365960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naderi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Guvencer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An anatomical study of the C-2 pedicle</article-title><source>J Neurosurg Spine</source><year>2004</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15478369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>ElMiligui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Koptan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Emran</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transpedicular screw fixation for type II Hangman's fracture: a motion preserving procedure</article-title><source>Eur Spine J</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1299</fpage><lpage>1305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20401619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaccaro</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transpedicle screw fixation of the cervical spine</article-title><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><year>1999</year><issue>358</issue><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10078131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalski</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>CC</given-names><suffix>2nd</suffix></name><name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cervical pedicle screws: comparative accuracy of two insertion techniques</article-title><source>Spine (Phila Pa 1976)</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>2675</fpage><lpage>2681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11034656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verheggen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hangman's fracture: arguments in favor of surgical therapy for type II and III according to Edwards and Levine</article-title><source>Surg Neurol</source><year>1998</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9508111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duggal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chamberlain</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Garza</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Espinoza-Larios</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonntag</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hangman's fracture: a biomechanical comparison of stabilization techniques</article-title><source>Spine (Phila Pa 1976)</source><year>2007</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17224812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brasiliense</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazaro</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonntag</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stabilization of the atlantoaxial joint with C1-C3 lateral mass screw constructs: biomechanical comparison with standard technique</article-title><source>Neurosurgery</source><year>2010</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21099568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hott</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Theodore</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonntag</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atlantoaxial stabilization with the use of C1-3 lateral mass screw fixation. Technical note</article-title><source>J Neurosurg Spine</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16925087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chittiboina</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wylen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vannemreddy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traumatic spondylolisthesis of the axis: a biomechanical comparison of clinically relevant anterior and posterior fusion techniques</article-title><source>J Neurosurg Spine</source><year>2009</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19929332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bilsky</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis and management of a metastatic tumor in the atlantoaxial spine</article-title><source>Spine (Phila Pa 1976)</source><year>2002</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1062</fpage><lpage>1069</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12004173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boriani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandiera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Biagini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chordoma of the mobile spine: fifty years of experience</article-title><source>Spine (Phila Pa 1976)</source><year>2006</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16481964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boriani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevalley</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chordoma of the spine above the sacrum. Treatment and outcome in 21 cases</article-title><source>Spine (Phila Pa 1976)</source><year>1996</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1569</fpage><lpage>1577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8817786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundaresan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Krol</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Spinal chordomas</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rengachary</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><source>Neurosurgery</source><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>McGraw-Hill, Health Professions Division</publisher-name><year>1996</year><fpage>1815</fpage><lpage>1825</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeMonte</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>E</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Callender</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Suk</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transmandibular, circumglossal, retropharyngeal approach for chordomas of the clivus and upper cervical spine. Technical note</article-title><source>Neurosurg Focus</source><year>2001</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>E10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16734402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strayer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Upper cervical spine chordoma: a case study</article-title><source>J Neurosci Nurs</source><year>2003</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14593939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piper</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management strategies for tumors of the axis vertebra</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>1996</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8613844</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>(A, B)</bold> X-ray of cervical spine later view in extension and flexion, respectively, showing destruction of the C2 body with translation in flexion and extension of the neck. <bold>(C, D)</bold> Computed tomography scan of cranio vertebral junction sagital sections showing C2 body destruction (by plasmocytoma). <bold>(E)</bold> Magnetic resonance imaging of the cervical spine TW2 sagital section showing the C2 body lesion with spinal cord compression.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="asj-8-735-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p><bold>(A, B)</bold> X-ray of cervical spine anterio-posterior and lateral view of Case 2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, after C1-C3 lateral mass screw and rod fixation. <bold>(C, D)</bold> Postoperative computed tomography scan of the cervical spine showing the sagital section <bold>(C)</bold> and axial section <bold>(D)</bold> at the level of C3, <bold>(E)</bold>-axial section at the level of C1, showing screws and rods in situ after operation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="asj-8-735-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Preoperative images. <bold>(A, B)</bold> Computed tomography scan of cervical spine sagital and axial sections, respectively. <bold>(C)</bold> X-ray of cervical spine lateral view and <bold>(D)</bold> magnetic resonance imaging of cervical spine sagital section (T1W) showing Hangman's fracture type III.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="asj-8-735-g003"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p><bold>(A, B)</bold> Peroperative pictures after C1-C3 lateral mass screw rod fixation and bone grafts <bold>(B)</bold>. <bold>(C, D)</bold> Postoperative X-ray of cervical spine anterio-posterior and lateral view, respectively, showing screw and rod in place.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="asj-8-735-g004"/></fig><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p><bold>(A, B)</bold> Magnetic resonance imaging of cervical spine sagital section in T1-weighted and T2-weighted images, respectively. <bold>(C, D)</bold> Computed tomography scan of cervical spine axial and sagital sections, respectively. <bold>(E, F)</bold> X-ray of cervical spine anterio-posteror and lateral view showing Hangman's fracture.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="asj-8-735-g005"/></fig><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p><bold>(A, B)</bold> Postoperative X-ray of cervical spine anterio-posterior and lateral view, respectively, after fixation of the C1-C3 lateral mass. Computed tomography scan of the cervical spine (postoperative). <bold>(C, D)</bold> Axial section at the level of C1 and C3, respectively. <bold>(E, F)</bold> Sagital sections showing screws and rod in proper places.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="asj-8-735-g006"/></fig><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Magnetic resonance imaging of the cervical spine T2-weighted image showing fused cervical vertebral bodies (ankylosing spondylitis) with fracture of C2 and C3 with angulation and spinal cord injury. <bold>(B)</bold> X-ray of cervical spine lateral view after ventilatory support with endotracheal intubation and cervical traction. <bold>(C)</bold> Chest X-ray posterio-anterior view, showing crowding of the ribs on the right side with bilateral lung contusion. <bold>(D)</bold> Shoulder X-ray showing fractured humeral neck with dislocation of the shoulder. <bold>(E, F)</bold> Computed tomography scan of the brain, showing anterior skull base fracture with frontal fracture and extradural hematoma with pneumocephalus.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="asj-8-735-g007"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Details of all patients of the series</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="asj-8-735-i001"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>MRI, magnetic resonance imaging; CV, cranio vertebral; CT, computed tomography; H/O, history of; RTA, road traffic accident.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>