<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Diabetes Investig</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Diabetes Investig</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jdi</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Diabetes Investigation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2040-1116</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2040-1124</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BlackWell Publishing Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25422774</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4234237</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jdi.12238</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mild-to-moderate intensity exercise improves cardiac autonomic drive in type 2 diabetes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goit</surname><given-names>Rajesh Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Paudel</surname><given-names>Bishnu Hari</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khadka</surname><given-names>Rita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>Roshan Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shrewastwa</surname><given-names>Mukesh Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Physiology, Nepalgunj Medical College</institution><addr-line>Banke, Nepal</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Physiology, B P Koirala Institute of Health Sciences</institution><addr-line>Dharan, Nepal</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Community Medicine, Nepalgunj Medical College</institution><addr-line>Banke, Nepal</addr-line></aff><aff id="au4"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Biochemistry, Nepalgunj Medical College</institution><addr-line>Banke, Nepal</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence</bold> Rajesh Kumar Goit Tel.: +977-9841401135 Fax: +977-31520690, E-mail address: <email>goit_rajesh@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>722</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by Asian Association of the Study of Diabetes (AASD) and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Aims/Introduction</title><p>The aim of the present study was to determine the effect of moderate aerobic exercise on cardiac autonomic function in type 2 diabetic patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>Heart rate variability of 20 patients with type 2 diabetes was assessed. Resting electrocardiogram for the heart rate variability analysis at spontaneous respiration was recorded for 5&#x000a0;min in the supine position before and after 6&#x000a0;months of supervised aerobic training given three times per week.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In time domain measures, the square root of the mean of the sum of the squares of differences between adjacent R-R intervals (RMSSD; 29.7 [26&#x02013;34.5] vs 46.4 [29.8&#x02013;52.2]&#x000a0;ms, <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.023) and the percentage of consecutive RR intervals that differ by more than 50&#x000a0;ms (pNN50; 10.7 [5.5&#x02013;12.7] vs 26.1 [6.6&#x02013;37.2]%, <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.025] were significantly increased after exercise. In frequency domain measures, low frequency (62.4 [59.1&#x02013;79.2] vs 37 [31.3&#x02013;43.3]&#x000a0;nu, <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.003) and low frequency/high frequency (1.67 [1.44&#x02013;3.8] vs 0.58 [0.46&#x02013;0.59]%, <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.009) were significantly decreased, whereas high frequency (95 [67&#x02013;149] vs 229 [98&#x02013;427]&#x000a0;ms<sup>2</sup>, <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.006) and high frequency (37.6 [20.8&#x02013;40.9] vs 63 [56.7&#x02013;68.7]&#x000a0;normalized units, <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.003) were significantly increased after exercise. In a Poincar&#x000e9; plot, standard deviation perpendicular to the line of the Poincar&#x000e9; plot (SD1; 21.3 [18.5&#x02013;24.8]&#x02013;33.1 [21.5&#x02013;37.2]&#x000a0;ms, <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.027) was significantly increased after exercise.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>These data suggest that three times per week moderate intensity aerobic exercise for 6&#x000a0;months improves cardiac rhythm regulation as measured by heart rate variability in type 2 diabetic patients.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Aerobic exercise</kwd><kwd>Heart rate variability</kwd><kwd>Type 2 diabetes</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Several population-based studies have shown that regular physical activity is an important component of a healthy lifestyle and lack of activity is a predictor of cardiovascular mortality<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>. Low levels of physical fitness are closely related to several chronic diseases, including hypertension, coronary heart disease, depression and type 2 diabetes<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>. Many studies have suggested the beneficial effects of regular exercise in preventing sudden cardiac death in healthy individuals and in patients with cardiovascular disease<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>.</p><p>It is commonly perceived that a regular heartbeat with sinus arrhythmia is a sign of a healthy heart. Thus, the rhythm of a healthy heart is characterized by significant beat-to-beat variability<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>. This heart rate variability (HRV) has been recognized as a powerful tool in the investigation of autonomic modulation of heart. Patients with type 2 diabetes show altered autonomic modulation of the heart as assessed by HRV<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>. Decreased HRV among patients with diabetes has been found to be predictive of cardiovascular morbidity and mortality<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>.</p><p>Exercise therapy has been shown to improve autonomic nervous system modulation of HRV in healthy individuals<xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>. Therefore, exercise training might improve cardiac autonomic regulation in a variety of clinical populations including type 2 diabetes. Thus, the main aim of the present study was to determine the effect of three times per week, 6-month, moderate aerobic exercise on cardiac autonomic function as measured by HRV in type 2 diabetic patients.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Participants</title><p>A total of 20 type 2 diabetic male patients volunteered to participate in supervised three times per week aerobic training of moderate intensity for 6&#x000a0;months. The exclusion criteria were overt cardiovascular disease, diabetic complications, chronic heart failure, hypertension, arrhythmias, known neuropathy of any other etiology, comorbid conditions (e.g. cancer, immunodeficiency, autoimmune diseases) and current smoking. In the case of smokers and alcohol users, participants with low nicotine and alcohol dependence were included<xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>. The participants with Ewing Score &#x02265;3 and vibration perception threshold &#x02265;6&#x000a0;V were also excluded from the study. Patients receiving dietary recommendations, insulin therapy, thiazolidinediones and angiotensin receptor blockers were also excluded. Ethical clearance was obtained from the ethics committee of Nepalgunj Medical College, Banke. Informed consent was obtained from all participants. The methods of measuring the parameters were entirely non-invasive, and blood was drawn only with a single use sterile syringe for biochemical parameters. The purpose, nature and potential risks of the study were explained to the participants before obtaining their written consent.</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical Examination</title><p>In a personal interview with the participants, a detailed history was obtained with special reference to age, duration, symptoms of neuropathy, diabetes-related complications and medication. All the participants were subjected to a clinical examination.</p><p>Each participant underwent the measurement of their weight and height recorded while wearing light indoor clothes, but no shoes. Using a measuring tape, waist circumference (midway between the lower rib margin and the top of the iliac crest) and hip circumference (the maximal circumference over the buttocks) were measured. Blood pressure was measured using the standard protocol. In addition, they underwent a detailed neurological examination. Non-invasive Ewing battery tests (Valsalva maneuver, heart rate response to standing up, heart rate response to deep breathing, blood pressure response to standing up, blood pressure response to sustained handgrip) were also carried out before the exercise program. Ewing battery tests are widely used for assessing cardiovascular autonomic neuropathy<xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>. Ewing scores were assigned as follows: 0 for a normal test, 0.5 for a borderline value and 1 for an abnormal value<xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>. Peripheral somatic neuropathy was assessed by a biothesiometer (Genesis Medical System, Hyderabad, India), measuring vibration perception threshold at toe, first metatarsal, third metatarsal, fifth metatarsal, instep and heel surfaces of each foot<xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>.</p><p>At the time of testing, all the participants were medication-free, stable in terms of cardiopulmonary function and showed no withdrawal symptoms. Possible diurnal variation was minimized by carrying out all tests in the same sequence between 09:00 and 11:00&#x000a0;hours, and maintaining the laboratory temperature at 26&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Training Program</title><p>The participants were enrolled in a 6-month program of aerobic exercise. Aerobic exercise (also known as cardio) is physical exercise of relatively low intensity that depends primarily on the aerobic energy-generating process. Under the supervision by trained personnel, the participants carried out thrice-a-week sessions of physical activity. In order to produce the desired metabolic effects, each exercise session lasted 50&#x000a0;min; 10&#x000a0;min of warm-up, 30&#x000a0;min of activity (brisk walking, light running) and 10&#x000a0;min of cool-down. Considering the linear relationship between heart rate and % VO<sub>2</sub> reserve, exercise intensity was set between 60 and 85% of the maximum heart rate, which was calculated by the following formula: ([220&#x000a0;&#x02013;&#x000a0;age&#x000a0;&#x02013;&#x000a0;resting heart rate]&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;% of maximum heart rate&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;resting heart rate)<xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Laboratory Measurements</title><p>The electrocardiogram (ECG) signals for HRV were recorded using an ECG machine (Magic R Series; Maestros, Mumbai, India) after a supine rest of 15&#x000a0;min. The resting ECG at spontaneous respiration was recorded for 5&#x000a0;min in the supine position at chart speed 100&#x000a0;mm/s. From ECG, R-R intervals were measured manually with a ruler. Then these R-R intervals were saved as an ASCII file. This format was readable by software &#x02018;HRV analysis software 1.1&#x02019;. This HRV analysis software, which calculates the time domain results, frequency domain results and non-linear measures of HRV, was developed by the Biomedical Signal Analysis Group, Department of Applied Physics, University of Kuopio, Kuopio, Finland.</p><p>The time domain analysis of HRV consisted of the standard deviation of all R-R intervals (SDNN); the square root of the mean of the sum of the squares of differences between adjacent R-R intervals (RMSSD) and pNN50, which is the proportion of the total R-R intervals that have differences of R-R intervals greater than 50&#x000a0;ms<xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>.</p><p>The frequency-domain analysis of HRV consisted of power of high frequency (HF; 0.15&#x02013;0.40&#x000a0;Hz), low frequency (LF; 0.04&#x02013;0.15&#x000a0;Hz) and very low frequency (VLF; below 0.04&#x000a0;Hz) power ranges<xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>.</p><p>It has been speculated that analysis of HRV based on the methods of non-linear dynamics might elicit valuable information for the physiological interpretation of HRV. One non-linear method is Poincar&#x000e9; plot. The Poincar&#x000e9; plot is a scatterplot of the current R-R interval plotted against the preceding R-R interval. Using the method described by Brennan<xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, these plots were used to extract indexes, such as length (SD2) and width (SD1) of the long and short axes of Poincar&#x000e9; plot images.</p><p>Venous blood was drawn in the morning after an overnight fast immediately before (baseline) and at the end of the training program (after 6&#x000a0;months). Plasma glucose was determined by standard laboratory procedures (BS-380; Diagnova Enzokit, RFCL, Haryana, India). Total cholesterol and triglycerides concentration were determined with a fully enzymatic analyzer (BS-380; Diagnova Enzokit, Haryana, India). Serum high-density lipoprotein cholesterol level was measured by using the phospho-tungstate precipitation method. Serum low-density lipoprotein cholesterol was calculated by the Friedewald's equation. Glycated hemoglobin was measured by ion exchange affinity chromatography (Kamineni Life Sciences, Hyderabad, India).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Different anthropometric, cardiorespiratory and biochemical variables were compared before and after exercise using paired samples <italic>t</italic>-test, and data are presented as mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SD. However, non-parametric Wilcoxon signed-rank test was applied for comparisons of the HRV and the results are presented as median (interquartile range). A <italic>P</italic>-value of &#x0003c;0.05 was considered statistically significant. Data were analyzed with statistical software <sc>spss</sc> Statistics 21, (IBM, New York, United States).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Participant Characteristics</title><p>The clinical and biochemical characteristics of study participants are shown in Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>. All these variables were significantly decreased after exercise. Figure<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1</xref> details the result from the 20 diabetic participants who completed all Ewing batteries tests before exercise.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinical and biochemical characteristics of participants before and after 6&#x000a0;months of exercise</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before exercise, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20 (mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SD)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After exercise, <italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x000a0;20 (mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SD)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes duration (years)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height (cm)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165.46&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight (kg)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.44&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.67</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.53&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.9</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body mass index (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.46&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.95&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.64</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waist hip ratio</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.27</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.64</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP (mmHg)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.84</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122.13&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DBP (mmHg)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.45&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.23&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.73</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulse rate (b.p.m.)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.65&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.23&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.88</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory rate (/min)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.78&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.27&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.66</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fasting glucose (mmol/L)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HbA<sub>1c</sub> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL cholesterol (mmol/L)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglycerides (mmol/L)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 was considered statistically significant. DBP, diastolic blood pressure; HbA<sub>1c</sub>, glycated hemoglobin; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; LDL, low-density lipoprotein; SBP, systolic blood pressure; SD, standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Number of normal, borderline and abnormal test responses in 20 diabetic participants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jdi0005-0722-f1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Heart rate Variability Measures</title><sec><title>Time domain variables</title><p>In the time domain variables, RMSSD and pNN50 were significantly increased, whereas SDNN was unaffected after exercise (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Time domain variables of participants before and after 6&#x000a0;months of exercise</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before exercise, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20 Median (interquartile range)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After exercise, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20 Median (interquartile range)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDNN (ms)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (29&#x02013;42)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (34&#x02013; 51)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMSSD (ms)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.7 (26&#x02013;34.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.4 (29.8&#x02013;52.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pNN50 (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7 (5.5&#x02013;12.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1 (6.6&#x02013; 37.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 was considered statistically significant. NS, statistically non-significant; pNN50, percentage of consecutive R-R intervals that differ by more than 50&#x000a0;ms; RMSSD, the square root of the mean of the sum of the squares of differences between adjacent R-R intervals; SDNN, standard deviation of all R-R intervals.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Frequency domain variables</title><p>The variables analyzed in frequency domain measures included power of LF and HF in ms<sup>2</sup>, and their normalized units (nu) and ratio of LF to HF (LF/HF). The HF power (ms<sup>2</sup>) and HF (nu) were significantly increased, whereas LF (nu) and LF/HF ratio were significantly decreased after exercise. However, LF power (ms<sup>2</sup>) was unaffected after exercise (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Frequency domain variables of participants before and after 6&#x000a0;months of exercise</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before exercise, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20 Median (interquartile range)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After exercise, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20 Median (interquartile range)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LF (ms<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199 (133&#x02013;337)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158 (62&#x02013;271)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LF (nu)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.4 (59.1&#x02013;79.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (31.3&#x02013;43.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HF (ms<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (67&#x02013;149)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229 (98&#x02013;427)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HF (nu)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.6 (20.8&#x02013;40.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (56.7&#x02013;68.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LF/HF (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 (1.44&#x02013;3.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 (0.46&#x02013;0.59)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 was considered statistically significant. HF, high frequency; LF, low frequency; NS, statistically non-significant; nu, normalized unit.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Poincar&#x000e9; plot of HRV</title><p>In Poincare plot SD1 was significantly increased, whereas SD2 was unaffected after exercise (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl4">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Poincar&#x000e9; plot variables of participants before and after 6&#x000a0;months of exercise</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before exercise, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20 Median (interquartile range)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After exercise, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20 Median (interquartile range)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD1 (ms)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3 (18.5&#x02013;24.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.1 (21.5&#x02013;37.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD2 (ms)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.5 (34.4&#x02013;64.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.6 (47.8&#x02013;79.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 was considered statistically significant. NS, statistically non-significant; SD1, standard deviation perpendicular to line of entity in Poincar&#x000e9; plot; SD2, standard deviation along the line of entity in Poincar&#x000e9; plot.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The present study was designed to determine long-term cardiovascular autonomic adaptation to a moderate aerobic exercise program in type 2 diabetic patients. The findings of the current study show predictable change in cardiac autonomic activity as measured by HRV among apparently sedentary, non-smoking, type 2 diabetic patients.</p><p>Cardiac autonomic function can be improved by better glycemic control, but also by physical training<xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>. Several biological mechanisms have been proposed, but the relative importance of these exercise-related mechanisms is still unknown<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>. They could possibly be related to subsequent improvements in body fat distribution, atherogenic lipoprotein profiles and blood pressure, as well as beneficial effects on muscular capillary density and autonomic nervous system balance<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>. In diabetes mellitus, physical activity has beneficial effects on both glucose metabolism and insulin sensitivity. These include increased sensitivity to insulin, decreased production of glucose by liver, a large number of muscle cells that utilize more glucose than adipose tissue and reduced obesity<xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>. One hypothesis is that regular exercise modulates cardiac autonomic control by enhancing vagal tone and lessening sympathetic influence<xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>. This shift toward greater vagal modulation could positively affect the prognosis of individuals with a variety of morbidities<xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>.</p><p>Just a few prospective studies have assessed the effects of exercise training on HRV<xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, and in agreement with the present study, those studies have found that HRV increased after training, although studies used either time domain measure or frequency domain measure for analysis of HRV. However, Loimaala <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>.<xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> reported no differences in the time domain or frequency domain HRV measures even after 12&#x000a0;months of training.</p><p>In the present study, RMSSD and pNN50, which reflect the vagal tone, were statistically increased after exercise; whereas SDNN, which reflects total variability and carries the strongest prognostic information in heart disease, was unaffected after exercise. The RMSSD and pNN50 also correlate highly with HF power, reflecting parasympathetic modulation<xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>. Thus, the time domain analysis of HRV showed increased parasympathetic activity in type 2 diabetic patients after exercise.</p><p>By using more specific information obtained from frequency domain measures concentrated around respiratory frequency, HF (ms<sup>2</sup>) and HF (nu) were significantly increased; LF (nu) and LF/HF (%) were significantly decreased, whereas LF (ms<sup>2</sup>) was unaffected after exercise. The HF component of HRV is considered to represent the vagal control of heart rate<xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>. Some authors have suggested that the LF component is a quantitative marker of sympathetic modulation<xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, and others that it is a marker of both sympathetic and vagal modulation<xref rid="b32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>. The LF/HF ratio is considered to reflect sympathovagal balance, and acts as an indicator for the sympathetic nervous activity<xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="b34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>. The LF (nu) is also considered as a marker of sympathetic nervous function<xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>. Thus, frequency domain analysis of HRV shows an increase in vagal activity and decrease in sympathetic activity in type 2 diabetic patients after exercise.</p><p>In Poincar&#x000e9; plot measures, SD1 was significantly increased, whereas SD2 was unaffected after exercise. SD1, which reflects the level of short-term HRV, is equivalent to the RMSSD; whereas SD2, which reflects the long-term HRV, is equivalent to SDNN<xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>. SDNN (Poincar&#x000e9; length) correlates with both LF power and HF power; and RMSSD (Poincar&#x000e9; width) correlates with HF power and, to a lesser extent, LF power<xref rid="b38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>. Thus, it also shows an increased vagal and decreased sympathetic influence in trained diabetic patients.</p><p>In conclusion, a three times per week, 6-month, moderate, supervised aerobic training program in type 2 diabetic patients who are clinically free of cardiovascular disease leads to significant improvements in cardiovascular autonomic function of HRV through increasing cardio-vagal tone and decreasing cardio-sympathetic tone. In addition, the present findings also suggest that thrice-a-week moderate intensity aerobic exercise is safe and could serve as a potential adjunct therapy in the management of people with type 2 diabetes. As the present study was limited by small sample size, further studies in a large number of type 2 diabetic patients are required to confirm that these beneficial effects observed in the biochemical and autonomic variables after the training period have favorable effects on the clinical outcome of the patients.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Froelicher</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical and exercise test markers of prognosis in patients with stable coronary artery disease</article-title><source>Curr Probl Cardiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7813229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pate</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physical activity and public health: a recommendation from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and the American College of Sports Medicine</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>1995</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7823386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Caspersen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physical activity and the incidence of coronary heart disease</article-title><source>Annu Rev Public Health</source><year>1987</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3555525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zipes</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellens</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sudden cardiac death</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1998</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>2334</fpage><lpage>2351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9826323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Routledge</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Townend</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heart rate variability&#x02014;a therapeutic target?</article-title><source>J Clin Pharm Ther</source><year>2002</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11975691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goit</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Paudel</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heart rate variability and vibration perception threshold in type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Int J Diabetes Dev Ctries</source><year>2013</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>139</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Astrup</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossing</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predictors of mortality in patients with type 2 diabetes with or without diabetic nephropathy: a follow-up study</article-title><source>J Hypertens</source><year>2007</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>2479</fpage><lpage>2485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17984670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kataoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Low heart rate variability is a risk factor for sudden cardiac death in type 2 diabetes</article-title><source>Diabetes Res Clin Pract</source><year>2004</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15036827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahroni</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyko</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prospective study of autonomic neuropathy as a predictor of mortality in patients with diabetes</article-title><source>Diabetes Res Clin Pract</source><year>2002</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12213355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>McCartney</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neural regulation of heart rate variability in endurance athletes and sedentary controls</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Res</source><year>1992</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1423437</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furlan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Piazza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dell'Orto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Early and late effects of exercise and athletic training on neural mechanisms controlling heart rate</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Res</source><year>1993</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>482</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8490949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pichot</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Denis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interval training in elderly men increases both heart rate variability and baroreflex activity</article-title><source>Clin Auton Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15834767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heatherton</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozlowski</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Frecker</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Fagerstrom test for nicotine dependence: a revision of the Fagerstrom Tolerance Questionnaire</article-title><source>Br J Addict</source><year>1991</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>1119</fpage><lpage>1127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1932883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baboor</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins-Biddle</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>AUDIT: The Alcohol Use Disorder Identification Test: Guidelines for Use in Primary Care</source><year>2001</year><edition>2nd edn</edition><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Martyn</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The value of cardiovascular autonomic function tests: 10&#x000a0;years experience in diabetes</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>1985</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4053936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goit</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Khadka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular autonomic function and vibration perception threshold in type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>J Diabetes Complications</source><year>2012</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22534513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Leutholtz</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between% heart rate reserved and% VO<sub>2</sub> reserve in treadmill exercise</article-title><source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source><year>1998</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9502363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Heart rate variability: standards of measurement, physiological interpretation and clinical use. Task Force of the European Society of Cardiology and the North American Society of Pacing and Electrophysiology</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1043</fpage><lpage>1065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8598068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Palaniswami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do existing measures of Poincare plot geometry reflect nonlinear features of heart rate variability?</article-title><source>IEEE Trans Biomed Eng</source><year>2001</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1342</fpage><lpage>1347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11686633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howorka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pumprla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harber</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of physical training on heart rate variability in diabetic patients with various degrees of cardiovascular autonomic neuropathy</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9217892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shephard</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Balady</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exercise as cardiovascular therapy</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1999</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>963</fpage><lpage>972</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10027821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wasserman</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zinman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ruderman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fuel homeostasis</article-title><source>The Health Professional's Guide to Diabetes and Exercise</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>Alexandria, VA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>47</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malfatto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Facchini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sala</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of cardiac rehabilitation and beta-blocker therapy on heart rate variability after first acute myocardial infarction</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>834</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9555771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhagyalakshmi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagaraja</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Anupama</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of supervised integrated exercise on heart rate variability in type 2 diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Kardiol Pol</source><year>2007</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17530559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loimaala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Huikuri</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;&#x000f6;bi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exercise training improves baroreflex sensitivity in type 2 diabetes</article-title><source>Diabetes</source><year>2003</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>1837</fpage><lpage>1842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12829654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurement of heart rate variability</article-title><source>West J Nurs Res</source><year>1995</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7863645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fouad</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarazi</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrario</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessment of parasympathetic control of heart rate by a noninvasive method</article-title><source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1984</year><volume>246</volume><fpage>H838</fpage><lpage>H842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6742149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saeki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Atogami</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reflex control of autonomic function induced by posture change during the menstrual cycle</article-title><source>J Auton Nerv Syst</source><year>1997</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9334995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specific physiological responses in women with severe primary dysmenorrhea during the menstrual cycle</article-title><source>J Physiol Anthropol Appl Human Sci</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>609</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malliani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombardi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular neural regulation explored in the frequency domain</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1991</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>482</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1860193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruscone</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Porta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Power spectral analysis of heart rate variability to assess the changes in sympathovagal balance during graded orthostatic tilt</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1994</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>1826</fpage><lpage>1831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7923668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akselrod</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ubel</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Power spectrum analysis of heart rate fluctuation: a quantitative probe of beat-to-beat cardiovascular control</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1981</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6166045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Appel</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Saul</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cohen RJ. Beat to beat variability in cardiovascular variables: noise or music?</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><year>1989</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1139</fpage><lpage>1148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2681319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Montano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Porta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between spectral components of cardiovascular variabilities and direct measures of muscle sympathetic nerve activity in humans</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1997</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1441</fpage><lpage>1448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9118511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Platisa</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reflection of heart rate regulation on linear and nonlinear heart rate variability measures</article-title><source>Physiol Meas</source><year>2006</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16400201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamen</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonkin</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Application of the Poincare plot to heart rate variability: a new measure of functional status in heart failure</article-title><source>Aust N Z J Med</source><year>1995</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7786239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Palaniswami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Poincare plot interpretation using a physiological model of HRV based on a network of oscillators</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>H1873</fpage><lpage>H1886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12384465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otzenberger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gronfier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamic heart rate variability: a tool for exploring sympathovagal balance continuously during sleep in men</article-title><source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>H946</fpage><lpage>H950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9724299</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>