<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Lat Am Enfermagem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rev Lat Am Enfermagem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rlae</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Revista Latino-Americana de Enfermagem</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0104-1169</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1518-8345</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Escola de Enfermagem de Ribeir&#x000e3;o Preto / Universidade de S&#x000e3;o
Paulo</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26625994</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4664003</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0104-1169.0669.2647</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Safety culture in the operating room of a public hospital in the
perception of healthcare professionals<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>Paloma Aparecida</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f6;ttems</surname><given-names>Leila Bernarda Donato</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>Maria Raquel Gomes Maia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>Maria Liz Cunha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>MSc, RN, Hospital de Base do Distrito Federal, Secretaria de Estado de
Sa&#x000fa;de, Bras&#x000ed;lia, DF, <country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>PhD, Adjunct Professor, Escola Superior de Ci&#x000ea;ncias da Sa&#x000fa;de, Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o
de Ensino e Pesquisa em Ci&#x000ea;ncias da Sa&#x000fa;de, Secretaria de Estado de Sa&#x000fa;de, Bras&#x000ed;lia, DF,
<country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>PhD, Adjunct Professor, Faculdade de Sa&#x000fa;de, Universidade de Bras&#x000ed;lia,
Bras&#x000ed;lia, DF, <country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>PhD, Adjunct Professor, Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Ensino e Pesquisa em Ci&#x000ea;ncias da
Sa&#x000fa;de, Secretaria de Estado de Sa&#x000fa;de, Bras&#x000ed;lia, DF, <country>Brazil</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Corresponding Author: Paloma Aparecida Carvalho Secretaria de Estado de
Sa&#x000fa;de do Distrito Federal Subsecretaria de Planejamento, Regula&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o, Avalia&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o e
Controle Setor de &#x000c1;reas Isoladas Norte - SAIN, Bloco B CEP: 70086-900, Bras&#x000ed;lia, DF,
Brasil E-mail:<email>paloma_carvalho@yahoo.com.br</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Nov-Dec</season><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>23</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1041</fpage><lpage>1048</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Objective:</title><p> to evaluate the perception of healthcare professionals about the safety culture
in the operating room of a public hospital, large-sized, according to the domains
of the Safety Attitudes Questionnaire (SAQ). </p></sec><sec><title>Method:</title><p> descriptive, cross-sectional and quantitative research, with the application of
the SAQ to 226 professionals. Descriptive data analysis, instrument consistency
and exploratory factor analysis. </p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p> participants were distributed homogeneously between females (49.6%) and males
(50.4%); mean age of 39.6 (SD&#x000b1;9.9) years and length of professional experience of
9.9 (SD&#x000b1;9.2) years. And Cronbach's ( of 0.84. It was identified six domains
proposed in the questionnaire: stress perception (74.5) and job satisfaction
(70.7) showed satisfactory results; teamwork environment (59.1) and climate of
security (48.9) presented scores below the minimum recommended (75); unit's
management perceptions (44.5), hospital management perceptions (34.9) and working
conditions (41.9) presented the lowest averages. </p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions:</title><p> the results showed that, from the perspective of the professionals, there is
weakness in the values, attitudes, skills and behaviors that determine the safety
culture in a healthcare organization.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Patient Safety</kwd><kwd>Organizational Culture</kwd><kwd>Health Services Evaluation</kwd><kwd>Surgicenters</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="9"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="25"/><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The safety of the healthcare services took over an important place in public healthcare
policies since the publication of the document entitled <italic>To err is human:
building a safer health system, published in 1999 by the Institute of Medicine
</italic>(IOM), of the United States of America (USA). Security, considered a quality
dimension and recognition that healthcare services are complex systems and that
healthcare can be highly damaging and lethal, sparked the search by experts and
researchers for continuous improvement strategies of work processes in this
area<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>In Brazil, only in 2013, safety of healthcare services was the subject of the National
Patient Security Programme of Ministry of Health (MH), as well as the Resolution of
Board of Directors (RDC) No. 36 of the National Health Surveillance Agency (ANVISA),
which established specific guidelines and actions for patient safety in the context of
the Unified Health System (SUS).</p><p>The search for quality in the healthcare services has increasingly found space in the
national and international agendas and discussions on healthcare reform. It is a gradual
and differentiated process that involves the reconfiguration in the relationships
between professionals and patients, between demand and healthcare supply, which can be
affected also by the variation in the levels of social healthcare inequality<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Strategies for improving the quality of healthcare services require systematic
evaluations. These go beyond the methodological debates on the purpose and utility of
the evaluation in decision-making, recognition of pluralism of values and distinct
points of view of the interest groups about the evaluation process<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. Thus, it is important that managers of healthcare services disseminate an
evaluative culture into organizations.</p><p>Surgical centers are considered high-risk scenarios and extremely susceptible to errors.
In this scenario, work processes are complex and interdisciplinary practices, with
strong dependence on the individual and team performance in environments dominated by
pressure and stress. Surgical complications account for a large proportion of deaths and
injuries (temporary or permanent) caused by the care process, considered
preventable<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>In this regard, to know the safety culture of the environment, in which it is intended
to operate, is an essential aspect to effect improvements. According to
the<italic>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality </italic>(AHRQ), the safety
culture is "the individual or collective product of values, attitudes, perceptions,
competencies and behavior patterns that determine the commitment, style and competence
of a healthcare organization in safety promotion"<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In turn, the climate of security is a measurable component of the safety
culture and can be assessed through the perception of professionals, since the attitudes
and values are more difficult to assess<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>To this end, the Safety Attitudes Questionnaire (SAQ) is an instrument developed by
researchers from the University of Texas (USA) that measures the climate of security
perceived by the healthcare professionals. It was designed based on the<italic>Intensive
Care Unit Management Attitudes Questionnaire</italic>, derived from the traditional
<italic>Flight Management Attitudes Questionnaire</italic>(FMAQ), used for over 20
years by the commercial aviation, to measure the safety perception of the flight
crews<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The items that comprise the SAQ were highly sensitive for assessing the
individual safety attitudes and exploration of the relationship between the safety
environment scores and results of care provided to patients. This instrument has been
used to assess the differences in the perception of proactive organizational commitment
to the safety of individuals working in the operating rooms of high and medium
complexity institutions in different countries. It contributes to the increase in the
probability of successful implementation of resource management tools and security
improvement, such as the World Health Organization Surgical Safety Checklist<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>The hospital where the study was carried out is characterized as a high complexity
service in all areas, especially in surgical procedures, in the public network of the
Federal District, a reference in the Central West region. It is in the process of
accreditation by the <italic>Joint Commission International </italic>and in the process
of implementation of several strategies to patient safety, among them is the
implementation of the WHO Surgical Safety Checklist.</p><p>This hospital was included, in 2012, in the Public Hospitals Restructuring Project (RHP)
of SUS Institutional Development Programme (Proadi-SUS). This action of the Ministry of
Health addresses the strengthening of SUS in partnership with philanthropic hospitals of
recognized quality through the training of workers and professionals, supporting to
certification and accreditation processes, for the management qualification of public
hospitals.</p><p>This study was guided by the question: what is the safety culture perception among
professionals working in the operating room of this hospital, according to the domains
of the SAQ? The objective was to evaluate the perception of healthcare professionals
about the safety culture in the operating room of a public hospital, large-sized,
according to the domains of the SAQ.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Method</title><p>A cross-sectional descriptive study with a quantitative approach was carried out. It was
used the Safety Attitudes Questionnaire (SAQ), with the version translated and validated
to Brazil. This instrument is composed of two parts: the first part contains 41
questions on patient safety perception and the second part contains questions about the
professional category, gender, age and length of professional experience<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>The 41 items of the SAQ are grouped into six domains: 1) Teamwork Environment (TWE):
quality of the relationship and collaboration between the members of a team (items 1-6);
2); Climate of Security (CS): professionals' perception about the organizational
commitment to patient safety (items 7-13); 3) Job Satisfaction (JS): positive view of
the workplace (items 15-19); 4) Stress Perception (SP): recognition of the influence of
stress factors in the performance of work (items 20-23); 5) Unit's Management Perception
(UMP) and Hospital Management Perception (HMP), both relating to the approval of
management or administrative actions (items 24-29); and 6) Working Conditions (WC):
perception of the work environment quality (items 30-32). The items 14 and 34-36 are not
part of any domain in the original instrument.</p><p>Each item of the SAQ follows a five-point Likert scale, organized and scored as follows:
totally disagree (0 points), partially disagree (25 points), neutral (50 points),
partially agree (75 points) and strongly agree (100 points ); the "not applicable"
option does not score. In the final score, 0 corresponds to the worst perception of the
climate of security and 100 to best perception. The calculation is made by adding the
answers of the items of each domain and dividing the result by the number of items of
each domain<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, after inversion of reverse items.</p><p>The study was carried out in the Surgical Center Core (NCC) of the Federal District Base
Hospital (HBDF), with a capacity of 855 beds, of which 482 are surgical beds, according
to the National Healthcare Facilities Register.</p><p>The SAQ was answered by 226 professionals (sample error of 0.05) working in the
reporting unit, including nurses, practical nurses, residents physicians and physicians
of surgical and anesthetic areas, dentists, administrative and environmental support
professionals. Inclusion criteria were: professional agreement to participate in the
study and length of professional experience in the service for more than six months.
Professionals away from the work activities during the collection period were excluded.
Participants were recruited in their own working environment, when they were asked to
respond to the instrument.</p><p>Data were collected from May to September 2013, in three shifts, by two scientific
initiation students of the final year of the nursing course and two nursing residents of
the surgical team of the hospital, trained by the researcher, who has extensive
experience in the operating room.</p><p>It was used the <italic>Statistical Package for Social Science </italic>(SPSS), version
20.0 and <italic>Rstudio</italic> 0.98.501 <italic>software</italic>. Descriptive
analysis, exploratory factor analysis and comparison between groups were carried out.
The descriptive analysis of the SAQ was carried out using the mean, median and standard
deviation (SD) of responses to items, calculated for each domain, ranging from 0 to 100.
Values greater than 75 mean strong agreement of the professionals on questions about
patient safety. The Kaiser-Meyer-Olkin Measure (KMO) evaluates how the data adjust to
the use of the factor analysis model, which resulted 0.75, allowing the use of this
analysis to data interpretation.</p><p>Along with the results of the factor analysis, there are the factor loadings that
represent the covariance between the items and factors studied, which allows to identify
which factor the item was linked. To estimate the factors, it was used the Component
Main method, in order to reduce the scope of the data and preserve the explanation of
data variability. Subsequently, it was carried out a rotation of factors to improve the
interpretation of results by means of the Promax oblique rotation.</p><p>Cronbach's &#x003b1; coefficient was used to analyze the internal consistency of the items also
called instrument reliability. The ( value ranged from 0 to 1, however, to prove the
internal consistency, it must present a value between 0.7 and 1.0. Results below 0.7
indicate that the instrument cannot measure the construct.</p><p>The research followed all ethical care foreseen in the Resolution 466/12 of the National
Health Council. The project was approved by the Ethics Research Committee of the
Foundation of Education and Health Sciences, of the State Office of Health of the
Federal District (CEP/FEPECS/SES/GDF), on 11/12/2012, with the advice number
144.024.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>The profile of participants was characterized by a homogeneous distribution among
females (49.6%) and males (50.4%), according to <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table
1</xref>. Regarding the length of professional experience, most respondents had
between 1 and 2 years (26.1%) and between 11 and 20 years (22.1%) of experience, with a
mean of 9.9 years (SD&#x000b1;9.2). Physicians are professionals with the longest length of
professional experience, followed by nursing technicians. The predominant age group was
between 31 and 50 years (63.3%), with a mean of 39.6 (SD&#x000b1;9.9). Physicians were the
professionals who most participated (73; 33.6%), followed by nursing technicians (65;
27.4%) and resident physicians (51; 22.6%).</p><p>
<table-wrap id="t1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>- Frequency of participants regarding gender, length of professional
experience, age and job title. Bras&#x000ed;lia, DF, Brazil, 2013</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="2"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Characteristic</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Frequency</bold>
</th><th colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
<bold>Percentage</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">49.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of professional
experience</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-11 months</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-2 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-4 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-10 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11-20 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21-39 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absents</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">1.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age group</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up to 30 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31-40 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41-50 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51-60 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Over 60 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absents</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Profession/occupation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Administrative</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurse</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physician</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resident Physician</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dentist</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Environmental support</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nursing technician</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">28.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">100.0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p>The total score of the SAQ, in the investigated unit, ranged from 34.5 to 74.9, per
domain, with mean of 53.5 (SD&#x000b1;13.9) and median of 52.4 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). The domains of job satisfaction (0.76), stress perception (0.74)
and hospital management perception (0.77) had significant internal consistency, with &#x003b1;
value higher than 0.7 and, therefore, ensuring the reliability of the construct.
However, the domains of teamwork environment (0.40), climate of security (0.50), unit's
management perception (0.63) and working conditions (0.58) showed ( value less than 0.7,
indicating low correlation amongst the items.</p><p>
<table-wrap id="t2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>
<bold>- Descriptive analysis and Cronbach's </bold>(<bold>, per domain, of the
Safety Attitudes Questionnaire, Bras&#x000ed;lia, DF, Brazil, 2013</bold>
</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Domains</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Cronbach's &#x003b1;</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Median</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Standard Deviation</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teamwork environment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Climate of Security</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Job satisfaction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress Perception</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unit's management perception </td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital management perception</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Work conditions </td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.84</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>53.5</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>52.4</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>13.9</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p>The scores also varied per occupational category, and resident physicians presented the
lowest mean (50.4), followed by nurses (51.1) and physicians (51.6). The highest
averages were achieved by the administrative (74.6), followed by the environmental
support (62.9) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>).</p><p>
<table-wrap id="t3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>- Score of the perceptions of professionals of the operating room, per job
title, according to the domains and total of the Security Attitudes
Questionnaire. Bras&#x000ed;lia, DF, Brazil, 2013</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Job Title</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>TWE*</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CS&#x02020;</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>JS</bold>
<bold><sup>&#x02021;</sup></bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SP</bold>
<bold><sup>&#x000a7;</sup></bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>UMP</bold>
<bold><sup>||</sup></bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>HMP</bold>
<bold><sup>&#x000b6;</sup></bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>WC**</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Administrative</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurses</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physicians</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resident physicians</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dentists</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nursing technicians</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Environmental support</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN3"><p>* Teamwork environment &#x02020; Climate of security &#x02021; Job satisfaction &#x000a7; Stress
perception || Unit&#x02019;s management perception &#x000b6; Hospital management perception
** Work conditions</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Participants were distributed homogeneously among females (49.6%) and males (50.4%).
Females predominated among the nursing professionals, while males predominated amongst
physicians. The participation of physicians (32.3%), combined or not with participation
of resident physicians (22.6%) reveals a singular characteristic of this research. In
studies with the application of the SAQ, the proportion of physicians is lower compared
to other healthcare team members<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Regarding the length of professional experience, it was observed that professionals with
over 5 years of experience account for over 60% of participants, due to the type of
employment contract of the professionals with the institution, which is a statutory
contract. The job stability of the professionals may contribute to changes in the labor
process, since the institution does not suffer the consequences of high personal
replacement rates (<italic>turnover</italic>).</p><p>A study carried out in US healthcare services showed that working conditions are
associated with injuries in patients and nurses. The registration of nursing hours per
patient/day showed a negative association with the falls and pressure ulcers. On the
other hand, the increased <italic>turnover</italic> of the staff in the unit has
increased the risk of injury in nurses, while its decrease has reduced the chances of
patient falls<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>The SAQ, in the assessed scenario, presented Cronbach's ( of 0.84, similar to that found
in the instrument translation study for Brazil (&#x003b1;=0.89). This value suggests that the
instrument is suitable for measuring the proposed construct. However, in the analysis
per domain, it was observed that Cronbach's <bold>&#x003b1; </bold>ranged from 0.4 to 0.7. The
TWE (0.4), CS (0.5) and JS (0.5) domains showed &#x003b1; values far below the recommended
(0.7), indicating low correlation between the items of these domains. This result
indicates the need for instrument application in other samples, for greater reliability
and validity of the instrument.</p><p>In a research carried out in Taiwan, the Cronbach's &#x003b1; ranged from 0.79 to TWE, 0.81 to
CS, 0.91 to JS, 0.87 to the management perception, and 0.78 to WC<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In Australia<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, Cronbach's ( ranged from 0.65 to 0.81, and in Norway<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, the Cronbach's ( ranged from 0.68 to 0.85, for the six domains that
compose the instrument.</p><p>Research has shown that item/total correlations between the domains were considered from
moderate to strong, with the exception of the SP domain<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. This domain has been poorly correlated with other domains of the SAQ,
thereby, some researchers<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
<sup>)</sup> suggest that this subscale should be omitted from the overall calculation
of the instrument and analyzed separately. However, moderate correlations of this domain
with the other domains and the total SAQ were found in the assessment of this healthcare
unit.</p><p>The total score of the SAQ ranged from 34.4 to 74.8, per domain, with average of 53.5.
The average score shows that the perception of the safety culture among professionals is
below international recommendations, which is 75 for a good perception of safety
culture. Some research using this instrument in the national and international contexts,
suggest that scores above 80 indicate a strong consensus among professionals on the
safety environment. However, those below 60 represent a warning sign for the
institutions, since they indicate the need for actions for implementing the safety
culture<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. It is worth mentioning that a study carried out in six public hospitals,
in three regions of Brazil, with 1301 professionals of medical and surgical wards, had
an average of 61.5<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>The perception of the professionals about the safety culture varied in relation to the
assessed domains. The teamwork environment presented an average of 59.1, with a mean of
58.3 (SD=18.5), a reasonable result when compared to the international literature.
Research carried out in Taiwan showed an average of 48.9% of positive attitudes
regarding the teamwork amongst hospital healthcare workers<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>)</sup> and 37% amongst respiratory therapists<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. However, in Greece, in 2011, it was found a score of 74.1 for this
domain<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. A coordinated team, with good communication and working cooperatively,
yields a more humanized care and avoid discontinuity and high-risk situations for the
patient.</p><p>Regarding the climate of security the average was 48.9 (SD&#x000b1;19.6). In Brazil, it was
found an average of 69.4<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, while other studies using the same instrument in Ireland<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
<sup>)</sup> and in the United States of America<sup>(19) </sup>showed results ranging
from 65.9 to 79.7, respectively. In Taiwan it was found an average of 21 for this
domain<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. The results of the NCC reveal a need for initiatives to promote patient
safety in this environment.</p><p>The job satisfaction domain (mean=70.6, SD&#x000b1;22.5) showed the second most favorable
outcome amongst NCC professionals, which is consistent with the findings of another
study, conducted in Brazilian hospitals (mean=77.6, SD&#x000b1;27.8)<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. By comparing with international studies<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, it is observed that in Brazil the professionals are more satisfied with
their work. This is a quite favorably result, since the job satisfaction directly
influences the safety culture and is related to fewer adverse events<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>The stress perception (mean 74.8; SD&#x000b1;25.64) is slightly below the recommended, which is
75. However, this domain was the one showing the best perception by the professionals of
the NCC. In the USA, a study assessing the differences in the perceptions on patient
safety amongst professions revealed that stress recognition and working conditions
differ according to the profile of caregivers and professionals. Anesthesiologists had
more favorable stress perception (mean=82) than nurses (mean=69) and surgeons (mean=65).
In the operating room, the perceptions about working conditions were less favorable
among nurses (mean=57) than among surgeons (mean=75)<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. A research carried out in Tehran, before and after a training course on
safety culture, in a teaching hospital, showed low stress perception by the managers,
with average ranging from 20.9 to 27.3<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>The UMP (mean=44.5, SD&#x000b1;21.6) and HMP (mean=34.4, SD&#x000b1;22.3) domains, related to the
management of the unit and the hospital, achieved the lowest scores among all domains of
the SAQ, followed by working conditions (mean=41.9, SD&#x000b1;25.9). Low scores regarding the
perception of professionals about hospital management indicate barriers between the
nursing staff and the hierarchical superiors with respect to the dialogue on patient
safety issues<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In the study carried out to characterize the safety culture perceptions,
in a national sample of agencies of Emergency Medical Services (EMS) in the USA and
Canada, it was observed a wide variation in the management perception (mean=67.2),
suggesting that this domain oscillates according to the prevailing management model in
the assessed scenario<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>In relation to the working conditions, studies carried out in Taiwan and Tehran obtained
scores of 31.8 and 59.1, respectively, among hospital workers<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
<sup>)</sup>, both considered low. In Tehran, this domain achieved a higher score, after
a process of education, increasing the average from 59.1 to 84.5<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Low perception in relation to the unit's management, hospital management and working
conditions suggests that professionals working in healthcare do not notice any
commitment from the institution's management with the latent factors of safety culture.
It also indicates the need for interventions to change this culture, such as continuing
education processes. The SAQ results showed that HMP and UMP domains presented low
correlation between the items that comprise them.</p><p>Healthcare organizations are highly complex systems, and therefore, need to implement a
management model focused on patient safety. Studies suggest that SAQ results may provide
a useful starting point by assessing the safety culture, because they serve as a
criterion to guide the needs and opportunities for quality improvement and patient
safety<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Systematic monitoring of safety culture can contribute to promoting teamwork and safe
care throughout the patient's stay in the service. It is emphasized that, the
interpretation and analysis of results are essential, as the average score of the SAQ
demonstrates that all domains are equally important and that poor performance in one
domain (climate of security) can be compensated by a good performance in other domain
(job satisfaction)<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p><p>In high reliability organizations, such as commercial aviation and nuclear energy,
climate of safety is a proactive measure, which supplements traditional retrospective
metrics such as number of deaths and accidents<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
<sup>)</sup>. In this sense, measurement of the climate of safety among healthcare
professionals supplements the retrospective metrics related to patient safety, such as
the number of adverse events, allowing the recognition of the system's weaknesses, as
well as the dimensions in which the service needs to invest more intensely. The
development of an organizational culture that prioritizes safety is critical to the
consolidation of strategies to improve the quality of the patient safety<sup>(</sup>
<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
<sup>)</sup>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The results of this study demonstrate, in the perspective of the professionals, weakness
in the values, attitudes, skills, competencies and behaviors that determine the safety
culture in a healthcare organization. It was observed a detachment from the hospital
management and the unit management, in relation to professionals, poor working
conditions and negative safety culture. Consistent interventions in these aspects are
suggested to provide a safe environment for both professionals and patients. These
results may be useful for the managers in the area, since they point out directions and
alternatives for promoting patient safety, such as communication among their teams and
introduction of new tools, such as the WHO Surgical Safety Checklist.</p><p>The limitations of this study include the use of perceptions rather than personal
behavior and lack of use of assistance results. It is suggested that follow-up surveys
on safety culture are used to assess the progress in the implementation of processes to
improve the surgical care and patient safety, as well as studies on adverse events and
incidents.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>To the professionals who participated in this study.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1" fn-type="other"><label>1</label><p> Paper extracted from master's thesis "Avalia&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da cultura de seguran&#x000e7;a entre
profissionais do centro cir&#x000fa;rgico de um hospital de porte especial: elementos para a
melhoria da qualidade do cuidado aos idosos submetidos a procedimentos cir&#x000fa;rgicos",
presented to Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Ensino e Pesquisa em Ci&#x000ea;ncias da Sa&#x000fa;de, Secretaria de Estado
de Sa&#x000fa;de do Distrito Federal, Bras&#x000ed;lia, DF, Brazil.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B01"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Corrigan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><source>To Err is Human: building a safer health system</source><publisher-loc>Washington (DC)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Committee on Quality of Health Care, Institute of Medicine, National
Academy Press</publisher-name><year>2000</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B02"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serapioni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Avalia&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da qualidade em sa&#x000fa;de</article-title><source>Reflex&#x000f5;es te&#x000f3;rico-metodol&#x000f3;gicas para uma abordagem multidimensional. Rev Cr&#x000ed;t
Ci&#x000ea;nc Soc.</source><year>2009</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>82</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B03"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leape</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawthers</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell Localio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The nature of adverse events in hospitalized patients-results of the
Harvard Medical Practice Study II</article-title><source>N Engl J Med.</source><year>1991</year><volume>324</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1824793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B04"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sammer</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lykens</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mains</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lackan</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What is patient safety culture? A review of the
literature</article-title><source>J Nurs Scholarsh.</source><year>2010</year><volume>42</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20618600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B05"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sexton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Helmreich</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Neilands</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vella</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Safety Attitudes Questionnaire: psychometric properties,
benchmarking data, and emerging research</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><issue>44</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16403235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B06"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carney</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Neily</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagian</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changing Perceptions of Safety Climate in the Operating Room With the
Veterans Health Administration Medical Team Training Program</article-title><source>Am J Med Qual.</source><year>2011</year><volume>26</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21447836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B07"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carney</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Neily</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagian</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in Nurse and Surgeon Perceptions of Teamwork: Implications
for Use of a Briefing Checklist in the OR</article-title><source>AORN J.</source><year>2010</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>722</fpage><lpage>729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20510945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B08"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bleakley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobbs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards culture change in the operating theatre: Embedding a complex
educational intervention to improve teamwork climate</article-title><source>Med Teach.</source><year>2012</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>e635</fpage><lpage>ee40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22905664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B09"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>REFL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassiani</surname><given-names>SHB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Question&#x000e1;rio Atitudes de Seguran&#x000e7;a: Adapta&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o transcultural do Safety
Attitudes Questionnaire - Short Form 2006 para o Brasil</article-title><source>Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem</source><year>2012</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>582</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deilk&#x000e5;s</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofoss</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patient safety culture lives in departments and wards: Multilevel
partitioning of variance in patient safety culture</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20356351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deilkas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofoss</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychometric properties of the Norwegian version of the Safety
Attitudes Questionnaire (SAQ), Generic version (Short Form 2006)</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18808693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominici</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnew</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerwin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Morlock</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do nurse and patient injuries share common antecedents? An analysis of
associations with safety climate and working conditions</article-title><source>BMJ Qual Saf.</source><year>2012</year><volume>21</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>111</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wung</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hospital safety culture in Taiwan: a nationwide survey using Chinese
version safety attitude questionnaire</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20698965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaboyer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Di</surname><given-names>Chamberlain</given-names></name><name><surname>Hewson-Conroy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Grealy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Elderkin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brittin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety culture in Australian Intensive Care Units: establishing a
baseline for quality improvement</article-title><source>Am J Crit Care.</source><year>2013</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23455858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A dissonant scale: stress recognition in the SAQ</article-title><source>BMC Res Notes.</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>302</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23902850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shie</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patient Safety attitudes among respiratory therapists in
Taiwan</article-title><source>Respir Care. Dec.</source><year>2011</year><volume>56</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1924</fpage><lpage>1929</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raftopoulos</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavlakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety climate in 5 intensive care units: a nationwide hospital survey
using the Greek-Cypriot version of the Safety Attitudes
Questionnaire</article-title><source>J Crit Care.</source><year>2013</year><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22762933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Relihan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Glynn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Silke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measuring and benchmarking safety culture: application of the safety
attitudes questionnaire to an acute medical admissions unit</article-title><source>Ir J Med Sci.</source><year>2009</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19437091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Utility of patient safety case finding methods and associations among
organizational safety climate, nurse injuries, and errors</source><publisher-loc>Baltimore (MD)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University</publisher-name><year>2008</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azimi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahadori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of Safety Culture Education on Improvement of Managers'
Attitudes towards Patients' Safety</article-title><source>Int J Collab Res Intern Med Public Health.</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>226</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rigobello</surname><given-names>MCG</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>REFL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassiani</surname><given-names>SHB</given-names></name><name><surname>Galon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Capucho</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Deus</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clima de seguran&#x000e7;a do paciente: percep&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o dos profissionais de
enfermagem</article-title><source>Acta Paul Enferm.</source><year>2012</year><volume>25</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>728</fpage><lpage>735</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairbanks</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Simeone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation in emergency medical services workplace safety
culture</article-title><source>Prehosp Emerg Care.</source><year>2010</year><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20809688</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Profit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Etchegaray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sexton</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hysong</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Safety Attitudes Questionnaire as a tool for benchmarking safety
culture in the NICU</article-title><source>Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonat Ed.</source><year>2012</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>132</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frankel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grillo</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pittman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Horowitz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Revealing and resolving patient safety defects: The impact fo
leadership walkrounds on frontline caregiver assessments of paciente
safety</article-title><source>Health Serv Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>43</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2050</fpage><lpage>2066</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18671751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Speroff</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nwosu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Greevy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinger</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organizational culture: variation across hospitals and connection to
patient safety climate</article-title><source>Qual Saf Health Care.</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21127115</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>