<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chin Med J (Engl)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Chin. Med. J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CMJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Chinese Medical Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0366-6999</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications &#x00026; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28229987</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5339929</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CMJ-130-559</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0366-6999.200554</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Kinetics of Hepatitis B Surface Antigen Level in Chronic Hepatitis B Patients who Achieved Hepatitis B Surface Antigen Loss during Pegylated Interferon Alpha-2a Treatment</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Ming-Hui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Lu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Xiao-Jing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Yao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Ge</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Shu-Ling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Ru-Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Lei-Ping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Zhen-Zhen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>Wen-Hao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Shu-Jing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Yao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Liver Diseases Center, Beijing Ditan Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing 100015, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Clinical Test Center, Beijing Ditan Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing 100015, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Yao Xie, Liver Diseases Center, Beijing Ditan Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing 100015, China E-Mail: <email xlink:href="xieyao00120184@sina.com">xieyao00120184@sina.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>05</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>130</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>565</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2017 Chinese Medical Journal</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background:</title><p>Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) loss/seroconversion is considered to be the ideal endpoint of antiviral therapy and the ultimate treatment goal in chronic hepatitis B (CHB). This study aimed to assess the patterns of HBsAg kinetics in CHB patients who achieved HBsAg loss during the treatment of pegylated interferon (PEG-IFN) &#x003b1;-2a.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Methods:</title><p>A total of 150 patients were enrolled, composing of 83 hepatitis B envelope antigen (HBeAg)-positive and 67 HBeAg-negative patients. Patients were treated with PEG-IFN &#x003b1;-2a180 &#x003bc;g/week until HBsAg loss/seroconversion was achieved, which occurred within 96 weeks. Serum hepatitis B virus deoxyribonucleic acid and serological indicators (HBsAg, anti-HBs, HBeAg, and anti-HBe) were determined before and every 3 months during PEG-IFN &#x003b1;-2a treatment. Biochemical markers and peripheral blood neutrophil and platelet counts were tested every 1&#x02013;3 months.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>Baseline HBsAg levels were 2.5 &#x000b1; 1.3 log IU/ml, and decreased rapidly at 12 and 24 weeks by 48.3% and 88.3%, respectively. The mean time to HBsAg loss was 54.2 &#x000b1; 30.4 weeks, though most patients needed extended treatment and 30.0% of HBsAg loss occurred during 72&#x02013;96 weeks. Baseline HBsAg levels were significantly higher in HBeAg-positive patients (2.9 &#x000b1; 1.1 log IU/ml) compared with HBeAg-negative patients (2.0 &#x000b1; 1.3 log IU/ml; <italic>t</italic> = 4.733, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), but the HBsAg kinetics were similar. Patients who achieved HBsAg loss within 48 weeks had significantly lower baseline HBsAg levels and had more rapid decline of HBsAg at 12 weeks compared to patients who needed extended treatment to achieve HBsAg loss.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusions:</title><p>Patients with lower baseline HBsAg levels and more rapid decline during early treatment with PEG-IFN are more likely to achieve HBsAg loss during 96 weeks of treatment, and extended therapy longer than 48 weeks may be required to achieve HBsAg loss.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Chronic Hepatitis B</kwd><kwd>Hepatitis B Surface Antigen</kwd><kwd>Kinetics</kwd><kwd>Pegylated Interferon Alfa-2a</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>I<sc>ntroduction</sc></title><p>Chronic hepatitis B (CHB) is a serious liver disease worldwide and is the leading cause of cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC).[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Antiviral therapy is the most effective intervention to slow the disease progression and preventing the occurrence of hepatic cancer and cirrhosis. Hepatitis B envelope antigen (HBeAg) seroconversion may be a strong predictor of improved clinical outcome in HBeAg-positive patients after interferon (IFN) treatment.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] However, a long-term follow-up study showed cumulative probabilities of hepatitis relapse in inactive HBsAg carriers of 10.2%, 17.4%, 19.3%, 20.2%, and 20.2% after 5, 10, 15, 20, and 25 years of follow-up, respectively, with an annual rate of 1.55%.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] Another long-term longitudinal study (up to 23 years) showed that 1&#x02013;17% of inactive carriers reverted back to HBeAg-positive chronic hepatitis.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Cirrhosis and HCC may still develop in some inactive hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) carriers.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] Interestingly, no cirrhosis or HCC occurred in patients with HBsAg loss after IFN treatment, indicating that HBsAg clearance is currently the only parameter associated with an excellent long-term prognosis.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] HBsAg loss/seroconversion is considered to be the ideal endpoint of antiviral therapy in both HBeAg-positive and -negative patients,[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and the ultimate treatment goal in CHB.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] However, HBsAg loss is rare in the natural course of CHB infection, with an annual rate of only 1.15%,[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] though treatment with pegylated (PEG)-IFN &#x003b1;-2a for 48 weeks can increase the incidence of HBsAg loss to 3%.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</p><p>PEG-IFN &#x003b1;-2a treatment is expensive and may be associated with adverse effects, and it is, therefore, crucial to identify those patients most likely to achieve HBsAg loss as a result of IFN-based therapy.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</p><p>We performed a retrospective study to assess the clinical characteristics and patterns of HBsAg kinetics in 150 CHB patients who achieved HBsAg loss/seroconversion during treatment with PEG-IFN &#x003b1;-2a. As a retrospective study, there were no shedding cases or dropouts in our entire study. In this study, only the data for clinical indicators were collected from the CHB patients during the IFN-treatment period, and all patients are currently being followed up. To the best of our knowledge and PubMed search results, this is the largest study enrolled 150 HBsAg loss/seroconversion patients during PEG-IFN &#x003b1;-2a treatment in the world.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec1-2"><title>M<sc>ethods</sc></title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Patients</title><p>The study population comprised 150 consecutive patients with CHB who achieved HBsAg loss/seroconversion during 96 weeks of PEG-IFN &#x003b1;-2a therapy at the Department of Hepatology of Beijing Ditan Hospital from December 2008 to May 2016. All patients had no contraindication to PEG-IFN therapy, aged from 18 to 55 years. HBsAg loss is designated as HBsAg from positive to negative, and anti-HBs is still negative; whereas, HBsAg seroconversion is designated as HBsAg from positive to negative, and the anti-HBs from negative to positive. Participants included na&#x000ef;ve patients, patients reached undetectable levels of serum hepatitis B virus deoxyribonucleic acid (HBV DNA) on nucleoside (acid) analogs (NA) treatment and those were HBV DNA-positive on NA treatment composing of relapse, resistance, or poor response.</p><p>All patients were positive for HBsAg and negative for anti-HBs before treatment of PEG-IFN &#x003b1;-2a. The exclusion criteria included active consumption of alcohol and/or drugs, coinfection with human immunodeficiency virus or hepatitis C virus, cirrhosis, autoimmune hepatitis, evidence of neoplastic liver disease, and contraindications to IFN.</p><p>Patients received PEG-IFN &#x003b1;-2a 180 &#x003bc;g/week by subcutaneous injection until HBsAg loss/seroconversion was achieved. Serum HBV DNA and serological indicators (HBsAg, anti-HBs, HBeAg, and anti-HBe) were determined before and every 3 months during PEG-IFN &#x003b1;-2a treatment. Biochemical markers and peripheral blood neutrophil and platelet counts were tested every 1&#x02013;3 months. HBsAg loss was defined as HBsAg &#x0003c;0.05 IU/ml, and seroconversion was defined as HBsAg loss with anti-HBs level &#x02265;10 mIU/ml. Undetectable serum HBV DNA after treatment was considered as a response. The study was conducted according to the guidelines of the <italic>Declaration of Helsinki</italic> and approved by the Ethics Committees of Beijing Ditan Hospital, Capital Medical University. All patients gave their written informed consent.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Laboratory measurements</title><p>HBsAg was quantified using the Architect HBsAg QT assay (Abbott Laboratories, Abbott Park, IL, USA; dynamic range, 0.05&#x02013;250.00 IU/ml). If HBsAg levels were &#x0003e;250 IU/ml, samples were diluted 1:500 with Architect HBsAg diluents to obtain a reading within the range of the calibration curve. Anti-HBs (range 0&#x02013;1000 mIU/ml), HBeAg, and anti-HBe were detected using Abbott Architect i2000 kits (Abbott Laboratories), based on an automated chemiluminescent microparticle immunoassay. Serum HBV DNA was quantitated using a commercially available real-time fluorescence quantitative polymerase chain reaction kit with a limit of detection of 500 copies/ml (Piji Company, Shenzhen, China). Liver function parameters, including serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase, albumin, and total bilirubin levels, were measured using an automated biochemical analyzer (Hitachi 7600-11; Hitachi, Tokyo, Japan). Peripheral blood neutrophils and platelets were counted using an automatic blood cell analyzer (Beckman Coulter LH750, USA).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS (version 11.5, SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). Serum HBV DNA levels and HBsAg concentrations were logarithmically transformed for analysis. Continuous variables were expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (SD) or median (range), and categorical variables as absolute and relative frequencies. Characteristics were compared between groups using Mann-Whitney or two-sample Student's <italic>t</italic>-tests for analysis of continuous variables, and Chi-square or Fisher's exact tests for analysis of categorical variables and Mann-Whitney and two-sample Student's <italic>t</italic>-tests for analysis of continuous variables, as appropriate. A two-sided <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>R<sc>esults</sc></title><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Baseline characteristics</title><p>Among a total of 1215 CHB patients, 680 HBeAg-positive and 535 HBeAg-negative, treated with PEG-IFN &#x003b1;-2a, 150 patients composing 83 HBeAg-positive and 67 HBeAg-negative patients who obtained HBsAg loss/seroconversion during PEG-IFN &#x003b1;-2a treatment were enrolled for analysis. One hundred and one patients were na&#x000ef;ve, and 49 patients experienced NA treatment (20 lamivudine, 18 entecavir, 8 adefovir dipivoxil, and 3 telbivudine) for a median of 24 months (range: 6&#x02013;108 months), in which 38 patients with undetectable HBV DNA load and 12 patients with positive for serum HBV DNA load.</p><p>The baseline HBsAg level in all patients was 2.5 &#x000b1; 1.3 log IU/ml, and the levels were significantly higher in HBeAg-positive (2.9 &#x000b1; 1.1 log IU/ml) compared with HBeAg-negative patients (2.0 &#x000b1; 1.3 log IU/ml; <italic>t</italic> = 4.733, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). The overall baseline serum HBV DNA load was 5.3 &#x000b1; 1.8 log copies/ml, and this was also significantly higher in HBeAg-positive (5.9 &#x000b1; 1.6 log copies/ml) than in HBeAg-negative patients (4.3 &#x000b1; 1.7 log copies/ml; <italic>t</italic> = 4.249, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). Baseline HBsAg levels were significantly lower in patients with undetectable HBV DNA on NA treatment compared with patients who remained serum HBV DNA-positive (1.8 &#x000b1; 1.3 log IU/ml vs. 2.7 &#x000b1; 1.2 log IU/ml; <italic>t</italic> = 4.010, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). The mean serum ALT level was 219.6 &#x000b1; 355.0 U/L, and 25.3% of patients had ALT levels &#x02265;5 upper limit of normal (ULN), including 15.3% of patients with &#x02265;10 ULN [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic and baseline characteristics of study population</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All patients (<italic>n</italic> = 150)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HBeAg-positive patients (<italic>n</italic> = 83)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HBeAg-negative patients (<italic>n</italic> = 67)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Statistical values</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years), mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.3 &#x000b1; 10.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8 &#x000b1; 10.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4 &#x000b1; 11.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.198*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender (male/female), <italic>n</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106/44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54/29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52/15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA-na&#x000ef;ve, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (67.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (63.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (71.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.382</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients reached viral response on-NAs, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (24.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (25.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (23.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040<sup>&#x02020;</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.841</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline HBV DNA load (log copies/ml), mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 &#x000b1; 1.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 &#x000b1; 1.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3 &#x000b1; 1.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.249*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT levels</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Values (U/L), mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219.6 &#x000b1; 355.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259.4 &#x000b1; 363.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170.3 &#x000b1; 340.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.535*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Values (U/L), median (Q1&#x02013;Q3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (28&#x02212;201)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (42&#x02212;223)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (21&#x02212;98)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003c;1 ULN, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (34.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (21.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (49.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;1 ULN &#x02264;values &#x0003c;2 ULN, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (19.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (18.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (20.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2 ULN &#x02264;values &#x0003c;5 ULN, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (21.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (28.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (11.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;5 ULN &#x02264;values &#x0003c;10 ULN, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (10.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (13.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (6.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02265;10 ULN, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (15.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (18.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (11.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline HBsAg level</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Values (log IU/ml), mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 &#x000b1; 1.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 &#x000b1; 1.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 &#x000b1; 1.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.733*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003c;1 log IU/ml, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (10.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (16.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.797<sup>&#x02020;</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="5" valign="top" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;1 log IU/ml &#x02264;values &#x0003c;2 log IU/ml, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (18.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (12.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (26.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2 log IU/ml &#x02264;values &#x0003c;3 log IU/ml, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (32.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (28.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (35.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;3 log IU/ml &#x02264;values &#x0003c;4 log IU/ml, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (31.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (39.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (20.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02265;4 log IU/ml, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (0.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (14.5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*Student&#x02019;s ttest; <sup>&#x02020;</sup>Chi-square test; others using Fisher&#x02019;s exact test. NAs: Nucleoside (acids) analogues. SD: Standard deviation; HBsAg: Hepatitis B surface antigen; ALT: Alanine aminotransferase; ULN: Upper limit of normal; HBV DNA: Hepatitis B virus deoxyribonucleic acid.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Virological response</title><p>Among 112 patients who were HBV DNA-positive before treatment, serum HBV DNA reached undetectable levels within 60 weeks (median: 15; Q1, Q3: 11&#x02013;26), and cumulatively, 34.8%, 72.3%, and 91.1% of viral response occurred at 12, 24, and 48 weeks [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>]. The time to viral response was significantly longer in HBeAg-positive patients compared to HBeAg-negative patients (18.5 weeks vs. 14.0 weeks; <italic>t</italic> = 3.081, <italic>P</italic> = 0.003) [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>].</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Viral response during treatment. Most patients achieved hepatitis B virus deoxyribonucleic acid response after 24 weeks treatment (a), and all patients reached serum hepatitis B virus deoxyribonucleic acid undetectable within 60 weeks of treatment (b).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMJ-130-559-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Viral and HBsAg responses during treatment</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All patients (<italic>n</italic> = 150)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HBeAg-positive patients (<italic>n</italic> = 83)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HBeAg-negative patients (<italic>n</italic> = 67)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to viral response (weeks)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.081</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.7 &#x000b1; 13.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.8 &#x000b1; 15.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2 &#x000b1; 9.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Median (Q1&#x02013;Q3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0 (11.0&#x02013;26.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 (11.0&#x02013;37.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0 (11.0&#x02013;20.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HBsAg decrease at 12 weeks (log IU/ml)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.899</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.370</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 &#x000b1; 1.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7 &#x000b1; 1.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 &#x000b1; 1.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Median (Q1&#x02013;Q3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.2&#x02013;2.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.2&#x02013;2.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (0.3&#x02013;2.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of HBsAg decline at 12 weeks (%), median (Q1&#x02013;Q3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.3 (47.2&#x02013;99.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.7 (34.0&#x02013;99.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.3 (47.2&#x02013;99.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.379</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.171</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HBsAg decline at 24 weeks (log IU/ml)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.286</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.775</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 &#x000b1; 1.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 &#x000b1; 1.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 &#x000b1; 1.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Median (Q1&#x02013;Q3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (1.1&#x02013;3.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9 (0.9&#x02013;3.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 (1.2&#x02013;3.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of HBsAg decline at 24 weeks (%), median (Q1&#x02013;Q3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.3 (60.9&#x02013;100.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.9 (53.5&#x02013;100.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.3 (70.4&#x02013;100.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.066</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.948</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time HBsAg loss (weeks)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.905</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.2 &#x000b1; 30.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.6 &#x000b1; 29.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5 &#x000b1; 29.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Median (Q1&#x02013;Q3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.0 (25.0&#x02013;80.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.0 (38.0&#x02013;85.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.0 (21.0&#x02013;71.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients with seroconversion, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (78.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (80.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (74.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.430*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to HBsAg seroconversion (weeks)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.420</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Mean &#x000b1; SD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.5 &#x000b1; 28.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.9 &#x000b1; 28.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.3 &#x000b1; 27.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Median (Q1&#x02013;Q3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.5 (28.0&#x02013;77.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5 (39.0&#x02013;85.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.5 (24.0&#x02013;70.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*Fisher&#x02019;s exact test. SD: Standard deviation; HBsAg: Hepatitis B surface antigen.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Treatment time to hepatitis B surface antigen clearance</title><p>The study population comprised 150 consecutive patients with CHB who all achieved HBsAg loss during PEG-IFN &#x003b1;-2a therapy. Among 150 patients, there were 117 patients who achieved HBsAg seroconversion. The treatment time to HBsAg loss and seroconversion were 54.2 &#x000b1; 30.3 weeks (median, 53.0; Q1, Q3, 25.0&#x02013;80.0) and 56.5 &#x000b1; 28.5 weeks (median, 55.5; Q1, Q3, 28.0&#x02013;77.0), respectively. However, 55.3% of HBsAg loss/seroconversion occurred after extended treatment (longer than 48 weeks), and 30.0% occurred during weeks 72&#x02013;96 of treatment [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>]. The time to HBsAg loss was significantly longer in HBeAg-positive patients compared with HBeAg-negative patients (62.0 weeks vs. 41.0 weeks; <italic>t</italic> = 2.905, <italic>P</italic> = 0.004) [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>], and patients with higher HBsAg levels needed longer treatment than patients with lower HBsAg levels to achieve HBsAg loss (<italic>F</italic> = 10.091, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>].</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Proportion of and time to hepatitis B surface antigen loss during pegylated interferon &#x003b1;-2a treatment. More than half of hepatitis B surface antigen loss occurred after extended treatment and one-third of patients needed 96 weeks of treatment to achieving hepatitis B surface antigen loss.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMJ-130-559-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Time to hepatitis B surface antigen loss on the basis of baseline hepatitis B surface antigen levels. The longer treatment time was needed in patients with higher baseline of hepatitis B surface antigen level for hepatitis B surface antigen loss.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMJ-130-559-g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Serum hepatitis B surface antigen kinetics</title><p>Among all patients, HBsAg levels decreased significantly at 12 and 24 weeks, with declines of 1.6 &#x000b1; 1.5 log IU/ml and 2.3 &#x000b1; 1.4 log IU/ml (48.3% and 88.3% of baseline), respectively [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>]. HBsAg levels at 48 weeks reached &#x0003c;100 IU/ml in 93.3% (140/150) of patients and only one patient had HBsAg levels &#x0003e;1000 IU/ml. The kinetics of HBsAg decline was similar in HBeAg-positive and -negative patients [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>]. In HBeAg-positive patients, HBsAg levels decreased by 40.7% and 85.9% of baseline, at 12 and 24 weeks, and those in HBeAg-negative patients were 56.3% and 92.3% [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>].</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Kinetics of hepatitis B surface antigen levels during pegylated interferon treatment. HBeAg-positive patients had higher hepatitis B surface antigen level baseline than HBeAg-negative patients, however, their kinetics during treatment were similar.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMJ-130-559-g004"/></fig><p>However, baseline HBsAg levels were significantly lower and HBsAg decrease at 12 weeks was more rapid in patients who achieved HBsAg loss within 48 weeks, compared to those who needed extended treatment longer than 48 weeks to achieve HBsAg loss (2.0 &#x000b1; 1.4 log IU/ml vs. 3.0 &#x000b1; 0.9 log IU/ml; <italic>t</italic> = 5.171, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) and (77.2% vs. 29.2%; <italic>t</italic> = 2.461, <italic>P</italic> = 0.015), respectively [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>].</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Kinetics of hepatitis B surface antigen levels in patients who achieved hepatitis B surface antigen loss within and after 48 weeks. Patients achieved hepatitis B surface antigen loss within 48 weeks of treatment had a lower hepatitis B surface antigen level baseline and sharp hepatitis B surface antigen decline during treatment compared with patients obtained hepatitis B surface antigen loss by extended treatment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CMJ-130-559-g005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>D<sc>iscussion</sc></title><p>HBsAg is the most important serological marker of HBV infection, and serum HBsAg level correlates with the intrahepatic amount and transcriptional activity of covalently closed circular DNA (cccDNA), the main replicative template of HBV.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] HBsAg loss and seroconversion to anti-HBs is generally considered to be the ultimate goal of therapy, indicating a complete response to treatment and the resolution of the disease. It reflects immunological control of the infection and confers an excellent prognosis in the absence of preexisting cirrhosis or concurrent infections with other viruses.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</p><p>IFN has antiviral and immunomodulatory properties that result in direct inhibition of viral replication and enhancement of the cell-mediated immune response in the process of virus clearance. Reportedly, PEG-IFN therapy can only achieve 30&#x02013;40% HBeAg seroconversion in HBeAg-positive patients, 19.2&#x02013;40.0% sustained viral response (SVR) after cessation of therapy in HBeAg-negative patients,[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and 2.0&#x02013;7.0% HBsAg loss/seroclearance,[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] which remains far from satisfactory. Even if HBeAg seroconversion and SVR are well-recognized, continuous long-term viral suppression does not ensure HBsAg clearance when treatment is discontinued. Therefore, it is important to identify pretreatment and on-treatment parameters for predicting patient response and nonresponse to IFN, especially with the aim of identifying patients likely to achieve HBsAg loss.</p><p>Well-known predictors of an SVR include low baseline HBV DNA, high ALT levels, younger age, female gender, and HBV genotype. Sustained responders tend to have lower baseline HBsAg and HBV DNA than nonsustained responders.[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] Low baseline HBsAg was shown to be more reliable than serum HBV DNA levels for predicting good response to PEG-IFN and lamivudine treatment in HBeAg-positive patients.[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] An important clinical characteristic of patients in the present study was low baseline HBsAg levels; 2.9 &#x000b1; 1.1 log IU/ml and 2.0 &#x000b1; 1.3 log IU/ml in HBeAg-positive and- negative patients, respectively. However, HBsAg levels of 3.0&#x02013;4.4 log IU/ml and 2.5&#x02013;4.0 log IU/ml have been previously reported in HBeAg-positive and -negative patients in similar studies.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] Although there were no control groups involving patients without HBsAg loss during PEG-IFN treatment in the current study, others demonstrated that low baseline HBsAg level was the only significant prognostic predictor of HBsAg seroconversion following conventional IFN treatment.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] These results suggest that CHB patients with low HBsAg levels should be considered PEG-IFN therapy to achieve HBsAg loss.</p><p>A 48-week course of PEG-IFN is recommended for CHB;[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] however, only 3% of patients obtained HBsAg loss after this recommended course. Long-term follow-up of PEG-IFN trials showed continuing HBsAg loss up to 11% at 3 and 4 years after stopping treatment,[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] but only 63% of HBeAg-negative patients had HBV DNA &#x02264;400 copies/ml 3 years after treatment, despite HBsAg levels &#x02264;19 IU/ml at the end of 48 weeks of treatment.[<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] This suggests that individualized treatment programs may be needed to consider extending the duration of therapy for CHB. Extended duration of therapy can increase the rate of SVR in HBeAg-negative patients treated with either standard or PEG-IFN therapies,[<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and can enhance the rate of HBeAg seroconversion after treatment in HBeAg-positive patients,[<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and the rate of HBsAg clearance after or during treatment.[<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] In the present study, more than half of the HBsAg clearance occurred after extended treatment, with 30.0% of patients needing treatment for 72&#x02013;96 weeks to achieve HBsAg loss. This indicates that extended treatment was essential for HBsAg clearance during PEG-IFN-based therapy.</p><p>Treatment should be optimized by careful patient selection and individualized treatment decisions in order to increase the success rate of IFN treatment and to minimize the risk of adverse events. Many studies have demonstrated that decrease of HBsAg during treatment was predictor of response and indicator for stopping IFN. HBsAg &#x0003c;1500 IU/ml at 12 weeks[<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and at 24 weeks[<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] were associated with and predictive of HBeAg seroconversion after IFN treatment in HBeAg-positive patients. A decrease in HBsAg levels compared to baseline predicted SVR in HBeAg-negative patients.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] Moreover, a decline in HBsAg was also significantly associated with HBsAg clearance after IFN treatment.[<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] However, the pattern of HBsAg decline in patients who achieved HBsAg clearance during IFN treatment remains unclear.</p><p>The present study showed that HBsAg levels decreased by 48.3% and 88.3% at 12 and 24 weeks, respectively, while 93.3% of patients achieved HBsAg &#x0003c;100 IU/ml and nearly all patients achieved HBsAg &#x0003c;1000 IU/ml. Although HBsAg levels in HBeAg-positive patients were higher than those in HBeAg-negative patients, the patterns of decline during treatment were similar in both groups. These results suggest that a rapid decline in HBsAg levels, regardless of baseline, is essential for HBsAg clearance during PEG-IFN treatment in both HBeAg-positive and -negative patients. Notably, baseline HBsAg levels were significantly lower and the degree of HBsAg decline at 12 weeks was significantly greater in patients who achieved HBsAg loss within 48 weeks, compared with those who needed extended treatment to achieve HBsAg loss. Thus, patients who achieve HBsAg loss within 48 weeks should have characteristics of lower baseline levels, sharp and rapid decline at early treatment time.</p><p>A decline in serum HBV DNA reflects a reduction in viral replication while a decline in serum HBsAg represents a reduction in the translation of mRNAs produced from transcriptionally-active cccDNA or integrated sequences.[<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] The viral response during treatment alone may not represent a reliable indicator of SVR to antiviral therapy, and the kinetics of HBV DNA and HBsAg level are dissociated in NA-treated patients and relapsers to PEG-IFN. Several studies have shown that combining cutoff levels for HBsAg and HBV DNA can reliably identify patients with inactive disease,[<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref><xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] and that HBsAg and HBV DNA kinetics are parallel in sustained responders to PEG-IFN.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref><xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</p><p>In the present study, all patients who were HBV DNA-positive before IFN treatment achieved viral response within 60 weeks, most within 48 weeks. However, most patients needed extended treatment for HBsAg clearance, suggesting that a strong immune response stimulated by IFN treatment could efficiently control viral replication and clear HBV-infected hepatocytes. Viral response was the essential condition for HBsAg clearance during IFN-based therapy.</p><p>In summary, the results of this study demonstrate that patients with lower baseline HBsAg sustained and rapid decline of HBsAg during treatment, and early viral response are more likely to achieve HBsAg clearance[<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] during IFN-based therapy. However, most patients needed extended treatment longer than 48 weeks to achieve HBsAg loss during treatment.</p><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>This study was supported by grants from Beijing Science and Technology Commission (No. D121100003912001), and Beijing Municipal Administration of Hospiatals Clinical Medicine Development of Special Funding, (No. ZY201402).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-9" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank all those who have been involved in this study, including the patients, the investigators and colleagues from Liver Diseases Center and Clinical Test Center (Beijing Ditan Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><bold>Edited by:</bold> Yi Cui</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>R<sc>eferences</sc></title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A decade-old change in the screening rate for hepatocellular carcinoma among a hepatitis B virus-infected population in Korea</article-title><source>Chin Med J</source><year>2016</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><comment>doi: 10.4103/0366-6999.172551</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26712427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konerman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lok</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interferon treatment for hepatitis B</article-title><source>Clin Liver Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1016/j.cld2016.06.002</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27742005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liaw</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spontaneous relapse of hepatitis in inactive HBsAg carriers</article-title><source>Hepatol Int</source><year>2007</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1007/s12072-007-9002-9</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19669355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fattovich</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Onofrio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Martone</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Donato</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term outcome of chronic hepatitis B in caucasian patients: Mortality after 25 years</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>2008</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1136/gut.2007.128496</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17715267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B surface antigen clearance in inactive hepatitis B surface antigen carriers treated with peginterferon alfa-2a</article-title><source>World J Hepatol</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>637</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><comment>doi: 10.4254/wjh.v8.i15.637</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27239256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>European Association for the Study of the Liver. EASL clinical practice guidelines: Management of chronic hepatitis B virus infection</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2012</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2012.02.010</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22436845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zoulim</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Durantel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiviral therapies and prospects for a cure of chronic hepatitis B</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><comment>pii: A021501</comment><comment>doi: 10.1101/cshperspect.a021501</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Piratvisuth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>KX</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcellin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thongsawat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooksley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Peginterferon alfa-2a, lamivudine, and the combination for HBeAg-positive chronic hepatitis B</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>2682</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa043470</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15987917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Westby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bermingham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill-Cawthorne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><collab>Guideline Development Group</collab><article-title>Diagnosis and management of chronic hepatitis B in children, young people, and adults: Summary of NICE guidance</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2013</year><volume>346</volume><fpage>f3893</fpage><comment>doi: 10.1136/bmj.f3893</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23804177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinot-Peignoux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Piratvisuth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunetto</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B surface antigen quantification: Why and how to use it in 2011 &#x02013; A core group report</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2011</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1121</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2011.06.006</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21718667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liaw</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B surface antigen seroclearance during chronic HBV infection</article-title><source>Antivir Ther</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><comment>doi: 10.3851/IMP1497</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20386068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Ashgar</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Aljumah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanai</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdo</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dafalla</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of peginterferon a-2a and predictors of response in HBeAg-negative, genotype D-naive patients</article-title><source>Hepatol Int</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>718</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1007/s12072-011-9319-2</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23936583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moucari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackiewicz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lada</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ripault</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Castelnau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinot-Peignoux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Early serum HBsAg drop: A strong predictor of sustained virological response to pegylated interferon alfa-2a in HBeAg-negative patients</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2009</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1151</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1002/hep.22744</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19115222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chim</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serum HBsAg quantification to predict response to peginterferon therapy of e antigen positive chronic hepatitis B</article-title><source>Aliment Pharmacol Ther</source><year>2010</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1323</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2036.2010.04474.x</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21050234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of pegylated interferon a2a in patients without HBeAg loss after the withdrawal of long-term lamivudine therapy</article-title><source>Virol J</source><year>2013</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>21</fpage><comment>doi: 10.1186/1743-422X-10-21</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23320822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcellin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonino</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yurdaydin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadziyannis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moucari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapprell</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B surface antigen levels: Association with 5-year response to peginterferon alfa-2a in hepatitis B e-antigen-negative patients</article-title><source>Hepatol Int</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1007/s12072-012-9343-x</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23518903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Croagh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Desmond</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B surface antigen levels during the natural history of chronic hepatitis B: A perspective on Asia</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2010</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>508</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2010.01.007</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20206400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonneveld</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoutendijk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Flink</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Close monitoring of hepatitis B surface antigen levels helps classify flares during peginterferon therapy and predicts treatment response</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2013</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1093/cid/cis859</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23042976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pegylated-interferon alpha therapy for treatment-experienced chronic hepatitis B patients</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0122259</fpage><comment>doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0122259</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25835020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buster</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Flink</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cakaloglu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sustained HBeAg and HBsAg loss after long-term follow-up of HBeAg-positive patients treated with peginterferon alpha-2b</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2008</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2008.05.031</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18585385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunetto</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moriconi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonino</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Farci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yurdaydin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B virus surface antigen levels: A guide to sustained response to peginterferon alfa-2a in HBeAg-negative chronic hepatitis B</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2009</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1141</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1002/hep.22760</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19338056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrillo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A pilot study of extended duration peginterferon alfa-2a for patients with hepatitis B e antigen-negative chronic hepatitis B</article-title><source>Am J Gastroenterol</source><year>2007</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>2718</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1111/j.1572-0241.2007.01449.x</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17662102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High rates of HBsAg loss and seroconversion result from prolonged course of pegasys treatment (in Chinese)</article-title><source>Chin J Hepatol</source><year>2011</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><comment>doi: 10.3760/cma.j.issn.1007-3418.2011.03.008</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sezaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term effects of peginterferon alfa-2a therapy in Japanese patients with chronic hepatitis B virus infection</article-title><source>Virol J</source><year>2015</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>225</fpage><comment>doi: 10.1186/s12985-015-0453-7</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26700861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lampertico</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vigan&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Costanzo</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagnelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fasano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Marco</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Randomised study comparing 48 and 96 weeks peginterferon a-2a therapy in genotype D HBeAg-negative chronic hepatitis B</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>2013</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2011-301430</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22859496</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okanoue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasebe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Karino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Imazeki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term follow up of peginterferon-a-2a treatment of hepatitis B e-antigen (HBeAg) positive and HBeAg negative chronic hepatitis B patients in phase II and III studies</article-title><source>Hepatol Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>992</fpage><lpage>1001</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1111/hepr.12638</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26670363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative serum HBsAg and HBeAg are strong predictors of sustained HBeAg seroconversion to pegylated interferon alfa-2b in HBeAg-positive patients</article-title><source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2010</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1498</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1111/j.1440-1746.2010.06282.x</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20796146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piratvisuth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcellin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Popescu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapprell</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothe</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B surface antigen: Association with sustained response to peginterferon alfa-2a in hepatitis B e antigen-positive patients</article-title><source>Hepatol Int</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1007/s12072-011-9280-0</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21701902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonneveld</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Piratvisuth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeuzem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gane</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Response-guided peginterferon therapy in hepatitis B e antigen-positive chronic hepatitis B using serum hepatitis B surface antigen levels</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2013</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>872</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1002/hep.26436</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23553752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunetto</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new role for an old marker, HBsAg</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2010</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2009.12.020</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20185190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaroszewicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Calle Serrano</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wursthorn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Deterding</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlue</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Raupach</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) levels in the natural history of hepatitis B virus (HBV)-infection: A European perspective</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2010</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>514</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2010.01.014</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20207438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunetto</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Colombatto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moriconi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciccorossi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Coco</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B surface antigen serum levels help to distinguish active from inactive hepatitis B virus genotype D carriers</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2010</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2010.04.052</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20451520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunetto</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcellin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherubini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yurdaydin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Farci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadziyannis</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Response to peginterferon alfa-2a (40KD) in HBeAg-negative CHB: On-treatment kinetics of HBsAg serum levels vary by HBV genotype</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>2013</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1153</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><comment>doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2013.07.017</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23872601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamic characteristics of serum hepatitis B surface antigen in Chinese chronic hepatitis B patients receiving 7 years of entecavir therapy</article-title><source>Chin Med J</source><year>2016</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>929</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><comment>doi: 10.4103/0366-6999.179802</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27064037</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>