<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Geriatr Cardiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Geriatr Cardiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JGC</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Geriatric Cardiology : JGC</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1671-5411</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Science Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28133470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5253410</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jgc-13-11-927</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11909/j.issn.1671-5411.2016.11.008</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letter To The Editor</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Radiofrequency catheter ablation of ventricular tachycardia in a patient with dermatomyositis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nierras</surname><given-names>Peter Carlo M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maranian</surname><given-names>Aida P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Ming-Shien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>Chung-Chuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Division of Cardiology, Department of Medicine, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Linkou, Taiwan, China</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Section of Cardiology, Department of Medicine, Philippine General Hospital, Manila, Philippines</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Section of Cardiology, Department of Medicine, Southern Philippines Medical Center, Davao City, Philippines</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Chang Gung University College of Medicine, Taoyuan, Taiwan, China</addr-line></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>*Correspondence to:</bold><email>2867@cgmh.org.tw</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>927</fpage><lpage>929</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Institute of Geriatric Cardiology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License, which allows readers to alter, transform, or build upon the article and then distribute the resulting work under the same or similar license to this one. The work must be attributed back to the original author and commercial use is not permitted without specific permission.</license-p></license></permissions><kwd-group><kwd>Dermatomyositis</kwd><kwd>Radiofrequency ablation</kwd><kwd>Ventricular tachycardia</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>A 51-year old male who presented at our hospital for recurrent palpitation for several months was diagnosed dermatomyositis ten years ago and had interstitial lung disease since two years ago. Recently, he was admitted for atypical hepatitis, and received maintenance treatment of oral corticosteroids. The twelve-lead ECG during palpitation showed ventricular tachycardia (VT) with a superior axis, left bundle branch block morphology at a rate of 160 beats/min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="jgc-13-11-927-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). In addition, paroxysmal atrial fibrillation with bigeminy and trigeminy ventricular premature beats (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="jgc-13-11-927-g001">Figure 1B</xref>) was also documented. Cardiac echocardiogram revealed dilated right ventricle (RV), left ventricle (LV) and both atria. Both LV and RV systolic function were subnormal (LV ejection fraction = 43%; RV fractional area change = 48%) with dyskinesia of the LV anteroseptal wall. Coronary angiography was normal. Cardiac MRI revealed areas of fatty tissue over the RV and LV apex, but there were no definite areas of fibrosis noted.</p><p>During electrophysiological studies, monomorphic VT (VT-1; cycle length: 390 ms; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jgc-13-11-927-g002">Figure 2A</xref>) was induced with isoproterenol instead of programed pacing protocols. The VT could not be entrained, but could be suppressed by rapid RV pacing (pacing cycle lengths within 340&#x02013;370 ms) and by 12 mg adenosine intravenous bolus injection. Endocardial 3D-electroanatomic mapping showed a focal VT with the earliest activation site at the posteroinferior RV septum. Radiofrequency catheter ablation (RFCA) using a non-irrigated Navistar Carto ablation catheter (Biosense Webster, Diamond Bar, CA, USA) was applied at the posteroinferior septum to terminate the VT successfully (red dots; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jgc-13-11-927-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). However, a second VT (VT-2; cycle length: 410 ms; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jgc-13-11-927-g002">Figure 2B</xref>) with a slightly different QRS morphology occurred after VT-1 ablation. The earliest activation site of VT-2 was close to the first successful ablation site (blue dots; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jgc-13-11-927-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). As shown by voltage map (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="jgc-13-11-927-g002">Figure 2D</xref>) and endocardial electrical recordings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="jgc-13-11-927-g002">Figure 2E</xref>), the earliest activation sites of VT-1 and VT-2 were located in low voltage zones. VT-2 was successfully eliminated by a second RFCA procedure. No VT was inducible thereafter and no recurrence of VT was documented by follow-up Holter and clinical visits.</p><p>Dermatomyositis rarely involves myocardial muscles but has been shown to be associated with arrhythmias, frequently manifesting as conduction disorders rather than rhythm disturbances.<xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>,<xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> Although ventricular ectopies are frequent, VT in patients with dermatomyositis is rare.<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>,<xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> The underlying pathophysiology is either by direct lesions of the conduction system or by myositis with contraction band necrosis and/or focal myocardial fibrosis. Dermatomyositis-related ventricular tachyarrhythmia is usually bradycardia-dependent, which was not seen in our patient.<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>,<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref></p><p>Would patients with dermatomyositis presenting with VT benefit from steroids, antiarrhythmic drugs, RFCA or implantable cardioverter defibrillator (ICD) therapy? Generally, optimal therapy of ventricular arrhythmias associated with systemic inflammatory disorders like dermatomyositis is not well established. Although steroids improve overall mortality, there are reported cases of VT exacerbation with steroids due to attenuation of inflammatory responses with subsequent fibrosis.<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> In this patient who is already on maintenance corticosteroids, increasing the dose or adding an immunosuppressive agent is an option. However, if the arrhythmia mechanism is not due to disease activity, these drugs may be harmful rather than beneficial. VT in the setting of structural heart disease with a reduced LVEF is commonly treated by ICD implantation.<xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> Retrospective trial however shows RFCA could be a primary effective management for VT in such patients without subsequent implantation of ICD.<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> The VTs in our case were isoproterenol-triggered, adenosine-suppressed, and focally originating from the posteroinferior RV septal area with the most likely underlying mechanism of abnormal automaticity. Therefore, it was expected that elimination of the triggers can cure the VT. Our patient received a successful 3D-electroanatomical mapping-guided RFCA at the earliest activation sites of the focal VTs with no recurrence, which highlights the role of electrophysiological study and RFCA in patients with dermatomyositis presenting with VT.</p><fig id="jgc-13-11-927-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Twelve-lead electrocardiograms.</title><p>(A): twelve-lead electrocardiogram during ventricular tachycardia; (B): ventricular premature beats and atrial fibrillation; (C): normal sinus rhythm. The morphologies of ventricular premature beat and ventricular tachycardia were quite similar.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jgc-13-11-927-g001"/></fig><fig id="jgc-13-11-927-g002" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Endocardial 3D-electroanatomic mapping and ablation.</title><p>(A): electrocardiogram of VT-1; (B): electrocardiogram of VT-2; (C): activation map during VT-1. The earliest activation site is located at the posteroinferior right ventricular septum where successful ablation was applied (red dots). The blue dots indicate the successful ablation sites of VT-2 ablation. Note that the blue dots are close to the red dots. Yellow arrow indicates tricuspid ring; (D): voltage map of the RV showing areas of low voltage areas involving the earliest activation sites of VT-1 and VT-2; (E): the earliest endocardial electrical signals at sites &#x0201c;a&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;b&#x0201d; (labeled in panel C) during VT-1 and VT-2, respectively, which preceded QRS by 30 ms. Bi: bipolar; LAT: local activation time; Uni: unipolar; VT: ventricular tachycardia.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jgc-13-11-927-g002"/></fig></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazzerini</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Capecchi</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Guideri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Connective tissue diseases and cardiac rhythm disorders: an overview</article-title>
<source>Autoimmun Rev</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>306</fpage>
<lpage>313</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16782554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sultan</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioannou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Outcome in patients with idiopathic inflammatory myositis: morbidity and mortality</article-title>
<source>Rheumatology</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>22</fpage>
<lpage>26</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11792875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dilaveris</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsiachris</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Inducible ventricular tachycardia due to dermatomyositis-related cardiomyopathy in the era of implantable cardioverter-defibrillator therapy</article-title>
<source>Circulation</source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>125</volume>
<fpage>967</fpage>
<lpage>969</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22354978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjeee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stratton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ventricular tachycardia as a presenting feature of dermatomyositis</article-title>
<source>Heart</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>88</volume>
<fpage>443</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12381621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roden</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A surprising new arrhythmia mechanism in heart failure</article-title>
<source>Circ Res</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>589</fpage>
<lpage>591</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14525920</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blanc-Guillemaud</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherif</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cellular electrophysiological changes in rats with heart failure and ventricular arrhythmias-<italic>in vitro</italic>-<italic>in vivo</italic> correlations</article-title>
<source>J Clin Basic Cardiol</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>23</fpage>
<lpage>28</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiramastu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Naito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Steroid treatment deteriorated ventricular tachycardia in a patient with right ventricle-dominant cardiac sarcoidosis</article-title>
<source>Int J Cardiol</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>132</volume>
<fpage>e85</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18037174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>DiMarco</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenbogen</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>2012 ACCF/AHA/HRS focused update incorporated into the ACCF/ AHA/HRS 2008 guidelines for device-based therapy of cardiac rhythm abnormalities: a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines and the Heart Rhythm Society</article-title>
<source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>61</volume>
<fpage>e6</fpage>
<lpage>e75</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23265327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maury</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baratto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeppenfeld</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Radio-frequency ablation as primary management of well-tolerated sustained monomorphic ventricular tachycardia in patients with structural heart disease and left ventricular ejection fraction over 30%</article-title>
<source>Eur Heart J</source>
<year>2014</year>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>1479</fpage>
<lpage>1485</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24536081</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>