<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Phys Ther Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Phys Ther Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JPTS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Physical Therapy Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0915-5287</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2187-5626</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Society of Physical Therapy Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28603373</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5462700</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jpts-2017-044</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1589/jpts.29.924</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Comparison therapeutic efficacy of underwater and overground walking training
on the healthy subjects balancing ability</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Si-A</given-names></name><degrees>PT</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Myoung-Kwon</given-names></name><degrees>PT, PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label> Department of Physical Therapy,
College of Rehabilitation Sciences, Daegu University, Republic of Korea</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Myoung-Kwon Kim, Department of Physical Therapy,
College of Rehabilitation Sciences, Daegu University: Jillyang, Gyeongsan, Gyeongbuk
712-714, Republic of Korea. (E-mail: <email xlink:href="skybird-98@hanmail.net">skybird-98@hanmail.net</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>29</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>924</fpage><lpage>926</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>2017&#x000a9;by the Society of Physical Therapy Science. Published by IPEC
Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. (CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>)</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>[Purpose] This study&#x02019;s working hypothesis is that underwater walking training is
beneficial for healthy subjects balance. [Subjects and Methods] Forty eight subjects
(Underwater walking group=25, Overground walking group=23) completed the experiment.
Healthy subjects with no orthopedic history of lower extremity injuries were recruited.
Gait training is performed using the underwater treadmill consisted of 30-minute walking
sessions, five times per week for four weeks. [Results] After the intervention, the
medial-lateral and anterior-posterior balance indices increased significantly.
[Conclusion] This study conducted underwater walking training on the healthy subjects,
with positive effects on balancing ability.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Balance</kwd><kwd>Gait</kwd><kwd>Underwater treadmill</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Balancing ability is defined as the ability to maintain the body&#x02019;s center of gravity while
minimizing sway in the base of support. Postural balance, on the other hand, indicates the
ability to continuously retain balance in accordance with the center of mass (COM) and
movement, and to maintain the proper postural control against actions and external rocking
within the base of support<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><sup>)</sup>. Gait training is a common method of improving the balancing
ability. It is recommended for aerobic capacity improvement, body fat reduction, lowering
the blood pressure, improving insulin sensitivity, and improving gait and balancing
abilities<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><sup>)</sup>. Research testing the effects
of gait training examines types and speed of walking. Underwater walking training is special
in that it provides a work-out environment of reduced gravity with the use of the buoyancy
of water<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><sup>)</sup>. Water workouts relieve stress
from weight on the joints, enhances muscular function without imposing excessive impact to
the muscle, and improves flexibility and balance<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Most research has focused on gait training in the ground, and there are very few
investigations of underwater walking training and its effects on balancing ability<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><sup>)</sup>.
Given this background, this study examines the effects of underwater walking training on the
healthy subjects balancing ability.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>SUBJECTS AND METHODS</title><p>Forty eight subjects (Underwater walking group=25, Overground walking group=23) completed
the experiment. The characteristics of the two groups (n=48) before and after intervention
are shown in <xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref><table-wrap id="tbl_001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Characteristics of the experimental and control groups pre- and post-intervention
(values are presented as means (standard deviations)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">EG (n=25)</th><th rowspan="3" align="left" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">CG (n=23)</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-test</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-test</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-test</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-test</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medial-lateral locus length (mm/s)<sup>a, b</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128.7 (21.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.1 (19.6)*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131.6 (19.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127.5 (18.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior-posterior locus length (mm/s)<sup>a, b</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188.3 (20.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175.2 (22.3)*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190.2 (19.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188.3 (20.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Index of balance function (score)<sup>a, b</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.3 (10.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.2 (9.6)*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.2 (12.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.3 (14.8)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>EG: underwater walking group; CG: overground walking group; *p&#x0003c;0.05.
<sup>a</sup>Significant difference between gains in the two groups. <sup>b</sup>Effect
size &#x0003e;0.70</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>. The selection criteria were as follows: no history of orthopedic surgery on a
lower limb, never taken any drug due to a neurologic problem, and no musculoskeletal system
disease. In underwater and overground walking training groups average ages, heights, and
weights were 20.14 &#x000b1; 1.27, 21.37 &#x000b1; 1.41&#x02005;years, 174.16 &#x000b1; 10.17, 172.54 &#x000b1; 8.67&#x02005;cm, and 72.35 &#x000b1;
6.58, 68.94 &#x000b1; 7.84&#x02005;kg, respectively. Sufficient explanation of this study&#x02019;s intent and the
overall purpose was given, and voluntary consent to participate in this study was obtained
from all of the subjects. Information on the study and written informed consent according to
the ethical standards of the Declaration of Helsinki were provided to all subjects prior to
their participation.</p><p>The trials consisted of underwater and overground walking training. The subjects either
walked on an underwater treadmill (HydroTrack<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Underwater Treadmill System,
Conray, Inc., Phoenix, AZ, USA) or walked on an overground treadmill (HL-1100, Healthlife,
Korea). The water temperature was set at about 33&#x02005;&#x000b0;C and the depth was fixed to reach up
between the subjects&#x02019; xiphoid process and the navel. The speed of the treadmill was limited
to a maximum velocity of 2&#x02013;4 m/s in both groups<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><sup>)</sup>. The both group consisted of 30-minute walking sessions, five times
per week for four weeks.</p><p>After the intervention, balance measuring equipment (Good Balance, Metitur, Finland) was
used to quantitatively measure each subject&#x02019;s balance ability<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><sup>)</sup>. The balance test was performed by a physical therapist who had
completed the course for the balance test method and was experienced in clinical practice
for over three years. To measure balance function, the subject was instructed to stand on a
triangle platform and maintain a symmetrical posture with the feet shoulder width apart. A
visual fixed point was located in front of the subject to minimize head movements. The
subject&#x02019;s arms were placed comfortably at the hip joints and the center of pressure (COP)
was measured for 30 seconds in the standing posture with the eyes open. COP was measured
three times and average values were calculated. The software also calculates several
variables describing the quantitative aspects of individual&#x02019;s test behaviour, e.g. amount
and speed of anterior-posterior and medial-lateral sway, amplitude of sway, the first moment
of sway velocity (combined amplitude and velocity of the movement of the center of
pressure), power spectrum analysis (FFT analysis) etc. Low score of anterior-posterior and
medial-lateral sway implies excellent balance ability. The index of balance function score
ranges between 0 and 100, and a higher score implies greater balance ability to perform the
task. A reliable and valid measurement of the functioning of posture control mechanisms is a
prerequisite for discovering the reasons for balance problems or evaluating the effects of
treatment and rehabilitation.</p><p>The mean and SD were calculated for each variable. Before the intervention, differences in
the general characteristics of the experimental group were analyzed by descriptive
statistics. Variables were compared before and after training within experimental group
using paired sample t-tests. The statistical analysis was conducted using SPSS 20.0 (SPSS,
Chicago, IL, USA), and statistical significance was accepted for p values &#x0003c;0.05</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>RESULTS</title><p>The underwater walking training showed significant increases in all variance after
intervention (p&#x0003c;0.05). Significant intergroup differences in post-training gains were
observed for all varience (p&#x0003c;0.05). The effect sizes of gains in the underwater and
overground walking training were high for medial-lateral and anterior-posterior locus
length, balance function indices (effect sizes 0.84, 1.11, and 0.96, respectively) (<xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This study assessed underwater walking training on healthy subjects, and the results showed
a positive effect on balancing ability. An earlier study found that a stretching exercise
increased balancing ability in healthy subjects<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><sup>)</sup>.When a person moves in the water, buoyancy and resistance of the
water induce rocking of posture. This body movement activates proprioception to maintain
upright posture<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><sup>)</sup>. Movement in the water
allows easier application of open and closed kinetic chain exercise than on the ground.</p><p>In the present study, a variable-speed underwater treadmill training with adjustable water
depth and frontal resistance provided by pump-driven directional water jets has been used as
a novel mode of aquatic exercise. This system theoretically provides a more favorable mode
of exercise for the overweight and obese, in that walking or jogging intensity (velocity and
resistance) can be controlled, whereas the buoyancy of water reduces the impact force of
ambulation<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Other researchers have previously investigated, physical function and walking ability were
improved in adults with incomplete spinal cord injury following a structured program of
underwater treadmill training featuring individualized levels of body weight support and
carefully staged increases in speed and duration<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><sup>)</sup>. From a clinical perspective, these findings highlight the potential
of underwater treadmill training in persons with physical disabilities and diseases that
would benefit from weight-supported exercise.</p><p>Underwater walking training provides a treatment environment that is psychologically
stable. The physical nature of water presents advantages in improving muscular strength and
endurance, motion range of joints, increase in cardiopulmonary abilities, and improving the
quality of life, as gait and balancing ability improve<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><sup>)</sup>. When adults with arthritis were treated with underwater walking
training, their balancing ability and motion range of joints improved<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><sup>)</sup>. It appears that buoyancy, temperature, and other qualities
of water stimulated proprioception and decreased postural rocking.</p><p>The underwater treadmill training has been used most frequently as a treatment modality in
sports injury or orthopedic rehabilitation settings and has only recently been used with
obese individuals. Therefore, further clinical controlled studies with larger sample sizes
and longer interventions should be carried out to validate the clinical benefits of the
underwater walking.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Machida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Relationship between the Berg Balance Scale and Static
Balance Test in hemiplegic patients with stroke</article-title>. <source>J Phys Ther
Sci</source>, <year>2013</year>, <volume>25</volume>:
<fpage>1043</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1049</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24259912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Uematsu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Influence of lower limb muscle fatigue on balance
function</article-title>. <source>J Phys Ther Sci</source>, <year>2013</year>,
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>335</lpage>. </mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Firshman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Borgia</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Valberg</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Effects of training at a walk on conventional and
underwater treadmills on fiber properties and metabolic responses of superficial digital
flexor and gluteal muscles to high-speed exercise in horses</article-title>. <source>Am
J Vet Res</source>, <year>2015</year>, <volume>76</volume>:
<fpage>1058</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1065</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26618730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Effects of underwater treadmill training on leg strength,
balance, and walking performance in adults with incomplete spinal cord
injury</article-title>. <source>J Spinal Cord Med</source>, <year>2015</year>,
<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24969269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sihvonen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sipil&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Taskinen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Fall incidence in frail older women after individualized
visual feedback-based balance training</article-title>. <source>Gerontology</source>,
<year>2004</year>, <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>416</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15477703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Behm</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bambury</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Effect of acute static stretching on force, balance,
reaction time, and movement time</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source>,
<year>2004</year>, <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1397</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1402</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15292749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Comparative efficacy of water and land treadmill training
for overweight or obese adults</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source>,
<year>2009</year>, <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1808</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1815</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19657288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Cider</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaufelberger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunnerhagen</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>: <article-title>Hydrotherapy&#x02014;a new approach to improve function in the
older patient with chronic heart failure</article-title>. <source>Eur J Heart
Fail</source>, <year>2003</year>, <volume>5</volume>:
<fpage>527</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>535</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12921815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Barela</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolf</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>: <article-title>Biomechanical characteristics of adults walking in shallow
water and on land</article-title>. <source>J Electromyogr Kinesiol</source>,
<year>2006</year>, <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>250</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>256</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16111894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>