<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nephrourol Mon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nephrourol Mon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.5812/numonthly</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Kowsar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nephro-urology Monthly</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2251-7006</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2251-7014</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Kowsar</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27896240</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5120252</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5812/numonthly.40182</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluation of Anti-<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> Antibodies in Hemodialysis Patients with Chronic Kidney Disease in Sari, Iran</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seyyedpour</surname><given-names>Seyyed Hosein</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff104211">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Afshar</surname><given-names>Parvaneh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff104212">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor104213">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barzegarnejad</surname><given-names>Ayoub</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff104214">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kalhori</surname><given-names>Shamsi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff109233">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agah</surname><given-names>Reza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff109234">5</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff104211"><label>1</label>Deputy of Health, Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, Sari, IR Iran&#x0200f;</aff><aff id="aff104212"><label>2</label>Referral Laboratory, Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, Sari, IR Iran&#x0200f; </aff><aff id="aff104214"><label>3</label>Department of Urology, Medical School, Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, Sari, IR Iran&#x0200f; </aff><aff id="aff109233"><label>4</label>Fatemeh Zahra Hospital, Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, Sari, IR Iran&#x0200f; </aff><aff id="aff109234"><label>5</label>Deputy of Treatment, Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, Sari, IR Iran&#x0200f;</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor104213"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: Parvaneh Afshar, Referral Laboratory, Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, Sari, IR Iran. Tel: +98-9111531715, Fax: +98-1133390353, E-mail: <email>Afshar164@yahoo.com</email><email>p.afshar@mazums.ac.ir</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e40182</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>03</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016, Nephrology and Urology Research Center</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial usages, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p><italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> has worldwide distribution and is one of the most prevalent infectious agents in humans.</p></sec><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>The aim of this study was to determine the prevalence of anti-<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> antibodies in hemodialysis patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD) in the hemodialysis unit of Fatemeh Zahra hospital at the Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences in Sari, Iran.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Seventy-three patients with CKD and 145 healthy volunteers were assessed for anti-<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> (IgG, IgM, and IgA) antibodies using a conventional ELISA technique.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The anti-<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> IgG antibody was detected in 80.8% of the cases in the patient group, while 31.5% of the cases in the CKD patient group and 31.8% in the control group were found to be positive for the anti-<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> IgA antibody. All the patients in the CKD group were negative for the anti-<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> IgM antibody, although 2.76% of the healthy volunteers were found to be positive. The present study suggests that there was no significant difference between the hemodialysis patient group and the healthy volunteers.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The epidemiological data collected in this study could serve as a reference for future studies and may be useful in developing preventive and educational strategies, and consequently reducing healthcare expenditure.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Toxoplasmosis</kwd><kwd>Hemodialysis</kwd><kwd>ELISA</kwd><kwd>IgM, IgG</kwd><kwd>IgA</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec203649"><title>1. Background</title><p><italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> is disseminated worldwide and is one of the most prevalent infectious agents in humans. <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> is an opportunistic parasite in which acute infection is usually asymptomatic in immunocompetent patients, and spontaneous recovery is the norm (<xref rid="A40182R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="A40182R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Generally, toxoplasmosis is dependent on many factors, such as sanitation levels, temperature, humidity, and contact with soil and domestic animals, with a seroprevalence that varies from 0% to 95% (<xref rid="A40182R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="A40182R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). The prevalence of <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> is about 22.5%, 0.27% - 12.9%, 23.1%, 80%, and 50% - 84% in the USA (<xref rid="A40182R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), South Korea (<xref rid="A40182R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), Turkey (<xref rid="A40182R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), and Brazil (<xref rid="A40182R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="A40182R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), respectively. According to Assmar et al. (<xref rid="A40182R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), the seroprevalence of <italic>Toxoplasma</italic>
<italic>gondii</italic> in Iran is 51.8%. Other studies have indicated that 55.7% of the population in the provinces of Mazandaran, Gilan, and Khozestan (<xref rid="A40182R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), 17.7% in Fars and Azarbayjan provinces (<xref rid="A40182R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="A40182R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), and 68.4% in the southern region of Tehran (<xref rid="A40182R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="A40182R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) are seropositive. Acute toxoplasmosis is asymptomatic in 80% of healthy hosts and only 20% of adults and children exhibit symptomatic infection (<xref rid="A40182R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). However the existence of <italic>Toxoplasma</italic> tissue cysts in hosts may contribute to the maintenance of immunity against reinfection, and their presence may also cause symptomatic toxoplasmosis under certain conditions, especially in infants with congenital toxoplasmosis and immunocompromised patients (<xref rid="A40182R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Studies have shown that renal failure patients, such as those on hemodialysis, are immunodeficient, and such patients are therefore at high risk for numerous infections (<xref rid="A40182R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>-<xref rid="A40182R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec203650"><title>2. Objectives</title><p>No studies have been conducted regarding toxoplasmosis in hemodialysis patients in the northeast of Iran. In the present study, we therefore aimed to determine the prevalence of anti-<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> IgG, IgM, and IgA antibodies in hemodialysis patients with chronic kidney disease (CKD) in Sari, Iran.</p></sec><sec id="sec203651"><title>3. Methods</title><p>From July to September 2013, this cross-sectional study was carried out on 73 patients with CKD undergoing regular hemodialysis in the hemodialysis unit of Fatemeh Zahra hospital at the Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences in Sari, Iran. A total of 145 healthy volunteers with normal creatinine and BUN levels and without any underlying renal disease (control group) who matched the CKD patients according to age, gender, and geographical area were selected. The study was approved by the local ethics committee, and informed consent was obtained from all the participants. Medical records as well as data such as age, sex, and the length of time on hemodialysis treatment were obtained from all the hemodialysis patients. To determine the seroprevalence of <italic>Toxoplasma</italic> infections, 10 mL of peripheral blood was taken under aseptic conditions from all the patients in the hemodialysis and control groups, and each sample was left for 30 - 60 minutes at room temperature for spontaneous clotting before being centrifuged at 1500 rpm for 10 minutes. The serum samples were stored in acid-washed polyethylene tubes and kept frozen at &#x02013;20&#x000b0;C until tested in Referral Laboratory of Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences. Anti-<italic>Toxoplasma</italic> gondii IgG, IgM, and IgA were determined using a conventional enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) technique. ELISA kits were purchased from the commercial manufacturer Pishtazteb, Iran, for the IgG and IgM tests, and EI 2410-9601 A (Euroimmun, Germany) was procured for the IgA test. According to the manufacturers&#x02019; recommendations, IgG absorbance levels &#x0003c; 9 were considered negative, 9 - 11 was considered borderline, and &#x0003e; 11 was positive; IgM absorbance levels &#x0003c; 0.9 were considered negative, 0.9 - 1.1 was assumed to be borderline, and &#x0003e; 1.1 was positive; and an IgA ratio &#x0003c; 0.8 was considered negative, a ratio &#x02265; 0.8 but &#x0003c; 1.1 was assumed to be borderline, while &#x02265; 11 was positive. In the event of a borderline test result, an additional blood sample was obtained 2 weeks later and retested in parallel with the first suspect sample. Using the results of both samples allowed for the proper evaluation of titer changes. The statistical analysis was performed using SPSS software version 18. The data were analyzed using a chi-squared test, and P &#x0003c; 0.05 were considered statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="sec203652"><title>4. Results</title><p>Of the 73 CKD patients, there were 40 males and 33 females aged between 28 and 88 years (mean: 62.32 &#x000b1; 12.06 years). The length of time on hemodialysis treatment was 3 - 13 weeks (mean: 12.05 &#x000b1; 1.97 weeks). In the control group comprising 145 healthy volunteers, there were 63 males and 82 females aged between 27 and 84 years (mean: 55.52 &#x000b1; 11.43 years).</p><p>In the present study, 59 of the 73 (80.8%) cases in the patient group and 132 of the 145 (91%) healthy volunteers (control group) were found to be positive for IgG antibodies, and 23 (31.5%) cases in the patient group and 46 (31.8%) healthy volunteers (control group) were found to be positive for IgA antibodies. The percentage of participants who were anti-<italic>Toxoplasma</italic>
<italic>gondii</italic> IgG-antibody positive in the control group was found to be significantly greater than in the CKD patient group, although the difference was not statistically significant for the IgA antibody (P &#x0003c; 0.05). Meanwhile, all the hemodialysis patients were negative for the anti-IgM antibody, as were four (2.76%) of the control group subjects, and no statistically significant difference was observed between the groups. The seroprevalence distribution of the three antibody groups and a comparison of the anti-<italic>Toxoplasma</italic> antibodies present among the hemodialysis patients and healthy volunteers are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl51488">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl51489">2</xref>, respectively. The relationship between duration of hemodialysis treatment and anti-<italic>Toxoplasma</italic>
<italic>gondii</italic> antibody seropositivity was also verified, and we found a significant difference between these two parameters (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 5.24, P = 0.155).</p><table-wrap id="tbl51488" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title> Seroprevalence of Positive <italic>Toxoplasma</italic> Antibodies in the Hemodialysis patients and Healthy Volunteers</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th style="text-align: left;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemodialysis Patients (n = 73)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy Volunteers (n = 145)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IgG, No. (%) (M/F)</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (80.8) (34/25)</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (91) (55/77)</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.901</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IgM, No. (%) (M/F)</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2.76) (0/4)</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IgA, No. (%) (M/F)</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (31.5) (11/12)</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (31.8) (22/24)</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.667</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn54345"><p>Abbreviations: M, male; F, female; Ig, immunoglobulin.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl51489" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title> A Comparison of the Anti-<italic>Toxoplasma</italic> Antibodies in the Hemodialysis Patients and Healthy Volunteers</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th style="text-align: left;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th style="border-bottom: solid thin;" colspan="4" rowspan="1">IgG+</th><th style="border-bottom: solid thin;" colspan="4" rowspan="1">IgG-</th></tr><tr><th style="text-align: left;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgM+ IgA+</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgM- IgA+</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgM+ IgA-</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgM- IgA-</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgM+ IgA+</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgM- IgA+</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgM+ IgA-</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgM- IgA-</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Hemodialysis patients (n = 73)</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (28.8)</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (52.1)</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.7)</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (16.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Healthy volunteers (n = 145)</bold>
</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (31.7)</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.7)</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (58.6)</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.1)</td><td style="text-align: center;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (6.9)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec203654"><title>5. Discussion</title><p>Toxoplasmosis, which is an indexed global public health concern (<xref rid="A40182R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), is an opportunistic infection that causes non-symptomatic infections in immunocompetent individuals (<xref rid="A40182R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Almost equal percentage prevalence, namely 80.6% and 91%, of anti-<italic>Toxoplasma</italic> gondii IgG antibody was revealed in the hemodialysis patients and healthy volunteers in this study, respectively. The results of the patient group share a similar frequency with figures reported in Turkey (76.5%) (<xref rid="A40182R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). However, the data in our study were higher than those reported by Sahinl et al. (<xref rid="A40182R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) (59.1%) and Maraghi et al. (<xref rid="A40182R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), Ebrahim Zadeh et al. (<xref rid="A40182R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) and Rezavand et al. (<xref rid="A40182R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) of 59.1% ,40.67% , 56.7% and 60%, respectively in Iran, and Aufy et al. (<xref rid="A40182R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) and Alvarado-Esquivel et al. (<xref rid="A40182R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) of 56.06%, 56.7% and 10%, respectively in Turkey, Egypt and Mexico; whereas in our results the percentage of Anti-Toxoplasma gondii IgG antibody in the volunteer group was more than other studies (<xref rid="A40182R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>-<xref rid="A40182R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Furthermore, in our study, there were no positive cases of anti-<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> IgM antibody in the patient group and only 2.76% of the healthy volunteer showed the IgM antibody. This result is the same as that of Ocak et al. (<xref rid="A40182R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) who studied hemodialysis patients and healthy volunteers in Turkey. On the other hand, Aufy et al. (<xref rid="A40182R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), Sahinl et al. (<xref rid="A40182R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), Maraghi et al. (<xref rid="A40182R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), Ebrahim Zadeh et al. (<xref rid="A40182R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) , Rezavand et al. (<xref rid="A40182R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) and Nissaptorn et al. (<xref rid="A40182R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) studies determined 16.7%, 6.8% , 8.6 %, 13.5%, 3.3% and 5.7% respectively in the patient groups, which is not compatible with our results.</p><p>The anti-<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> IgA antibody was prevalent in 61.5% of the hemodialysis patients and 31.8% of the healthy volunteers in our study. These data were higher than those reported by Sahinl et al. (<xref rid="A40182R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) across both groups. The outcome in our study was different from those reported in certain studies where such differences may have been related to local environmental conditions.</p><p>Additionally, our study indicated that there was no significant association between anti-<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> due to IgG antibody frequency and the duration of hemodialysis treatment in either sex, whereas such a correlation was shown in the studies of Sahinl et al. (<xref rid="A40182R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) in Iran and Ocak et al. (<xref rid="A40182R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) in Turkey.</p><sec id="sec203653"><title>5.1. Conclusion</title><p>We conducted a case-controlled study to determine the prevalence of anti-<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> IgG, IgM, and IgA antibodies in hemodialysis patients with CKD in Sari, Mazandaran Province, Iran. Nowadays hemodialysis patients should be tested for <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> regularly. Clinicians should become more aware of these patients, and parasitological surveys should be carried out steadily to eliminate the risk of severe toxoplasmosis. Additionally, it is recommended that this study be extended to include a large sample of CKD patients on hemodialysis from other cities in Mazandaran Province, Iran. The epidemiological data collected in this study could serve as a reference for future studies and may be useful in developing preventive and educational strategies, and consequently reducing healthcare expenditure.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors are grateful to the staff of Fatemeh Zahra hospital and the referral laboratory of the Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, Iran.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="afn56178" fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Funding/Support:</bold>This research was supported with a grant from the research deputy of the Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences (HSR 91-4). This study was approved by the ethics committee of the Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, and written informed consent was obtained from each participant prior to enrolment.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="A40182R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sensini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxoplasma gondii infection in pregnancy: opportunities and pitfalls of serological diagnosis.</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect.</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2006.01444.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16700697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Toxoplasma gondii: past, present and future].</article-title><source>Zhongguo Ji Sheng Chong Xue Yu Ji Sheng Chong Bing Za Zhi.</source><year>2009</year><volume>27</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20066975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tenter</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Heckeroth</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxoplasma gondii: from animals to humans.</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>30</volume><issue>12-13</issue><fpage>1217</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11113252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name><name><surname>Egwu</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumshe</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroprevalence of human infection with Toxoplasma gondii and the associated risk factors, in Maiduguri, Borno state, Nigeria.</article-title><source>ATMPH.</source><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Liesenfeld</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxoplasmosis.</article-title><source>Lancet.</source><year>2004</year><volume>363</volume><issue>9425</issue><fpage>1965</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(04)16412-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15194258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroprevalence of Toxoplasma gondii infection and characteristics of seropositive patients in general hospitals in Daejeon, Korea.</article-title><source>Korean J Parasitol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3347/kjp.2009.47.2.125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19488418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altintas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yolasigmaz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yazar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakru</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitapcioglu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of Toxoplasma antibodies in residence of central Izmir and surrounding rural area.</article-title><source>Act Parasitol Tur.</source><year>1998</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bahia-Oliveira</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Azevedo-Silva</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Orefice</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Addiss</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Highly endemic, waterborne toxoplasmosis in north Rio de Janeiro state, Brazil.</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis.</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid0901.020160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12533282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spalding</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Amendoeira</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serological screening and toxoplasmosis exposure factors among pregnant women in South of Brazil.</article-title><source>Rev Soc Bras Med Trop.</source><year>2005</year><volume>38</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15821794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Assmar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Amirkhani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Piazak</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hovanesian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kooloobandi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Etessami</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxoplasmosis in Iran. Results of a seroepidemiological study.</article-title><source>Bull Soc Pathol Exot.</source><year>1997</year><volume>90</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9264742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Edrissian</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Assad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serological survey of toxoplasmosis in the northern part of Iran, using indirect fluorescent antibody technique.</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg.</source><year>1978</year><volume>72</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">360498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghorbani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Edrissian</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Afshar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serological survey of human toxoplasmosis in mountainous regions of the north-west and south-west parts of Iran (1976-77).</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg.</source><year>1981</year><volume>75</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7022791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salahi-Moghaddam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hafizi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A serological study on Toxoplasma gondii infection among people in south of Tehran, Iran.</article-title><source>Korean J Parasitol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3347/kjp.2009.47.1.61</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19290094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Beattie</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxoplasmosis of animals and man.</article-title><source>Boca Raton.</source><year>1988</year><volume>1</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Remington</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nizet</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><source>Infectious diseases of the fetus and newborn: expert consult.</source><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Elsevier Health Sciences</publisher-name><isbn>1437736378</isbn></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahinl</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Yazar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Demirtas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yalcin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokgoz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Anti-Toxoplasma gondii antibodies in haemodialysis patients with chronic renal failure.</article-title><source>Yonsei Med J.</source><year>2003</year><volume>44</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>288</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3349/ymj.2003.44.2.288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12728470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ocak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Eskiocak</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Aytac</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-Toxoplasma gondii antibodies in hemodialysis patients receiving long-term hemodialysis therapy in Turkey.</article-title><source>Saudi Med J.</source><year>2005</year><volume>26</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1378</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16155651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maraghi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadyad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheikhi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamakhteh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Latifi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study the anti-Toxoplasma antibodies (IgG and IgM) in hemodialysis patients of Abadan and Khoramshahr cities Southwest Iran in 2011 using ELISA.</article-title><source>JJM.</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebrahim Zadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bamedi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Etemadi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahrakipour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saryazdipour</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxoplasmosis as a complication of transfusion in hemodialysis patients.</article-title><source>Iran J ped hematol oncol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24734160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rezavand</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Poornaki</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokhtari</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andalibian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and determination of the prevalence of Toxoplasma gondii in patients with chronic renal failure by ELISA and PCR.</article-title><source>Asian Pacific J Tropical Disease.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2222-1808(15)61044-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aufy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahgoub</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Adel</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serological detection of Toxoplasma gondii in chronic renal failure patients and renal transplant recipients.</article-title><source>J Egypt Soc Parasitol.</source><year>1991</year><volume>36</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>943</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20120757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarado-Esquivel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liesenfeld</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres-Castorena</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Estrada-Martinez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbina-Alvarez</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos-de la Rocha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>Seroepidemiology of Toxoplasma gondii infection in patients with vision and hearing impairments, cancer, HIV, or undergoing hemodialysis in Durango, Mexico.</article-title><source>J Parasitol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>96</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1645/GE-2378.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20557194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="A40182R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nissapatorn</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroepidemiology of toxoplasmosis in renal patients.</article-title><source>Southeast Asian J Trop Med Public Health</source><year>2011</year><volume>42</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21710842</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>