<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Exp Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin. Exp. Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1111/(ISSN)1365-2249</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CEI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical and Experimental Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0009-9104</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1365-2249</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27727448</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5217865</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cei.12882</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CEI12882</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Translational</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Inflammation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impaired calcium mobilization in natural killer cells from chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis patients is associated with transient receptor potential melastatin 3 ion channels</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">Calcium ion mobilization in natural killer cells</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">T. Nguyen <italic>et al</italic>.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="cei12882-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><address><email>Thao.nguyen@griffith.edu.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="cei12882-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="cei12882-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cei12882-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="cei12882-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="cei12882-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cei12882-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="cei12882-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="cei12882-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cei12882-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="cei12882-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cei12882-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Staines</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="cei12882-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="cei12882-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="cei12882-cr-0006" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marshall&#x02010;Gradisnik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="cei12882-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="cei12882-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="cei12882-aff-0001"><label><sup>1</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">The National Centre for Neuroimmunology and Emerging Diseases</named-content><institution>Menzies Health Institute</institution><named-content content-type="city">Gold Coast</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">QLD</named-content><country country="AU">Australia</country></aff><aff id="cei12882-aff-0002"><label><sup>2</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">School of Medical Science</named-content><institution>Griffith University</institution><named-content content-type="city">Gold Coast</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">QLD</named-content><country country="AU">Australia</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label>Correspondence: T. Nguyen, Griffith University, Mailbox 64, Level 8, G40, Parklands Drive, Southport, QLD 4222, Australia. E&#x02010;mail: <email>Thao.nguyen@griffith.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>187</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cei.2017.187.issue-2</issue-id><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> &#x000a9; 2017 British Society for Immunology <copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2016 The Authors. Clinical &#x00026; Experimental Immunology published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd on behalf of British Society for Immunology</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy-nc"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution&#x02010;NonCommercial</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:CEI-187-284.pdf"/><abstract><title>Summary</title><p>Transient receptor potential melastatin subfamily 3 (TRPM3) ion channels play a role in calcium (Ca<sup>2+</sup>) cell signalling. Reduced TRPM3 protein expression has been identified in chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis (CFS/ME) patients. However, the significance of TRPM3 and association with intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization has yet to be determined. Fifteen CFS/ME patients (mean age 48&#x000b7;82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9&#x000b7;83 years) and 25 healthy controls (mean age 39&#x000b7;2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;12&#x000b7;12 years) were examined. Isolated natural killer (NK) cells were labelled with fluorescent antibodies to determine TRPM3, CD107a and CD69 receptors on CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup>NK cells and CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup> NK cells. Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux and NK cytotoxicity activity was measured under various stimulants, including pregnenolone sulphate (PregS), thapsigargin (TG), 2&#x02010;aminoethoxydiphenyl borate (2APB) and ionomycin. Unstimulated CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup> NK cells showed significantly reduced TRPM3 receptors in CFS/ME compared with healthy controls (HC). Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux showed no significant difference between groups. Moreover, PregS&#x02010;stimulated CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup>NK cells showed a significant increase in Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux in CFS/ME patients compared with HC. By comparison, unstimulated CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells showed no significant difference in both Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux and TRPM3 expression. PregS&#x02010;stimulated CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells increased TRPM3 expression significantly in CFS/ME, but this was not associated with a significant increase in Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux. Furthermore, TG&#x02010;stimulated CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells increased K562 cell lysis prior to PregS stimulation in CFS/ME patients compared with HC. Differential expression of TRPM3 and Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux between NK cell subtypes may provide evidence for their role in the pathomechanism involving NK cell cytotoxicity activity in CFS/ME.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="cei12882-kwd-0001">cell surface molecules</kwd><kwd id="cei12882-kwd-0002">inhibitory/activating receptors</kwd><kwd id="cei12882-kwd-0003">natural killer cells</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Stafford Fox Medical Research Foundation</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Change for ME Charity</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Alison Hunter Memorial Foundation</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Mason Foundation</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Queensland Co&#x02010;Investment Program</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="5078"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>component-id</meta-name><meta-value>cei12882</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>February 2017</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:5.0.0 mode:remove_FC converted:06.01.2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="cei12882-sec-0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis (CFS/ME) is a complex illness presenting with debilitating post&#x02010;exertional malaise accompanied by other neurological, immunological, autonomic and ion transport impairments <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">1</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2</xref>. The most consistent biological evidence reported in CFS/ME has been reduced natural killer (NK) cell cytotoxicity (reviewed by Stayer <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref>).</p><p>NK cells belong to the innate immune system and are distinguished into two main subsets known as CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup> NK cells and CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells. CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup> NK cells are predominately immunosurveillance cells with potent cytokine production, whereas CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells are cytotoxic and kill infected, tumour or &#x02018;missing self&#x02019; cells <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">4</xref>.</p><p>Activated NK cells increase CD69 receptors and may be modulated by protein kinase C (PKC) and protein tyrosine kinases <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">5</xref>. NK cells from CFS/ME patients have been reported to have a significant reduction in CD69 receptors after stimulation <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref>. When NK cells come into contact with virus&#x02010;infected or tumour cells, an immune synapse is formed and degranulation is activated. Degranulation is detected when NK cells increase the lysosome&#x02010;associated membrane protein&#x02010;1 (LAMP&#x02010;1, CD107a) receptor <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref>. NK cells require Ca<sup>2+</sup> to regulate cellular functions, which play a major role in signalling pathways that are essential for development of immune synapse formation, cytokine production and cytotoxic activity <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref>.</p><p>Transient receptor potential (TRP) ion channels modulate ion entry in the cell plasma membrane, and are expressed differentially on tissues throughout the body. Their dysfunction has been associated with several diseases, such as cancer, glomerulosclerosis and polycystic kidney disease <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>. Transient receptor potential melastatin 3 ion channels (TRPM3) are transmembrane ion channels belonging to the melastatin subfamily of TRP cation ion channels <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref>. There are seven isotypes identified in the human TRPM3 gene; in particular, the TRPM3&#x003b1;2 isotype has been characterized as having a Ca<sup>2+</sup> and Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion&#x02010;conducting pore <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">12</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref>. TRPM3 ion channels are expressed in various tissues, predominantly in sensory neurones, kidney, brain, pituitary gland and pancreas. While expressed ubiquitously in mammalian cells, the roles and functions of TRPM3 have yet to be determined in immune cells <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>. TRPM3 ion channels are activated selectively by a potent neurosteroid, pregnenolone sulphate (PregS) <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">14</xref>. Pregnenolone is synthesized from cholesterol by many tissues, including adrenal glands, brain and skin. These tissues have been reported to express TRPM3 <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>. Physiologically, PregS plays a role in both the central nervous system and immune system, which include improvement of memory and cognitive function, enhanced neuronal myelination, activation of neurotransmitter&#x02010;gated channels, modulation of glutamate&#x02013;nitric oxide&#x02013;guanosine 3&#x02032;,5&#x02032;&#x02010;(cyclic) phosphate pathways, regulation of insulin secretion and the management of noxious pain <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">14</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">15</xref>.</p><p>Recently, TRPM3 ion channels were identified on NK cells and B cells from CFS/ME patients <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref>, and these cells were shown to have significantly reduced expression of the TRPM3 receptor on the cell surface compared with healthy controls (HC) <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>. However, the role of TRPM3 in terms of receptor number and Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization following stimulants, such as PregS on NK cell function, has not been investigated in CFS/ME patients. Therefore, the objective of this study was to determine the effects of PregS on TRPM3, including CD69 and CD107a receptor expression in NK cells. Additionally, we investigated intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization and cytotoxic activity of NK cells after PregS treatment in HC and CFS/ME patients.</p></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0002"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="cei12882-sec-0003"><title>Participants</title><p>CFS/ME patients meeting the Fukuda definition were included into the study, along with HC <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2</xref>. All participants were recruited between the ages of 18 and 65 years, with no previous history of smoking or chronic disease (autoimmune diseases, cardiac diseases and primary psychological disorders). Participants were further excluded if pregnant, breast feeding or taking hormone therapy and pharmaceutical immunoregulatory medications. Alternatively, participants on immunoregulatory medications were included into the study if medications were discontinued 2 weeks prior to their blood collection.</p><p>Participants living in the South East Queensland region of Australia donated 80 ml of blood between 8:00 a.m. and 10:30 a.m. Seventy ml of blood was used to isolate NK cells for further study, while the remaining 10 ml was used for routine pathology screening to help determine any underlying illness. Pathology results included a full blood cell count, electrolytes, erythrocyte sedimentation rate, C&#x02010;reactive protein, dehydroepiandrosterone, adrenocorticotrophic hormone and cortisol. All participants completed a self&#x02010;reported questionnaire on their current symptoms, which also included the Short&#x02010;Form Health Survey (SF&#x02010;36) and WHO Disability Assessment Schedule 2.9 (WHO DAS 20.0) to assess participants' physical health.</p></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0004"><title>Drugs and antibodies</title><p>
<italic>In&#x02010;vitro</italic> assays consisted of using the following drugs at a final concentration of 1 &#x003bc;M ionomycin, 50 &#x003bc;M 2&#x02010;aminoethoxydiphenyl borate (2&#x02010;APB), 1&#x000b7;42 &#x003bc;M thapsigargin (TG) and 1&#x000b7;35 &#x003bc;M PregS. All drugs were purchased from Bio&#x02010;Techne (Tocris Bioscience, Sussex, UK) except ionomycin, which was purchased from Sigma (Mansfield, Victoria, Australia). Antibodies CD3, CD56, CD16, CD69 and CD107a were purchased from Beckon Dickinson Bioscience (Miami, FL, USA). TRPM3 primary and secondary antibody was purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Dallas, TX, USA). Isotypes were used to determine negative cell populations. TRPM3 primary antibody was blocked by peptide amino acids that bind to the 816&#x02010;897aa of TRPM3 of human origin (Accession number Q9HCF6) and binds to the extracellular domain to determine non&#x02010;specific binding.</p></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0005"><title>NK cells</title><p>Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) were isolated from ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid (EDTA) whole blood by centrifugation over a density gradient medium (Ficoll; GE Healthcare, Pittsburgh, PA, USA), followed by magnetic isolation for unlabelled NK cells using EasySep, as described by the manufacturer's instructions. Isolated NK cells from PBMCs were determined to be 90&#x000b7;4%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x000b7;82 purity for CFS/ME patients and 91&#x000b7;6%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5&#x000b7;61 for HC. Isolated NK cells were identified as CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>&#x02013;/dim</sup> and CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells.</p></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0006"><title>TRPM3, CD69 and CD107a surface expression on NK cells</title><p>TRPM3 expression on resting NK cell subsets was identified as described previously <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref>. Briefly, NK cells were labelled with CD3, CD56, CD16 and primary TRPM3 antibodies for 30 min at room temperature. NK cells were washed and stained with TRPM3 secondary antibody for 30 min. Stimulated NK cells were assessed further in the presence of PregS, ionomycin, 2APB&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS and TG&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS for 4 h at 37&#x002da;C. Cells were stained with CD69, CD107a and TRPM3 primary antibody for 30 min to determine CD69, CD107a and TRPM3 receptor expression on CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup> NK cells and CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cell subpopulations. True cell counting beads were used to calculate NK cell concentration as well as absolute cell counts and was determined using the manufacturer's instructions outlined in the following formula:
<disp-formula id="cei12882-disp-0001"><mml:math id="nlm-math-1"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0007"><title>Cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> in NK cells</title><p>Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux was performed as described previously <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref>. Briefly, Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization in NK cells was measured in the presence of ionomycin, 2&#x02010;APB and TG. Ionomycin is an ionopore that raises cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> levels independently of activated receptors, whereas 2&#x02010;APB and TG inhibit Ca<sup>2+</sup>&#x02010;dependent receptors on the endoplasmic reticulum (ER). 2&#x02010;APB prevent the release of intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores compared to TG, which inhibit the replenishment of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> into intracellular stores (Fig. <xref rid="cei12882-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Furthermore, assessment of Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx&#x02010;dependent TRPM3 receptors was determined using PregS. Isolated NK phenotypes were stimulated with PregS. Following this, NK cells were preincubated with either TG or 2APB prior to PregS stimulation. Cells were stimulated for 5 min and recorded in real time on flow cytometry.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="cei12882-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Systematic representation of calcium ions mobilization. Ionomycin is an ionopore that allows extracellular calcium ion into the cytosol. 2&#x02010;APB is a non&#x02010;selective TRPM and IP<sub>3</sub>R receptor, whereas thapsigargin inhibits intracellular calcium stores replenishment. ER&#x02009;=&#x02009;endoplasmic reticulum; SOC&#x02009;=&#x02009;store&#x02010;operated calcium channel; CRAC&#x02009;=&#x02009;calcium release activated channel; TRPM3&#x02009;=&#x02009;transient receptor potential melastatin subfamily 3; STIM&#x02009;=&#x02009;stromal interaction molecule; SERCA&#x02009;=&#x02009;sarco/endoplasmic reticulum Ca<sup>2+</sup>&#x02010;ATPase; IP<sub>3</sub>R&#x02009;=&#x02009;inositol trisphosphate receptor; PregS&#x02009;=&#x02009;pregnenolone sulphate; 2&#x02010;APB&#x02009;=&#x02009;2&#x02010;aminoethoxydiphenyl borate; Ca<sup>2+</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;calcium.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="CEI-187-284-g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0008"><title>NK cytotoxic activity</title><p>NK cell cytotoxicity baseline measurements were performed using 25 : 1, 12 : 1, 6 : 1 and 1 : 1 effector to target ratios, as described previously <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref>. NK cell cytotoxicity activity was measured indirectly through the percentage of apoptotic K562 cells. The NK cells were stimulated for 20 min in the presence of ionomycin, TG, 2APB and PregS or a combination of TG&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS and 2APB&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS. Cells were washed and plated with K562 cells at a 1 : 1 ratio, followed by incubation for 4 h at 37&#x002da;C. K562 cells were stained with annexin V and 7&#x02010;amino&#x02010;actinomycin D (7&#x02010;AAD) to determine K562 cell viability. K562 cell viability was determined into four stages; live/viable K562 cells (annexin V<sup>&#x02013;</sup> 7AAD<sup>&#x02013;</sup>), K562 cells undergoing early stage apoptosis (annexin V<sup>+</sup> 7AAD<sup>&#x02013;</sup>), late stage apoptosis (annexin V<sup>+</sup> 7AAD<sup>+</sup>) and dead K562 cells (annexin V<sup>&#x02013;</sup> 7AAD<sup>+</sup>). K562 cell death was calculated as described previously <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref> and outlined below.
<disp-formula id="cei12882-disp-0002"><mml:math id="nlm-math-2"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">E</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi><mml:mn>562</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">g</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi><mml:mn>562</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi><mml:mn>562</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi><mml:mn>562</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi><mml:mn>562</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi><mml:mn>562</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi><mml:mn>562</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0009"><title>Data and statistical analyses</title><p>Data were exported from FacDiva version 8.1 and analysed using FlowJo software version 10 (TreeStar, Inc., Ashland, OR, USA). Data were quantified using <sc>spss</sc> version 22.2 software (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA). Multivariate analysis of variance (<sc>manova</sc>) was performed to determine TRPM3 receptor expression in various stimulation conditions between HC and CFS/ME groups, as well as within each group. The Mann&#x02013;Whitney statistical <italic>U</italic>&#x02010;test was used to determine the specific relationship effects between each stimulant (PregS, TG&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS and 2APB&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS) on TRPM3, CD69 and CD107a surface expression on NK cell subsets from CFS/ME patients and HC. The Gaussian smoothing method was applied on the Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux response curve, prior to analyses of area under the curve (AUC), time of peak and slope. NK cell cytotoxic activity was measured by the percentage of K562 cell deaths as described by Aubry <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref>. Statistical significance was reported at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0010"><title>Results</title><sec id="cei12882-sec-0011"><title>Participants</title><p>A total of 40 participants were included in this investigation, 25 of which were HC and 15 were CFS/ME. The participants' demographic and standard serological results were recorded (Table <xref rid="cei12882-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap">1</xref>). There were no significant differences in gender, body mass index (BMI), full blood counts, electrolytes, stress hormones or inflammatory markers between HC and CFS/ME. There was a significant between&#x02010;group difference for age, as CFS/ME patients were significantly older than HC.</p><table-wrap id="cei12882-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Participants' demographic and serological results</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000border-right:solid 1px #000000" width="80pt" span="1"/><col style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000border-right:solid 1px #000000" width="80pt" span="1"/><col style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000border-right:solid 1px #000000" width="80pt" span="1"/><col style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000border-right:solid 1px #000000" width="80pt" span="1"/><col style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000border-right:solid 1px #000000" width="80pt" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HC</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CFS</th><th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>&#x02010;value</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td rowspan="6" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">General demographics</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female (%, <italic>n</italic>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68% (17)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70&#x000b7;6% (12)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male (%, <italic>n</italic>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32% (8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29&#x000b7;4% (5)</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x000b7;20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;12&#x000b7;124</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48&#x000b7;824&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9&#x000b7;838</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0&#x000b7;01</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#x000b7;387&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4&#x000b7;383</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#x000b7;602&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4&#x000b7;945</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;894</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Illness demographics</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SF&#x02010;36 score</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical functioning (%)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;000</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59&#x000b7;166&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;27&#x000b7;289</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0&#x000b7;016</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Role limitations due to physical health (%)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97&#x000b7;5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7&#x000b7;905</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x000b7;083&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7&#x000b7;216</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0&#x000b7;000</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Role limitations due to emotional problems (%)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96&#x000b7;66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10&#x000b7;540</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;46&#x000b7;056</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0&#x000b7;000</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Energy/fatigue (%)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;12&#x000b7;292</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x000b7;833&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;16&#x000b7;899</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0&#x000b7;000</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emotional well&#x02010;being (%)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83&#x000b7;2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7&#x000b7;495</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10&#x000b7;531</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0&#x000b7;000</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social functioning (%)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94&#x000b7;75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11&#x000b7;453</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28&#x000b7;125&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;25&#x000b7;497</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0&#x000b7;000</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain (%)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97&#x000b7;5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5&#x000b7;270</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43&#x000b7;75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;29&#x000b7;435</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0&#x000b7;000</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General health (%)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81&#x000b7;5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;12&#x000b7;258</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34&#x000b7;166&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;15&#x000b7;930</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0&#x000b7;000</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO DAS 2.0 (%)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;069&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;218</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41&#x000b7;078&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;16&#x000b7;216</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0&#x000b7;000</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="25" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">Serology report</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full blood count</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC (&#x000d7;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x000b7;736&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000b7;241</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x000b7;212&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000b7;162</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;218</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphocytes (&#x000d7;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x000b7;865&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;604</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x000b7;967&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;468</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;560</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocytes (&#x000d7;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;314&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;097</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;332&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;090</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;547</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophils (&#x000d7;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x000b7;363&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;831</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x000b7;708&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;961</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;222</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eosinophils (&#x000d7;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;160&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;088</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;182&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;128</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;517</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basophils (&#x000d7;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;029&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;019</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;027&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;014</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;609</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelets (&#x000d7;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263&#x000b7;000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;68&#x000b7;512</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">244&#x000b7;588&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;78&#x000b7;167</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;424</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haemoglobin (g/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138&#x000b7;000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11&#x000b7;384</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142&#x000b7;941&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10&#x000b7;556</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;163</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haematocrit (%)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;413&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;031</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;428&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;029</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;134</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RBC (&#x000d7;10<sup>12</sup>/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x000b7;670&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;368</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x000b7;769&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;371</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;395</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCV (fL)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88&#x000b7;560&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x000b7;927</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89&#x000b7;588&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x000b7;355</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;383</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Electrolytes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium (mmol/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136&#x000b7;600&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000b7;345</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129&#x000b7;325&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;33&#x000b7;152</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;278</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potassium (mmol/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x000b7;116&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;405</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x000b7;125&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;218</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;935</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloride (mmol/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102&#x000b7;560&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000b7;960</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102&#x000b7;313&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000b7;089</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;703</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bicarbonate (mmol/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26&#x000b7;280&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000b7;011</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27&#x000b7;563&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000b7;097</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;057</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anion gap (mmol/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x000b7;800&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000b7;893</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x000b7;750&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000b7;352</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;941</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inflammatory markers</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESR (mm/h)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13&#x000b7;240&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9&#x000b7;854</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#x000b7;882&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8&#x000b7;950</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;905</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP (mg/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x000b7;973&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000b7;165</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x000b7;417&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x000b7;620</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;633</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress hormones</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHEA sulphate (&#x003bc;mol/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x000b7;132&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000b7;129</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x000b7;733&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000b7;230</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;576</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACTH (ng/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x000b7;880&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8&#x000b7;303</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#x000b7;625&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6&#x000b7;386</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;361</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cortisol (nmol/l)</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">358&#x000b7;640&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;132&#x000b7;282</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286&#x000b7;067&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;89&#x000b7;850</td><td align="char" char="." valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b7;068</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="cei12882-note-0001"><p>Data shown are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation. HC&#x02009;=&#x02009;healthy controls; CFS&#x02009;=&#x02009;chronic fatigue syndrome; BMI&#x02009;=&#x02009;body mass index; WBC&#x02009;=&#x02009;white blood cell; RBC&#x02009;=&#x02009;red blood cell; MCV&#x02009;=&#x02009;mean corpuscular volume; ESR&#x02009;=&#x02009;erythrocyte sedimentation rate; CRP&#x02009;=&#x02009;C&#x02010;reactive protein; DHEA&#x02009;=&#x02009;dehydroepiandrosterone; ACTH&#x02009;=&#x02009;adrenocorticotrophic hormone. WHO DAS&#x02009;=&#x02009;World Health Organization Disability Assessment Schedule; SF&#x02010;26&#x02009;=&#x02009;Short&#x02010;Form Health Survey. Bold type indicates statistical significance (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>CFS/ME patients reported greater impairment compared with HC in all SF&#x02010;36 subscales (lower scores indicate greater impairment; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;05) and WHO DAS 2.0 subscales (higher scores indicate greater impairment; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;05), as shown in Table <xref rid="cei12882-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap">1</xref>. Significantly reduced SF&#x02010;36 scores and elevated WHO DAS 2.0 scores have been observed previously in other CFS/ME studies <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">19</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">20</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">21</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0012"><title>TRPM3 expressed on CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>&#x02013;/dim</sup> NK cells</title><p>CFS/ME had significantly reduced expression for TRPM3 receptors without stimulation in CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>&#x02013;/dim</sup> NK cells compared with HC (Fig. <xref rid="cei12882-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a&#x02013;c) Similarly, TG&#x02010;stimulated CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>&#x02013;/dim</sup> NK cells had depleted intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores and significantly reduced TRPM3 receptor expression in CFS/ME compared with HC (Fig. <xref rid="cei12882-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). Overall, CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>&#x02013;/dim</sup> NK cells from both groups (CFS/ME and HC) had increased TRPM3 receptors after depletion of intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores with TG and/or in combination with activating TRPM3 receptor with PregS, when compared without stimulation (Fig. <xref rid="cei12882-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). Furthermore, inhibiting inositol trisphosphate receptor (IP<sub>3</sub>R) with 2APB and/or in combination with activating the TRPM3 receptor with PregS in CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>&#x02013;/dim</sup>TRPM3<sup>+</sup> NK cells was not significantly different between or within each HC and CFS group (Fig. <xref rid="cei12882-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="cei12882-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Natural killer (NK) cell TRPM3 expression in HC and CFS/ME patients. CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup> NK cells expressed TRPM3 as cells/ml under various conditions. (a) Unstimulated PregS and ionomycin. (b) TG and TG&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS. (c) 2APB and 2APB&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS. CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells expressed TRPM3 as cells/ml under various conditions. (d) PregS and ionomycin. (e) TG and TG&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS. (f) 2APB and 2APB&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS. Data are represented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error of the mean. Asterisks (*) and (**) represent statistical significance at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;05 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;01, respectively. US&#x02009;=&#x02009;unstimulated; PregS&#x02009;=&#x02009;pregnenolone sulphate; TG&#x02009;=&#x02009;thapsigargin; HC&#x02009;=&#x02009;healthy controls; 2&#x02010;APB&#x02009;=&#x02009;2&#x02010;aminoethoxydiphenyl borate; CFS/ME&#x02009;=&#x02009;chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis. [Colour figure can be viewed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wileyonlinelibrary.com">wileyonlinelibrary.com</ext-link>]</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="CEI-187-284-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0013"><title>TRPM3 expressed on CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells</title><p>There was no significant between&#x02010;group difference in TRPM3 expression without stimulation of CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells. However, there was a significant between&#x02010;group difference (CFS/ME and HC) in TRPM3 expression following PregS stimulation (Fig. <xref rid="cei12882-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d). Interestingly, within the HC group there was a significant increase in TRPM3 ion channels on PregS&#x02010;stimulated CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells compared without stimulation. The CFS/ME group showed no significant difference in TRPM3 ion channel numbers in CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells after PregS stimulation. In addition, ionomycin&#x02010; stimulated CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells within HC and CFS/ME groups demonstrated a significant increase in TRPM3 ion channels (Fig. <xref rid="cei12882-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d). Similarly, CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup>TRPM3<sup>+</sup> NK cells within both groups increased TRPM3 receptors with TG&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS, TG and ionomycin when compared without stimulation. By comparison, no significant difference was observed after 2APB or 2APB&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS stimulation between or within each of the groups (HC and CFS/ME) (Fig. <xref rid="cei12882-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>f).</p></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0014"><title>Activation markers on NK cell subsets</title><p>There was no significant difference in either CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>&#x02013;/dim</sup> or CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells in CD107a and CD69 receptors between groups (data not shown). However, both NK cell subsets within groups showed no significant difference in CD69 receptor numbers between unstimulation and PregS. There was a significant reduction of CD69 receptor after TG and TG&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS stimulations (Fig. S<xref rid="cei12882-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells within groups showed a further reduction of CD69 receptor after 2APB and ionomycin compared without stimulation.</p><p>Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization in NK cell subsets was determined using FlowJo, as shown in Fig. <xref rid="cei12882-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. Each subset Ca<sup>2+</sup> response curve was reported as peak time (peak <italic>t</italic>) to determine the time for a reaction to reach its maximum. Slope is determined as follows: a positive slope implies that the <italic>y</italic>&#x02010;axis value is increasing over the time&#x02010;period, while a negative value implies that it is decreasing. The AUC is calculated to determine the duration and magnitude of Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux, which is represented as a single number.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="cei12882-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>FlowJo analysis of Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization response in isolated natural killer (NK) cells. (a) Gating strategies for CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup> NK cells and CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells are shown as a pseudocolour dot&#x02010;plot. (b) NK cell Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux is response over time, and displayed as a pseudocolour dot&#x02010;plot. (c) Summary of the kinetic analysis of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux in NK cells. Peak <italic>t</italic> is the time that the maximum <italic>y</italic>&#x02010;axis value occurred for the specific time range noted. Peak is the magnitude of the <italic>y</italic>&#x02010;axis value at its maximum for the specific time range noted. The mean of the <italic>y</italic>&#x02010;axis (mean <italic>Y</italic>) value is for the time range noted. The slope is the gain or loss of intensity over the duration of the time range for the calculated linear regression line of the data in this range. The area under the curve (AUC) is indicated by the grey stripes. Background of the calcium curve is shaded in pink. Post&#x02010;stimulant calcium response curve is shaded in purple.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="CEI-187-284-g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0015"><title>Intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization</title><p>CD56<sup>bright</sup> CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup> NK cell Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux showed significantly increased AUC in CFS/ME compared with controls after PregS (Fig. <xref rid="cei12882-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). There was no significant difference in the AUC in CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup>TRPM3<sup>+</sup> NK cells (Fig. <xref rid="cei12882-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b). Overall, within both groups there was an increase in AUC after PregS stimulation compared with no stimulation.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="cei12882-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Cytoplasmic calcium in natural killer (NK) cells from HC and CFS/ME patients. (a) CD56<sup>bright</sup> CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup> NK cell calcium flux response area under the curve. (b) CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup>TRPM3<sup>+</sup> NK cell calcium flux response area under the curve. Data are represented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error of the mean. Asterisks (*) and (**) represent statistical significance at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;05 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;01, respectively. Abbreviations: US&#x02009;=&#x02009;unstimulated; PregS&#x02009;=&#x02009;pregnenolone sulphate; TG&#x02009;=&#x02009;thapsigargin; HC&#x02009;=&#x02009;healthy controls; CFS/ME&#x02009;=&#x02009;chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="CEI-187-284-g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0016"><title>NK cytotoxic activity</title><p>NK cells demonstrated significantly increased cytotoxic activity when stimulated with TG&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS in CFS/ME compared with the HC group. No significant between&#x02010;group differences were seen with PregS, ionomycin and 2APB (Fig. <xref rid="cei12882-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="cei12882-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Natural killer (NK) cell cytotoxic activity after incubation with ionomycin, PregS, TG&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS and 2APB&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS in HC and CFS/ME. Note significant elevation of K562 cell death in CFS/ME following TG&#x02009;+&#x02009;PregS. Data are represented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error of the mean. Asterisk (*) represents statistical significance at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0&#x000b7;05. PregS&#x02009;=&#x02009;pregnenolone sulphate; 2&#x02010;APB&#x02009;=&#x02009;2&#x02010;aminoethoxydiphenyl borate; TG&#x02009;=&#x02009;thapsigargin; CFS/ME&#x02009;=&#x02009;chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="CEI-187-284-g005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0017"><title>Discussion</title><p>Previous investigations have reported significant reductions in NK cell cytotoxic activity in CFS/ME patients, and the current investigation supports those findings <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref>. The current investigation also confirms our previous results of significantly reduced TRPM3 receptors on NK cells as well as significantly reduced intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization in isolated NK cells <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref>. The current investigation showed inhibition of the ER Ca<sup>2+/</sup>ATPase pump and depletion of intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores followed by PregS&#x02010;activated TRPM3 increased cytotoxic activity in NK cells from CFS/ME patients (Fig. <xref rid="cei12882-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="cei12882-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>A conceptual natural killer (NK) model for chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis (CFS/ME) patients. Pregnenolone sulphate (PregS) is a potent steroid that activated transient receptor potential melastatin 3 ion channels (TRPM3) on NK cell subsets. PregS in combination with thapsigargin elevated cytoplasmic calcium and is suggested to phosphorylate extracellular&#x02010;regulated kinase (ERK) 1/2 and polarization of secretory granules for degranulation in CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells, resulting in target K562 cell death, whereas PregS&#x02010;stimulated CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup> NK cells may activate p38 MAPK signalling pathways involved in the nuclear factor kappa B (NF&#x02010;&#x003ba;&#x003b2;) inflammatory immune response.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-13" xlink:href="CEI-187-284-g006"/></fig><p>TRPM3 receptors are constitutively open <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">12</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref> and are activated by steroids <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">15</xref>, hypotonic cell swelling and Ca<sup>2+</sup> store depletion <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>, but these findings are inconsistent <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref>. Our results support increased TRPM3 surface protein expression when intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores are depleted through inhibition of the ER Ca<sup>2+/</sup>ATPase pump when activated by PregS.</p><p>Under no stimulation, CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup>TRPM3<sup>+</sup> NK cells from CFS/ME demonstrated significantly lower TRPM3 surface expression compared with HC, which is consistent with previous findings <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref>. TRPM3 can be activated by PregS concentration in the range of 0&#x000b7;1&#x02013;5 &#x003bc;M, corresponding to physiological PregS serum concentrations <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">24</xref>. At 1&#x000b7;35 &#x003bc;M PregS (within physiological range), CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup>TRPM3<sup>+</sup> NK cells did not change between groups. However, these cells increased intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> significantly compared with HC. In comparison, PregS&#x02010;stimulated CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells increased TRPM3 receptor expression significantly and may not be associated with Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux in CFS/ME patients. This is based on the assumption that an increase in TRPM3 receptor should result in an increase in cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> levels. A possible rationale for this finding may be that TRPM3 ion channels expressed on CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells have impaired Ca<sup>2+</sup> flux function, which is compensated by increasing their surface expression. Moreover, it may be suggested that single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) identified in TRPM3 genomic DNA from PBMCs and NK cells in CFS/ME patients result in impaired protein expression and reduced TRPM3 Ca<sup>2+</sup> function <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>. Importantly, when Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx is prevented or reduced, an immunological synapse is not formed, preventing the formation of mitotic spindles for cytoskeleton movement to facilitate the secretory vesicles leading to abnormal lysis of target cells <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">25</xref>. The deficits identified above may thus contribute to impaired lysis of CFS/ME NK cells.</p><p>Interestingly, our study supports the finding that ionomycin alone does not improve NK cytotoxic activity, but it elevates TRPM3 expression on CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells compared with HC. TRPM3 expression is increased when ionomycin raises cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> through phospholipase C&#x02010;dependent mobilization of Ca<sup>2+</sup> stores <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">26</xref>. Prolonged treatment with ionomycin has been reported previously to render NK cells hyporesponsive, and hence these cells probably require a higher signal intensity to mount an effective response <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">27</xref>.</p><p>CFS/ME patients have significantly decreased extracellular&#x02010;regulated kinase (ERK) 1/2 in CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells and significantly increased mitogen&#x02010;activated protein kinase kinase (MEK) 1/2 and p38 in CD56<sup>bright</sup>CD16<sup>dim/&#x02013;</sup> NK cells following incubation with K562 cells <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">28</xref>. ERK 1/2 is activated in a P13K&#x02010;dependent manner that may also be associated with cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> ion levels through activation of TRPM3 <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>. In the absence of phosphatidylinositol biphosphate TRPM3 is not activated, resulting in reduced cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup>
<xref rid="cei12882-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">29</xref>. Stimulating CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells with TG prior to PregS resulted in a significant elevation in cytotoxic activity. These findings are noteworthy, as it has been reported that depleting intracellular stores with TG increases activity of ERK. Phosphorylation of ERK 1/2 allows polarization of secretory granules for degranulation and therefore increased NK cell lysis in CFS patients <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">30</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">31</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">32</xref>.</p><p>CFS/ME patients have been reported to have a significant reduction in CD69 expression on T cells and NK cells upon stimulation, which may correspond to impaired initial cell activation through a PKC&#x02010;dependent signalling pathway <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref>. However, this current investigation found no significant difference between groups. <italic>In vitro</italic>, degranulation is activated in NK cells when an immunosynapse is formed between NK cells and K562 tumour cells <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">33</xref>. During degranulation, cytolytic granules containing lytic proteins are released and CD107a receptors are expressed on the NK cell surface. In the current investigation CD107a was not significantly different between groups, and this finding is supported by others <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">28</xref>. PKC is activated by elevated intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration, which activates ERK signalling pathways and transcription factors <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">32</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">34</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">35</xref>. Inhibition of PKC has been shown to impaired signaling pathways that activate TRPM3&#x02010;induced transcription factor activator protein&#x02010;1 (AP&#x02010;1) <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">35</xref>. Our results also show that CD69 is reduced when NK cells are stimulated with TG. However, in combination with PregS stimulation, which facilitates an increase in cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> and activates PKC and ERK signalling pathways, NK cell cytotoxic activity in CFS/ME patients increased.</p><p>The current investigation confirms our previous reports of significant changes in TRPM3 receptor numbers in NK cells in CFS/ME. Following PregS stimulation, however, there was no significant increase in Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization in CD56<sup>dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cells from CFS/ME patients. These novel findings suggest that TRPM3 receptor function is impaired, resulting in impaired Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization with adverse consequences for homeostasis. As TRPM3 receptors are expressed throughout the human body, the current findings suggest that impaired TRPM3 function may play a significant role in the multisystemic pathomechanism of CFS/ME. Other TRP receptors, such as TRPM1, may possibly have a similar role in CFS/ME pathomechanism due to its sequence homology with TRPM3; however, further investigation is warranted <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">36</xref>. We have previously identified genomic changes in other TRPs and autonomic receptors, which should be investigated further <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">37</xref>, <xref rid="cei12882-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">38</xref>.</p><p>The results of this study are considered preliminary, and are limited by our small sample size. Accordingly, we found that our CFS/ME patients were older compared with HC; however, routine pathological screening showed no difference between groups. As CFS/ME is a heterogeneous condition, future directions aim to optimize these findings in a larger cohort. In this pilot study, we characterized our CFS/ME patients by reduced NK cytotoxic activity compared with HC. We further aimed to capture those with significant functional impairment according to SF&#x02010;36 and WHO DAS 2.0 disability scores. To define further the role of TRPM3 and Ca<sup>2+</sup>, future study will examine findings in distinct clinical phenotypes of CFS/ME to elucidate the distinct physiological effects of this mechanism.</p></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0018"><title>Conclusions</title><p>TRPM3 activity and function in NK cells in CFS/ME patients is impaired, resulting in changes in Ca<sup>2+</sup> ion concentration in the cytosol and intracellular stores which may, in turn, change the NK cells' activation threshold. Cytotoxic NK cells from CFS/ME patients may attempt to compensate for impaired TRPM3 receptors by increasing intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> for sufficient NK cell activity. Increasing Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations to activate the ERK signalling pathway may help to improve NK cell cytotoxicity in CFS/ME. Improvement of Ca<sup>2+</sup>&#x02010;dependent NK activity may help to improve the immune system in CFS/ME patients to facilitate a quicker response to eliminate pathogens. Moreover, improvement of cell&#x02010;to&#x02010;cell interaction could improve the development of antigen&#x02010;specific memory cells. This investigation may inform the pathomechanism of reduced NK cell cytotoxicity in CFS/ME patients.</p></sec><sec id="cei12882-sec-0020"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors declare that they have no disclosures.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Additional supporting information may be found in the online version of this article at the publisher's web&#x02010;site</p></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><caption><p>
<bold>Fig. S1</bold>. NK cell CD69 expression in HC and CFS/ME patients. A. CD56<sup>Bright</sup>CD16<sup>Dim/&#x02212;</sup> NK cells expressed CD69 as cells/ml under various conditions including PregS, TG, 2APB and ionomycin. B. CD56<sup>Dim</sup>CD16<sup>+</sup> NK cell expressed TRPM3 as cells/ml under various conditions including PregS, TG, 2APB and ionomycin. Data are represented as Mean with SEM. Asterisk (*) represents statistical significance at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;(0.05). Abbreviations: US: Unstimulated, PregS: Pregnenolone sulphate, TG: Thapsigargin, HC: Healthy controls, CFS/ME: Chronic Fatigue Syndrome/Myalgic Encephalomyelitis.</p></caption><media xlink:href="CEI-187-284-s001.pptx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="cei12882-sec-0019"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This study was supported by funding from the Stafford Fox Medical Research Foundation, Change for ME Charity, Alison Hunter Memorial Foundation, Mason Foundation and Queensland Co&#x02010;Investment Program.</p></ack><ref-list content-type="cited-references"><title>References</title><ref id="cei12882-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Carruthers</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>van de Sande</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>De Meirleir</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic>et al</italic>
<article-title>Myalgic encephalomyelitis: international consensus criteria</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>270</volume>:<fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21777306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Fukuda</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Straus</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hickie</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sharpe</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dobbins</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Komaroff</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>The chronic fatigue syndrome: a comprehensive approach to its definition and study. International Chronic Fatigue Syndrome Study Group</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
<year>1994</year>; <volume>121</volume>:<fpage>953</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7978722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Stayer</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Low NK cell activity in chronic fatigue syndrome (CFS) and relationship to symptom severity</article-title>. <source>J Clin Cell Immunol</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>348</fpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Draghi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yawata</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gleimer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yawata</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Valiante</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Parham</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Single&#x02010;cell analysis of the human NK cell response to missing self and its inhibition by HLA class I</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>105</volume>:<fpage>2028</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15528315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Borrego</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pena</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Solana</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Regulation of CD69 expression on human natural killer cells: differential involvement of protein kinase C and protein tyrosine kinases</article-title>. <source>Eur J Immunol</source>
<year>1993</year>; <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1039</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8477800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Mihaylova</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>DeRuyter</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rummens</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bosmans</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Maes</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Decreased expression of CD69 in chronic fatigue syndrome in relation to inflammatory markers: evidence for a severe disorder in the early activation of T lymphocytes and natural killer cells</article-title>. <source>Neuro Endocrinol Lett</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>477</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17693977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Alter</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Malenfant</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Altfeld</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>CD107a as a functional marker for the identification of natural killer cell activity</article-title>. <source>J Immunol Methods</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>294</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15604012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Schwarz</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Qu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hoth</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Calcium, cancer and killing: the role of calcium in killing cancer cells by cytotoxic T lymphocytes and natural killer cells</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>1833</volume>:<fpage>1603</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23220009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Nilius</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>TRP channels in disease</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>1772</volume>:<fpage>805</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17368864</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic>et al</italic>
<article-title>Expression and characterization of human transient receptor potential melastatin 3 (hTRPM3)</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>278</volume>:<fpage>20890</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12672827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Oberwinkler</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Philipp</surname>
<given-names>SE.</given-names>
</string-name> TRPM3. Handbook of experimental pharmacology <year>2014</year>; <volume>222</volume>:<fpage>427</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Oberwinkler</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lis</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Giehl</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Flockerzi</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Philipp</surname>
<given-names>SE.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Alternative splicing switches the divalent cation selectivity of TRPM3 channels</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>280</volume>:<fpage>22540</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15824111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Fruhwald</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Camacho Londono</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dembla</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic>et al</italic>
<article-title>Alternative splicing of a protein domain indispensable for function of transient receptor potential melastatin 3 (TRPM3) ion channels</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>287</volume>:<fpage>36663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22961981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Nilius</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Voets</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>A TRP channel&#x02010;steroid marriage</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19043430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Harteneck</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Pregnenolone sulfate: from steroid metabolite to TRP channel ligand</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>12012</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24084011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Nguyen</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Staines</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nilius</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Marshall&#x02010;Gradisnik</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Novel identification and characterisation of transient receptor potential melastatin 3 ion channels on natural killer cells and B lymphocytes: effects on cell signalling in chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis patients</article-title>. <source>Biol Res</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27245705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Marshall&#x02010;Gradisnik</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Huth</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chacko</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Johnston</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Staines</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Natural killer cells and single nucleotide polymorphisms of specific ion channels and receptor genes in myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome</article-title>. <source>Appl Clin Genet</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27099524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Aubry</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Blaecke</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lecoanet&#x02010;Henchoz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic>et al</italic>
<article-title>Annexin V used for measuring apoptosis in the early events of cellular cytotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Cytometry</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>204</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10520200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Johnston</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Brenu</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hardcastle</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>A comparison of health status in patients meeting alternative definitions for chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis</article-title>. <source>Health Qual Life out</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>64</fpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Jason</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic>et al</italic>
<article-title>Fatigue scales and chronic fatigue syndrome: issues of sensitivity and specificity</article-title>. <source>Disabil Stud Q</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1375</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21966179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Reeves</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Maloney</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic>et al</italic>
<article-title>Prevalence of chronic fatigue syndrome in metropolitan, urban, and rural Georgia</article-title>. <source>Popul Health Metr</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17559660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Grimm</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kraft</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sauerbruch</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Schultz</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Harteneck</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Molecular and functional characterization of the melastatin&#x02010;related cation channel TRPM3</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>278</volume>:<fpage>21493</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>501</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12672799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Vriens</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Owsianik</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hofmann</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic>et al</italic>
<article-title>TRPM3 is a nociceptor channel involved in the detection of noxious heat</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>482</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21555074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Majeed</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Agarwal</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Naylor</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic>et al</italic>
<article-title>Cis&#x02010;isomerism and other chemical requirements of steroidal agonists and partial agonists acting at TRPM3 channels</article-title>. <source>Br J Pharmacol</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>161</volume>:<fpage>430</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20735426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Mace</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dongre</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hsu</surname>
<given-names>HT</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic>et al</italic>
<article-title>Cell biological steps and checkpoints in accessing NK cell cytotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Immunol Cell Biol</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24445602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Dedkova</surname>
<given-names>EN</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sigova</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zinchenko</surname>
<given-names>VP.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Mechanism of action of calcium ionophores on intact cells: ionophore&#x02010;resistant cells</article-title>. <source>Membr Cell Biol</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10768486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Romera&#x02010;Cardenas</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lopez&#x02010;Cobo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Garcia&#x02010;Cuesta</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Long</surname>
<given-names>EO</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Reyburn</surname>
<given-names>HT.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Ionomycin treatment renders NK cells hyporesponsive</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0150998</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27007115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Huth</surname>
<given-names>TK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Staines</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Marshall&#x02010;Gradisnik</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>ERK1/2, MEK1/2 and p38 downstream signalling molecules impaired in CD56 dim CD16+ and CD56 bright CD16 dim/&#x02013; natural killer cells in chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis patients</article-title>. <source>J Transl Med</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27098723</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>Toth</surname>
<given-names>BI</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Oberwinkler</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Voets</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Phosphoinositide regulation of TRPM channels &#x02013; TRPM3 joins the club!</article-title>
<source>Channels (Austin)</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26517445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gamero</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic>et al</italic>
<article-title>Control of lytic function by mitogen&#x02010;activated protein kinase/extracellular regulatory kinase 2 (ERK2) in a human natural killer cell line: identification of perforin and granzyme B mobilization by functional ERK2</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>187</volume>:<fpage>1753</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9607917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Trivedi</surname>
<given-names>PP</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ge</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Krzewski</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Strominger</surname>
<given-names>JL.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Many NK cell receptors activate ERK2 and JNK1 to trigger microtubule organizing center and granule polarization and cytotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>104</volume>:<fpage>6329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17395718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0032">
<string-name>
<surname>Maloney</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tsygankova</surname>
<given-names>OM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic>et al</italic>
<article-title>Activation of ERK by Ca2+ store depletion in rat liver epithelial cells</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>276</volume>:<fpage>C221</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9886938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0033">
<string-name>
<surname>Shabrish</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Madkaikar</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>A modified NK cell degranulation assay applicable for routine evaluation of NK cell function</article-title>. <source>J Immunol Res</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>2016</volume>:<fpage>3769590</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27413758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0034">
<string-name>
<surname>Rubil</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rossler</surname>
<given-names>OG</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Thiel</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>CREB, AP&#x02010;1, ternary complex factors and MAP kinases connect transient receptor potential melastatin&#x02010;3 (TRPM3) channel stimulation with increased c&#x02010;Fos expression</article-title>. <source>Br J Pharmacol</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>173</volume>:<fpage>305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26493679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0035">
<string-name>
<surname>Lesch</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hui</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lipp</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Thiel</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Transient receptor potential melastatin&#x02010;3 (TRPM3)&#x02010;induced activation of AP&#x02010;1 requires Ca2+ ions and the transcription factors c&#x02010;Jun, ATF2, and ternary complex factor</article-title>. <source>Mol Pharmacol</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>87</volume>:<fpage>617</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25576487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0036">
<string-name>
<surname>Lambert</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Drews</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rizun</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic>et al</italic>
<article-title>Transient receptor potential melastatin 1 (TRPM1) is an ion&#x02010;conducting plasma membrane channel inhibited by zinc ions</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>286</volume>:<fpage>12221</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21278253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0037">
<string-name>
<surname>Marshall&#x02010;Gradisnik</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Huth</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chacko</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Johnston</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Staines</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Natural killer cells and single nucleotide polymorphisms of specific ion channels and receptor genes in myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome</article-title>. <source>Appl Clin Genet</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27099524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cei12882-bib-0038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cei12882-cit-0038">
<string-name>
<surname>Marshall&#x02010;Gradisnik</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Brenu</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nilius</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ramos</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Staines</surname>
<given-names>DR.</given-names>
</string-name>
<article-title>Examination of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in transient receptor potential (TRP) ion channels in chronic fatigue syndrome patients</article-title>. <source>Immunol Immunogenet Insights</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>