<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="correction"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int. J. Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJO</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1019-6439</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1791-2423</issn><publisher><publisher-name>D.A. Spandidos</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27826623</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5063429</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/ijo.2016.3714</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijo-49-05-2189</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Corrigendum</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Corrigendum</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>49</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2189</fpage><lpage>2189</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Li et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License</ext-link>, which permits use and distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="corrected-article" id="d36e61" vol="41" page="1809" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="22948234" ext-link-type="pubmed"/></article-meta></front><body><p><bold>Adenovirus-mediated overexpression of BMP-9 inhibits human osteosarcoma cell growth and migration through downregulation of the PI3K/AKT pathway</bold></p><p>BO LI, YUEHUA YANG, SHENGDAN JIANG, BINBIN NI, KE CHEN and LEISHENG JIANG</p><p>Int J Oncol 41: 1809-1819, 2012; DOI: 10.3892/ijo.2012.1617</p><p>Following the publication of this article, an interested reader drew to our attention an anomaly associated with the presentation of the western blots in <xref rid="f1-ijo-49-05-2189" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B and C</xref>. These contained the same GAPDH control data, even though <xref rid="f1-ijo-49-05-2189" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B and C</xref> were intended to show the inhibition of osteosarcoma cell migration by a recombinant adenovirus (ad) expressing bone morphogenetic protein 9 (adBMP-9) in two different cell lines, MG-63 and HOS, respectively.</p><p>After having re-examined our original data, we realize that the same GAPDH control bands were inadvertently selected for <xref rid="f1-ijo-49-05-2189" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B and C</xref>.</p><p>A corrected version of <xref rid="f1-ijo-49-05-2189" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, containing alternative data obtained from the experiments performed in duplicate, is presented below. Western blot assay was performed to examine the effect of adBMP-9 on metalloproteinase-9 (MMP-9) expression, showing that the expression of MMP-9 protein was significantly inhibited in the adBMP-9 group compared with the ad-green fluorescent protein (GFP) and the control (CON) groups in the MG-63 and HOS cell lines. In addition, no marked differences were noted between the ad-GFP group and the CON group. The error made with the selection of the control data did not affect the results in this study. We sincerely apologize for this mistake, and thank the reader of our article who drew this matter to our attention. Furthermore, we regret any inconvenience this mistake has caused.</p><fig id="f1-ijo-49-05-2189" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Inhibition of osteosarcoma cell migration by adBMP-9 in MG-63 and HOS cell lines. (A) Wound-healing assay showed that the migration capacity of OS cells in adBMP-9 group was markedly lower than those in ad-GFP group and CON group. No difference was found between ad-GFP group and CON group. (B and C) Western blot assay was performed to examine the effect of adBMP-9 on MMP-9 expression, showing that the expression of MMP-9 protein was significantly inhibited in adBMP-9 group compared with the ad-GFP group and CON group in MG-63 and HOS cell lines. No difference was found between ad-GFP group and CON group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJO-49-05-2189-g00"/></fig></body></article>