<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Int Oral Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Int Oral Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIOH</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of International Oral Health : JIOH</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0976-7428</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0976-1799</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dentmedpub Research and Printing Co</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26028904</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4441238</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JIOH-7-53</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>An <italic>In Vitro</italic> Comparative Evaluation of Fracture Resistance of Custom Made, Metal, Glass Fiber Reinforced and Carbon Reinforced Posts in Endodontically Treated Teeth</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sonkesriya</surname><given-names>Subhash</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Olekar</surname><given-names>Santosh T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saravanan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Somasunderam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>Rashmi Singh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chaurasia</surname><given-names>Vishwajit Rampratap</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Senior Lecturer, Department of Prosthodontics, Government College of Dentistry, Indore, Madhya Pradesh, India</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Reader, Department of Oral &#x00026; Maxillofacial Pathology &#x00026; Microbiology, New Horizon Dental College &#x00026; Research Institute, Bilaspur, Chhattisgarh, India</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Reader, Department of Conservative Dentistry and Endodontics, Sri Venkateswara Dental College, Puducherry, India</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Faculty Member, Department of Prosthodontics, Mahsa University, Kualalumpur, Malaysia</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Senior Lecturer, Department of Pedodontics, Sinhgad Dental College &#x00026; Hospital, Pune, Maharashtra, India</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Postgraduate Student, Department of Conservative Dentistry &#x00026; Endodontics, KLE&#x02019;S Dental College, Belgaum, Karnataka, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold><italic>Correspondence:</italic></bold> Dr. Chaurasia VR. Department of Conservative Dentistry &#x00026; Endodontics, KLE&#x02019;S Dental College, Belgaum, Karnataka, India. Email: <email xlink:href="anilkk44@gmail.com">anilkk44@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Journal of International Oral Health</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background:</title><p>Posts are used to enhance crown buildup in pulpless teeth with destructed crown portion. Different types of post are used in endodontically treated teeth. The aim of the present <italic>in vitro</italic> study was to evaluate fracture resistance of custom made, metal, glass fiber reinforced and carbon reinforced posts in endodontically treated teeth.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>An <italic>in vitro</italic> study was carried out on extracted 40 human maxillary central incisor teeth, which was divided into four groups with 10 samples in each group with custom made, metal post, glass fiber reinforced, and carbon reinforced posts. The samples were decoronated at cemento-enamel junction and endodontically treated. Post space was prepared and selected posts were cemented. The composite cores were prepared at the height of 5 mm and samples mounted on acrylic blocks. Later fracture resistance to the compressive force of samples was measured using Universal Testing Machine.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>The maximum resistance to the compressive force was observed in carbon reinforced and glass fiber reinforced posts compared others which is statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.001) and least was seen in custom fabricated post.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>It is concluded that carbon reinforced fiber post and glass fiber posts showed good fracture resistance compared to custom made and metal posts.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Carbon reinforced post</kwd><kwd>custom post</kwd><kwd>fracture</kwd><kwd>fracture resistance</kwd><kwd>glass fiber post</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Endodontically treated teeth should be restored since there is a loss of structure, changes in physical characters, dehydration and altered esthetic of remaining tooth structure. Post and core with full coronal restoration is a common method to restore coronal portion of lost tooth structure. Dowel is a post placed in the root of a non-vital tooth to retain core portion.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Endodontic post can be metallic or nan-metallic, custom made or prefabricated, esthetic or non-esthetic. Custom and metallic post was widely used to strengthen the endodontically treated teeth. With increase demand for esthetic and better physical quality, various tooth-colored posts such as glass fiber reinforced post, carbon fiber post, zirconia post, and composite post were developed.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Modulus of elasticity for stainless steel and titanium posts are 20 and 10 times greater than dentine, whereas glass fiber reinforced post are bonded to composite core and have modulus of elasticity nearly equal to that of dentine hence reduces possibility of root fracture.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> There are very few published studies comparing fracture resistance of the metal and fiber posts. Hence the present study was aimed to compare the fracture resistance of endodontically treated teeth restored with different posts such as custom made, metallic, fiber reinforced and carbon reinforced posts.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>Totally 40 extracted maxillary incisors free from caries, fracture and cervical abrasion were collected for <italic>in vitro</italic> study and stored in normal saline at room temperature (24-28&#x000b0;C). Root canal treatment, followed by the obturation was carried out on selected specimens. The selected teeth were randomly assigned into four experimental groups with ten in each group (Group A: Custom post, Group B: Stain less metal post, Group C: Fiber reinforced post, Group D: Carbon fiber reinforced post). The samples were decoronated at cemento-enamel junction and endodontically treated. Post space was prepared and selected posts were cemented.</p><p>In all groups, post space preparation was done by removing the gutta-percha with peeso-reamer and leaving 4 mm of gutta-percha apically. In Group A, direct inlay pattern of post and core was prepared. The pattern was casted With Type III cast gold alloy. The post space was treated with chelating agent (Glyde Germany), and subsequently irrigated with 5.25% sodium hypochlorite to remove the smear layer. The post and core were cemented with dual cure adhesive cement (Panvia F, Kuraray, Osaka, Japan). In Group B, C and D after post space preparation, selected posts (stainless steel, glass fiber reinforced and carbon reinforced posts) were cemented with dual cure resin cement and composite core build-up was done to the height of 5 mm.</p><p>All specimens were mounted on the acrylic block, and subjected to the compressive force at 1 mm diameter at an angle of 130&#x000b0; to long axis of the tooth using Instron Universal Testing Machine. The force at fracture was measured in MPa. Data were tabulated and statistically analyzed using analysis of variance and <italic>t</italic>-tests (SPSS version 21, IBM).</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>Results</title><p>In the present study carbon fiber reinforced posts and glass fiber reinforced posts showed highest fracture resistance as compared to custom post and metal posts (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref> showed that there was no significant difference between glass fiber (Group C) and carbon fiber posts (Group D) and between custom post (Group A) and metal posts (Group B, where as between other groups it is statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.001).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Mean, median and standard deviation values for fracture resistance in different groups (MPa).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIOH-7-53-g001"/></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparative evaluation between experimental groups.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JIOH-7-53-g002"/></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Esthetic, functional, and structural rehabilitation of pulpless teeth is critically important for successful endodontic therapy.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Clinically, longevity of post-core-crown system for endodontically treated teeth depends on the design, length and diameter of the post, ferrule effect, cementation and amount of remaining tooth substance.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Since many years custom post was used commonly for restoring endodontically treated teeth. Use of prefabricated posts reduced the laboratory and chair side time. Prefabricated posts are as available as metallic or fiber posts. In 1992, glass fiber posts were introduced. Fiber posts are strong, improves esthetics, reduces corrosion and toxicity.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Glass fiber posts are composed of unidirectional glass fibers embedded in a resin matrix which increases the post strength without changes in modulus of elasticity. In a glass reinforced fiber posts stress is distributed in broader surface area, hence reduces the chances of root fracture.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></p><p>In the present study, carbon fiber reinforced posts and glass fiber reinforced posts showed highest fracture resistance as compared to custom post and metal posts (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref> showed that there was no significant difference between glass fiber (Group C) and carbon fiber posts (Group D) and between custom post (Group A) and metal posts (Group B, where as between other groups it is statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.001).</p><p>Results of our study is in agreement with the study by Dean <italic>et al</italic>. <italic>in vitro</italic> study, who observed no root fractures with carbon post, 50 % of teeth had root fracture with cast post.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Similarly Fredriksson <italic>et al</italic>. and Preethi and Kala observed good clinical success with carbon posts and glass fiber posts.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Makade <italic>et al</italic>. concluded that, glass fiber post is better compared to metal posts.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Our results are consistent with Kantor and Pines, Sirimai <italic>et al</italic>. and Sidoli <italic>et al</italic>.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>-<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Robbins recommended use of post to increase the fracture resistance.<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p><p>Whereas Martinez-Insua <italic>et al</italic>. observed significantly higher fracture strength with cast post and core as compared to carbon fiber posts.<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Ferrari <italic>et al</italic>. concluded that composite posts systems are superior to cast post and core system, and they observed 14% failure with cast post system.<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Adanir and Belli concluded that for clinical success, posts shorter than clinical crowns should be avoided<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Jalalian and Mirzaei concluded from their study that, fiber posts with larger diameter adhere to the root structure more efficiently.<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></p><p>Makade <italic>et al</italic>. found that teeth restored with cast post and core found to have cervical and middle third root fracture whereas glass fiber posts demonstrated only core fracture.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Garhnayak <italic>et al</italic>. concluded that incorporation of ferrule offered some degree of stress reduction in post restored teeth.<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Present <italic>in vitro</italic> study helps to know about the physical quality of different types of posts which can be useful in post selection and clinical successful outcome of endodontic therapy.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>It is concluded that carbon reinforced fiber post and glass fiber posts showed good fracture resistance compared to custom made and metal posts. This <italic>in vitro</italic> study helps in the selection of posts for successful endodontic therapy.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold><italic>Conflicts of Interest: None</italic></bold></p></fn><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold><italic>Source of Support: Nil</italic></bold></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makade</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Meshram</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Warhadpande</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparative evaluation of fracture resistance of endodontically treated teeth restored with different post core systems - an <italic>in-vitro</italic> study</article-title><source>J Adv Prosthodont</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21814618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preethi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical evaluation of carbon fiber reinforced carbon endodontic post, glass fiber reinforced post with cast post and core: A one year comparative clinical study</article-title><source>J Conserv Dent</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20351975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keswani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Maria</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Punga</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparative evaluation of the retention of tooth coloured and stainless steel endodontic posts: An <italic>in-vitro</italic> study</article-title><source>J Clin Diagn Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>ZC04</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24959506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeansonne</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> evaluation of a carbon fiber post</article-title><source>J Endod</source><year>1998</year><volume>24</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10023259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fredriksson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Astb&#x000e4;ck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pamenius</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arvidson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A retrospective study of 236 patients with teeth restored by carbon fiber-reinforced epoxy resin posts</article-title><source>J Prosthet Dent</source><year>1998</year><volume>80</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9710815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kantor</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Pines</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparative study of restorative techniques for pulpless teeth</article-title><source>J Prosthet Dent</source><year>1977</year><volume>38</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">333108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sirimai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Riis</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgano</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An <italic>in vitro</italic> study of the fracture resistance and the incidence ofvertical root fracture of pulpless teeth restored with six post-and-coresystems</article-title><source>J Prosthet Dent</source><year>1999</year><volume>81</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>262</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10050112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sidoli</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Setchell</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An <italic>in vitro</italic> evaluation of a carbon fiber-based post and core system</article-title><source>J Prosthet Dent</source><year>1997</year><volume>78</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9237139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Restoration of the endodontically treated tooth</article-title><source>Dent Clin North Am</source><year>2002</year><volume>46</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12014038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Insua</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rilo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Santana</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the fracture resistances of pulpless teeth restored with a cast post and core or carbon-fiber post with a composite core</article-title><source>J Prosthet Dent</source><year>1998</year><volume>80</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9813801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vichi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Godoy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical evaluation of fiber-reinforced epoxy resin posts and cast post and cores</article-title><source>Am J Dent</source><year>2000</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>15B</fpage><lpage>8B</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adanir</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Belli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of different post lengths&#x02019; effect on fracture resistance of a glass fiber post system</article-title><source>Eur J Dent</source><year>2008</year><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19212505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jalalian</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirzaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> evaluation of the effect of different diameters of quartz fiber posts on fracture resistance of dental roots</article-title><source>Rev Clin Pesq Odontol</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garhnayak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkash</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sehgal</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Garhnayak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Comparative study of the stress distribution in different endodonticpost-retainedteeth with and without ferrule design-a finite element analysis</article-title><source>ISRN Dent</source><year>2011</year><volume>2011</volume><fpage>102329</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21991454</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>