<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Prev Med Hyg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Prev Med Hyg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Preventive Medicine and Hygiene</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1121-2233</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2421-4248</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Pacini Editore SpA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25916023</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4718329</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title xml:lang="en">Hand hygiene behavior among urban slum children
and their care takers in Odisha, India</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>PATI</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>KADAM</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>CHAUHAN</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Indian Institute of Public Health, Bhubaneswar, Public Health Foundation of India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">Correspondence: Sanghamitra Pati, Indian Institute of Public Health, Bhubaneswar, Public Health Foundation of India - Tel. +91-8010 335 915 - E-mail: <email xlink:href="sanghamitra.pati@iiphb.org">sanghamitra.pati@iiphb.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>55</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Copyright by Pacini Editore SpA, Pisa, Italy</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License, which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any digital medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way. For details, please refer to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><title>Summary</title><sec id="sa"><title>Objective.</title><p>To study the knowledge and practice of hand washing among mothers and children of shikharchandi slum of Bhubaneswar, Odisha and to recommend possible measures to improve the current practices.</p></sec><sec id="sb"><title>Methodology.</title><p>Present cross-sectional study was carried out in the Shikharchandi slum located in the Bhubaneswar city of Orissa state in India. 150 women and 80 children were interviewed. Children questionnaire were prepared to suit to their age and according to local context. Components of sanitation like food handling and hand washing were covered in this questionnaire.</p></sec><sec id="sc"><title>Results.</title><p>Hand washing before preparing food is being practiced by 85% of women. Of all women interviewed, 77% wash hands before serving food. Only 15% children said soap was available in their school to wash hands. Out of total children interviewed, 76% told that their teachers tell about sanitation and hand washing in the class. Only 5% children told they were consulted by doctor/health worker during last 3 months. As many as 81% children told that they wash their hands before taking food and 19% children said they take their food without washing hands. Though most of the children told that they wash hands before taking food, but only 17.5% told that they use soap for hand washing. Only 29% children told that their teachers check hand washing in school. When asked about critical timing of hand washing, 44% children told about at least two critical timings and 56% were unaware about the critical timings of hand washing.</p></sec><sec id="sd"><title>Conclusion.</title><p>Inadequate knowledge on this among our study participant is a point of concern. Systematic integration of health and hygiene education in schools through curricular modifications could be an appropriate strategy.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Key words</title><kwd>Hygiene</kwd><kwd>Hand washing</kwd><kwd>Slum</kwd><kwd>Knowledge</kwd><kwd>Attitude</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction" id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Communicable diseases continue to be the major contributor to global morbidity and mortality [<xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Sixty two percent and 31 % of all deaths in Africa and south-Asia, respectively are due to infectious diseases [<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. According to WHO estimates, 3.8 million children aged less than five die each year from diarrhea and acute respiratory tract infections [<xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. An estimated 88 percent of diarrheal deaths worldwide are attributable to unsafe water, inadequate sanitation and poor hygiene [<xref rid="R04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Clean water and hand-washing are viewed as the most cost effective intervention for preventing diarrheal diseases [<xref rid="R05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Various studies have highlighted that simple act of hand-washing and basic hygiene behavior could prevent diarrhea, acute respiratory infection and skin infections [<xref rid="R06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Despite much evidence supporting the effectiveness of personal hygiene behavior, they are yet to be practiced widely. It is observed that young children and their mothers in developing countries fail to wash their hand adequately after fecal contact [<xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Magnitude of the problem is more in urban slums with reduced access to safe water and sanitation.</p><p>Children from poorest urban are three times more likely to die before the age of five than children from wealthiest urban and rural areas [<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. A study conducted in Mumbai slum shows that 30% of all morbidity can be accounted for by water related infection [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Understanding usual hand-washing is an important baseline assessment for any programme intended to improve sanitation, hand hygiene and water quality. However, there are limited data that have assessed the hand hygiene behavior of children and their mothers particularly in slums.</p><p>Keeping this in view the present study was taken up to understand the knowledge, attitude and practices relating to hand-washing of urban slum children and their mothers. The objective of the study was to access handwashing behavior among the participants so as to identify and overcome barriers to proper hand hygiene practices.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="S2"><title>Methodology</title><p>The present cross-sectional study was carried out in the Shikharchandi slum located in the Bhubaneswar city of Orissa state in India. Sikharchandi slum is authorized and the largest slum of the city with 1,500 hundred household and total population of around 6,000. It was decided to take 10% of all households for the study purpose. Thus a total of 150 households were selected. This slum is divided into three clusters. There are total 600 households each in cluster one and cluster three and 300 households in cluster two. Stratified random sampling was carried out to select the households from each of these three clusters proportionately. For the study 10% of households are selected from each cluster. Total selected houses were 60 households each from cluster one and three and 30 households from cluster two. 150 women and 80 children were interviewed. Children between age group of 6 to 12 were separately interviewed. Questionnaire was prepared by adopting the theme of core questionnaire on sanitation by WHO and EHP. Semi structured questionnaire was developed which was suitable to local context. Children questionnaire were prepared to suit to their age and according to local context. Components of sanitation like food handling and hand washing were covered in this questionnaire. The questionnaire was pretested in non study area and necessary changes were made accordingly. Data was entered in MS Excel and analyzed using statistical software SPSS Version 17.0. Verbal consent was taken before interview of mothers and they were well informed about purpose of the study and confidentiality. Verbal consent of parents was taken prior to interview of children.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="S3"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 150 participants were selected for study, out of which 36% were having the BPL card. Mean age of women participant was 31 years and the range was from 17 to 55 years. Participants were comprised of all castes, 24% of them belong to SC, 7% were from ST community, 48% belongs to OBC and 21% belongs to other caste. Main languages spoken in the community were Oriya, Telugu, Hindi and Bengali. Out of all households interviewed, 55% live in kaccha house and 45% live in pakka house; 30% families lived in single room, 49% living in two room house and 21% lived in more than two room house; 63% were from Orissa and 37% were migrated from neighboring states like 27% were migrated from Andhra Pradesh, 9% were migrated from West Bengal and 2% are migrated from Bihar. Participants are grouped as housewives and working women. Working women were either skilled or unskilled profession. Pre-primary teacher, ASHA, tailor were labeled as skilled workers. Those who are working as daily laborer, maid servant, sari seller, vegetable seller and rag pickers were grouped as unskilled workers. Among participants 38% are housewives, 9% were skilled workers and 53% were unskilled workers. Twenty two percent households have income less than 5,000 rupees per month, 57% households earn 5,000 to 10,000 rupees per month and remaining 21% households have monthly income more than 10,000 rupees (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Tab. I</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Tab. I.</label><caption><p>Demographic Characteristics of participant (Mother).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S. No.</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">BPL Cards</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Education</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Literate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Illiterate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">43</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">House</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rent</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">own</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Household condition</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kutcha</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pakka</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">65</td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Rooms in house</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Less than 2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">More than two</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">76</td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Caste</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OBC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">87</td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Language</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oriya</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hindi</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Telugu</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bengali</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">98</td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Native state</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orissa</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Andhra Pradesh</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">West Bengal</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other states</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Size of family</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Less than 5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 to 9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 and above</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">110</td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Income(in rupees/month)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Less than 5000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5000 to 10000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Above 10000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">111</td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Occupation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housewife</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skilled*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unskilled**</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Hand washing before preparing food is being practiced by 85% of women. Still 15% reports that they were not practicing hand washing. Of all women interviewed, 77% wash hands before serving food. When asked about who serves, 43% reported that mother serves the food while in 42% families children take food themselves and remaining 15% told other members like grandmother, sister or aunt serves the food (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Tab. II</xref>). When asked about availability of soap in school, 15% children said soap was available in their school to wash hands but for 85% students soap was not available in school to wash hands. Out of total children interviewed, 76% told that their teachers tell about sanitation and hand washing in the class while 24% told that their teacher doesn't tell about sanitation and hand washing. Only 5% children told they were consulted by doctor/health worker during last 3 months. As many as 81% children told that they wash their hands before taking snacks in school and 19% children said they take their snacks without washing hands. Though most of the children told that they wash hands before taking snacks in school, but only 17.5% told that they use soap for hand washing. Only 29% children told that their teachers check hand washing in school. When asked about critical timing of hand washing, 44% children told about at least two critical timings and 56% were unaware about the critical timings of hand washing.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Tab. II.</label><caption><p>Hand-washing Practices among women.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S. No</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Options</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Numbers (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hand washing before preparing food</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<break/>
No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128 (85)<break/>
22 (15)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hand washing before serving food</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<break/>
No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116(17)<break/>
34(23)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hand wash with soap after toilet</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<break/>
No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108(72)<break/>
42(28)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use of slipper</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<break/>
No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93(62)<break/>
57(38)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hand washing with only water is as good as hand washing with water and soap</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<break/>
No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7(4)<break/>
143(96)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Tab. III.</label><caption><p>Hand-washing Practices among children.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S. No.</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Options</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soap is available in school to wash hands.</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<break/>
No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (15)<break/>
68 (85)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teacher tells about sanitation and hand washing in class.</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<break/>
No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (76)<break/>
19 (24)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Visited by health worker/Doctor in school during last 3 months.</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<break/>
No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (5)<break/>
76 (95)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hand washing before taking food.</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<break/>
No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (81)<break/>
15 (19)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use soap for hand washing before taking food.</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<break/>
No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (17.5)<break/>
66 (82.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teacher checks hand washing in school.</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<break/>
No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (29)<break/>
57 (71)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Who enforce to wash hands.</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mother<break/>
Sister<break/>
Other family members<break/>
teacher</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47(59)<break/>
20 (25)<break/>
18 (22)<break/>
23 (29)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tells at least 2 critical time of hand washing.</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<break/>
No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (44)<break/>
45 (56)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hand washing with soap after toilet.</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes<break/>
No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (61)<break/>
31 (39)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study of urban slum mothers we assessed the knowledge attitude and practices of hand hygiene. Of the mother surveyed, seventy two percent were found to practice hand washing by soap after defecation. This is lower than the WHO study where they found this was practiced by 84% women. The lower level could be due to non availability of soap and decreased perceived susceptibility to diarrhea. Although, 96% of the women were of the opinion that hand washing with water and soap is better compared to simple hand washing, it is not reflected in their practice. This could be explained by the fact that women are not able to link infections like diarrhea directly with their own hand washing behavior. Limited knowledge appears not to be constraint in this case. However, the translation of knowledge into sustainable behavior needs to be reinforced. Behavioral Intervention aimed to improve hand hygiene practices should focus on this important issue should be taken up in order to improve the hand hygiene practices of the respondents. Earlier studies by Ray et al. have also highlighted similar findings [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In our study area 85% of the mother use hand washing before preparation of food, which encouraging. This differs from the study by Ray SK in two communities of eastern India where hand washing was not practiced before "preparing food" and after handling "raw vegetables" [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Another encouraging finding of the present study was 77 % women practicing hand washing before serving food. These behaviors need to be reinforced for preventing Fecal-Oral transmission of infectious agent. Use of slippers was found to be practiced by 62% of the mothers, which could be taken as satisfactory, considering their socio-economic condition.</p><p>Our study additionally explored the knowledge, attitude and practices of hygiene among school children (6-12 years) from the same households. We attempted to find the contextual factors contributing to hand washing practices of the children. It included both school and family level influencers. As many as 81% children practiced hand washing before taking food out of which only 17.5% use soap for hand washing. Sixty one percent children used soap for hand washing after toilet. This could be due to Non or limited availability of soap in both school and household. In a similar study on hand washing among school children in Colombia, it was observed that only 33.6% of children were washing hands with soap before eating and after defecation [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Our participants have better hygiene practice which could be attributed to increased awareness. There appears to be low supervision by the teachers when compared to mothers for enforcing hand washing. This might lead to decreased motivation among the students for regular hand washing. Educating teachers to inculcate hygiene behavior among the students is of prime concern. Future school based hand hygiene interventions should take this into account. Health educators (physician, nurse, health worker) play an important role in this regard. Bearing in mind that, the school has been recognized as a vital setting for health promotion, our findings display a strong deficit of such initiatives. When asked about at least two critical times of hand washing only 44% of surveyed students could answer correctly. In a KAP study of hygiene in Ethiopia found that 52% of the students have adequate knowledge of proper hygiene, which is higher than the present study [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Critical times of hand washing are crucial in breaking the chain of fecal oral contamination, a major cause of diarrheal diseases. Inadequate knowledge on this among our study participant is a point of concern. Systematic integration of health and hygiene education in schools through curricular modifications could be an appropriate strategy.</p><p>Due to the restricted time period and resource constraint, the study was conducted only in one slum and it cannot represent the entire situation of the other slums of the Bhubaneswar and that of entire state. So the results of this study cannot be generalized to the other slums. So it is suggested that more similar studies should taken up to assess sanitation status of slum areas in future.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R01"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab collab-type="author">
World Health Organization
</collab><source>Better Health for Poor Children</source><comment>[Accessed August 4, 2009]. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/child_adolescent_health/documents/a91061/en/index.html">http://www.who.int/child_adolescent_health/documents/a91061/en/index.html</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R02"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Danquah</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name><name><surname>Aunger</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Planned, motivated and
habitual hygiene behavior: an eleven country review</article-title><source>Health
Educ Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>655</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19286894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R03"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="gov"><collab collab-type="author">
World Health Organization
</collab><source>World Health Statistics</source><year>2009</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R04"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global mortality, disability, and the
contribution of risk factors: Global Burden of Disease Study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1997</year><volume>349</volume><fpage>1436</fpage><lpage>1442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9164317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R05"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Breman</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Measham</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Disease
Control Priorities in Developing Countries</source><year>2006</year><edition>2nd ed.</edition><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford
University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R06"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luby</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Agboatwalla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Feikin</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of handwashing
on child health: A randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2005</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16023513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R07"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shahid</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenough</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Samadi</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Handwashing
with soap reduces Diarrhoea and spread of bacterial pathogen
in a Bangladesh village</article-title><source>J Diarrhoeal Dis Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8870400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R08"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>LiKosek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bern</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrant</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The global burden of diarrhoeal
disease, as estimated from studies published between
1992 and 2000</article-title><source>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</source><year>2003</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12764516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R09"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="gov"><collab collab-type="author">
World health organization/UNICEF
</collab><source>Diarrhea why children
are still dying and what can be done</source><year>2009</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Field survey on water supply, sanitation
and associated health impacts in urban poor communities,
a case from Mumbai city, India</article-title><source>Water Sci Technol</source><year>2002</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>275</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A pilot survey on hand washing
among some communities of West Bengal</article-title><source>Indian J Pub Health</source><year>2006</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>230</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaman</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Laskar</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hand washing practices in two
communities of two states of eastern India: An Interventional
Study</article-title><source>Indian J Pub Health</source><year>2010</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21245581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez-Quintero</surname></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumark</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hand washing among school children in Bogot&#x000e1;, Colombia</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><year>2009</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19008513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vivas</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelaye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aboset</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Knowledge, Attitudes and
Practices (KAP) of hygiene among school children in Angolela,
Ethiopia</article-title><source>J Prev Med Hyg</source><year>2010</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21155409</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>