<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Braz J Med Biol Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Braz. J. Med. Biol. Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Brazilian Journal of Medical and Biological Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0100-879X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1414-431X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Associa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Brasileira de Divulga&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Cient&#x000ed;fica</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23579633</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3854406</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1414-431X20132322</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Biomedical Sciences</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of melatonin on the functional recovery from
experimental traumatic compression of the spinal cord</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schiaveto-de-Souza</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>da-Silva</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Defino</surname><given-names>H.L.A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bel</surname><given-names>E.A.Del</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Departamento de Morfofisiologia, Universidade Federal do Mato Grosso
do Sul, Campo Grande, MS, Brasil</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Departamento de Morfologia,Estomatologia e Fisiologia, Faculdade de
Odontologia de Ribeir&#x000e3;o Preto, Universidade de S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Ribeir&#x000e3;o Preto, SP,
Brasil</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Departamento de Orthopedia e Traumatologia, Faculdade de Medicina de
Ribeir&#x000e3;o Preto, Universidade de S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Ribeir&#x000e3;o Preto, SP, Brasil</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding: E.A. Del Bel, Departamento de Morfologia, Estomatologia e
Fisiologia, Faculdade de Odontologia de Ribeir&#x000e3;o Preto, Universidade de S&#x000e3;o Paulo,
14049-904 Ribeir&#x000e3;o Preto, SP, Brasil, +55-16-3602-4047, E-mail:
<email>eadelbel@usp.br</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>46</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License, which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Spinal cord injury is an extremely severe condition with no available effective
therapies. We examined the effect of melatonin on traumatic compression of the spinal
cord. Sixty male adult Wistar rats were divided into three groups: sham-operated
animals and animals with 35 and 50% spinal cord compression with a polycarbonate rod
spacer. Each group was divided into two subgroups, each receiving an injection of
vehicle or melatonin (2.5 mg/kg, intraperitoneal) 5 min prior to and 1, 2, 3, and 4 h
after injury. Functional recovery was monitored weekly by the open-field test, the
Basso, Beattie and Bresnahan locomotor scale and the inclined plane test.
Histological changes of the spinal cord were examined 35 days after injury. Motor
scores were progressively lower as spacer size increased according to the motor scale
and inclined plane test evaluation at all times of assessment. The results of the two
tests were correlated. The open-field test presented similar results with a less
pronounced difference between the 35 and 50% compression groups. The injured groups
presented functional recovery that was more evident in the first and second weeks.
Animals receiving melatonin treatment presented more pronounced functional recovery
than vehicle-treated animals as measured by the motor scale or inclined plane.
NADPH-d histochemistry revealed integrity of the spinal cord thoracic segment in
sham-operated animals and confirmed the severity of the lesion after spinal cord
narrowing. The results obtained after experimental compression of the spinal cord
support the hypothesis that melatonin may be considered for use in clinical practice
because of its protective effect on the secondary wave of neuronal death following
the primary wave after spinal cord injury.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Spinal cord injury</kwd><kwd>Melatonin</kwd><kwd>Functional recovery</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="40"/><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Spinal cord injury (SCI) results in the loss of function below the lesion. The
compression of the spinal cord that follows vertebral displacement and edema is
considered to be a very frequent cause of traumatic spinal cord lesion. Secondary injury
following the primary impact includes a number of biochemical and cellular alterations,
localized edema, hemorrhage, thrombosis, vasospasm, and loss of vasculature
autoregulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref>. Primary traumatic mechanical
injury to the spinal cord causes the death of a number of neurons that cannot be
recovered or regenerated. Some neurons continue to die for hours after traumatic SCI
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B02"> 2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B03">3</xref>.
This secondary neuronal death may be caused by substances released from cells in
response to the primary injury. Over a period of minutes to hours the affected area
undergoes complex processes that give rise to secondary damage. The initial procedures
are thought to be decisive for the evolution of the events that ensue during the
evolution of the injury <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref>.</p><p>Several studies have revealed that early interventions can produce positive effects
regarding the consequences of secondary injury <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B02">
2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B03">3</xref>. Growing evidence has shown that
melatonin (5-methoxy-<italic>N</italic>-acetyltryptamine) is a neuroprotective compound.
Melatonin is a neurohormone synthesized from L-tryptophan in the pineal gland, retina
and gastrointestinal tract, released into the blood with a circadian rhythm that peaks
during the night in mammals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B04">4</xref>. Its rhythmic
production by the pineal gland was described in human beings over 20 years ago. However,
melatonin production is not confined exclusively to the pineal gland, but other tissues
including retina, Harderian glands, gut, ovary, testes, bone marrow, and lens also
produce it. Melatonin is rapidly absorbed because of its lipophilic nature, and readily
crosses the blood-brain barrier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B05">5</xref>. Reduction of
endogenous melatonin after pinealectomy makes rats more vulnerable to trauma and
exogenous melatonin administration has an important neuroprotective effect. The spinal
cord is particularly vulnerable to free radical oxidation because of its high lipid
content. Pharmacological doses of melatonin do not produce <italic>in vivo</italic>
toxic effects and seem to support some features of the antioxidant defense systems <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B05">5</xref>.</p><p>The question of the neuroprotective effect of melatonin after spinal cord injury is
controversial. After compression ischemic-induced SCI, Fujimoto et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B06">6</xref> showed that melatonin reduced the occurrence of
neutrophil-induced lipid peroxidation, and that it facilitated recovery of the damaged
spinal cord. Topsakal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref> showed that
melatonin applied early after SCI not only reduced lipid peroxidation but also prevented
the decrease of superoxide dismutase and glutathione peroxidase, components of the
endogenous antioxidant system. Protection of the spinal cord against lipid peroxidation
by melatonin was similar to that provided by methylprednisolone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B03">3</xref>. However, Gu&#x000ed;zar-Sahag&#x000fa;n et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B08">8</xref> showed no pharmacological neuroprotection in melatonin-treated rats in an
animal model of spinal surgery-induced neurological damage (no differences in their
locomotor performance or in the amount of spared cord tissue).</p><p>The purpose of the present study was to further investigate the neuroprotective effect
of melatonin. We examined the effect of melatonin on neurobehavioral impairment produced
by traumatic compression of the spinal cord in rats. The tested hypothesis was that the
use of melatonin immediately after spinal cord compression could improve the rate and
extent of motor recuperation of the animals. The results reported here support the
benefit of exogenous melatonin as a therapeutic intervention for spinal cord injury
induced by compression.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Material and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals</title><p>Male Wistar rats (250-300 g, n = 60) were kept in a temperature-controlled room
(23&#x000b0;C) with a 12-h light/dark cycle (lights on at 7:00 am) and with free access to
water and food. Experiments were performed between 8:00 and 12:00 am. The experiments
were carried out according to the guidelines of the Brazilian Society of Neuroscience
and Behavior that comply with the National Institutes of Health Guide for care and
use of laboratory animals. A white noise generator provided a constant background
noise and the apparatus was cleaned and dried before each session with 70% ethanol to
minimize olfactory cues.</p></sec><sec><title>Spinal cord compression</title><p>Spacers (manufactured using a polycarbonate rod) were designed to induce spinal cord
compression, as described by Dimar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B09">9</xref>.
They were manufactured in such a way as to decrease the rat's average spinal canal
diameter by 35% (0.78-mm thick spacer) and 50% (1.11-mm thick spacer). The spacers
were precisely measured to ensure correct dimensions using microcalipers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B09">9</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Surgical procedure</title><p>All surgical techniques were performed under aseptic conditions. Animals were
anesthetized with an intraperitoneal (<italic>ip</italic>) injection of 250 mg/kg
2,2,2-tribromoethanol (Aldrich Chemical Company, USA), followed by subcutaneous
administration of penicillin. After shaving the skin, animals were kept in a
stereotaxic apparatus (David Kopf, USA) and a posterior incision in the skin and
underlying muscles was made in the mid-thoracic region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>. Muscles were retracted and a mid-thoracic total laminectomy
was performed at the level of the T10 vertebra. When required, the dura mater was
exposed. According to the experimental group, spacers of different sizes were
introduced under the T9 lamina in the dorsal epidural space to promote spinal cord
compression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>), while in the
sham-operated group no spacer was introduced and the spinal cord was free of
compression. In the compression groups, the spacers were kept under the T9 lamina
until the end of the experiment.</p><fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Schematic overview of placement of the spacer under the T9 lamina to
promote spinal cord compression.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0100-879X-bjmbr-46-04-00348-gf01"/></fig><p>After the surgical procedure, the paraspinal fascia, muscle and skin were closed with
4-0 nylon suture (Ethicon, Brazil). The animals were placed in a warming chamber and
body temperature was maintained at approximately 37&#x000b0;C until they were fully awake, at
which time they were returned to their home cages, 2 or 3 rats per cage.
Postoperative care included regular bladder expression.</p></sec><sec><title>Behavioral evaluation methods</title><p>Behavioral parameters were recorded preoperatively and 1, 7, 14, 21, 28, and 35 days
after the experimental procedure. The same animals were tested in the open arena and
evaluated by the Basso, Beattie and Bresnahan (BBB) locomotor score and inclined
plane test.</p><p>
<italic>Open-field test</italic>. To assess their exploratory behavior, rats were
tested in an open field consisting of a circular wooden box (72 cm in diameter)
surrounded by 49-cm high transparent walls with an open top. The floor was subdivided
into 12 equal size fields. In this test, each rat was gently placed in the center of
the open field and hand-operated counters and stopwatches were used to score. Two
different behavioral measures of spontaneous activity were used: locomotion or
exploratory movement, measured as the number of floor units entered with the four
paws, and rearing frequency, as the number of times the animal stood on its hind
limbs. The two different parameters of spontaneous behavior used were empirically
found to be best for measurements of individual and group behaviors. Exploratory
measures are necessary since stationary activity may not accurately reflect the
groups' exploratory behavior in the field. We evaluated changes in each parameter
individually.</p><p>
<italic>BBB locomotor scale</italic>. The BBB scale, elaborated by Basso et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>, is used to analyze specific components of
functional behavior such as limb movement, trunk position/instability, paw
placement/position, stepping, coordination, toe clearance, and tail position. The
scores range from 0 (no detectable hind limb movement) to 21 (normal locomotion) and
have been extensively described elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>.
The locomotor activity of individual animals was evaluated in the circular wooden
open arena for 4 min by 1 examiner observing the rat. The observer did not touch the
animal in the open field. A rating sheet described by Basso et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref> was used for individual animal recording.</p><p>
<italic>Inclined plane test</italic>. The inclined plane test was performed as
described by Rivlin and Tator <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>. In this test
the rat was placed on a mat in such a way that its body axis was perpendicular to the
axis of an inclined board, which could be adjusted to provide a slope of varying
grade. The angle of the inclined plane was the maximum angle of the plane at which a
rat could maintain itself for at least 5 s.</p></sec><sec><title>Histological analysis</title><p>After 35 days the animals (n = 10 per group) were deeply anesthetized with a lethal
<italic>ip</italic> injection of 25% urethane, and sacrificed by intracardiac
perfusion with 0.01 M PBS (200 mL, pH 7.4) followed by 4% paraformaldehyde in 0.1 M
phosphate buffer (200 mL, pH 7.4). The spinal cord was rapidly removed and soaked in
the same fixative solution for 2 h (4&#x000b0;C) and then cryoprotected by overnight soaking
in 30% sucrose/phosphate buffer. Thoracic segments of the spinal cord were frozen in
isopentane (-40&#x000b0;C, Sigma, USA) and stored at -70&#x000b0;C until the time for the
histochemical procedures.</p><p>
<italic>Histochemistry for NADPH-diaphorase.</italic> Forty-micrometer serial
sections were cut with a cryostat (Leica, Germany) and neuroanatomical sites were
identified using the Paxinos and Watson atlas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>. NADPH-diaphorase (NADPH-d) activity was measured by incubating
free-floating sections in 0.1 M phosphate buffer, pH 7.4, containing 0.3% Triton-X
100 (Sigma), 0.1 mg/mL Nitroblue tratrazolium (Sigma) and 0.1 mg/mL &#x003b2;-NADPH, at 37&#x000b0;C
for 90 min in the dark. The sections were dipped for 10 min in phosphate buffer,
dried, rinsed in distilled water, and mounted for microscopic observation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>. Slices from about 8 mm of the spinal cords
were examined with a microscope linked to a computer-assisted image-processing system
through a video camera. For cell density quantification, the spinal cord was divided
into five regions: 1) the superficial lamina (laminae I and II), 2) the nucleus
proprius (laminae III and IV), 3) the intermediolateral cell column, 4) the region
around the central canal (lamina X), and 5) the ventral horn (laminae VIII and IX).
NADPH-d-positive neuron density was measured in a blind manner in two regions of
interest, i.e., rostral (0.0-3.9 mm) and caudal (0.0-3.9 mm) spinal segments beyond
the narrowing site.</p></sec><sec><title>Experimental groups</title><p>The experimental groups (n = 10 per group) were formed according to the degree of
spinal canal narrowing (sham-operated, 35% compression and 50% compression) and the
administration of melatonin or vehicle, for a total of 6 experimental groups: SO-V
(sham-operated + vehicle), 35%-V (narrowing of 35% + vehicle), 50%-V (narrowing of
50% + vehicle), SO-M (sham-operated + melatonin), 35%-M (narrowing of 35% +
melatonin), and 50%-M (narrowing of 50% + melatonin). Melatonin (Sigma, 2.5 mg/kg
dissolved in absolute ethanol-saline, 5:95, v/v) or vehicle was administered
<italic>ip</italic> at 5 min prior to and 1, 2, 3, and 4 h after injury. Dosage
was in accordance with the pharmacokinetic properties of melatonin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref> and as described by Fujimoto et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B06">6</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The behavioral data were submitted to repeated measure multivariate analysis of
variance (MANOVA) followed by one-way ANOVA and the Duncan <italic>post hoc</italic>
test in case of significant treatment x time interaction. The Student
<italic>t</italic>-test was also used to compare drug treatments. The same tests
were used to assess the effects of compression and of melatonin treatment on
NADPH-d-positive neurons of different gray matter Rexed laminae. Pearson's
correlation coefficient was employed to compare the behavioral tests. The level of
significance was set at P &#x0003c; 0.05. Data are reported in graphs as means &#x000b1; SE, with
the number of data points indicated for each mean.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Open-field test</title><p>Quantitative analysis of ambulation in order to evaluate locomotive ability is
presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2</xref>. A 35% narrowing of the
spinal cord canal resulted in a significant decrease of squares crossed by the
animals when compared to the SO-V group at days 1, 7, and 14 after injury. In the
50%-V animals, an additional decrease was detected at days 1, 7, 14, and 28, although
this decrease was more pronounced in the 50%-V group than in the 35%-V group only on
the first day (F<sub>2,19</sub> variation from 6.13 to 29.02, P &#x0003c; 0.01). Rearing
behavior decreased with time in all groups (time effect: F<sub>6,114</sub> = 58.42, P
&#x0003c; 0.0001). However, this decrease was more pronounced in animals with narrowing of
the spinal cord canal at all times post-injury (F<sub>2,19</sub> variation from 17.91
to 69.31, P &#x0003c; 0.0001). No difference was observed between the 35%-V and 50%-V
groups (P &#x0003e; 0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Melatonin treatment did not affect the ambulation of rats. Numbered squares
crossed in an open arena were measured 24 h before (-1) and 1, 7, 14, 21, 28,
and 35 days after narrowing of the spinal cord canal. Each point represents the
mean &#x000b1; SE for 9-11 rats. <sup>+</sup>P &#x0003c; 0.001 compared to sham-operated
group from vehicle-treated animals, on days 1, 7 and 14 after narrowing of the
spinal cord canal (ANOVA with the Duncan <italic>post hoc</italic> test).
<sup>++</sup>P &#x0003c; 0.001 compared to sham-operated group from
vehicle-treated animals, on days 1, 7, 14, and 28 after narrowing of the spinal
cord canal and compared to 35% narrowing from vehicle-treated animals, on the
first day after narrowing of the spinal cord canal (ANOVA with the Duncan
<italic>post hoc</italic> test). Melatonin application did not change the
number of floor units crossed by the animals of the three groups (MANOVA, P
&#x0003e; 0.05). 35% = 35% narrowing group; 50% = 50% narrowing group. Open symbols
= vehicle-treated groups; filled symbols = melatonin-treated groups.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0100-879X-bjmbr-46-04-00348-gf02"/></fig><fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Melatonin treatment increased the rearing behavior. Rearing behavior in an
open arena was measured 24 h before (-1) and 1, 7, 14, 21, 28, and 35 days
after narrowing of the spinal cord canal. Each point represents the mean &#x000b1; SE
for 9-11 rats. *P &#x0003c; 0.05 compared to the vehicle-treated group (independent
Student <italic>t</italic>-test). <sup>+</sup>P &#x0003c; 0.0001 compared to
sham-operated group from vehicle-treated animals at all times after narrowing
of the spinal cord canal (ANOVA with the Duncan <italic>post hoc</italic>
test). No difference was observed between the 35%-V and 50%-V groups (P &#x0003e;
0.05). 35% = 35% narrowing group; 50% = 50% narrowing group. Open symbols =
vehicle-treated groups; filled symbols = melatonin-treated groups.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0100-879X-bjmbr-46-04-00348-gf03"/></fig><p>Melatonin application did not change the number of floor units crossed by the animals
of the three groups (drug effect: SO-M, F<sub>1,15</sub> = 0.83, P = 0.38; 35%-M,
F<sub>1,13</sub> = 0.77, P = 0.40; 50%-M, F<sub>1,19</sub> = 0.26, P = 0.61). In
contrast, the number of rearing events was modified by melatonin in the 35%-M group
(drug effect: F<sub>1,13</sub> = 5.45, P = 0.036). Animals that received melatonin
explored the vertical space more than vehicle-treated ones on days 14 and 35 after
injury (t<sub>13</sub> ranging from -2.35 to -2.18, P &#x0003c; 0.05). However, in the
sham-operated and 50% groups, melatonin had no effect on rearing behavior (drug
effect: sham-operated, F<sub>1,15</sub> = 0.72, P = 0.41; 50%, F<sub>1,19</sub> =
3.93, P = 0.06).</p></sec><sec><title>BBB locomotor score</title><p>After laminectomy, no functional deficit was detected in the animals at any time
point of assessment (21 points; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4</xref>).
Narrowing of the spinal cord canal produced changes in locomotor behavior (narrowing
effect: F<sub>2,28</sub> = 226.09, P &#x0003c; 0.0001). Animals of the 35%-V and 50%-V
groups exhibited significant locomotor impairment at days 1, 7, 14, 21, 28, and 35
after narrowing compared to SO-V ones (F<sub>2,28</sub> ranging from 30.90 to 953.79,
P &#x0003c; 0.0001). Rats of the 50%-V group showed significantly lower scores than 35%-V
animals at all times analyzed post-injury (P &#x0003c; 0.05). On the first day after
injury, 35%-V and 50%-V animals presented BBB scores close to 2. Progressive
functional recuperation was observed over time for both the 35%-V and 50%-V groups
(35%-V, F<sub>6,54</sub> = 86.47, P &#x0003c; 0.0001; 50%-V, F<sub>6,60</sub> = 128.77, P
&#x0003c; 0.0001). Recuperation was more pronounced in the 35% group, whose average BBB
score increased from 2 on the first day to 17 after 35 days (15 points). The
recuperation range was about 10 points in the 50%-V group.</p><fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Melatonin treatment improved the BBB score. Results of the Basso, Beattie
and Bresnahan (BBB) locomotor scale measured 24 h before (-1) and 1, 7 14, 21,
28, and 35 days after narrowing of the spinal cord canal. Each point represents
the mean &#x000b1; SE for 9-11 rats. *P &#x0003c; 0.05 compared to the vehicle-treated group
(independent Student <italic>t</italic>-test). <sup>+</sup>P &#x0003c; 0.0001
compared to sham-operated group from vehicle-treated animals, at all times
after narrowing of the spinal cord canal (ANOVA with the Duncan <italic>post
hoc</italic> test). <sup>++</sup>P &#x0003c; 0.0001 compared to sham-operated
group and 35% narrowing from vehicle-treated animals, at all times after
narrowing of the spinal cord canal (ANOVA with the Duncan <italic>post
hoc</italic> test). 35% = 35% narrowing group; 50% = 50% narrowing group.
Open symbols = vehicle-treated groups; filled symbols = melatonin-treated
groups.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0100-879X-bjmbr-46-04-00348-gf04"/></fig><p>Melatonin did not alter the locomotor performance of SO-M animals (drug effect:
F<sub>1,19</sub> = 0.00, P = 1.00). However, BBB scores for melatonin-treated
animals were always higher than the scores for vehicle-treated animals in the 35%-M
group (t<sub>17</sub> varying from -4.76 to -2.34, P &#x0003c; 0.04). Likewise, the same
effect was observed in the 50%-M group on days 21 and 28 (day 21, t<sub>20</sub> =
-2.33, P = 0.03; day 28, t<sub>20</sub> = -2.42, P = 0.025). While on the first day
after injury 35%-V animals presented BBB scores close to 2, 35%-M animals had a score
of only about 9. After 35 days, 35%-M animals presented scores of about 20, whereas
35%-V animals presented scores of about 17 with no complete toe clearance, tail down
and trunk instability.</p></sec><sec><title>Inclined plane test</title><p>In the pretest, the angle of the inclined plane at which one rat could maintain
itself for at least 5 s was about 85 degrees for all groups (F<sub>2,28</sub> = 0.34,
P = 0.71). In the SO-V group there was no difference in average maximum angle at any
time analyzed (F<sub>6,54</sub> = 1.20, P = 0.32). For the 35%-V and 50%-V groups,
the average maximum angle decreased strikingly after narrowing and did not return to
a normal level after 5 weeks (F<sub>2,28</sub> ranging from 62.84 to 494.08, P &#x0003c;
0.0001). Furthermore, a 50% narrowing produced a more pronounced decrease in angle
degree than a 35% narrowing at days 7, 14, 21, 28, and 35 post-injury (P &#x0003c;
0.05).</p><p>Post-injury, the average maximum angle at which a rat could maintain itself on the
inclined plane differed significantly between melatonin- and vehicle-treated rats in
35 and 50% animals (drug effect: 35%, F<sub>1,17</sub> = 10.03, P = 0.006; 50%,
F<sub>1,20</sub> = 7.67, P = 0.012, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Figure
5</xref>). Melatonin-treated animals in the 35%-M group showed higher mean angle
degrees than 35%-V animals at all time points post-injury (t<sub>17</sub> ranging
from -3.58 to -2.18, P &#x0003c; 0.05). In 50%-M rats the average maximum angle at which a
rat could maintain itself on the inclined plane was detected at days 1, 28 and 35
(t<sub>20</sub> ranging from -3.39 to -0.78, P &#x0003c; 0.05).</p><fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Melatonin treatment increased the angle on the inclined plane test. Results
of the inclined plane test measured 24 h before (-1) and 1, 7, 14, 21, 28, and
35 days after narrowing of the spinal cord canal. Each point represents the
mean &#x000b1; SE for 9-11 rats. *P &#x0003c; 0.05 compared to the vehicle-treated group
(independent Student <italic>t</italic>-test). <sup>+</sup>P &#x0003c; 0.0001
compared to sham-operated group from vehicle-treated animals, at all times
after narrowing of the spinal cord canal (ANOVA with the Duncan <italic>post
hoc</italic> test). <sup>++</sup>P &#x0003c; 0.0001 compared to sham-operated
group at all times after narrowing of the spinal cord canal and <sup>++</sup>P
&#x0003c; 0.05 compared to 35% narrowing, from vehicle-treated animals, on days 7,
14, 21, 28, and 35 after narrowing of the spinal cord canal (ANOVA with the
Duncan <italic>post hoc</italic> test). 35% = 35% narrowing group; 50% = 50%
narrowing group. Open symbols = vehicle-treated groups; filled symbols =
melatonin-treated groups.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0100-879X-bjmbr-46-04-00348-gf05"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Correlation between the BBB locomotor scale and the inclined plane test</title><p>A strong correlation between BBB score and inclined plane angle degree was observed
(r = 0.95, r<sup>2</sup> = 0.90, P &#x0003c; 0.0001). BBB scores of 0, 7, 14, and 21
corresponded to approximately 23, 44, 65, and 86 degrees on the inclined plane,
respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>NADPH-d histochemistry</title><p>A photomicrograph of a typical spinal cord thoracic segment from a vehicle-treated
animal, labeled with NADPH-d histochemistry is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Figure 6</xref>. Rats were sacrificed 35 days after sham operation (A-C)
or 35% (D-F) or 50% (G-I) spinal cord narrowing. NADPH-d histochemistry revealed
integrity of the labeled neurons (A-C) in the intermediolateral nucleus and lamina 10
(motoneurons). Photomicrographs in Panels D-I confirm the severity of the spinal cord
lesion. Analysis of NADPH-d activity in the spinal cords of the experimental groups
showed that the density of labeled neurons varied with percent compression and with
time (compression effect: F<sub>2,160</sub> = 144.34, P &#x0003c; 0.0001; time effect:
F<sub>4,160</sub> = 3.95, P = 0.004) but not with melatonin treatment (drug
effect: F<sub>1,160</sub> = 0.77, P = 0.38). Six to 48 h after both rostral and
caudal spinal cord compression (0.0 to 0.39 mm for both sides) in the 35%-V and 50%-V
groups, the density of NADPH-d-positive neurons decreased compared to SO-V animals in
all Rexed laminae (F<sub>2,15</sub> ranging from 4.69 to 38.63, P &#x0003c; 0.03).
Moreover, after 24 h, the density of NADPH-d-positive neurons observed in the laminae
I-IV of 50%-V animals, caudal segment, was lower than in 35%-V animals. This was also
observed for laminae III and IV after 48 h, and for laminae I to IV and the
intermediolateral nucleus after 35 days (Duncan <italic>post hoc</italic> test, P
&#x0003c; 0.05). The data for vehicle-treated animals, 24 h after surgery, are shown in
<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>.</p><fig id="f06" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Photomicrograph of a typical thoracic spinal cord segment labeled by
NADPH-d activity 35 days after the experimental procedure for the sham-operated
+ vehicle (SO-V) group (<italic>A</italic>, <italic>B</italic> and
<italic>C</italic>), the narrowing of 35% + vehicle (35%-V)
(<italic>D</italic>, <italic>E</italic> and <italic>F</italic>) group and
the narrowing of 50% + vehicle (50%-V) (<italic>G</italic>, <italic>H</italic>
and <italic>I</italic>) group. <italic>D-I</italic> photomicrographs confirmed
the severity of the spinal cord lesion. Arrows in <italic>B</italic> highlight
NADPH-d-positive neurons in the intermediolateral nucleus and in the ventral
horn from gray matter. The arrow in <italic>C</italic> highlights
NADPH-d-positive neurons in lamina X of Rexed from gray matter. The arrow in
<italic>H</italic> shows formation of a cavity near the central part of the
spinal cord between white and gray matter. DH = dorsal horn; GM = gray matter;
VH = ventral horn; WM = white matter; IML = intermediolateral nucleus; CC =
central canal.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0100-879X-bjmbr-46-04-00348-gf06"/></fig><p>
<table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><graphic xlink:href="0100-879X-bjmbr-46-04-00348-gt01"/></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Based on behavioral and histological analyses, the present study showed that melatonin
administration significantly improved functional recuperation after SCI, extending
previous results <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B09">9</xref> obtained by the analysis of
narrowing of the spinal cord canal and BBB locomotor score.</p><p>The hormone melatonin participates in many physiologic functions including regulation of
circadian rhythms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>. More recently, melatonin
was found to be a highly efficient scavenger of hydroxyl and peroxyl radicals as well as
an electron donor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>. Being lipophilic and
hydrophilic, it has an extreme diffusibility for scavenging in cells and in every
subcellular compartment. The efficacy of melatonin has been tested in many neurological
disease models where free radicals have been pointed out as a pathologic causal factor.
Thus, melatonin has been associated with neuroprotective effects in Alzheimer's and
Parkinson's diseases, glutamate excitotoxicity and ischemia-reperfusion injury, amongst
others <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>. Although the primary protective effect
of melatonin can be related to its ubiquitous direct and indirect antioxidant actions,
other beneficial functions of melatonin are not precluded <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B04">4</xref>. Compared to methylprednisolone, melatonin exerts considerable
neuroprotection, with the most prominent protective effect on myelin, nuclear axons and
mitochondria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B03">3</xref>. There is strong evidence that
this hormone could be a powerful tool to prevent the secondary wave of neuronal death
after SCI.</p><p>Narrowing of the spinal cord canal, as described by Dimar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B09">9</xref>, is an easy and suitable method for the study of SCI, which
produces gradual narrowing of the spinal cord canal resulting in progressive functional
impairment and histological damage directly related to the degree of narrowing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B09">9</xref>.</p><p>Laboratory rodents perform a wide variety of behaviors, many of which are relevant to
assessing the integrity of spinal pathways. Different kinds of measurements can be
potentially used to assess behavioral recovery after SCI in rats. A combination of
functional tests for each animal has been recommended to provide a quantifiable and
comprehensive analysis of sensorimotor function in spinal-injured rodents <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>.
According to Muir and Weeb <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>, a comprehensive
analysis should include each of the following three components: i) an assessment of
reflex function; ii) a measure of motor abilities during spontaneous locomotor activity,
and iii) a measure of abilities during one or more trained behavioral tasks. Measurement
of reflex function provides an indication of integrity of a particular spinal pathway.
Spontaneous movement provides an initial screening of overall motor abilities. Finally,
assessing the performance of trained behaviors eliminates differences in motivation
between animals and provides more detailed and specific measures of functional
abilities.</p><p>Locomotion over a flat surface is a behavior that involves the whole body. Rearing on
the hind limbs involves primarily individual limbs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>. While just qualitative observations of locomotion are not sufficiently
sensitive to assess the pattern of locomotion deficit <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>, exploratory activity, rearing and grooming events are sensitive
parameters for the detection of sensorimotor deficiencies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>. In summary, the results of the present study indicate that
spinal cord injury produces a decrease in spontaneous locomotor activity as measured in
an open-field test in spite of melatonin treatment. One day after surgery all animals,
including the sham-operated ones, presented a decrease in ambulation, which, however,
was more evident in the animals that suffered spinal cord compression. The decrease of
ambulation by sham-operated animals can be explained by the repeated exposure to the
open field with the novelty factor being pulled out. These results are in agreement with
previous ones from Metz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref> and Giglio et
al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>.</p><p>The BBB scale was designed to assess recovery of hind limb function after SCI <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>. Each point in the score represents a specific
set of characteristics demonstrated by the animal during spontaneous open-field
locomotion. Although the BBB scale uses ordinal scores <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>, the use of parametric statistics to evaluate its results has been more
recently recommended. This would facilitate interpretation of the results between
laboratories and provide a common methodology for behavioral data <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>. In addition, Metz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref> found that animals with low locomotion capacity presented a closer
relationship between the BBB scale <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref> and
activity in the open field. In the present study, the BBB scale was able to consistently
identify functional impairment after SCI. Furthermore, by this method it was possible to
differentiate the locomotor outcomes produced by gradual narrowing of the spinal cord
canal and to show the progressive functional recuperation after injury.</p><p>The BBB scoring system correlated highly with the inclined plane test. When animals were
assessed on the inclined plane the same impairment profile was observed, as also
reported by Fujimoto et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B06">6</xref> after compression
ischemia-induced SCI. Although the inclined plane is a test where the quality of
movement is not considered by this traditional, easy and quick method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>, it was possible to identify and differentiate
functional deficits caused by the gradual narrowing of the spinal cord canal almost to
the same extent as observed with the BBB score, a more comprehensive and detailed test.
On the first day after injury, assessment of the animals on the inclined plane test was
not able to show a difference between the 35%-V and 50%-V groups, whereas the difference
was evident when using the BBB score system. Our results suggest that the inclined plane
can be a reliable and easy test to be used together with other methods of behavior
assessment to provide a complete overview of the motor behavior of the animal, helping
to highlight discrete recovery after SCI.</p><p>The neuroprotective effects of melatonin were confirmed in our study. These beneficial
behavioral changes were more evident when animals were assessed by the BBB scale and by
the inclined plane test. In agreement with the aforementioned findings, these methods
were more reliable than others in highlighting the functional impairments caused by
narrowing of the spinal cord canal after SCI. The preventive effect of melatonin was
evident in 35%-M animals as early as on the first day post-injury, with
melatonin-treated animals showing higher BBB scores and angle degrees on the inclined
plane than vehicle-treated ones, suggesting that functional impairment was prevented by
drug treatment early after the experimental procedure.</p><p>The progression of traumatic central nervous system injuries follows an archetypal
course through primary and secondary damaging events, which are distinct in their
spatiotemporal windows. There is a consensus that the best time window to use melatonin
for a neuroprotective effect is just after the SCI event, using a single dose <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref> or multiple doses <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B06">6</xref>. Although there is no consensus regarding the use of single- or
multiple-dose schemes, most of these studies have shown protective effects regarding
both histological and behavioral aspects. In this study, we used five doses of melatonin
in the acute window of 4 h as previously described by Fujimoto et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B06">6</xref>, which were sufficient to improve the behavioral
outcomes.</p><p>Our hypothesis is that the improvement in motor behavior observed in melatonin-treated
animals after SCI is related to the properties of melatonin that prevent the secondary
wave of neuronal death following the primary one after SCI, including reactive
astrogliosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>. This may result from the
inhibition of cysteine proteases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>, scavenging
of hydroxyl and peroxyl radicals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,
inhibition of nitric oxide synthase (NOS) activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>, or yet by other mechanisms that
are not completely understood. Melatonin is supposed to prevent astrogliosis following
acute SCI as demonstrated by Samantaray et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>
in a study in which a single dose of melatonin after weight-drop SCI attenuated the
degree of astrocytosis in the penumbra, decreasing calpain and glial fibrillary acidic
protein levels to those seen in vehicle-treated animals 48 h after injury.</p><p>Melatonin has also been shown to inhibit NOS activity <italic>in vitro</italic> and
<italic>in vivo</italic>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>.
Melatonin application decreased NO production in cultured cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>, in brain homogenates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>
and after global or focal brain injury following ischemia/reperfusion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>.
Moreover, cerebral lipid peroxidation induced by NO donors was reduced by melatonin
treatment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>. NO is implicated in an enormous
number of biological functions both in physiological and pathological conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>. As a free radical, NO seems to play a major role
in the secondary lesion after acute spinal cord injury <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>. The increased formation of NO, peroxynitrite and nitrated proteins
shortly after spinal cord contusion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref> must play
an important role in the destructive and reparative events taking place following acute
spinal cord injury, depending on the amount of NO produced <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref> and the redox conditions of the environment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>, among other factors. Hu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref> showed a time-dependent differential increase in constitutive NOS and
inducible NOS after lesion produced by dynorphin microinjection to the rat spinal cord.
The same was observed after contusive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref> and
compressive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref> spinal cord injury.</p><p>In our study, NADPH-d-positive neurons decreased in the rostral and caudal regions near
the compression site after SCI in spite of melatonin treatment. Moreover, this decrease
was mainly observed in the dorsal Rexed laminae (I-V) and more evident in the groups
subjected to 50% compression. These results can be a reflex of the general neuronal loss
after acute SCI and do not seem to explain the behavioral outcome observed in the
melatonin-treated animals.</p><p>Our results confirm that melatonin acts as a neuroprotective agent after traumatic
compression of the spinal cord. This may support the importance of beginning the
neuroprotective treatment within the first 3-h period after SCI as reported in NASCIS
III <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>. These findings encourage further
investigation of the potential role of melatonin in the neuroprotective process after
injury.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors are indebted to Luciana N. Nascimento for skillful assistance during the
study and to Prof. F.S. Guimar&#x000e3;es (Departamento de Farmacologia, FMRP-USP) for advice
concerning statistical analysis and text revision. This article was taken from the
thesis for the PhD in Sciences of A. Schiaveto-de-Souza. Research supported by CNPq,
FAPESP, and Don Bosco Universidade, Mato Grosso do Sul (A. Schiaveto-de-Souza
fellowship).</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B01"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mautes</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinzierl</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vascular events after spinal cord injury: contribution
to secondary pathogenesis</article-title><source>Phys Ther</source><year>2000</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>687</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10869130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B02"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Comeau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Purdy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Duration of lipid peroxidation after acute spinal cord
injury in rats and the effect of methylprednisolone</article-title><source>Neurosurg Focus</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>E5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/FOC.2008.25.11.E5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18980479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B03"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaptanoglu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuncel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Palaoglu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Konan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Demirpence</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilinc</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the effects of melatonin and
methylprednisolone in experimental spinal cord injury</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>2000</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/jns.2000.93.1.0077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10879762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B04"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Korkmaz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical aspects of melatonin</article-title><source>Saudi Med J</source><year>2008</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1537</fpage><lpage>1547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18997997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B05"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Munoz-Hoyos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacological actions of melatonin in oxygen radical
pathophysiology</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><year>1997</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>2255</fpage><lpage>2271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0024-3205(97)00030-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9194681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B06"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potent protective effects of melatonin on experimental
spinal cord injury</article-title><source>Spine</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>769</fpage><lpage>775</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007632-200004010-00003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10751286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B07"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Topsakal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozveren</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Akdemir</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiftikci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of prostaglandin E1, melatonin, and
oxytetracycline on lipid peroxidation, antioxidant defense system, paraoxonase
(PON1) activities, and homocysteine levels in an animal model of spinal cord
injury</article-title><source>Spine</source><year>2003</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1643</fpage><lpage>1652</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12897486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B08"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gu&#x000ed;zar-Sahag&#x000fa;n</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Balderas</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Franco-Bourland</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Cruz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grijalva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibarra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lack of neuroprotection with pharmacological
pretreatment in a paradigm for anticipated spinal cord lesions</article-title><source>Spinal Cord</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sc.2008.85</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18607385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B09"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dimar</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Glassman</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Raque</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of spinal canal narrowing and timing of
decompression on neurologic recovery after spinal cord contusion in a rat
model</article-title><source>Spine</source><year>1999</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1623</fpage><lpage>1633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007632-199908150-00002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10472095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giglio</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Defino</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>da-Silva</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>de-Souza</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bel</surname><given-names>EA Del</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavioral and physiological methods for early
quantitative assessment of spinal cord injury and prognosis in
rats</article-title><source>Braz J Med Biol Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1613</fpage><lpage>1623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0100-879X2006001200013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17160271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basso</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beattie</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bresnahan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sensitive and reliable locomotor rating scale for open
field testing in rats</article-title><source>J Neurotrauma</source><year>1995</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/neu.1995.12.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7783230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rivlin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tator</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Objective clinical assessment of motor function after
experimental spinal cord injury in the rat</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>1977</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/jns.1977.47.4.0577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">903810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paxinos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>The rat brain in stereotaxic coordinates</source><publisher-loc>Burlington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><year>2005</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histochemical mapping of nitric oxide synthase in the
rat brain</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>1992</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>755</fpage><lpage>784</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0306-4522(92)90184-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1371855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogerio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>QL de</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nucci</surname><given-names>G de</given-names></name><name><surname>Langone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuroprotective action of melatonin on neonatal rat
motoneurons after sciatic nerve transection</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>926</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(01)03286-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11814404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The utility of melatonin in reducing cerebral damage
resulting from ischemia and reperfusion</article-title><source>J Pineal Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-079X.2003.00034.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12614473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative damage in the central nervous system:
protection by melatonin</article-title><source>Prog Neurobiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0301-0082(98)00052-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9770244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kunkel-Bagden</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bregman</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods to assess the development and recovery of
locomotor function after spinal cord injury in rats</article-title><source>Exp Neurol</source><year>1993</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/exnr.1993.1017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8432357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mini-review: assessment of behavioural recovery
following spinal cord injury in rats</article-title><source>Eur J Neurosci</source><year>2000</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>3079</fpage><lpage>3086</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1460-9568.2000.00205.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10998091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramon-Cueto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Avila</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two modes of microtubule-associated protein 1B
phosphorylation are differentially regulated during peripheral nerve
regeneration</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>815</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(98)01092-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9878743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metz</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Merkler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Fouad</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient testing of motor function in spinal cord
injured rats</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>883</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(00)02778-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11074045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerlinger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokeach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The factorial nature of the F and D
scales</article-title><source>J Pers Soc Psychol</source><year>1966</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/h0023731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5969995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheff</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Saucier</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A statistical method for analyzing rating scale data:
the BBB locomotor score</article-title><source>J Neurotrauma</source><year>2002</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1251</fpage><lpage>1260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/08977150260338038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12427332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samantaray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sribnick</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Knaryan</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name><surname>Matzelle</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yallapragada</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Melatonin attenuates calpain upregulation, axonal damage
and neuronal death in spinal cord injury in rats</article-title><source>J Pineal Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-079X.2007.00534.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18086148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>DX</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Suppression of oxygen toxicity by
melatonin</article-title><source>Zhongguo Yao Li Xue Bao</source><year>1998</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10437151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>DX</given-names></name><name><surname>Osuna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gitto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Actions of melatonin in the reduction of oxidative
stress. A review</article-title><source>J Biomed Sci</source><year>2000</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>444</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02253360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11060493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lahiri</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions between melatonin, reactive oxygen species,
and nitric oxide</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><year>1999</year><volume>893</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.1999.tb07847.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10672259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morfim</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordova</surname><given-names>CA de</given-names></name><name><surname>Charao</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>V de</given-names></name><name><surname>Creczynski-Pasa</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Melatonin protects against pro-oxidant enzymes and
reduces lipid peroxidation in distinct membranes induced by the hydroxyl and
ascorbyl radicals and by peroxynitrite</article-title><source>J Pineal Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>262</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-079X.2003.00085.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14521632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pre-treatment with melatonin reduces volume of cerebral
infarction in a permanent middle cerebral artery occlusion stroke model in the
rat</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>2002</year><volume>318</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(01)02503-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11803119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Melatonin reduces nitric oxide level during ischemia but
not blood-brain barrier breakdown during reperfusion in a rat middle cerebral
artery occlusion stroke model</article-title><source>J Pineal Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-079X.2003.00014.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12562502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Escames</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrero</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Munoz-Hoyos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Melatonin and vitamin E limit nitric oxide-induced lipid
peroxidation in rat brain homogenates</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>1997</year><volume>230</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(97)00498-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9272682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagliaro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential biological effects of products of nitric
oxide (NO) synthase: it is not enough to say NO</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>2137</fpage><lpage>2149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0024-3205(03)00593-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12927585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amar</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenesis and pharmacological strategies for
mitigating secondary damage in acute spinal cord injury</article-title><source>Neurosurgery</source><year>1999</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>1027</fpage><lpage>1039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00006123-199905000-00052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10232536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of reactive nitrogen species in secondary
spinal cord injury: formation of nitric oxide, peroxynitrite, and nitrated
protein</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2000</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>2144</fpage><lpage>2154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-4159.2000.0752144.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11032904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kroncke</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fehsel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolb-Bachofen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide: cytotoxicity versus cytoprotection - how,
why, when, and where?</article-title><source>Nitric Oxide</source><year>1997</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/niox.1997.0118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9701050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuroprotective and neurodestructive functions of nitric
oxide after spinal cord hemisection</article-title><source>Exp Neurol</source><year>2000</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>472</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/exnr.1999.7278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10686069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiang</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Constitutive and inducible nitric oxide synthases after
dynorphin-induced spinal cord injury</article-title><source>J Chem Neuroanat</source><year>2000</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0891-0618(99)00039-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10697245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diaz-Ruiz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibarra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Severiano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Guizar-Sahagun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Grijalva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Constitutive and inducible nitric oxide synthase
activities after spinal cord contusion in rats</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>2002</year><volume>319</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(01)02540-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11834310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakahara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yone</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Setoguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaura</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Arishima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changes in nitric oxide and expression of nitric oxide
synthase in spinal cord after acute traumatic injury in rats</article-title><source>J Neurotrauma</source><year>2002</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1467</fpage><lpage>1474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/089771502320914697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12490011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bracken</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepard</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Holford</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Leo-Summers</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Methylprednisolone or tirilazad mesylate administration
after acute spinal cord injury: 1-year follow up. Results of the third National
Acute Spinal Cord Injury randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>1998</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>699</fpage><lpage>706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/jns.1998.89.5.0699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9817404</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>