<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Lab Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Lab Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ALM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Annals of Laboratory Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2234-3806</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2234-3814</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Korean Society for Laboratory Medicine</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23826561</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3698303</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3343/alm.2013.33.4.255</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Microbiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Comparative Evaluation of Three Chromogenic Media Combined with Broth Enrichment and the Real-Time PCR-Based Xpert MRSA Assay for Screening of Methicillin-Resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in Nasal Swabs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Seungok</given-names></name><degrees>M.D.</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Yeon-Joon</given-names></name><degrees>M.D.</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Kang-Gyun</given-names></name><degrees>M.T.</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jekarl</surname><given-names>Dong Wook</given-names></name><degrees>M.D.</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>Hyojin</given-names></name><degrees>M.D.</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>Jin-Kyung</given-names></name><degrees>M.T.</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>Sin Won</given-names></name><degrees>R.N.</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Jung Eun</given-names></name><degrees>R.N.</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Jung Hye</given-names></name><degrees>R.N.</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>Seon Mi</given-names></name><degrees>R.N.</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>Ju Hee</given-names></name><degrees>R.N.</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, Korea.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Seoul St. Mary's Hospital, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, Korea.</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Intensive Care Unit, Seoul St. Mary's Hospital, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, Korea.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding author: Yeon-Joon Park. Department of Laboratory Medicine, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul St. Mary's Hospital, 222 Banpo-daero, Seocho-gu, Seoul 137-701, Korea. Tel: +82-2-2258-1640, Fax: +82-2-2258-1719, <email>yjpk@catholic.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>33</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Korean Society for Laboratory Medicine.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>We evaluated the performance of three chromogenic media (Brilliance agar I [Oxoid, UK], Brilliance agar II [Oxoid], and ChromID MRSA [Biom&#x000e9;rieux, France]) combined with broth enrichment and the Xpert MRSA assay for screening of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We obtained 401 pairs of duplicate nasal swabs from 321 patients. One swab was suspended overnight in tryptic soy broth; 50-&#x000b5;L aliquots of suspension were inoculated on the three chromogenic media. Brilliance agar I and II were examined after 24 hr, and ChromID MRSA, after 24 and 48 hr. The paired swab was processed directly using real-time PCR-based Xpert MRSA assay.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>True positives, designated as MRSA growth in any of the culture media, were detected with the prevalence of 17% in our institution. We report the sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value, and negative predictive value of MRSA growth as follows: 92.3%, 94.0%, 75.9%, and 98.4% in Brilliance agar I (24 hr); 92.7%, 97.9%, 90.0%, and 98.5% in Brilliance agar II (24 hr); 95.6%, 95.8%, 82.3%, and 99.1% in ChromID MRSA (24 hr); 100%, 92.5%, 73.1%, and 100% in ChromID MRSA (48 hr); 92.6%, 96.7%, 85.1%, and 98.5% in Xpert MRSA assay. The agreement between the enriched culture and Xpert MRSA assay was 96.0%.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Three chromogenic culture media combined with enrichment and Xpert MRSA assay demonstrated similar capabilities in MRSA detection. The Xpert MRSA assay yielded results comparable to those of culture methods, saving 48-72 hr, thus facilitating earlier detection of MRSA in healthcare settings.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Chromogenic agars</kwd><kwd>Xpert MRSA assay</kwd><kwd>Methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) is one of the important nosocomial pathogens worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Patients carrying MRSA are at a greater risk for developing an <italic>S. aureus</italic> infection, compared with methicillin-susceptible <italic>S. aureus</italic> (MSSA)-colonized or non-colonized patients in the intensive care unit (ICU) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Active surveillance and isolation policy have been recommended for controlling the spread of MRSA in healthcare facilities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. In Korea, <italic>S. aureus</italic> is the second most common isolate (16.6%) among hospital isolates, and the methicillin-resistance rate of <italic>S. aureus</italic> was about 69%, according to the 2009 KONSAR study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. A timely, affordable, and reliable screening method for MRSA is essential to improve hospital infection control, and there is a continued debate about the turn-around time, cost per test, and cost benefit.</p><p>The Xpert MRSA assay (Cepheid, Sunnyvale, CA, USA) is a real-time PCR assay that targets the staphylococcal cassette chromosome <italic>mec</italic> (SCC<italic>mec</italic>)-<italic>orfX</italic> junction created by incorporation of the genetic element carrying <italic>mecA</italic> into the <italic>S. aureus</italic> chromosome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The assaycan detect, within only 2 hr, strains with all SCC<italic>mec</italic> types, including SCC<italic>mec</italic> I, II, III, IVa, V, and VI found in healthcare-acquired (HA) and community-acquired (CA) MRSA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Currently, various selective and differential chromogenic media are available that allow direct colony color-based identification of the pathogen from the primary culture 18-24 hr after incubation. However, broth enrichment and incubation for 48 hr are necessary to increase the detection sensitivity, especially in cases with low bacterial density [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><p>In this study, we compared the clinical performance of three chromogenic media (Brilliance agar I [Oxoid Ltd., Cambridge, UK], Brilliance agar II [Oxoid], and ChromID MRSA [Biom&#x000e9;rieux, Lyon, France]) combined with broth enrichment and the Xpert MRSA assay for MRSA detection by using nasal swabs from ICU patients.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><sec><title>1. Sample collection</title><p>This study was performed during March-May 2010. A total of 401 nasal samples were collected consecutively from 321 patients admitted to the ICU. The screening for MRSA was carried out on the first day in the ICU (321 initial samples) and was repeated weekly in 55 patients (80 follow-up samples) with prolonged hospitalization. The paired swabs (Copan, Brescia, Italy) were collected from each nostril of the same patient, respectively. The swab pair was transported at room temperature, and each swab was randomly used in the following process within 2 hr of collection.</p></sec><sec><title>2. Culture screening methods</title><p>One of the paired swabs was suspended in tryptic soy broth (TSB) (Becton, Dickinson and Company, Sparks, MD, USA) with 6.5% NaCl; after overnight incubation, 50 &#x000b5;L aliquots of suspension were inoculated on Brilliance agar I, Brilliance agar II, and ChromID MRSA. The two Brilliance agars were incubated for 24 hr (Brilliance agar I [24 hr] and Brilliance agar II [24 hr], respectively), and they were examined according to the manufacturer's recommendation. ChromID MRSA was incubated for 48 hr, and it was then examined at 24 and 48 hr (ChromID MRSA [24 hr] and ChromID MRSA [48 hr], respectively) by two investigators. Potential colonies were captured and identified as <italic>S. aureus</italic> if they tested positive for catalase production and latex agglutination tests (Eiken Chemical Co., Tokyo, Japan). Methicillin resistance was confirmed by oxacillin (1 &#x000b5;g) (Becton, Dickinson and Company) and cefoxitin (30 &#x000b5;g) (Becton, Dicksinson, and Company) disk diffusion susceptibility tests, according to the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute guideline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. The remaining TSB was frozen at -70&#x02103; for further evaluation. A true-positive culture was defined as growth with phenotypic features compatible with MRSA and was affirmed by confirmatory testing (catalase and latex agglutination tests). A false-positive culture was defined as growth with phenotypic features compatible with MRSA, but was affirmed as non-MRSA by confirmatory testing.</p></sec><sec><title>3. Xpert MRSA assay</title><p>The second swab of the pair was processed directly using the GeneXpert system (Cepheid) with Xpert MRSA cartridge (Cepheid) according to the manufacturer's instruction. In brief, the swab was placed in the elution reagent (black cap), vortexed at high speed for 10 sec, and dispensed into the port "S" of the Xpert MRSA cartridge. The cartridge was inserted and subjected to real-time PCR in the GeneXpert system, and the result was reported by the GeneXpert software (Cepheid). If the MRSA threshold (C<italic><sub>T</sub></italic>) value of the sample was &#x02264;36, it was positively identified as MRSA.</p></sec><sec><title>4. Multiplex PCR for SCC<italic>mec</italic> typing</title><p>Staphylococcal cassette chromosome <italic>mec</italic> (SCC<italic>mec</italic>) typing and subtyping was performed by the multiplex PCR assay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], which was updated to properly identify SCC<italic>mec</italic> types IV and V [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>5. Data analysis</title><p>A true-positive result, which was used as a reference result, was presumed as growth of MRSA in any one of the enriched chromogenic media. The sensitivity (%), specificity (%), positive predictive value (PPV, %), and negative predictive value (NPV, %) of each method was determined. For cases showing discrepant results between Xpert MRSA assay and cultures, both tests were repeated using the remaining TSB.</p><p>The C<italic><sub>T</sub></italic> values between two groups (initial screening samples versus follow-up screening samples; concordant samples versus discordant samples) were compared using the one-way ANOVA test (SPSS 13.0; SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). The threshold for statistical significance was a <italic>P</italic> value &#x0003c;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>1. Comparison of three culture media</title><p>MRSA was identified in 68 (68/401, 17.0%) samples in at least one of the culture media. The prevalence of MRSA was 13.4% (43/321) for initial screening and 31.3% (25/80) for follow-up screening samples. The comparison of four screening methods is summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. The sensitivity was highest with ChromID MRSA (48 hr) (68/68, 100%), followed by ChromID MRSA (24 hr) (65/68, 95.6%), and lowest in both Brilliance agar I (24 hr) and Brilliance agar II (24 hr) (63/68, 92.6%). The specificity and PPV was highest with Brilliance agar II (24 hr) (95.8% and 90.0%, respectively) of all the culture media. NPVs were &#x02265;98% in all the culture methods.</p><p>There were 25, 14, 20, and 7 samples in which growth on ChromID MRSA (48 hr), ChromID MRSA (24 hr), Brilliance agar I (24 hr), and Brilliance agar II (24 hr), respectively, was initially mistaken for MRSA, resulting in false-positive findings. The implicated isolates were mainly <italic>Enterococcus</italic> spp. (15/25), followed by coagulase-negative Staphylococcus (4/25) in ChromID MRSA; <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. (8/20), followed by coagulase-negative Staphylococcus (5/20) and methicillin-susceptible <italic>S. aureus</italic> (4/20) in Brilliance agar I; and methicillin-resistant coagulase-negative Staphylococcus (4/7) and methicillin-susceptible <italic>S. aureus</italic> (3/7) in Brilliance agar II.</p></sec><sec><title>2. Comparison of Xpert MRSA assay with enriched culture</title><p>The Xpert MRSA assay showed positive results for 74 samples. Moreover, when growth of MRSA on any of the enriched culture media was designated as a reference method, the total agreement with the culture was 96.0% (385/401) in the initial analysis. The sensitivity, specificity, PPV, and NPV of the Xpert MRSA assay were 92.6%, 96.7%, 85.1%, and 98.5%, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). An "invalid" result was obtained in 0.7% (3/401) samples, indicating the sample processing control (SPC) did not meet the acceptable criteria; invalidity might be caused by inadequate processing of MRSA, specimen-associated inhibition of the real-time PCR assay, or air bubbles formed in the reaction tube.</p><p>The discrepant results were observed in 16 samples (5 culture-positive, PCR-negative; 11 culture-negative, PCR-positive) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). For 5 samples showing culture-positive and PCR-negative results, the repeated Xpert MRSA assay using remaining TSB revealed all positive results and the C<italic><sub>T</sub></italic> values were variable (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). For 11 samples showing culture-negative and PCR-positive results, the repeated Xpert MRSA assay using the remaining TSB revealed negative results for 10 samples. The mean C<italic><sub>T</sub></italic> value of 11 discordant samples with culture-negative and PCR-positive results was significantly higher than that of 63 concordant samples (31.0 vs. 24.6, respectively, <italic>P</italic>=0.001). However, the mean C<italic><sub>T</sub></italic> values between initial screening samples and follow-up screening samples were similar (25.9 vs. 25.1, respectively, <italic>P</italic>=0.597).</p></sec><sec><title>3. SCC<italic>mec</italic> typing of isolates</title><p>By re-culturing the remaining frozen TSB from 54 culture-positive patients, 52 MRSA isolates were obtained. For two TSB samples, the re-culturing failed. SCC<italic>mec</italic> type II was the most common (34/52); it was followed by SCC<italic>mec</italic> type IV (13/52), SCC<italic>mec</italic> type III variant (3/52), and SCC<italic>mec</italic> type IV variant (2/52). There was no difference in the detection rates of these SCC<italic>mec</italic> types among chromogenic agars and the X-pert MRSA assay.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this study, three enriched-culture methods showed good overall performance for detecting MRSA. In particular, ChromID MRSA showed higher sensitivity, but its specificity was lower than Brilliance agar II. The detection sensitivity using ChromID MRSA increased up to 4.4% (from 95.6% at 24 hr to 100% at 48 hr) with extended incubation; inversely, the specificity decreased to 3.3% (from 95.8% at 24 hr to 92.5% at 48 hr), which corresponds to a previous report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. The results of Brilliance agar II (24 hr) were satisfactory at &#x02265;90% with respect to sensitivity, specificity, PPV, and NPV for MRSA detection. ChromID MRSA (48 hr) showed the lowest specificity due to false-positive growth of <italic>Enterococcus</italic> spp. and methicillin-resistant coagulase-negative Staphylococci (MRCoNS). In contrast to the previous report where the MRCoNS and enterococci were the major species producing false-positive results on Brilliance agar I [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. was the major isolate in this study, and this problem was not observed with Brilliance agar II.</p><p>When the enriched culture was designated as a reference method, the sensitivity and specificity of the Xpert MRSA assay in this study were 92.6% and 96.7%, respectively, which were higher than those in the previous studies with a similar design. In one study for the comparison of Xpert MRSA assay with broth-enriched MRSA-Select chromogenic agar (Bio-Rad Life Science Group, Marnes-La-Coquette, France) with a prevalence of 22.1%, the sensitivity and specificity were 84% and 92%, respectively, for detecting MRSA from a nasal site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In a multicenter study for the comparison of Xpert MRSA assay with broth-enriched CHROMagar (Becton, Dickinson and Company) with the prevalence of 5.2-44%, the sensitivity and specificity were 86.3% and 94.9%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The analytical sensitivity (limit of detection, LoD) of the Xpert MRSA assay was about 50 colony-forming units (CFU) per swab, according to the manufacturer's instruction. It was also reported by Rossney et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] that the LoD of the Xpert MRSA assay was 58 CFU per swab, and it was threefold lower but six-fold higher than those of direct and enrichment cultures, respectively. The higher specificity in this study might be due to the use of three kinds of media and a longer incubation time up to 48 hr. The mean C<italic><sub>T</sub></italic> value of the false-positive (culture-negative and PCR-positive) samples was significantly higher than that of concordant samples (31.0 vs. 24.6). These findings are in line with the previous studies showing that the discrepancies between the Xpert MRSA assay and culture method occurred exclusively when the bacterial density was low [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] and agree with the fact that the C<italic><sub>T</sub></italic> value in the Xpert MRSA assay correlates strongly with the bacterial density in the samples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. The discordance from the five false-negative results might be partially explained by the cases with low bacterial density of MRSA in the nostrils or disparity in the specimens from two nostrils (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). The reason for the one discrepancy of a sample yielding culture-negative and PCR-positive results, even in the repeated test using the remaining enrichment TSB, might be the fact that SCC elements lacking the functional <italic>mecA</italic> gene can be detected by the Xpert MRSA assay, because it does not specifically target the <italic>mecA</italic> gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Another explanation for the one culture-negative and PCR-positive sample is the limitation in the experimental design for <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains that may require anaerobic incubation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p><p>There was no difference in the detection rates of SCC<italic>mec</italic> types among chromogenic agars and Xpert MRSA assay. The majority of the isolates were SCC<italic>mec</italic> type II that is known as HA-MRSA clone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], followed by SCC<italic>mec</italic> type IV that is emerging as a CA-MRSA clone in Korea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><p>In conclusion, the performance of the three chromogenic media combined with enriched culture and the Xpert MRSA assay was good (&#x0003e;92% of both sensitivity and specificity). Notably, the agreement rate between the Xpert MRSA assay and the enriched-culture methods was high (96%) in this study. The Xpert MRSA assay could give results comparable to culture methods within 1 hr. This early detection can help save 48-72 hr, and help in prevention and control of MRSA infection in health-care settings.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Oxoid and Cepheid for providing chromogenic media and Xpert MRSA assay kits, respectively.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiological characteristics of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Korean J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coopersmith</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kollef</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> nasal colonization and subsequent infection in intensive care unit patients: does methicillin resistance matter?</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20426656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Oriola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huskins</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Noskin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Harriman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Legislative mandates for use of active surveillance cultures to screen for methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and vancomycin-resistant enterococci: position statement from the Joint SHEA and APIC Task Force</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17326014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Further increases in carbapenem-, amikacin-, and fluoroquinolone-resistant isolates of <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> spp. and <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> in Korea: KONSAR study 2009</article-title><source>Yonsei Med J</source><year>2011</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>793</fpage><lpage>802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21786445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arbefeville</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroeger</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Diekema</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and genetic relatedness of methicillin-susceptible <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolates detected by the Xpert MRSA nasal assay</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>2996</fpage><lpage>2999</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21677066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolk</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Picton</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pancholi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginocchio</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multicenter evaluation of the Cepheid Xpert methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) test as a rapid screening method for detection of MRSA in nares</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>758</fpage><lpage>764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19129414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makgotlho</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kock</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoosen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lekalakala</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dove</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular identification and genotyping of MRSA isolates</article-title><source>FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19712080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossney</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Herra</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the Xpert methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) assay using the GeneXpert real-time PCR platform for rapid detection of MRSA from screening specimens</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>3285</fpage><lpage>3290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18685003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolk</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marx</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schifman</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of MRSASelect Agar, CHROMagar Methicillin-Resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) Medium, and Xpert MRSA PCR for detection of MRSA in Nares: diagnostic accuracy for surveillance samples with various bacterial densities</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>3933</fpage><lpage>3936</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19828738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malhotra-Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrahantes</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabiiti</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lammens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vercauteren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ieven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of chromogenic media for detection of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1040</fpage><lpage>1046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20164268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</collab><source>Performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing, M100-S20</source><publisher-loc>Wayne, PA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CLSI</publisher-name><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsayed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Louie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Conly</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel multiplex PCR assay for characterization and concomitant subtyping of staphylococcal cassette chromosome <italic>mec</italic> types I to V in methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>5026</fpage><lpage>5033</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16207957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milheiri&#x000e7;o</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lencastre</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Update to the multiplex PCR strategy for assignment of mec element types in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2007</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>3374</fpage><lpage>3377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17576837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stenehjem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rimland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Crispell</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Stafford</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaynes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Satola</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cepheid Xpert MRSA cycle threshold in discordant colonization results and a quantitative measure of nasal colonization burden</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>2079</fpage><lpage>2081</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22442322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichelberger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid identification of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in blood cultures by use of the direct tube coagulase test</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>2267</fpage><lpage>2269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17522280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsueh</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spread of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> between the community and the hospitals in Asian countries: an ANSORP study</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2011</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>1061</fpage><lpage>1069</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21393157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Panton-Valentine leukocidin positive <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolated from blood in Korea</article-title><source>Korean J Lab Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18094590</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of Brilliance agar I, Brilliance agar II, ChromID MRSA, and Xpert MRSA assay for screening of MRSA from 401 nasal swabs</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alm-33-255-i001"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>*</sup>A true positive culture was determined if MRSA was detected in one or more of the three culture media tested, and it was used as a reference culture result.</p><p>Abbreviations: MRSA, Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus; PPV, positive predictive value; NPV, negative predictive value; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Analysis of 16 samples showing discrepancy between enriched culture and Xpert MRSA assay for MRSA screening</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="alm-33-255-i002"/><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviations: MRSA, Methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>; BAP, blood agar plate; SCC<italic>mec</italic>, staphylococcal cassette chromosome <italic>mec</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>