<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24343202</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3865466</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep03513</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep03513</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Terahertz conductivity of topological surface states in Bi<sub>1.5</sub>Sb<sub>0.5</sub>Te<sub>1.8</sub>Se<sub>1.2</sub></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Chi Sin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Bin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Xingquan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Shi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>Hong-Wei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Lan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rusydi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">b</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Jian-Xin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>Elbert E. M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c3">c</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Division of Physics and Applied Physics, School of Physical and Mathematical Sciences, Nanyang Technological University</institution>, Singapore 637371, <country>Singapore</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>NUSNNI-NanoCore, Department of Physics, National University of Singapore</institution>, 117542, <country>Singapore</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Theoretical Division and Center for Integrated Nanotechnologies</institution>, Los Alamos National Laboratory, Los Alamos NM 87545, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>wanglan@ntu.edu.sg</email></corresp><corresp id="c2"><label>b</label><email>phyandri@nus.edu.sg</email></corresp><corresp id="c3"><label>c</label><email>elbertchia@ntu.edu.sg</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>3513</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>09</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2013, Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Topological insulators are electronic materials with an insulating bulk and conducting surface. However, due to free carriers in the bulk, the properties of the metallic surface are difficult to detect and characterize in most topological insulator materials. Recently, a new topological insulator Bi<sub>1.5</sub>Sb<sub>0.5</sub>Te<sub>1.7</sub>Se<sub>1.3</sub> (BSTS) was found, showing high bulk resistivities of 1&#x02013;10&#x02005;&#x003a9;.cm and greater contrast between the bulk and surface resistivities compared to other Bi-based topological insulators. Using Terahertz Time-Domain Spectroscopy (THz-TDS), we present complex conductivity of BSTS single crystals, disentangling the surface and bulk contributions. We find that the Drude spectral weight is 1&#x02013;2 orders of magnitude smaller than in other Bi-based topological insulators, and similar to that of Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> thin films, suggesting a significant contribution of the topological surface states to the conductivity of the BSTS sample. Moreover, an impurity band is present about 30&#x02005;meV below the Fermi level, and the surface and bulk carrier densities agree with those obtained from transport data. Furthermore, from the surface Drude contribution, we obtain a ~98% transmission through one surface layer &#x02014; this is consistent with the transmission through single-layer or bilayer graphene, which shares a common Dirac-cone feature in the band structure.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>The special features of a topological insulator &#x02014; insulating bulk and conducting surface<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>, have been attributed to the presence of time-reversal symmetry and spin-orbit interaction<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. Earlier-discovered three-dimensional topological insulators such as Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>, Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub> and Sb<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub> have a high concentration of bulk carriers, resulting in a weakly-insulating bulk electronic state and making it difficult to detect the metallic surface states<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>. In BSTS<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, non-stoichiometry-induced donors and acceptors compensate each other, yielding high bulk resistivities of 1&#x02013;10 &#x003a9;.cm and high contribution (~70%) of the total conductance by surface transport, thus showing a greater contrast between the bulk and surface resistivities compared to Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>, Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub> and even Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>2</sub>Se<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>. THz-TDS is a non-contact far-infrared optical technique suitable for probing the low-energy excitations of strongly correlated electronic systems such as cuprate superconductors<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>, pnictide superconductors<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>, and colossal magnetoresistance manganites<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>. In this Report, we present the temperature-dependent optical conductivity of BSTS samples at temperatures 5&#x02013;150&#x02005;K in the far-infrared regime (0.4&#x02013;3.0&#x02005;THz). By modeling the total conductance as the sum of Drude and Lorentz components, we were able to obtain a Drude weight to be 1&#x02013;2 orders of magnitude smaller than other Bi-based topological insulators<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>, and close to the value for the surface state of Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> thin films<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>. This suggests a significant contribution of the topological surface states to the conductivity of the BSTS sample.</p><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Sample growth, electronic transport and ARPES</title><p>Samples were grown by the modified Bridgeman method (Methods section)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>. In-plane DC resistivity data were taken using a Quantum Design Physical Property Measurement System (PPMS), as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>. Both the temperature dependence and the absolute values of resistivity are consistent with those in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>. Scanning Electron Microscopy with Energy Dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (SEM-EDX) data of the BSTS samples were reported in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>, giving the chemical composition of the sample, and consistent with previous publications<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>. Evidences for two-dimensional surface properties in our samples were given by ambipolar<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>, as well as angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) data. The inset of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref> shows ARPES data of Bi<sub>1.5</sub>Sb<sub>0.5</sub>Te<sub>1.8</sub>Se<sub>1.2</sub> single crystals obtained from a Scienta R4000 electron analyzer at the Surface, Interface and Nanostructure (SINS) beamline at Singapore Synchrotron Light Source (SSLS) (Methods section). The data show the surface state at the vicinity of <italic>&#x00393;</italic> point, which is an important signature of a sample being a topological insulator. The observed surface state does have a similar feature to that in a previous report of ARPES on Bi<sub>1.5</sub>Sb<sub>0.5</sub>Te<sub>1.7</sub>Se<sub>1.3</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>. Note that, due to the limited energy resolution, many detailed structures are unresolved at this stage. In this Report we focus on the optical properties in the THz regime.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>THz-TDS</title><p>Details of the THz-TDS setup are given in the Methods section. By finding the ratio between the sample <inline-formula id="m7"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e366" xlink:href="srep03513-m7.jpg"/></inline-formula> and reference <inline-formula id="m8"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e369" xlink:href="srep03513-m8.jpg"/></inline-formula> spectra, one is able to obtain the complex transmittance, <inline-formula id="m9"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e372" xlink:href="srep03513-m9.jpg"/></inline-formula>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref> shows the amplitude of the experimental transmittance of BSTS, <inline-formula id="m10"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e378" xlink:href="srep03513-m10.jpg"/></inline-formula>, at various temperatures. A periodicity due to multiple reflections within the sample is observed at low temperatures and gets washed out with increasing temperature above ~100&#x02005;K. We account for these reflections in Eq. (1) below when we extract the optical conductivity. In addition, a drop in <inline-formula id="m11"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e382" xlink:href="srep03513-m11.jpg"/></inline-formula> to zero has been observed at ~1.7&#x02005;THz and after which, rises again at ~2.8&#x02005;THz. This corresponds to an optical phonon mode at 1.9&#x02005;THz, to be described later. By fitting the experimental <inline-formula id="m12"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e385" xlink:href="srep03513-m12.jpg"/></inline-formula> to the theoretical expression <disp-formula id="m1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e388" xlink:href="srep03513-m1.jpg"/></disp-formula>one is able to obtain the complex refractive index of the sample, <inline-formula id="m13"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e391" xlink:href="srep03513-m13.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Here <italic>d</italic> ( = 60&#x02005;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m) is the sample thickness, <italic>c</italic> is the speed of light in vacuum, and the summation in Eq. (1) accounts for multiple reflections of the THz pulse inside the sample, with the number of reflections <italic>M</italic> = 6. Note that, due to the considerable thickness of the sample, we could not assume infinite reflections of the THz pulse inside the sample, as was usually assumed for nanometer-thickness thin films.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Drude-Lorentz model</title><p>The complex refractive index is then used to calculate the complex conductivity <inline-formula id="m14"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e412" xlink:href="srep03513-m14.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula id="m15"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e415" xlink:href="srep03513-m15.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="m16"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e418" xlink:href="srep03513-m16.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="m17"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e421" xlink:href="srep03513-m17.jpg"/></inline-formula> being the permittivity of free space, and <inline-formula id="m18"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e424" xlink:href="srep03513-m18.jpg"/></inline-formula> the high-frequency dielectric constant. As an unknown quantity, <inline-formula id="m19"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e428" xlink:href="srep03513-m19.jpg"/></inline-formula> was initially set to 1 when we calculate the experimental conductance, via the expression <inline-formula id="m20"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e431" xlink:href="srep03513-m20.jpg"/></inline-formula> (<italic>t<sub>bulk</sub></italic> = 60&#x02005;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m); then it will be used as a fitting parameter<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref> in the conductance fitting for each temperature. We model the conductance to contain a Drude (D) free-carrier contribution averaged over the surface and bulk, and a Lorentz (L) contribution from the insulating bulk, similar to the analysis carried out for Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref> and given by <inline-formula id="m21"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e452" xlink:href="srep03513-m21.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where <disp-formula id="m2"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e455" xlink:href="srep03513-m2.jpg"/></disp-formula>The fitting parameters <italic>&#x003c9;<sub>pD</sub></italic> and <italic>&#x003b3;<sub>D</sub></italic> denote the plasma frequency and scattering rate of the Drude component, respectively. <italic>&#x003c9;<sub>pL</sub></italic>, <italic>&#x003c9;<sub>oL</sub></italic> and <italic>&#x003b3;<sub>L</sub></italic> are the plasma frequency, oscillator frequency and the scattering rate of the Lorentz component, respectively. The temperature dependence of these fitting parameters will be discussed later. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3(a)</xref> shows the real and imaginary components of the experimental complex conductance <inline-formula id="m22"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e487" xlink:href="srep03513-m22.jpg"/></inline-formula> of the sample at 30&#x02005;K, alongside the fit to the Drude-Lorentz model, and the respective Drude and Lorentz contributions. Compared to other Bi-based topological insulators<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>, the low-frequency response of our BSTS sample is Lorentz-like with a very small Drude offset (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3(a)</xref>). This is consistent with our BSTS sample having a large bulk resistivity.</p><p>We estimate how dc conductivity of BSTS varies with temperature by plotting the low-frequency <italic>&#x003c3;</italic><sub>1</sub> (<italic>&#x003c9;</italic> = 0.4&#x02005;THz) versus temperature, then fitting it to the thermally-activated hopping model given by<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>
<disp-formula id="m3"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e508" xlink:href="srep03513-m3.jpg"/></disp-formula>from 5&#x02005;K to 150&#x02005;K, where <italic>A</italic> is a constant, <italic>D</italic> is a nonzero offset at 0&#x02005;K, &#x00394; is the activation energy, and <italic>k<sub>B</sub></italic> is the Boltzmann constant. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3(b)</xref> shows the low-frequency conductivity together with the fit to Eq. (3), with <italic>D</italic> = (2.80 &#x000b1; 0.01)&#x02005;(&#x003a9;.cm)<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and activation energy &#x00394; = (26.7 &#x000b1; 0.2)&#x02005;meV. The fitted value of &#x00394; is consistent with the results by Ren <italic>et al.</italic> that vary between 22 and 53&#x02005;meV<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>. A similar energy scale of 30&#x02013;40&#x02005;meV has also been found in Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>2</sub>Se, which has been attributed to transitions from the impurity bound states to the electronic continuum<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>.</p><p>We next discuss factors that contribute to the frequency and temperature dependence of the surface and bulk conductance, by looking at the temperature dependence of the fitting parameters in Eq. (2). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figures 4(a) and (b)</xref> display the temperature-dependent Drude plasma frequency (<italic>&#x003c9;<sub>pD</sub></italic>) and Lorentz plasma frequency (<italic>&#x003c9;<sub>pL</sub></italic>) respectively, while <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figs. 4(c) and (d)</xref> show the Drude (<italic>&#x003b3;<sub>D</sub></italic>) and Lorentz (<italic>&#x003b3;<sub>L</sub></italic>) scattering rates respectively. First note that the absolute values of these fitting parameters are consistent with those obtained for Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> thin films<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>. We found <italic>&#x003c9;<sub>pD</sub></italic> to increase significantly with temperature, while <italic>&#x003b3;<sub>D</sub></italic> (proportional to charge carrier mobility) shows marginal increase with temperature. As for bulk carrier dynamics, both <italic>&#x003c9;<sub>pL</sub></italic> and <italic>&#x003b3;<sub>L</sub></italic> exhibit marginal correlation with temperature. Since the square of plasma frequency <italic>&#x003c9;<sub>p</sub></italic>, is directly proportional to the charge carrier density <italic>N</italic> via the relation <inline-formula id="m23"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e612" xlink:href="srep03513-m23.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where <italic>e</italic> denotes the elementary charge and <italic>m</italic>* is the effective mass of the charge carrier, this suggests the increase in the surface charge density with temperature while the scattering rate changes only marginally. This is unlike the case of conventional metals, where the increase in resistivity with increasing temperature originates from the increase in scattering rate, with the charge density remaining temperature independent. The increase in surface charge carrier density may be due to the contribution of bulk carriers from the donor impurity band to the topological surface states (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref>). This band, situated ~30&#x02005;meV ( = activation gap &#x00394;) below the Fermi level, starts to contribute carriers to the Dirac cone above 60&#x02005;K, leading to a rise in the Drude spectral weight <inline-formula id="m24"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e625" xlink:href="srep03513-m24.jpg"/></inline-formula>. This relationship between &#x00394; and <inline-formula id="m25"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e628" xlink:href="srep03513-m25.jpg"/></inline-formula> is supported by our fit of <inline-formula id="m26"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e631" xlink:href="srep03513-m26.jpg"/></inline-formula> (in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4(a)</xref>) with Eq. (3) &#x02014; a good fit was obtained with &#x00394; = (31 &#x000b1; 4)&#x02005;meV (solid line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4(a)</xref>), consistent with the earlier-obtained value of &#x00394; = (26.7 &#x000b1; 0.2)&#x02005;meV from the <italic>&#x003c3;</italic>(<italic>&#x003c9;</italic> = 0.4&#x02005;THz) fit. This is not surprising, since, from Eq. (2), <inline-formula id="m27"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e647" xlink:href="srep03513-m27.jpg"/></inline-formula>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref> shows a schematic of the relative positions of the valence band, Dirac point, impurity band, chemical potential, and conduction band in BSTS &#x02014; they are consistent with that obtained from transport data of BSTS with similar composition<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>. Note that in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, though the Fermi level is pinned to the impurity band in the bulk, the impurity band bends downwards at the surface, such that the impurity band now lies below the Fermi level at the sample surface.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Drude spectral weight</title><p>In an optical conductivity study of a group of Bi-based topological insulators that does <italic>not</italic> include BSTS<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>, the far-infrared conductivity of its most compensated sample (Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>2</sub>Se) is still affected by the extrinsic charge carriers due to non-stoichiometry and doping. In Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>, in order to compare the charge densities due to the (a) topological surface states and (b) free (extrinsic) carriers in the bulk, the optical spectral weight was calculated using <disp-formula id="m4"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e679" xlink:href="srep03513-m4.jpg"/></disp-formula>where the cutoff frequency, set at &#x003a9;<italic><sub>max</sub></italic> = 500&#x02005;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, separates the low-frequency excitations from the interband transitions. We perform the same calculation for our BSTS sample using the Drude fitting parameters. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6(a)</xref> displays the spectral weight of BSTS as a function of frequency, calculated at 5&#x02005;K, and superposed with data from other Bi-based topological insulators from Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>. The dashed line indicates the Drude spectral weight of Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> thin films, which was attributed to the topological surface states<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>. We see that, compared to the spectral weights of other Bi-based topological insulators, the Drude spectral weight of our BSTS sample is one order of magnitude smaller than the most compensated sample &#x02014; Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>2</sub>Se, and is comparable to that of Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> thin film. This is a clear indication that in BSTS, in comparison to other Bi-based topological insulator samples, the effect of the 3D bulk states is further suppressed, and the topological surface states could be more clearly resolved.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Surface and bulk carrier density</title><p>Now that we have established the Drude component to have a significant two-dimensional surface contribution, we then re-express the experimental Drude conductance <inline-formula id="m28"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e721" xlink:href="srep03513-m28.jpg"/></inline-formula> in Eq. (2) as <disp-formula id="m5"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e724" xlink:href="srep03513-m5.jpg"/></disp-formula>where the first term on the right-hand-side is the two-dimensional Drude conductance arising from a linear (Dirac-like) dispersion of the surface carriers<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>, with the factor 2 accounting for the top and bottom surfaces of the sample. The second term on the right-hand-side is the three-dimensional Drude conductance from the bulk carriers similar to Eq. (2), <italic>&#x003c4;</italic> = 1/<italic>&#x003b3;<sub>D</sub></italic>, <italic>N<sub>surf</sub></italic> the surface electron density (of one surface), <italic>N<sub>bulk</sub></italic> the bulk electron density, <italic>&#x003bd;<sub>f</sub></italic> = 6.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>&#x02005;m/s the Fermi velocity<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, and <italic>m</italic>* = 0.32<italic>m<sub>e</sub></italic> the electron effective mass<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>. By fitting the 10&#x02005;K data to Eq. (7) from the 60-&#x003bc;m sample shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3</xref>, and another 90-&#x003bc;m sample shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Fig. 7</xref> later, we obtain two simultaneous equations in <italic>N<sub>surf</sub></italic> and <italic>N<sub>bulk</sub></italic>, which are solved to give <italic>N<sub>surf</sub></italic> = 3.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>13</sup>&#x02005;cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> and <italic>N<sub>bulk</sub></italic> = 1.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>16</sup>&#x02005;cm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>. We note that, though the obtained bulk carrier density is comparable to that obtained from transport measurements with <italic>N<sub>bulk</sub></italic> = 2.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>16</sup>&#x02005;cm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, the surface carrier density is one order of magnitude larger than that from the transport measurements with <italic>N<sub>surf</sub></italic> = 1.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup>&#x02005;cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>. The origin of this discrepancy may come from the nature of optical techniques versus transport measurements. For a system like BSTS with impurity-induced inhomogeneity, the optical technique not only measures the carriers which directly scatter off impurities, but also free carriers which move back and forth within an area with a linear dimension determined by the mean free path. Both types of carriers contribute to an average Drude conductivity. On the other hand, in transport measurements, only the delocalized carriers throughout the whole region between two electrical contacts are measured. A similar reasoning has also been proposed for the optical study of phase-separated manganite thin films<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. Scanning tunnelling microscopy of Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> and Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub> revealed inhomogeneity of the local density of states on the surface near the Dirac point, due to charge disorder caused by bulk defects (&#x0201c;defect-induced charged puddles&#x0201d;)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>. To lend further credence to the quality of our BSTS THz-TDS data, we note that&#x02009;the larger value of <italic>N</italic><sub>surf</sub> from optical spectroscopy compared to transport measurements was also seen in Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>. For example, THz-TDS data on Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> by Aguilar <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref> obtained <italic>N</italic><sub>surf</sub> ~ 2.1&#x02013;3.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>13</sup>&#x02005;cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, which agrees with our data for BSTS (3.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>13</sup>&#x02005;cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>). Transport data on Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> yielded smaller values of <italic>N</italic><sub>surf</sub>: 4.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>12</sup>&#x02005;cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> from Shubnikov de Haas (SdH) oscillations of single crystals<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>, and 7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>11</sup>&#x02005;cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> from SdH oscillations of nanostructures<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Transmission through surface layer</title><p>We next use the fitting results from Eq. (5) to estimate the transmission change through the surface state of our BSTS sample, with an estimated thickness of ~2&#x02005;nm<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>. From the two-dimensional Drude conductance <inline-formula id="m29"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e929" xlink:href="srep03513-m29.jpg"/></inline-formula> and thus conductivity <inline-formula id="m30"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e932" xlink:href="srep03513-m30.jpg"/></inline-formula>, we can obtain the Drude real and imaginary dielectric constant given by (in SI units) <inline-formula id="m31"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e935" xlink:href="srep03513-m31.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="m32"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e938" xlink:href="srep03513-m32.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The extinction coefficient <italic>&#x003ba;</italic>(<italic>&#x003c9;</italic>) is then given in terms of <italic>&#x003b5;</italic><sub>1</sub>(<italic>&#x003c9;</italic>) and <italic>&#x003b5;</italic><sub>2</sub>(<italic>&#x003c9;</italic>) by <disp-formula id="m6"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e965" xlink:href="srep03513-m6.jpg"/></disp-formula>At 10&#x02005;K and 1&#x02005;THz, <italic>&#x003ba;</italic> &#x02248; 210, hence the absorption coefficient <inline-formula id="m33"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e971" xlink:href="srep03513-m33.jpg"/></inline-formula> at 1&#x02005;THz is &#x003b1;(1&#x02005;THz) = 8.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>&#x02005;m<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Finally, the transmission (of 1-THz component) through one pass of one (top or bottom) surface layer is <italic>exp</italic>(&#x02212;<italic>&#x003b1;t<sub>surf</sub></italic>) ~ 98.3%. This THz transmission of ~98% is consistent with that of single-layer graphene<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref> or bilayer graphene<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. Whether this similarity is due to the common Dirac-cone feature in their band structures, is an intriguing question.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Effect of aging</title><p>Our data might be complicated by two effects. First, in ARPES data of BSTS, although the chemical potential was initially in the bulk gap, the chemical potential on the surface, after 30 hours, has shifted upwards into the conduction band<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>. However, transport data showed that the surface chemical potential remains in the bulk gap even after one month of exposure to air<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>. Second, the valence, conduction and impurity bands bend downwards at the surface due to air exposure<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>. All the data shown in this paper were taken within 24 hours after cleaving. In order to ascertain that the temperature dependences in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4</xref> are not due to aging or band-bending effects, we took data on another freshly cleaved 90-&#x003bc;m BSTS sample, but now in the temperature sequence 10&#x02005;K &#x02192; 50&#x02005;K &#x02192; 90&#x02005;K &#x02192; 150&#x02005;K &#x02192; 10&#x02005;K &#x02192; 50&#x02005;K &#x02192; 90&#x02005;K &#x02192; 150&#x02005;K, all under 2 hours 15 minutes. The conductivity [<italic>&#x003c3;</italic><sub>1</sub>(<italic>&#x003c9;</italic>)] spectra at the respective temperatures is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Fig. 7</xref>. Our results show that, within the short time span of data-taking, the conductivity values at the same temperature were reproducible over different runs. Hence, provided we take our data in a reasonably short time (~hours), the optical properties of BSTS shown in our paper are not sensitive to aging or band bending. This conclusion is consistent with SdH data of BSTS &#x02014; the SdH oscillations were observed even after long exposure to air (one month), whose magnetic field dependence signified the 2D nature of these oscillations, strongly suggesting the robustness of the surface state against aging<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>. It is also consistent with the ARPES data of Bi<sub>2</sub>(Te-Se)<sub>3</sub> topological insulator, where no significant aging effects were found for more than two weeks after cleaving, under a good vacuum condition<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Phonons</title><p>From the conductance fittings, we also obtained the oscillator frequency <italic>&#x003c9;</italic><sub>0<italic>L</italic></sub> = (1.92 &#x000b1; 0.04)&#x02005;THz, and temperature independent. This oscillator can be attributed to an optical phonon mode, which also agrees with the THz-TDS data of Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> thin films<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>, where a similar optical phonon has been found at ~2.0&#x02005;THz. This result is also consistent with the <inline-formula id="m34"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1049" xlink:href="srep03513-m34.jpg"/></inline-formula> longitudinal optical phonon obtained by pump-probe<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref> and Raman<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref> studies on Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>. A similar phonon mode has also been observed in Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub> thin films at 1.84&#x02005;THz<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In summary, we measured the terahertz conductivity of Bi<sub>1.5</sub>Sb<sub>0.5</sub>Te<sub>1.8</sub>Se<sub>1.2</sub> as a function of temperature using THz-TDS. We have modeled the experimental conductance as a sum of a Drude term and a Lorentz term. By careful analysis of the temperature dependence of the Drude term and the optical spectral weight, we found the topological surface states to be more clearly resolved compared to other Bi-based topological insulator samples. The present work has demonstrated for the first time by use of TDS-THz spectroscopy that the bulk insulating character can be enhanced through the compensation of non-stoichiometry-induced donors and acceptors in Bi<sub>1.5</sub>Sb<sub>0.5</sub>Te<sub>1.8</sub>Se<sub>1.2</sub>. This success is due to the unique capability of TDS-THz in differentiating the surface and bulk contribution to the conductivity of a material like topological insulators. Future thickness-dependent THz conductivity studies of topological insulator thin films, and the identification of relative surface and bulk contributions, will further advance our understanding of the electronic states in these technologically important materials.</p></sec><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Sample growth</title><p>BSTS single crystals were synthesized by melting high purity (99.9999%) Bi, Sb, Te and Se with molar ratio 1.5:0.5:1.8:1.2 at 850&#x000b0;C in an evacuated quartz tube. The temperature was then gradually decreased to room temperature over a span of three weeks<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>. The BSTS single crystal was then cleaved repeatedly <italic>ex situ</italic> to a thickness of 60&#x02005;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m while maintaining a large surface area (~4 &#x000d7; 4&#x02005;mm<sup>2</sup>), then placed into a cryostat under 3 minutes.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>ARPES</title><p>ARPES data were taken with the Scienta R4000 electron analyzer at the Surface, Interface and Nanostructure (SINS) beamline at Singapore Synchrotron Light Source (SSLS). The incoming photon energy was set to be 60&#x02005;eV with linear polarization, and energy resolution of about 140&#x02005;meV. The photon energy and Fermi level were calibrated using a clean gold foil which is thoroughly sputtered before measurement. The samples were in-situ cleaved inside the chamber, at a pressure of 1&#x02013;2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>&#x02005;mbar. Data were taken at 300&#x02005;K.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>THz-TDS</title><p>THz transmission of the BSTS single crystal was measured using a conventional THz-TDS system (TeraView Spectra 3000) incorporated with a Janis ST-100-FTIR cryostat. The THz signal was generated and detected by photoconductive antennae fabricated on low temperature-grown GaAs films. The aperture diameter is 3.5&#x02005;mm, allowing for an accurate measurement of the THz signal down to ~0.4&#x02005;THz. The time-domain electric field of the THz pulse signal is transmitted through the BSTS sample <inline-formula id="m35"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1134" xlink:href="srep03513-m35.jpg"/></inline-formula>, while the reference signal <inline-formula id="m36"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1137" xlink:href="srep03513-m36.jpg"/></inline-formula> is transmitted through vacuum. 1800&#x02005;THz traces were taken in 60 seconds for each reference or sample run. The sample holder was moved back and forth between the sample and reference positions by means of a vertical motorized stage with a resolution of 2.5&#x02005;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m. Fast Fourier Transform (FFT) was then performed on the time-domain THz signal to obtain the amplitude and phase of the THz spectra. Since the THz-TDS detects both the amplitude and phase of the THz signal, there is no need to use the Kramers-Kronig transformation to extract the real and imaginary components of the material optical parameters.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>B.X. and L.W. prepared the samples and conducted electrical measurements. ARPES measurements were taken by S.C., H.-W.O. and A.R. THz-TDS data were taken by C.S.T. and X.Q.Z. and analyzed by C.S.T., J.-X.Z. and E.E.M.C. Insight into physical mechanism was provided by J.-X.Z. The manuscript was prepared by C.S.T. and E.E.M.C. with assistance from J.X.Z. and A.R. The project was initiated by L.W. and E.E.M.C. and led by E.E.M.C.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank A. Castro Neto, D. Talbayev, V. Venkatesan, P. Di Pietro and S. Lupi for discussions. L.W. acknowledges funding from Singapore National Research Foundation RCA-08/018 and Singapore Ministry of Education AcRF Tier 2 (MOE2010-T2-2-059). E.E.M.C. acknowledges support from Singapore Ministry of Education AcRF Tier 1 (RG 13/12), Tier 2 (ARC 23/08), as well as the National Research Foundation Competitive Research Programme (NRF-CRP4-2008-04). J.-X.Z. is supported by the National Nuclear Security Administration of the U.S. DOE at LANL under Contract No. DE-AC52-06NA25396, the US. DOE Office of Basic Energy Sciences, and in part by the Center for Integrated Nanotechnologies, a U.S. DOE Office of Basic Energy Sciences user facility.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The birth of topological insulators</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>464</volume>, <fpage>194</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20220837</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>M. Z.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Topological insulators</article-title>. <source>Rev. Mod. Phys.</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>3045</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>A topological Dirac insulator in a quantum spin Hall phase</article-title>. <source>Nature (London)</source>
<volume>452</volume>, <fpage>970</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>974</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18432240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Checkelsky</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Quantum Interference in Macroscopic Crystals of Nonmetallic Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub></article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>103</volume>, <fpage>246601</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20366216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Angular-dependent oscillations of the magnetoresistance in Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> due to the three-dimensional bulk Fermi surface</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>195309</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Aharonov-Bohm interference in topological insulator nanoribbons</article-title>. <source>Nat. Mater.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>229</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20010826</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Analytis</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Bulk Fermi surface coexistence with Dirac surface state in Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>: A comparison of photoemission and Shubnikov-de Haas measurements</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>205407</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Large bulk resistivity and surface quantum oscillations in the topological insulator Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>2</sub>Se</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>241306</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Taskin</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Observation of Dirac Holes and Electrons in a Topological Insulator</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>107</volume>, <fpage>016801</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21797561</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Di Pietro</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Optical conductivity of bismuth-based topological insulators</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
<volume>86</volume>, <fpage>045439</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Averitt</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Ultrafast optical and far-infrared quasiparticle dynamics in correlated electron materials</article-title>. <source>J. Phys.: Condens. Matter</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>R1357</fpage> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>R. V.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>N. P. Pair-breaking effects and coherence peak in the terahertz conductivity of superconducting BaFe<sub>2&#x02212;2x</sub>Co<sub>2x</sub>As<sub>2</sub> thin films</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>180514</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>R. V.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Terahertz Response and Colossal Kerr Rotation from the Surface States of the Topological Insulator Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub></article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>087403</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22463570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Indications of surface-dominated transport in single crystalline nanoflake devices of topological insulator Bi<sub>1.5</sub>Sb<sub>0.5</sub>Te<sub>1.8</sub>Se<sub>1.2</sub></article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
<volume>87</volume>, <fpage>085442</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arakane</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Tunable Dirac cone in the topological insulator Bi<sub>2&#x02212;x</sub>Sb<sub>x</sub>Te<sub>3&#x02212;y</sub>Se<sub>y</sub></article-title>. <source>Nat. Comm.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>636</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Singleton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<source>Band Theory and Electronic Properties of Solids</source> (Oxford, New York - US, <year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Optimizing Bi<sub>2&#x02212;<italic>x</italic></sub>Sb<italic><sub>x</sub></italic>Te<sub>3&#x02212;<italic>y</italic></sub>Se<italic><sub>y</sub></italic> solid solutions to approach the intrinsic topological insulator regime</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
<volume>84</volume>, <fpage>165311</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>R. V.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Aging and reduced bulk conductance in thin films of the topological insulator Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub></article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Phys.</source>
<volume>113</volume>, <fpage>153702</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Horng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Drude conductivity of Dirac fermions in graphene</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>165113</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rauer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Thickness dependent phase separation in La<sub>0.7</sub>Ca<sub>0.3</sub>MnO<sub>3</sub> films</article-title>. <source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>3777</fpage> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beidenkopf</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Spatial fluctuations of helical Dirac fermions on the surface of topological insulators</article-title>. <source>Nat. Phys.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>939</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Petrushevsky</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Probing the surface states in Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> using the Shubnikov-de Haas effect</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
<volume>86</volume>, <fpage>045131</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Synthesis and quantum transport properties of Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> topological insulator nanostructures</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>1264</fpage>; 10.1038/srep01264 (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23405278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Crossover of the three-dimensional topological insulator Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> to the two-dimensional limit</article-title>. <source>Nat. Phys.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>584</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Broadband electromagnetic response and ultrafast dynamics of few-layer epitaxial graphene</article-title>. <source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>172102</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>X. Q.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Terahertz conductivity of twisted bilayer graphene</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>110</volume>, <fpage>067401</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23432306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Reversible tuning of the surface state in a pseudobinary Bi<sub>2</sub>(Te-Se)<sub>3</sub> topological insulator</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
<volume>86</volume>, <fpage>085112</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Spatially resolved femtosecond pump-probe study of topological insulator Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub></article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>235306</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Ultrafast carrier and phonon dynamics in Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> crystals</article-title>. <source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>97</volume>, <fpage>182102</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Raman and far-infrared investigation of phonons in the rhombohedral V<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;VI<sub>3</sub> compounds Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub>, Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>, Sb<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub> and Bi<sub>2</sub>(Te<sub>1&#x02212;<italic>x</italic></sub>Se<italic><sub>x</sub></italic>)<sub>3</sub> (0 &#x0003c; <italic>x</italic> &#x0003c; 1), (Bi<sub>1&#x02212;<italic>y</italic></sub>Sb<italic><sub>y</sub></italic>)<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub> (0 &#x0003c; <italic>y</italic> &#x0003c; 1)</article-title>. <source>Phys. Status Solidi B</source>
<volume>84</volume>, <fpage>619</fpage> (<year>1977</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Raman Spectroscopy of Few-Quintuple Layer Topological Insulator Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> Nanoplatelets</article-title>. <source>Nano. Lett.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>2407</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21604748</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>A. Q.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X. F.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Venkatasubramanian</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Ultrafast dynamics of photoexcited coherent phonon in Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub> thin films</article-title>. <source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>92</volume>, <fpage>011108</fpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>In-plane DC resistivity.</title><p>Inset = ARPES data of BSTS single crystal. Notice the band dispersion near the Fermi level.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep03513-f1"/></fig><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Amplitude of complex transmittance, <inline-formula id="m37"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1159" xlink:href="srep03513-m37.jpg"/></inline-formula>, at various temperatures.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep03513-f2"/></fig><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>(a) Real conductance <italic>G</italic><sub>1</sub>(<italic>&#x003c9;</italic>) at 30&#x02005;K. Inset shows the imaginary conductance <italic>G</italic><sub>1</sub>(<italic>&#x003c9;</italic>). (O) = data. Solid lines = Drude (green) and Lorentz (blue) contributions, and the fit to data (red). (b) Low-frequency real conductivity &#x003c3;<sub>1</sub> versus temperature. (O) = data. Solid line = fit to Eq. (3).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep03513-f3"/></fig><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Temperature dependence of the (a) Drude plasma frequency <italic>&#x003c9;<sub>pD</sub></italic>, (b) Lorentz plasma frequency <italic>&#x003c9;<sub>pL</sub></italic>, (c) Drude scattering rate <italic>&#x003b3;<sub>D</sub></italic>, and (d) Lorentz scattering rate <italic>&#x003b3;<sub>L</sub></italic>.</title><p>Solid line = fit to Eq. (3).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep03513-f4"/></fig><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Schematic of band diagram of BSTS, with the (donor) impurity band lying just below the Fermi level.</title><p>The relative positions of the valence band, Dirac point, Fermi level and conduction band were taken from Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref> for a Bi<sub>1.5</sub>Sb<sub>0.5</sub>Te<sub>1.7</sub>Se<sub>1.3</sub> sample. &#x00394; = activation gap.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep03513-f5"/></fig><fig id="f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Spectral weight of various Bi-based topological insulators at 5&#x02005;K calculated using Eq. 4.</title><p>Dashed line represents the contribution from topological surface carriers of Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub> thin film<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>. Adapted with permission from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4</xref> of Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>. Copyright 2012 by the American Physical Society.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep03513-f6"/></fig><fig id="f7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Real conductivity [<italic>&#x003c3;</italic><sub>1</sub>(<italic>&#x003c9;</italic>)] of a 90-&#x003bc;m-thick BSTS sample at 10&#x02005;K, 50&#x02005;K, 90&#x02005;K and 150&#x02005;K. Experimental data were taken in the sequence: 10&#x02005;K &#x02192; 50&#x02005;K &#x02192; 90&#x02005;K &#x02192; 150&#x02005;K &#x02192; 10&#x02005;K &#x02192; 50&#x02005;K &#x02192; 90&#x02005;K &#x02192; 150&#x02005;K.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep03513-f7"/></fig></floats-group></article>